<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23069499"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="UK shale gas resources may be much greater than thought, says a report, while the government announces financial benefits for &#34;fracking&#34; communities."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T14:23:28"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68404000/jpg/_68404054_cuad26.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="'Far more' UK shale gas resources"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23069499"/>
         <title>BBC News - UK shale gas resources 'greater than
thought'</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">15:23</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">UK shale gas resources 'greater than
thought'</h1>
            <div class="has-icon-comment dna-comment-count-simple"> </div>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68405000/jpg/_68405663_68405662.jpg"
                 alt="George Osborne"/>
               <p class="caption">Osborne: "Local communities should get, for
example, at least Ã‚Â£100,000 for every
fracking well that is created"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">UK shale gas
resources may be far greater than previously thought, a report for
the government says.</p>
            <p>The British Geological Survey estimates there may be 1,300
trillion cubic feet of shale gas present in the north of England -
double previous estimates.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile the government has announced measures to enable shale
gas drilling as part of its infrastructure plans.</p>
            <p>Energy Minister Michael Fallon described shale gas as "an
exciting new energy resource".</p>
            <p>The BGS said its estimate for shale gas resources in the Bowland
Basin region, which stretches from Cheshire to Yorkshire,
represented potential resources, but "not the gas that might be
possible to extract".</p>
            <p>"Shale gas clearly has potential in Britain but it will require
geological and engineering expertise, investment and protection of
the environment," it said.</p>
            <p>Drilling companies have previously estimated that they may be
able to extract around 10% of this gas - equivalent to around 130
trillion cubic feet.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68420000/gif/_68420744_shale_gas624x372.gif"
                 width="624"
                 height="372"
                 alt="Shale gas map"/>
            </div>
            <p>If the estimates are proved correct, that would still suggest
recoverable reserves of shale gas far in excess of the three
trillion cubic feet of gas currently consumed in the UK each
year.</p>
            <p>Shale gas is extracted through "fracking" - the controversial
process of freeing trapped gas by pumping in a mixture of water,
sand and chemicals.</p>
            <p>The process has helped boost the domestic
energy industry in the US in recent years, where oil production has
risen and gas prices have plummeted.</p>
            <p>
               <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/estimates-of-shale-gas-resource-in-north-of-england-published-alongside-a-package-of-community-benefits">
In a statement</a>, the Department of Energy and Climate Change
said: "Though it is early days for shale in the UK, it has the
potential to contribute to the UK's energy security, increase
inward investment and growth."</p>
            <p>The government has unveiled a package of reforms to encourage
development in the industry.</p>
            <p>They include new planning guidelines to make the process of
approving new drilling sites more streamlined, and a consultation
on tax incentives to encourage exploration.</p>
            <p>Communities affected by shale gas drilling are also expected to
receive Ã‚Â£100,000 in "community benefits"
and 1% of production revenues, should sites start producing
gas.</p>
            <p>"Shale gas represents an exciting new potential energy resource
for the UK, and could play an important part in our energy mix,"
said Energy Minister Michael Fallon</p>
            <p>"Development must be done in partnership with local people. We
welcome the commitments from industry on community benefits.</p>
            <p>"This will provide a welcome boost for communities who will host
shale exploration and production as well as offering strong
assurances that operators will engage with them and work to the
highest health, safety and environmental standards."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/50833000/gif/_50833618_shale_extraction_diagram_464.gif"
                 width="464"
                 height="352"
                 alt="Infographic showing shale gas extraction"/>
            </div>
            <p>He said communities hosting shale gas drilling could benefit
from cheaper bills, regeneration schemes and new community
facilities like playgrounds and sports halls.</p>
            <p>The incentives are designed to overcome significant scepticism
surrounding the process of fracking, which has generated
environmental concerns.</p>
            <p>Critics argue that it can cause earth tremors and pollute water
supplies, and that shale gas wells could blight the countryside and
affect house prices.</p>
            <p>They also want investment in green energy sources, rather than
fossil fuels.</p>
            <p>Labour's shadow energy minister, Tom Greatrex, conceded that gas
would remain "an important part of our energy mix in the
future".</p>
            <p>But he dismissed the announcement of incentives as "a desperate
attempt to draw attention away from the government's cuts to
infrastructure investment... and its abject failure to get the
economy growing".</p>
            <p>Currently the UK's shale industry remains in its infancy, with
relatively small energy companies such as IGas and Cuadrilla until
recently the only firms with licences to explore share gas
resources.</p>
            <p>Centrica, the owner of British Gas, announced its intention to
buy a stake in one licence in the Bowland Basin owned by Cuadrilla
earlier this month.</p>
            <p>The report for the government comes as energy regulator <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23081695">Ofgem warned that the
risks of power blackouts</a> has increased because excess capacity
in the power industry has fallen in the UK.</p>
            <p>The watchdog has twice warned in recent months that the amount
of spare power is shrinking, partly due to some gas generators
being taken out of service.</p>
            <p>Centrica has already withdrawn two of its gas plants from
operation. In April, SSE confirmed that it too would mothball gas
plants and put off investments in new ones.</p>
            <p>Adam Scorer, of the lobby group Consumer Futures, said:
"Projections of ever-tighter capacity margins understandably raise
fears of higher electricity prices.</p>
            <p>"Government and regulator need to agree on the most realistic
capacity scenarios, the least-cost ways of reducing demand and,
where necessary, of incentivising new generation capacity."</p>
            <p>Announcing further details of the government's spending review
to parliament, Treasury Secretary Danny Alexander said the
government had agreed "strike prices" in an effort to boost
investment in renewable forms of energy.</p>
            <p>The prices mean the government will guarantee to pay a certain
price for energy generated through on-shore and off-shore wind,
tidal, wave, bio-mass and solar power.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1292933534734"
                  href="/news/science-environment-12043213">How to get gas from hard rock
<span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1312649995828"
                  href="/news/uk-14432401">Q&amp;A: What is fracking?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1366932358809"
                  href="/news/science-environment-22300050">UK shale gas bonanza 'not
assured'</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/49353000/jpg/_49353261_007788859-1.jpg"
                    alt="image of Roger Harrabin"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Roger Harrabin</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Environment analyst</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>The truly massive shale gas resource of the north of England may
bring tax revenues and possibly - not definitely - lead to lower
bills, but it won't help the environment.</p>
            <p>This week the government's climate change advisers warned that
the UK was failing to keep pace with legally binding cuts in the
CO2 emissions that are disrupting the climate.</p>
            <p>The Environment Agency warns that if we want to keep burning gas
we will have to rely on unproven technology to capture the carbon
emissions in order to meet climate change targets.</p>
            <p>It also warns that gas escaping from fractured wells may
increase climatic disruption.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile the International Energy Agency warns that the world
can only burn a third of its existing fossil fuel reserves without
a serious risk of de-stabilising the climate.</p>
            <p>Shale gas plans will meet local environmental opposition
too.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
