<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23129474"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A university project examines how to find a more tolerant future after war"/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T23:12:45"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68505000/jpg/_68505550_garentina180.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Can you teach the intolerant to be tolerant?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23129474"/>
         <title>BBC News - Kosovo tackles tough questions of religion and
conflict</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">3 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:12</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Kosovo tackles tough questions of religion
and conflict</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Sean
Coughlan</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News education
correspondent</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68490000/jpg/_68490288_garentina304.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="405"
                 alt="Garentina Kraja"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Garentina Kraja reported Kosovo's war and is now
teaching students about resolving conflict</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Garentina Kraja's
adult life has been a mirror of Kosovo's recent history and the
attempts of Europe's youngest country to build a new identity.</p>
            <p>From a teenage war correspondent and refugee she is now a
presidential adviser and teaches a university course about
tolerance and resolving conflict, in a country sitting across
political, religious and ethnic fault-lines.</p>
            <p>Kosovo is still a country shaped by the brutal ethnic conflict
that followed the disintegration of Yugoslavia - and where old
spectres of ethnic violence returned to haunt modern Europe.</p>
            <p>The course, taught at the University of Prishtina and the
American University of Kosovo, is an original project in its own
right, trying a different approach to tackling the toxic appeal of
sectarianism and religious extremism.</p>
            <p>It is the result of another figure who has woven in and out of
her story - Tony Blair. She first saw him in a refugee camp in
Macedonia in 1999, where she was sheltering with her family and
thousands of other displaced ethnic Albanians.</p>
            <p>The next unlikely meeting place was more than a decade later,
when she was a student at Yale University. Having had her education
"stolen away" by war, she had been invited to study in the United
States.</p>
            <p>And an international relations course at Yale was offered with
the former UK prime minister as a lecturer. It had an unusual
angle.</p>
            <p>Mr Blair wanted to look at the role of religion in conflict,
with the view that it had become a diplomatic blind spot. While it
was common to analyse disputes in terms of ideology, economics and
ethnic tensions, the role of religious belief was left to one side,
a ghost in the mechanics of peacemaking.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68490000/jpg/_68490287_018457138-1.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Protests by Albanian Kosovans against negotiations with Serbia"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Albanian Kosovans protesting last week
against improving relations with Serbia</span>
            </div>
            <p>Ms Kraja says she was "sceptical". Her family was Muslim, but
she had grown up in a secular home, where religion was a marginal
part of her identity.</p>
            <p>But she says it made her think about the patterns of the
conflict in Kosovo she had covered as a war correspondent and how
religion had been "hijacked by different forces to further their
own agendas".</p>
            <p>"Religion didn't cause the war, it was about territory. But
destroying a mosque or a church became a way of destroying a
community's identity."</p>
            <p>Religion had become part of the process of prosecution and
reprisals, it was a way of one community "demonising the
other".</p>
            <p>She talks of the traumatic experiences of covering the war,
visiting villages where dozens of people from the same family had
been massacred. There had been a systematic use of rape as a weapon
of terror, she says.</p>
            <p>She watched soldiers eating ice cream in the sunshine after they
had levelled a village.</p>
            <p>There was a process of dehumanising victims, she says, robbing
them of their individual identity, labelling them as a communal
enemy.</p>
            <p>And part of this includes the misuse of religion, she says.
Since the Kosovo war, the 9/11 terror attacks had added another
layer of rhetoric about clashes between east and west and the
dangers of religious fundamentalism.</p>
            <p>She not only attended the course, she has ended up teaching it.
The project, the Faith and Globalisation Initiative, is now
operating across 20 international universities, with the aim of
tackling the "vacuum of knowledge" about the role of religion.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68490000/jpg/_68490283_018471628-1.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Kosovo Serbs gather to mark the anniversary of the 1389 Battle of Kosovo at Gazimestan"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Serbs last week marked the anniversary
of the Battle of Kosovo in 1389</span>
            </div>
            <p>Tempers can become frayed in classes, says Ms Kraja. The idea of
tolerance and free speech gets tested by extreme views. "It can
become inflamed... How do you engage with people who deal in
absolute truths?"</p>
            <p>But she says it is important to keep such arguments in the
public sphere, rather than letting youngsters disappear into the
radicalised margins.</p>
            <p>"If we're serious about a tolerant, inclusive society, we need
to be able to understand each other. If you want to condemn
intolerance you need to understand it.</p>
            <p>"It's the missing part of the debate. Even if we're ambivalent
about religion, you need to understand it. These debates need to be
out in the open."</p>
            <p>It raises big questions for a young democracy. Where are the
boundaries of free speech? How do you accommodate the rights of a
distrustful minority? How do you balance the rights of victims with
the need for reconciliation? How much should religious identity be
allowed to intrude upon a secular public domain?</p>
            <p>In Kosovo it means practical questions such as whether Muslim
school pupils should be allowed to wear headscarves. At present,
they're not. There is also a debate about whether religious
education should be introduced, against fears that it could be
turned into a form of religious instruction.</p>
            <p>Kosovo is an extraordinary cauldron of contradictions. It's a
living example of the multiple layers of identity.</p>
            <p>If "Balkanisation" has come to mean the fragmentation of states
into incompatible pieces, then Kosovo is Balkanised even by the
standards of the Balkans.</p>
            <p>The majority population is ethnic Albanian, mostly Muslim,
although the naming of the main street Mother Teresa Boulevard
reflects there are also Christians.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68490000/jpg/_68490285_000103169-1.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="405"
                 alt="Tony Blair, Kosovan refugees, May 1999"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Tony Blair visited refugees from Kosovo in May
1999</span>
            </div>
            <p>There is a minority Serb population in a region with a deep
historical significance for Serbians - and Serbia does not
recognise the legitimacy of Kosovo as a separate state.</p>
            <p>A Nato military force still remains in place to keep the
peace.</p>
            <p>Kosovo's national museum is virtually a shrine to Nato, in
honour of the military intervention that ousted Serb forces in
1999. But reverberating through the galleries is the call to prayer
from the ancient mosque next door.</p>
            <p>Photos of God Bless America posters are cheek by jowl with
minarets.</p>
            <p>Traffic in Pristina hurtles along roads bearing names of 1990s
leaders such as Bill Klinton and Tonibler (the Albanian rendering
of Tony Blair). This remains an outpost of pre-Iraq optimism.</p>
            <p>While members of the eurozone have doubts about their currency,
the Kosovans, perhaps the last great enthusiasts for
internationalism, have already adopted the euro as their
currency.</p>
            <p>This is also disputed territory for the international community.
When Kosovo declared independence five years ago it was recognised
by the US, UK and France, but Russia and China have still not
accepted its statehood.</p>
            <p>The normalisation of relations with Serbia remains part of a
wider international chess game, including Serbia's aim to join the
European Union.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68498000/jpg/_68498532_017846652-1.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Commemorating the missing in Kosovo's war"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Commemorating the victims of Kosovo's
war</span>
            </div>
            <p>And the spectacularly youthful demographics of the country bear
little relation to the ageing populations elsewhere in Europe. An
estimated 60% are aged under 30, so the need to tackle youth
unemployment is vital for any future political stability.</p>
            <p>According to US figures, Kosovo already has the lowest per
capita income in Europe.</p>
            <p>Kosovo is also a reminder of how old nightmares can rise from
the deep freezer of history. Yugoslavia buried the idea of national
and religious identity, but it sprang back to life with dark and
brutal savagery.</p>
            <p>She says that when the convoys shuffled into refugee camps they
were like figures from the 1930s and 1940s, but at the same time
they all had mobile phones. This was the MTV generation caught up
in medieval ethnic slaughter.</p>
            <p>Charlotte Keenan, chief executive of the Tony Blair Faith
Foundation which runs the university project, says she wants to
support efforts to prevent religious conflict in Kosovo.</p>
            <p>"We believe that in order to truly understand the modern world,
you must understand religion's impact upon it."</p>
            <p>For Garentina Kraja, the ambitions for Kosovo might seem modest
but are ambitious in the context of its recent history. "We need to
become a boring democracy."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-12686570">Knowledge
economy</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372201973947"
                     href="/news/business-22688596">World's most family-friendly
countries</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371614407779"
                     href="/news/business-22938868">IMF enters university market</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1321964761634"
                     href="/news/education-15838288">Getting in touch</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1370992443551"
                     href="/news/business-22756408">G8: Bail out education not the
banks</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
