<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23259935"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Apple conspired with publishers to fix the price of electronic books, a US judge rules, but the company says it will appeal against the decision."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-10T17:49:32"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68653000/jpg/_68653368_59611280.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Apple guilty of e-books price fixing"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23259935"/>
         <title>BBC News - Apple conspired to fix e-book prices, judge
rules</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">10 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">18:49</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Apple conspired to fix e-book prices,
judge rules</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/59603000/jpg/_59603780_59603779.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Tim Cook"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Several book publishers have already settled their
cases</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Apple conspired with
publishers to fix the price of electronic books, a US judge has
ruled.</p>
            <p>Manhattan Judge Denise Cote said the iPad maker "conspired to
restrain trade".</p>
            <p>But the firm's spokesman, Tom Neumayr, said Apple would appeal
against the ruling and fight "false allegations".</p>
            <p>Five publishers that were originally named as defendants
alongside Apple have already reached settlements, including
Penguin.</p>
            <p>The judge ordered a new hearing to determine damages to be
imposed on Apple.</p>
            <p>The US Department of Justice said the conspiracy was designed to
challenge online retailer Amazon's dominance of the fast-growing
e-books market.</p>
            <p>Penguin settled its case for $75m
(Â£49m). Hachette, HarperCollins and Simon
&amp; Schuster created a $69m fund for refunds to consumers, while
Macmillan settled for $26m.</p>
            <p>Judge Cote said: "The plaintiffs have
shown that the publisher defendants conspired with each other to
eliminate retail price competition in order to raise e-book prices,
and that Apple played a central role in facilitating and executing
that conspiracy.</p>
            <p>"Without Apple's orchestration of this conspiracy, it would not
have succeeded as it did in the spring of 2010," she said.</p>
            <p>US Assistant Attorney General Bill Baer called the ruling "a
victory for millions of consumers who choose to read books
electronically".</p>
            <p>He said the judge agreed with the Justice Department and 33
state attorneys general that executives at the highest levels of
Apple orchestrated a conspiracy with five major publishers to raise
prices.</p>
            <p>"Through today's court decision and previous settlements with
five major publishers, consumers are again benefiting from retail
price competition and paying less for their e-books,'' Mr Baer
said.</p>
            <p>Consumer groups in the US cheered the news.</p>
            <p>"If we let companies get away with this type of price fixing,
consumers will be denied a substantial part of the benefits of the
digital revolution," said Dr Mark Cooper of the Consumer Federation
of America, which had filed a supporting brief in the case.</p>
            <p>But after the ruling, Mr Neumayr insisted that Apple had brought
innovation and competition to the market, not restricted it.</p>
            <p>"Apple did not conspire to fix e-book pricing and we will
continue to fight against these false accusations,'' he said.
"We've done nothing wrong."</p>
            <p>Previously, Apple's attorney, Orin Snyder, had told the court
that Judge Cote would set a "dangerous precedent" if she concluded
that Apple manipulated e-book prices.</p>
            <p>However, Columbia University law professor Scott Hemphill said
today's ruling was narrow and would be unlikely to set any legal
precedent.</p>
            <p>"It may send some signals to tech companies about what they can
and can't do," said Prof Hemphill.</p>
            <p>"But the precedential value is limited because the ruling is by
a district court."</p>
            <p>However, he added that the judge in this case took particular
pains to anticipate a challenge from Apple - something that chief
executive Tim Cook hinted at earlier this year, when he dismissed
the idea of a settlement.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370305877204"
                  href="/news/business-22762653">Apple e-book deal 'cost
millions'</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370268572176"
                  href="/news/business-22751548">Apple
trial 'not just about books' <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68660000/jpg/_68660039_samira.jpg"
                    alt="image of Samira Hussain"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Samira Hussain</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
business reporter, New York</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>This is certainly a big win for the US government. But what's
interesting is how it proved its case.</p>
            <p>It was the collusion between publishers and Apple that caught
the eye of regulators and led to today's decision.</p>
            <p>The court relied heavily on incriminating internal emails from
Apple's Senior Vice President, Eddy Cue, to each of the publishers
named in the lawsuit.</p>
            <p>It also relied on testimony from the late Steve Jobs. Yes, Steve
Jobs.</p>
            <p>That came from transcripts of interviews with Walter Isaacson,
the author of Mr Jobs' biography.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
