<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23097575"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="India doubles the price of natural gas, in an effort to kick-start investment in the country's domestic production."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T10:21:18"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68432000/jpg/_68432107_indiagasprices.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="India doubles price of natural gas"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23097575"/>
         <title>BBC News - India doubles price of natural gas to attract
investment</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">11:21</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">India doubles price of natural gas to
attract investment</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68429000/jpg/_68429753_indiagasprices.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="A roadside teashop owner makes tea next to LPG cylinders in New Delhi. "/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Gas prices in India will double in April
next year</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The government of
India has approved a doubling of natural gas prices, in a
politically-sensitive move that will take effect around the time of
next year's elections.</p>
            <p>It is hoped that the first rise in the price of gas for three
years will increase investment in the sector.</p>
            <p>The rise will have a knock-on effect on the cost of electricity,
transport fuel, fertiliser and cooking gas.</p>
            <p>Shares in India's domestic gas producers rose sharply on the
news.</p>
            <p>The Cabinet Committee on Economic Affairs said the price of
domestically produced natural gas should rise to $8 per unit, from
the current $4.20, in April next year.</p>
            <p>Indian state energy companies welcomed the news, saying it will
increase investment within the sector and help to attract money
from outside.</p>
            <p>"It is more than expected. We expected up to $6.70 (per unit).
This is really positive. It will encourage us to invest more in
exploration," said TK Ananth Kumar, finance director at state-run
Oil India.</p>
            <p>Demand for gas in India, which is Asia's third-largest economy,
far exceeds production. However, the government keeps prices
artificially low, and this has deterred investment in developing
production capacity, including the building of pipelines and
terminals for more expensive liquid natural gas (LNG).</p>
            <p>Coal and oil dominate India's energy mix at the moment, with
coal accounting for 56% and oil 26%. India's government aims to
double the proportion of natural gas to 20% by 2020.</p>
            <p>However, the price increase is unlikely to be popular with
voters, who go to the polls for both local and national elections
within the next 12 months.</p>
            <p>Shares in the country's gas producers jumped significantly. The
largest state-run energy explorer, ONGC, saw its shares rise by
more than 10% at one point on the Mumbai Stock Exchange, while
shares in privately-owned Reliance Industries gained 5%.</p>
            <p>The Communist Party of India (CPI) described the price rise as a
"disaster", which would lead to accelerating inflation and higher
costs for farmers.</p>
            <p>CPI leader Gurudas Dasgupta said the government had caved in to
"pressure" from the corporate sector.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371709520647"
                  href="/news/business-22981979">India rupee falls to all-time
low</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372028413866"
                  href="/news/business-23003532">Caste or Class?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
