<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23143559"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Energy firms must do more to tackle electricity theft, a third of which is said to be for cannabis farms, Ofgem says."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-03T15:04:05"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68516000/jpg/_68516563_power.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Ofgem urges energy theft crackdown"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23143559"/>
         <title>BBC News - Ofgem wants power firms to tackle electricity
theft</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">3 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">16:04</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Ofgem wants power firms to tackle
electricity theft</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/67665000/jpg/_67665653_cannabisfarm.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Cannabis farm"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Ofgem estimates a third of stolen electricity powers
cannabis farms in the UK</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The energy regulator
wants power firms to do more to combat electricity theft, a third
of which is stolen each year to power cannabis farms.</p>
            <p>Ofgem has published proposals to combat a problem that it says
costs customers Â£200m a year.</p>
            <p>Ofgem said new rules should force suppliers to detect and
investigate problems, or risk a fine.</p>
            <p>The regulator estimates that there are up to 25,000 cases of
electricity theft each year.</p>
            <p>Under the proposals, suppliers are being asked to set up a
national theft-risk assessment service to help them target premises
where there are strong suspicions that electricity is being stolen,
most commonly through tampering with meters.</p>
            <p>Ofgem says theft costs paying electricity customers the
equivalent of Â£7 each a year.</p>
            <p>The Ofgem proposals include:</p>
            <ul>
               <li>Setting up an industry code of practice governing how theft
investigations should be carried out to ensure there is a
consistent approach across the industry</li>
               <li>Coordinating efforts to tackle theft relating to cannabis farms
with other agencies such as the Home Office and local police
forces</li>
               <li>Sharing best practice across the industry about how cases of
theft have been identified</li>
               <li>Setting up a 24-hour hotline to report suspected theft</li>
            </ul>
            <p>Andrew Wright, Ofgem chief executive, said: "The reforms build
on similar obligations we introduced at the start of this year for
suppliers to address gas theft more vigorously.</p>
            <p>"All these measures will help to improve the confidence of
consumers, who want reassurance that the energy market is
fair."</p>
            <p>Energy UK, the trade association for the industry, welcomed
Ofgem's consultation.</p>
            <p>"Electricity theft is dangerous and illegal," it said.
"Electricity theft also costs honest customers money which is why
energy companies take this - and gas theft - very seriously.</p>
            <p>"Ofgem's consultation is a positive move to cut down crime, and
we look forward to working closely with them and others in the
industry on this."</p>
            <p>Ian Peters, managing director of residential energy at British
Gas, said that the company would co-operate fully with Ofgem.</p>
            <p>"Electricity and gas theft is a serious issue, which places
lives at risk and adds unnecessary costs to customers' bills. We
estimate that the annual cost to UK customers of gas and
electricity theft is up to Â£500m."</p>
            <p>The deadline for responses to Ofgem's proposals is 28 August,
with a theft-risk assessment service scheduled to be up and running
in the first quarter of 2015.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372330621723"
                  href="/news/business-23081695">Ofgem warns of power shortage
risk</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story" rel="published-1371017534081" href="/news/22867835">Ofgem set to shake up energy market</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
