<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23181876"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The European Central Bank (ECB) keeps interest rates at a historic low level of 0.5%, and says they will stay at that level or lower for &#34;an extended period&#34;."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T19:46:26"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68548000/jpg/_68548065_67345999.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="ECB says rates to stay at record low"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23181876"/>
         <title>BBC News - ECB says rates to stay low for 'extended
period'</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">20:46</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">ECB says rates to stay low for 'extended
period'</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68549000/jpg/_68549755_68549754.jpg"
                 alt="Mario Draghi"/>
               <p class="caption">President Mario Draghi says the ECB expects to
hold interest rates for "an extended period"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The European Central
Bank (ECB) president, Mario Draghi, has said that rates will remain
at current or lower levels for an "extended period".</p>
            <p>"Monetary policy will remain accommodative for as long as
necessary," he told a news conference.</p>
            <p>This represents the first time that the ECB has given an
<a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23145755">indication of
its future guidance on the rate of interest in the
eurozone.</a>
            </p>
            <p>The ECB left interest rates at the historic low level of 0.5% on
Thursday.</p>
            <p>The decision not to cut rates further comes amidst a backdrop of
political crisis in Portugal after two key ministers resigned.</p>
            <p>Earlier this week, Finance Minister Vitor Gaspar, who has
overseen unpopular austerity measures in the country for the past
two years, handed in his resignation.</p>
            <p>That was followed by the foreign minister
and junior coalition leader, Paulo Portas.</p>
            <p>Bond yields in the country rose above 8% on Wednesday as Prime
Minister Pedro Passos Coelho tried to stabilise his coalition.</p>
            <p>Asked if there had been too much austerity in Portugal, Mr
Draghi said that he thought the country had achieved "very
remarkable results".</p>
            <p>"It has been a painful route and the results have been quite
significant, remarkable, if not outstanding.</p>
            <p>"We are reassured by the new (finance) minister, by everything
we know about her, so from this point of view, Portugal is in safe
hands."</p>
            <p>Speaking at a news conference following the ECB's interest rate
announcement, Mr Draghi would not be drawn on how long he expected
rates to remain low, only that the decision was "unanimous".</p>
            <p>"It's not six months, it's not 12 months - it's an extended
period of time," he said.</p>
            <p>On his reasons for revealing the ECB's plan to keep rates low,
Mr Draghi said: "We have an outlook of inflation in the medium
term, such that it would justify this new way of communication our
forward guidance - a downward bias in interest rates."</p>
            <div class="marketdata-widget">
               <h2>
                  <a href="/news/business/market_data/currency/13/12/default.stm">Euro v US
Dollar</a>
               </h2>
               <span class="date">Last Updated at 08 Jul 2013, 11:26</span>
               <span class="chart-key">*Chart shows local time</span>
               <img src="/news/business/market_data/chart?chart_primary_ticker=FX^EUR:USD&amp;chart_time_period=2_day&amp;canvas_colour=000000&amp;primary_chart_colour=CC0000&amp;use_transparency=0&amp;plot_colour=ffffff&amp;cp_line_colour=1F4F82&amp;margin_left=35&amp;margin_bottom=20&amp;margin_right=20&amp;time_24hr=1&amp;tiny_chart=1&amp;tiny_month_view=1&amp;logo_strength=light&amp;y_axis_left=1&amp;x_axis_plain=1&amp;cp_line=1&amp;cp_line_style=dotline&amp;charting_freq=1_minute&amp;co_dimension^width=271&amp;co_dimension^height=170&amp;small_chart_x_label_format=1&amp;date_label_spacing=30"
                 alt="EUR:USD intraday chart"/>
               <table>
                  <colgroup>
                     <col class="md-col1"/>
                     <col class="md-col2"/>
                     <col class="md-col3"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                     <tr>
                        <th scope="col">€1 buys</th>
                        <th scope="col">change</th>
                        <th scope="col">%</th>
                     </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td>1.2858</td>
                        <td class="up">
                           <span>+</span>
                           <div class="statshi">+0.00</div>
                        </td>
                        <td class="up">
                           <span>+</span>
                           <div class="statshi">+0.23</div>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
            </div>
            <p>Kathleen Brooks, research director at
Forex said: "Forward guidance is the future of monetary policy this
side of the Atlantic, and with growth rates in the eurozone still
so weak, we could see accommodative policy for some time.</p>
            <p>"The details surrounding the ECB's forward guidance policy are
still cloudy, which could add to market uncertainty and weigh on
the euro in the coming days."</p>
            <p>Mr Draghi also said that extensive discussions had taken place
about a possible interest rate cut this month.</p>
            <p>The euro fell sharply on the news that interest rates could be
cut further, with the currency falling 0.8% against the dollar to
$1.2903.</p>
            <p>"The risks surrounding the economic outlook for the euro area
continue to be to the downside," said Mr Draghi.</p>
            <p>Along with Portugal, several European countries are still
failing to deliver economic growth, including France, Spain, Italy
and Greece.</p>
            <p>The eurozone as a whole remains in its longest recession since
it was created in 1999, and is expected to contract further this
year.</p>
            <p>Following the ECB announcement, the International Monetary Fund
warned that Italy, the eurozone's third-largest economy, will
shrink by 1.8% this year - worse than the 1.5% contraction it had
previously forecast.</p>
            <p>It said the government of Prime Minister Enrico Letta must
accelerate current economic reforms, and said unemployment was
"unacceptably high".</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372956066419"
                  href="/news/business-23190168">Independence day for central
banks</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372937089750"
                  href="/news/business-23145755">Q&amp;A: What is 'forward
guidance'?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372928007175"
                  href="/news/world-europe-23178275">Portugal battles to defuse
crisis</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/52585000/jpg/_52585201_52585200.jpg"
                    alt="image of Andrew Walker"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Andrew Walker</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
World Service economics correspondent</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>Britain and the eurozone are not the US. Obvious perhaps, but
the markets seem to have welcomed this clear indication that
central banks on this side of the Atlantic will get their policies
back to normal at their own pace.</p>
            <p>Markets have been affected by comments from US Federal Reserve
officials suggesting that their efforts to stimulate the economy
could be reined in a little sooner than was expected.</p>
            <p>The ECB and the Bank of England have made it plain that they are
in no hurry to follow. No wonder. The US economy is growing a lot
more convincingly, although it is still far from back to
normal.</p>
            <p>Britain has managed some growth, but it has been erratic, while
the most recent eurozone figures showed a sixth consecutive quarter
of contraction. Financial markets probably understood that, but
they were glad to have some confirmation.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
