<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23251089"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="China reports weaker than expected trade data, underlying concerns of a slowdown in the world's second-largest economy,"/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-10T03:52:16"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68643000/jpg/_68643516_169317842.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="China's exports and imports decline"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23251089"/>
         <title>BBC News - China reports weaker than expected trade
data</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">10 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">04:52</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">China reports weaker than expected trade
data</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68643000/jpg/_68643500_169317842.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Workers at a factory in China"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Manufacturing and export sectors are key
drivers of China's economic growth</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">China has reported
an unexpected fall in its exports and imports, adding to concerns
of a slowdown in its economy.</p>
            <p>Exports fell 3.1% in June from a year earlier, indicating weak
global demand for Chinese goods. Most analysts had expected a 4%
increase in shipments.</p>
            <p>Imports fell 0.7% from a year ago, showing a subdued domestic
demand.</p>
            <p>China, the world's second-largest economy, has been keen to
rebalance its economy, after a decline in global demand hurt its
export-led growth.</p>
            <p>China's economy grew at an annual pace of 7.7% in the January to
March quarter, compared with 7.9% in the previous three months.</p>
            <p>There have been concerns that its growth may slow further, not
least because of a protracted slowdown in its key export markets in
the US and Europe.</p>
            <p>At the same time, policymakers have found it tough to boost
domestic consumption enough to offset a decline in foreign
sales.</p>
            <p>Analysts said the surprise fall in exports and imports in June
indicated that China's economic growth was likely to remain under
pressure in the coming months.</p>
            <p>"We expect both export and import data may remain at a
relatively low level in the second half, due to weak demand at home
and abroad," said Wang Jin, an analyst at Guotai Junan Securities
in Shanghai.</p>
            <p>Various organisations, including the World Bank and the
International Monetary Fund, have recently cut their outlook for
China's growth,</p>
            <p>Chinese export data had shown positive
signs of a gradual recovery in external demand in recent
months.</p>
            <p>However, that had not been in line with data from other regional
countries - which have been showing a slowdown in their export
growth.</p>
            <p>That triggered speculation that some Chinese exporters may be
overstating their shipments in an attempt to bypass restrictions on
bringing funds into the country.</p>
            <p>Prompted by these concerns, Chinese authorities, who keep a
tight grip on capital flows in and out of country, have announced
steps to control any illegal flows.</p>
            <p>In May, China's foreign exchange regulator, the State
Administration of Foreign Exchange (SAFE), said it would increase
its scrutiny of export invoices and impose tougher penalties on
firms providing false data.</p>
            <p>Analysts said that the weaker-than-expected figures in June were
partially because of the crackdown on such practices.</p>
            <p>"Both exports and imports are weaker than market consensus,
partially a result of Beijing's crackdown on speculative capital
inflows disguised as trade," said Wang Jin.</p>
            <p>"From this sense, we can say last month's export figure may
reflect a true picture of the current trade situation."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373360605818"
                  href="/news/business-23238024">China's inflation rate rises to
2.7%</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372807451986"
                  href="/news/business-23029251">Why China's financial jitters
matter</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372649441025"
                  href="/news/business-23123610">China manufacturing growth slows</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Both exports and imports are weaker than
market consensus, partially a result of Beijing's crackdown on
speculative capital inflows disguised as trade”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Wang Jin</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Guotai Junan Securities</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
