<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23134276"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Zynga's founder Mark Pincus steps down from the struggling social gaming company, to be replaced by key Microsoft executive Don Mattrick."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T21:56:24"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68492000/jpg/_68492432_markanddon.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Struggling Zynga appoints Xbox boss"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23134276"/>
         <title>BBC News - Zynga appoints Microsoft Xbox chief Don Mattrick
to top job</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">22:56</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Zynga appoints Microsoft Xbox chief Don
Mattrick to top job</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68486000/jpg/_68486295_markanddon.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Mark Pincus and Don Mattrick"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Zynga founder Mark Pincus (left) and Don
Mattrick</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Social gaming
company Zynga has named former Microsoft executive Don Mattrick as
chief executive.</p>
            <p>Mark Pincus, the company's founder and current CEO, said he will
stay on as chairman and chief product officer.</p>
            <p>"Zynga is a great business that has yet to realize its full
potential," said Mr Mattrick in an email to employees.</p>
            <p>At Microsoft, Mr Mattrick was head of interactive entertainment,
the key division that includes Xbox, which is about to launch a new
console.</p>
            <p>Before that, he helped develop popular
games like "The Sims" and "FIFA" for Electronic Arts.</p>
            <p>"I've always saidâ¦ that if I
could find someone who could do a better job as our CEO I'd do all
I could to recruit and bring that person in," said Mr Pincus in
<a href="http://blog.zynga.com/2013/07/01/big-day/">a separate
email</a> to staff.</p>
            <p>"I'm confident that Don is that leader."</p>
            <p>Shares in the company, which are down by more than 50% for the
year, shot up once word of the leadership change was first broken
by the website AllThingsD.com.</p>
            <p>At Microsoft, Mr Mattrick helped turn the Xbox business into a
profitable venture after years of losses. His departure comes just
as Microsoft prepares to launch a new version of the console, the
Xbox One.</p>
            <p>Gamers have attacked the high price, Microsoft's plan to require
an internet connection at least once a day and attempts to limit
the sharing of used games.</p>
            <p>Last month, Microsoft reversed its position on the Internet
connection and said it would allow game sharing.</p>
            <p>Zynga has had difficulty almost since its stock market debut in
December 2011, when it was valued at $1bn
(Â£656m). News of the appointment sent Zynga
shares more than 10% higher.</p>
            <p>Struggling to replicate the success it found with games like
FarmVille and Words With Friends, it bought OMGPOP, the company
behind the popular game Draw Something, for $200m
(Â£131m) in March of 2012. It shut OMGPOP
less than a year later.</p>
            <p>Mobile has also proven challenging for the company, which used
to rely on its close ties with Facebook for users.</p>
            <p>"The gaming market is an especially tough one, particularly as
user behaviour shifts dramatically towards gaming on phones and
tablets," said Clark Fredricksen, of eMarketer. "It's a world of
hit-makers and miss-hits."</p>
            <p>Recently the company has looked to online gambling as another
revenue stream, but that has not yet had an impact on the bottom
line. More than 20% of its staff has been let go in the past year,
and it has shuttered several offices.</p>
            <p>Mr Pincus is the second high profile founder of a social media
company to resign, following Groupon chief executive Andrew Mason's
departure in February.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371678201592"
                  href="/news/technology-22980973">Microsoft U-turn in Xbox games
row</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370888618052"
                  href="/news/technology-22848625">Xbox One launch and price
revealed</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370608626718"
                  href="/news/technology-22812743">Microsoft defends pre-owned
rules</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">Leo Kelion</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Technology reporter</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>Don Mattrick's decision to quit Microsoft follows a bruising E3
tech show last month.</p>
            <p>It was bad enough that the Xbox One was undercut on price by the
PlayStation 4, but the Canadian executive also found himself mocked
for introducing restrictions on second-hand games and insisting
players log onto the net at least once a day.</p>
            <p>His attempt at damage control only made matters worse. Saying
that those wanting an offline mode could still buy the
last-generation Xbox 360 was branded "ridiculous" by one news site
and even led to claims he had "single-handedly alienated the entire
military".</p>
            <p>When Mr Mattrick blogged details of a U-turn one week later,
traffic to the webpage was so great it temporarily became
inaccessible.</p>
            <p>Despite these recent troubles, Mr Mattrick can take credit for
having helped Microsoft outsell Sony in the US and UK for the
current console generation.</p>
            <p>Moving to Zynga offers him a fresh start, but joining a firm
that has recently cancelled games, lost top talent, cut jobs and
seen sales drop off means the pressure on him is unlikely to
ease.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
