<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23240707"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The owner of the New York Stock Exchange is set to take control of a key scandal-hit bank interest rate, a UK government-backed committee announces."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-09T17:06:36"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68628000/jpg/_68628427_68628013.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="NYSE Euronext to control Libor rate"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23240707"/>
         <title>BBC News - Libor interest rate to be controlled by NYSE
Euronext</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">9 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">18:06</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Libor interest rate to be controlled by
NYSE Euronext</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68628000/jpg/_68628012_68628011.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Canary Wharf skyline"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Barclays, UBS and RBS have all been implicated in
the Libor scandal</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The owner of the New
York Stock Exchange is set to take control of a key scandal-hit
bank interest rate.</p>
            <p>NYSE Euronext has won the contract for setting the London
Inter-bank Offered Rate (Libor), a government-backed committee
announced.</p>
            <p>Libor is used to set trillions of dollars of financial
contracts.</p>
            <p>The move follows the revelation that banks had been manipulating
the rate. Barclays, UBS and RBS have all been fined for their roles
in the scandal.</p>
            <p>They were found to have colluded in fixing the Libor setting in
order to boost the profits of traders in the run-up to the
financial crisis.</p>
            <p>The new rate-setting body, to be known as NYSE Euronext Rate
Administration, will be based in the UK and regulated by the
Financial Conduct Authority (FCA).</p>
            <p>"This change will play a vital role in restoring the
international credibility of Libor," said Baroness Hogg, chair of
the committee tasked with selecting a new administrator for the
interest rate.</p>
            <p>"Today marks a significant step in implementing the
recommendations in my review of Libor," said Martin Wheatley, chief
executive of the FCA and author of a report for the government on
how the interest rate should be reformed.</p>
            <p>"The selection of a new administrator, who will need to be
authorised, and then subject to ongoing scrutiny by the FCA, is an
important step in enhancing the integrity of Libor."</p>
            <p>Libor is set in London and is meant to reflect the average rate
that banks pay to lend to each other.</p>
            <p>It is used to benchmark everything from car loans and mortgages
to complex financial transactions around the world.</p>
            <p>At the moment, it is calculated by Thomson Reuters for the
British Bankers' Association (BBA), based on estimates received
from 16 major international banks in London of how much they must
pay in order to borrow cash from other banks.</p>
            <p>Under the new agreement, the rate would be calculated by
estimates received from those same banks, as well as by using
transaction data monitored by NYSE Euronext. It is hoped that by
augmenting the self-reporting with transaction data it will help
further prevent the rate from falling prey to manipulation.</p>
            <p>An oversight committee will also be created to set up a code of
conduct on how banks can operate.</p>
            <p>Both of these factors will be in place by the time NYSE Euronext
takes over the contract, in early 2014.</p>
            <p>Stuart Sloan, executive director of NYSE Euronext, told the BBC
that NYSE Euronext was also "committed to restoring the credibility
of Libor."</p>
            <p>The BBA welcomed the move and said that restoring confidence in
Libor was a priority.</p>
            <p>"We have been working hard with regulatory authorities and the
government to put in place much-needed reforms to the system," said
BBA's chief executive Anthony Browne.</p>
            <p>"The new administrator will take over a benchmark with better
regulatory oversight and improved governance."</p>
            <p>Thomson Reuters will continue to make the calculations until the
new entity is set up.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373284022230"
                  href="/news/business-23229300">Reckless bankers to face jail
threat</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371040134320"
                  href="/news/business-22871584">Libor change responds to scandal</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
