<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23206002"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Top banks are putting their submissions to the Treasury to run a potential Â£20bn sale of the part-nationalised Lloyds Bank."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-07T09:24:10"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68573000/jpg/_68573938_lloyds.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Banks line up to run Lloyds sale"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23206002"/>
         <title>BBC News - Banks line up to take part in Lloyds share
sale</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">7 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">10:24</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Banks line up to take part in Lloyds share
sale</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/67203000/jpg/_67203055_lloyds.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Lloyds branch facia"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The sale of the taxpayers stake in Lloyds is being
prepared although UKTI says it is not imminent</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Top banks are
putting their submissions to the Treasury to run a potential
Â£20bn sale of the nationalised part of
Lloyds Bank.</p>
            <p>Banks have until Monday to make their pitch to handle the
sell-off of the government's 39% holding in Lloyds, with the sale
of RBS, which is 81% owned by the taxpayer, to come later.</p>
            <p>The sale method has not been decided.</p>
            <p>On Friday, BBC business editor Robert Peston said approaches had
come in from some countries' sovereign wealth funds.</p>
            <p>He said private-equity businesses had also shown interest in
buying around 10% of Lloyds, either just before or simultaneous
with a more conventional placing of shares with investment
institutions,.</p>
            <p>The Sunday Times reported that Temasek, the Singapore
government's investment arm, is willing to buy 10% of Lloyds'
shares for Â£4.5bn.</p>
            <p>Temasek is a shareholder in rival UK-headquartered bank Standard
Chartered.</p>
            <p>While the method of sell-off is being considered, UK Financial
Investments (UKFI), which manages the government's shares, will
pick a shortlist of banks to handle it.</p>
            <p>Later, it will narrow down the field.</p>
            <p>UKFI said in a statement that the move was "merely planning
formally for as and when a transaction takes place" and was "by no
means an indication" that something was imminent.</p>
            <p>The Lloyds sale is expected to kick off with up to
Â£5bn of the government's holding for sale,
with a classic 1980's-style privatisation - a direct sale of the
shares to retail investors - unlikely.</p>
            <p>One method may be to offer large blocks of shares to
professional, institutional buyers, or even, as our correspondent
reports, sovereign wealth or private equity funds.</p>
            <p>The Reuters news agency said on Friday that the biggest names in
international banking were eager to take part, although the fee
income from the sale was likely to be modest when compared with
usual commercial terms.</p>
            <p>It said banks would be keen to participate for the prestige, and
mentioned HSBC, Barclays, UBS and Credit Suisse as likely to be
among them.</p>
            <p>In June, Chancellor George Osborne said the government was ready
to start selling its Lloyds shares, which on Friday were trading at
64p, above the government's breakeven price of just above 61p.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373028221939"
                  href="/news/business-23201574">Peston: Quick sale of 10% of
Lloyds?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372774619671"
                  href="/news/business-23141402">Watchdog warned Co-op over
Lloyds</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371084149322"
                  href="/news/business-22883471">MPs launch Project Verde inquiry</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
