<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23243310"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Even before the latest violence, Egypt's middle class were leaving, sparking fears of a brain drain."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-09T23:22:03"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68631000/jpg/_68631076_nabilafamily1a.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Hard choices in Egypt's middle class"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23243310"/>
         <title>BBC News - Egypt's upheaval raises middle-class brain drain
fears</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">10 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:22</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Egypt's upheaval raises middle-class brain
drain fears</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Simon
Atkinson</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Business reporter, BBC
News, Cairo</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68628000/jpg/_68628614_nabilafamily1a.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Nabily Hamdy and her four children before they left Egypt"/>
               <span style="width:624px;">Nabila Hamdy and her children are
leaving Egypt</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Since the toppling
of Hosni Mubarak in 2011, many of Egypt's middle class have felt
let down with basic state services such as education and security -
some have even decided to leave. It's a group whose talents are
vital to the country's economic future.</p>
            <p>Pushing her twin daughters back and forwards on swings in the
garden, Nabila Hamdy is all smiles.</p>
            <p>With a spacious home, four healthy children and a nanny to help
look after them, she knows she has plenty of reasons to be
contented.</p>
            <p>But part of the reason for her happiness is that she is leaving
behind the house, the garden and the nanny (not to mention her
driver) to start a new life in the UK with her husband, airline
pilot Mohamed, and youngsters Zeina, Zein, Aisha and Fatma</p>
            <p>"My husband has been wanting to leave for the past 10 years, but
I've been saying, 'No, no, it's Egypt, it's home,'" 36-year-old
Nabila says.</p>
            <p>"I'm very proud of Egypt, but since the 2011 revolution things
have been bad here, really bad. There's no police, no sense of
security, no sense of safety. You're afraid and it's scary."</p>
            <p>The move to the UK, where the couple have a house, was pretty
much complete by the time Egypt's latest power struggle saw
Mohammed Morsi forced from office.</p>
            <p>And while Nabila deplored what she argues were changes in
society under a Muslim Brotherhood-led government, especially a
sense that women were being treated as second-class citizens, the
family's minds were made up despite the power shift.</p>
            <p>"I won't have the same lifestyle, I won't have the help I am
used to," Nabila says.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68245000/jpg/_68245385_middleclass.jpg"
                 alt="Family"/>
               <p class="caption">How the middle-class revolution is changing the
world</p>
            </div>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68255000/jpg/_68255201_nmc.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="96"
                 alt="The New Middle Class"/>
            </div>
            <p>"But I will be able to guarantee that my kids will be able to
walk the streets safely, that my girls will grow up being treated
with respect. I am blessed to have this opportunity and though I
love my country, I love my kids more."</p>
            <p>Her family are at the top end of a very broad group in Egypt
that defines itself as middle class.</p>
            <p>And while numbers are hard to pin down - and though there are
some exiled Egyptians returning to their homeland - Nabila is not
alone in choosing to leave,</p>
            <p>"We're hearing there's quite a trend of a brain drain this
summer," says economist Angus Blair, president of the Cairo-based
Signet Institute.</p>
            <p>"These are people in the middle class who don't like some
societal changes that are happening - increased intolerance,
perhaps interference in the way that they live."</p>
            <p>He cites reports from one private school that 200 of the 1,500
Egyptian pupils have not been enrolled for the autumn term.</p>
            <p>And while this might be partly down to parents rethinking school
fees during a time of double-digit inflation, Mr Blair believes it
is also the result of middle-class families leaving the
country.</p>
            <p>"I think that's a shame because Egypt could do with this class
of entrepreneurs and others who also take some form of decision in
society," he adds.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68628000/gif/_68628612_afr_me_growth.gif"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="The middle class in Africa and the Middle East is projected to grow from 137 million in 2009 to 341 million by 2030"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Source: UN/Brookings
Institution</span>
            </div>
            <p>Middle-class Egyptians played a big part in the overthrow of
Hosni Mubarak early in 2011.</p>
            <p>And it was a disillusioned middle class who were among the
hundreds of thousands on the streets across Egypt last week,
pressure that led to Mohammed Morsi being pushed out as
president.</p>
            <p>It was news greeted optimistically by Samir Abdel Aziz Saber,
who lives with his wife and three children in an apartment in a
dusty Cairo suburb where donkeys still compete for space with cars
on the road.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68631000/jpg/_68631145_sameerfamily1a.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Samir Saber tutoring his children "/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Samir Saber is still paying for private schooling
even though the family's cost of living has gone up by
30%</span>
            </div>
            <p>Though his living conditions and income from work in a firm of
architects are far below those of Nabila's family, the 40-year-old
also considers himself middle class.</p>
            <p>He has no plans yet to pull his eldest boys Hassan and Said out
of private school even though he is struggling to pay the fees,
with his salary largely unchanged but the price of food up by as
much as 30%.</p>
            <p>Sitting on the sofa helping the boys with homework, he admits
one way to make money would be to find work abroad.</p>
            <p>But as he could not afford to take his family, he will not be
joining the movement of middle-class Egyptians seeking a better
life overseas.</p>
            <p>"I prefer to stay with my kids and be next to them when they are
growing up," Samir says.</p>
            <p>"I have to be with them whether the country is OK or not - I
have to be with my kids. If I think of going somewhere else, to me
this is like running away."</p>
            <div class="comment-introduction">
               <p class="introduction">Do you think of yourself as middle class?
Have you made drastic changes in your life and have become middle
class? Please tell us your story using the form below.</p>
            </div>
            <form id="comment-form"
               action="http://www.bbc.co.uk/cgi-bin/cgiemail/email/newsv6/form.txt">
               <div>
                  <input type="hidden"
                      value="Middle class brain drain 23243310"
                      name="email_subject"/>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <input type="hidden" value="Talkingpoint" name="mailto"/>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <input type="hidden"
                      value="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/10631033"
                      name="success"/>
               </div>
               <fieldset class="contact_details">
                  <label class="required" for="email_name">
                     <span class="required">(Required)</span>
                     <span class="email_name-prompt">Name</span>
                     <input type="text" size="30" id="email_name" name="email_name"/>
                  </label>
                  <label class="required" for="email_from">
                     <span class="required">(Required)</span>
                     <span class="email_from-prompt">Your E-mail address</span>
                     <input type="text" size="30" id="email_from" name="email_from"/>
                  </label>
                  <label class="required" for="email_country">
                     <span class="required">(Required)</span>
                     <span class="email_country-prompt">Town &amp; Country</span>
                     <input type="text" size="30" id="email_country" name="email_country"/>
                  </label>
                  <label class="required" for="email_telephone">
                     <span class="required">(Required)</span>
                     <span class="email_telephone-prompt">Your telephone number</span>
                     <input type="text"
                         size="30"
                         id="email_telephone"
                         name="email_telephone"/>
                  </label>
               </fieldset>
               <fieldset class="message">
                  <label class="required" for="email_comments">
                     <span class="required">(Required)</span>
                     <span class="email_comments-prompt">Comments</span>
                     <textarea rows="8" cols="30" id="email_comments" name="email_comments"/>
                  </label>
               </fieldset>
               <fieldset class="submit">
                  <p class="disclaimer">If you are happy to be contacted by a BBC
journalist please leave a telephone number that we can contact you
on. In some cases a selection of your comments will be published,
displaying your name as you provide it and location, unless you
state otherwise. Your contact details will never be published. When
sending us pictures, video or eyewitness accounts at no time should
you endanger yourself or others, take any unnecessary risks or
infringe any laws. Please ensure you have read the terms and
conditions.</p>
                  <p class="terms">
                     <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/#4">Terms and
conditions</a>
                  </p>
                  <button type="submit">
                     <span>Send</span>
                  </button>
                  <button type="reset" class="not-submit">
                     <span>Clear</span>
                  </button>
               </fieldset>
            </form>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-13845032">New
Middle Class</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371597188986"
                     href="/news/business-22951558">The global
middle class revolution <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                     </a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373238453659"
                     href="/news/business-23199502">Chinese Dream?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372632063615"
                     href="/news/business-23087135">Made in the USA?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372028413866"
                     href="/news/business-23003532">Caste or Class?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
