<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23192664"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Samsung Electronics, the world's biggest mobile phone and TV maker, has forecast weaker-than-expected profits for the April to June quarter."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-05T04:05:45"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68560000/jpg/_68560532_167256621.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Samsung profit outlook misses estimates"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23192664"/>
         <title>BBC News - Samsung issues weaker than expected profit
forecast</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">5 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">05:05</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Samsung issues weaker than expected profit
forecast</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68560000/jpg/_68560528_167256621.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Samsung Galaxy S4"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The sales of the Samsung Galaxy S4 have disappointed
some analysts</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Samsung Electronics,
the world's biggest mobile phone and TV maker, has forecast
weaker-than-expected profits for the April to June quarter.</p>
            <p>It has estimated an operating profit of 9.5 trillion won
($8.3bn; Ã‚Â£5.5bn) for the quarter. Most
analysts had expected a figure closer to 10.1tn won.</p>
            <p>The success of its smartphones has been key to Samsung's recent
growth.</p>
            <p>However there have been concerns that its growth rate may be
slowing despite the launch of new models.</p>
            <p>Samsung shares fell 3.8% after the profit guidance. Its shares
have dropped more than 15% since early June, after a various
brokerages downgraded their outlook for the firm.</p>
            <p>"The slowdown in its handset business appears to be worse than
expected and the disappointing result simply reinforces the market
view that Samsung's smartphone growth momentum is slowing," said
Lee Sei-chul, an analyst at Seoul-based Meritz Securities.</p>
            <p>Samsung has enjoyed tremendous success in
the smartphone market in recent years. The popularity of its Galaxy
range of smartphone saw it replace Nokia as the world's biggest
mobile phone maker last year.</p>
            <p>According to research firm Strategy Analytics, Samsung accounts
for almost 95% of the Android smartphone sector's profits.</p>
            <p>But despite all that success, there have been concerns in recent
weeks that the rate of growth that Samsung's smartphones have
enjoyed in recent years may be slowing, a trend that may eventually
hurt profits.</p>
            <p>Earlier this month, South Korea's Woori Investment &amp;
Securities cut its earnings forecast for the technology giant. That
was followed by similar moves from JP Morgan, Goldman Sachs,
Merrill Lynch and others.</p>
            <p>The concerns have been triggered in part by the launch of new
products from rival manufacturers as well as relatively low-cost
smartphones by Chinese firms.</p>
            <p>Analysts said that for Samsung to be able to maintain its high
growth rate the firm needed to come up with new and innovative
products and also reduce its reliance on the mobile phone business
to drive growth.</p>
            <p>"One of the biggest risks for Samsung Electronics going forward
is that 70% of total operating profit comes from mobile business,"
said Jeff Kim of Hyundai Securities.</p>
            <p>"Diversification is key. Wearable devices are the next stage in
a saturated industry that needs constant innovation to survive.</p>
            <p>"We'll see flexible smartphones in the fourth quarter from
Samsung and LG Electronics, and iWatch and Galaxy Watch are
expected to be one of the first waves."</p>
            <p>However, some analysts were sceptical about whether wearable
devices would bolster earnings.</p>
            <p>"It's more likely to complement its earnings at best," said Byun
Han-joon, an analyst at KB Investment &amp; Securities.</p>
            <p>Jung Sang-jin, a fund manager at Dongbu Asset Management, added:
"The problem is no one is sure whether these products can really
wow investors and consumers."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371772863081"
                  href="/news/technology-22983706">Is Samsung's phone strategy
smart?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1369915663656"
                  href="/news/technology-22715713">Samsung launches Galaxy S4
Mini</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372871951111"
                  href="/news/technology-23170757">Samsung buys TV firm Boxee</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">One of the biggest risks for Samsung
Electronics going forward is that 70% of total operating profit
comes from mobile business”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Jeff Kim</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Hyundai Securities</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
