<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23222318"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Shares of South Korean carrier, Asiana Airlines, fall nearly 6% in Seoul, after one of its planes crash landed in San Francisco over the weekend."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-08T06:41:34"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68599000/jpg/_68599814_68589162.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Asiana shares dip after crash landing"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23222318"/>
         <title>BBC News - Asiana shares fall after San Francisco crash
landing</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">8 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">07:41</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Asiana shares fall after San Francisco
crash landing</h1>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68590000/jpg/_68590591_hi018577735.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Plane wreckage on the runway (7 July 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:624px;">More than 300 people were on Asiana Airlines flight
which had taken off from South Korea's capital, Seoul</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Shares of South
Korean carrier, Asiana Airlines, fell nearly 6% in Seoul, after one
of its planes crash landed in San Francisco over the weekend.</p>
            <p>US investigators have said the Boeing 777 was "significantly
below" its target speed near the runway and the pilot tried to
abort the landing.</p>
            <p>The plane with 307 people came down short of runway on Saturday,
killing two people and injuring dozens.</p>
            <p>Analysts said the incident may hurt Asiana's earnings in the
near term.</p>
            <p>"Any airline that goes through a crash landing does take a hit
to its reputation in the short term," Chris De Lavigne, an
aerospace analyst with consulting form Frost &amp; Sullivan told
the BBC.</p>
            <p>"We are likely to see some people cancel their bookings and
think whether it is safe to fly Asiana, until there is sufficient
reassurance from the airline that it has found the root cause and
sorted it out."</p>
            <p>Mr Lavigne added that the airline may also have to face
additional costs in the form of fines from the authorities and
possible damages claims from some passengers.</p>
            <p>Five people are in critical condition at San Francisco General
Hospital, hospital spokesperson Rachael Kagan said. Three others
are being treated at Stanford Hospital.</p>
            <p>Altogether 181 people were taken to hospital, mostly with minor
injuries.</p>
            <p>There were 291 passengers and 16 crew on board, Asiana said. All
of the passengers have been accounted for.</p>
            <p>Deborah Hersman, the chief of the US
National Transportation Safety Board (NTSB), told a news conference
on Sunday that there was a call to increase the plane speed about
two seconds before the impact.</p>
            <p>She said the pilot then requested a "call to go around" and not
land.</p>
            <p>For its part, the South Korean airline has said that it is
currently not aware of any engine or mechanical problems.</p>
            <p>Yoon Young-doo, the head of the airline has said that he was not
ruling out human error but added the pilots were experienced
veterans.</p>
            <p>Analysts said that while it was too early to make any
conclusions, the airline needed to act fast to recover from the
incident.</p>
            <p>"The first thing for Asiana to do is to really get down to the
bottom of why this crash occurred," said Mr Lavigne.</p>
            <p>"And if it is down to human error, make sure that it puts the
procedures into place to ensure that it never happens again."</p>
            <p>However, he added that the airline had a good overall reputation
and was "very well run".</p>
            <p>As for Boeing, analysts said that the incident was unlikely to
have any impact on the plane maker's reputation, not least because
the airlines has so far ruled out any engine or mechanical
problems.</p>
            <p>The 777 aircraft is used by many major airlines and has a good
safety record.</p>
            <p>The only previous notable crash of a 777 plane occurred when a
British Airways flight landed short of the runway at London's
Heathrow Airport in 2008.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="/news/business/aerospace/">Aerospace and
Defence</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371769930599"
                     href="/news/business-22992654">'Hybrid plane' aims to cut fuel
usage</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371683396977"
                     href="/news/business-22968362">Has the fighter pilot had his
day?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371598020343"
                     href="/news/business-22954428">Will the Boeing and Airbus duopoly
crack?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371510705365"
                     href="/news/business-22937832">Bruce Dickinson's airline
ambitions</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">The first thing for Asiana to do is to
really get down to the bottom of why this crash occurred”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Chris De Lavigne</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Frost &amp; Sullivan</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
