<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23249466"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Further details of the privatisation of Royal Mail are expected to be announced in the House of Commons later."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-10T07:16:16"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68641000/jpg/_68641486_royalmailvan.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Royal Mail set for share flotation"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23249466"/>
         <title>BBC News - Royal Mail share flotation details set to be
announced</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">10 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">08:16</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Royal Mail share flotation details set to
be announced</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68641000/jpg/_68641308_royalmailvan.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="A Royal Mail van leaves the Mount Pleasant sorting office"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The Royal Mail privatisation could
happen as soon as the autumn</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Ministers are
expected to announce further details of the privatisation of Royal
Mail later.</p>
            <p>The government is expected to press ahead with its plan for a
share flotation, possibly by the autumn.</p>
            <p>The sale is likely to value the business at
Ã‚Â£2bn-Ã‚Â£3bn, and at
least 10% of shares will be set aside for postal workers.</p>
            <p>Members of the Communication Workers Union (CWU) are
overwhelmingly opposed to the privatisation.</p>
            <p>Ministers are expected to say that selling shares on the stock
market has been chosen over selling off the business to a private
operator.</p>
            <p>Companies such as TNT and DHL had been suggested as possible
buyers.</p>
            <p>Speaking on BBC Radio 4's Today programme, Business Minister
Michael Fallon said the time was now right to "free up" Royal Mail
and give it access to private capital that would allow it to
grow.</p>
            <p>"It's been turned round in the last two or three years, and it's
ready now to be a successful commercial business," he said.</p>
            <p>Royal Mail is revamping its business in order to focus less on
the delivery of letters and more on parcels, following the rapid
growth of internet shopping.</p>
            <p>A boom in parcel delivery helped Royal Mail to more than double
its profits last year, after many years of losses.</p>
            <p>Royal Mail staff may be in line for a
windfall if the government opts to give postal workers 10% of
shares at a discount or for free, as part of the share sale
plan.</p>
            <p>But a spokesman for the CWU said on Monday that postmen were
"deeply suspicious" of the idea of a share scheme.</p>
            <p>In a letter to Mr Fallon, the union warned that if the
government did not think again about the privatisation, then "the
threat to terms and conditions of postal workers will inevitably
lead to strike action".</p>
            <p>CWU general secretary, Billy Hayes, said: "Nobody outside of
government and their potential investors wants their postal service
sold. The public consistently oppose the sale and recently 96% of
workers voted against."</p>
            <p>The CWU represents about two-thirds of Royal Mail's 150,000
workforce.</p>
            <p>If the flotation goes ahead, it is likely to be one of the
biggest since large utility companies such as British Gas were
privatised in the 1980s.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68645000/jpg/_68645562_68645561.jpg"
                 alt="Dave Ward, deputy General Secretary of the Communication Workers Union"/>
               <p class="caption">Dave Ward, CWU: "If you bring in private owners
to Royal Mail they will change the priorities of the company"</p>
            </div>
            <p>The flotation will not include the Post Office. The two are
separate companies with independent boards. The Royal Mail sorts
and delivers letters and parcels, while the Post Office is the
national network of branches that offer postal, governmental and
financial services. The Post Office itself is not for sale.</p>
            <p>The sell-off of Royal Mail is not a big surprise - the
government enacted the necessary legislation through the Postal
Services Act 2011. The idea was first mooted under the last Labour
government.</p>
            <p>Chuka Umunna MP, Labour's shadow business secretary, said the
government was pushing ahead with the privatisation simply to "dig
the Chancellor, George Osborne, out of a hole of his own
making".</p>
            <p>"There are still huge unresolved issues around competition, and
ministers haven't said how much capital they expect the business
will be able to raise after privatisation or how the proceeds of
the sale will be used," he said.</p>
            <p>The Royal Mail can trace its history back to a forerunner
established in 1516 during the reign of Henry VIII. The General
Post Office (GPO) was then brought into being in 1660. Adhesive
postage stamps were introduced in 1840.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373410832515"
                  href="/news/business-23249762">Robert Peston: Privatisation
paradox</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372691733338"
                  href="/news/business-23131325">Union rejects Royal Mail pay
rise</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371647350576"
                  href="/news/business-22973480">Postal workers reject
privatisation</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Unlike the great privatisations of the past,
of the gas, electricity and telecoms industry, there will be no
aggressive attempt to sell the shares to individuals - there will
be no campaign such as the famous 'Tell Sid' adverts of the 1980s
for the flotation of British Gas”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <div class="correspondent-byline">
               <a href="/news/correspondents/robertpeston/">
                  <span class="byline-picture">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/53409000/jpg/_53409471_peston-112x81.jpg"
                       alt="image of Robert Peston"/>
                  </span>
               </a>
               <a href="/news/correspondents/robertpeston/">
                  <span class="byline-name">Robert Peston</span>
               </a>
               <span class="byline-title">Business editor</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/correspondents/robertpeston/">Read more from
Robert</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
