<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23095938"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A new documentary for Radio 4 by Robert Peston examines how computers, not humans, do most of the trading on financial markets these days."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-07T23:08:01"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68600000/jpg/_68600834_178bb998-f08b-4fad-a03a-66d8c2c2bd0d.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Dark magic: Rise of robot traders"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23095938"/>
         <title>BBC News - A dark magic: The rise of the robot
traders</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">8 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:08</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">A dark magic: The rise of the robot
traders</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Laurence
Knight</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Business reporter, BBC
News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68566000/jpg/_68566762_robotsindexpicv2copy.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="New York Stock Exchange traders in 1987 (left) and computer servers (right)"/>
               <span style="width:624px;">Trading places: The frantic dealer
floors of the 1980s have been replaced by vast ranks of computer
servers</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">"Humans cannot
compete on speed, it's as simple as that."</p>
            <p>Ten years ago, John Coates was a trader in Wall Street.</p>
            <p>Today, he is a neuroscientist at Cambridge University, and
spends his days monitoring traders' hormones to see what makes them
tick.</p>
            <p>"There are simple tests you can do. When you see a green
light... you click a mouse. The fastest you can do that is 100 to
120 milliseconds. Any basic cognitive processing, figuring things
out, then maybe 200 to 300 milliseconds.</p>
            <p>"The trouble is, the boxes - last time I looked - they were
processing a trade in 10 milliseconds, and today I think... we're
talking about millionths of a second."</p>
            <p>Those "boxes" are the robot traders - computers that make their
own decisions about when to buy and sell, but a thousand times
faster than any human can.</p>
            <p>When you think of a trading floor in
London or New York, perhaps you imagine a gaggle of sweaty men
elbowing each other out of the way as they use elaborate finger
movements to convey their frantic orders.</p>
            <p>It's an image popularised by the 1980s comedy Trading Places.
<a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/an-oral-history-of-trading-places-2013-6">
But it's also 30 years out of date</a>.</p>
            <p>For the fact is that financial trading has undergone a
computerised revolution akin to Amazon's takeover of the High
Street. All the real action has moved to cyberspace.</p>
            <p>Take the New York Stock Exchange. These days, most trading does
not take place behind its famous neoclassical facade just off Wall
Street, but in far less glamorous New Jersey.</p>
            <p>That is where the NYSE has set up a vast electronic trading
facility covering 10 acres (four hectares), housing row upon row of
computer servers.</p>
            <p>And many more acres are occupied by the servers of the robot
trading firms hooked up to it.</p>
            <p>Computerised trading is an inherently secretive world.</p>
            <p>The trading firms keep a tight hold of their trading strategies,
people and computer code (or "algorithms").</p>
            <p>Otherwise a rival might figure out their
complex-yet-fully-automated trading patterns, and then copy them,
or worse still, dupe their computers into handing over
millions.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68604000/jpg/_68604887_102705264-1.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Liffe floor traders in 1992"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The loadsamoney traders of the 1980s
have been consigned to the dustbin of history</span>
            </div>
            <p>Remco Lenterman, the head of one such firm, IMC in the
Netherlands, is trying to demystify his business.</p>
            <p>He says: "In the old days, 10 years ago, a desk of equity
traders would have between 80 and 100 of human traders at an
investment bank. Today there's maybe eight of them left.</p>
            <p>"What they do is operate algos that effectively are mimicking
what traders used to do, and they're tweaking constantly these
algos and monitoring the risk of what goes on in the market."</p>
            <p>In other words, the iconic high-testosterone Loadsamoney traders
of the past - the "Masters of the Universe" derided by the American
author Tom Wolfe in the Bonfire of the Vanities - have been ousted
by "quants", the nerdy brainboxes who design and run the computer
programmes.</p>
            <p>In <a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/newsweek/2013/01/04/eunuchs-of-the-universe-tom-wolfe-on-wall-street-today.html">
a recent post-script to his novel written for the Daily Beast</a>,
Tom Wolfe lamented the emasculation of his anti-heroes, renaming
them "Eunochs of the Universe".</p>
            <p>Firms such as Lenterman's make their money by scraping a tiny
profit margin on an unthinkably huge volume of rapid-fire buying
and selling.</p>
            <p>Different algo traders use very different strategies. But they
all share the need to identify trading opportunities - fleeting
discrepancies between the available market price and where the
computer deems the price ought to be - and then react to them
faster than anyone else.</p>
            <p>It is called the "race to zero". And it
has led to the investment of billions of dollars in faster, smarter
computers, and in the fastest possible connections.</p>
            <p>At stock exchanges across the planet, traders pay hefty fees to
"co-locate" their servers directly next to the exchanges.</p>
            <p>And hundreds of millions have been spent on <a href="http://www.wired.com/business/2012/08/ff_wallstreet_trading/2/">building
straighter cables</a> to shave a few fractions of a second off the
time it takes to transmit orders between the world's big trading
centres: London, New York, Chicago and Tokyo.</p>
            <p>All this can seem a little irrational when the UK and US
governments are struggling to scrape together enough money to
upgrade the infrastructure needed to ferry humans from one place to
another.</p>
            <p>There is, however, a darker side to this rush to
computerise.</p>
            <p>For example, accidents can happen.</p>
            <p>Last August, the hi-tech financial firm Knight Capital was
brought to the verge of bankruptcy by an algorithm that went
haywire, <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-19214294">racking up more than
$440m of losses in just 45 minutes</a> before it was switched
off.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the most famous mishap was the now legendary Flash
Crash, at 2.45pm in New York on 6 May 2010.</p>
            <p>In a few minutes the New York Stock Exchange plunged, and then
just as suddenly recovered again. Share prices in some firms, such
as the consultancy Accenture, plummeted to a fraction above zero,
while Apple soared to $100,000.</p>
            <p>For months afterwards, nobody could explain what had gone
wrong.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/47820000/jpg/_47820157_jex_689006_de27-1.jpg"
                 alt="Wall Street "/>
               <p class="caption">For days afterwards, the New York Flash Crash of
6 May 2010 left investors and regulators perplexed</p>
            </div>
            <p>
               <a href="http://www.sec.gov/news/studies/2010/marketevents-report.pdf">The
official US regulatory investigation</a> said it had been triggered
by a single order, placed by a large institution, using an
algorithmic trading strategy.</p>
            <p>But, what made things far worse was a "hot potato" effect: amid
the confusion, one by one the robot traders tried to cut and run,
and the stock exchange's computers got swamped.</p>
            <p>The new algorithmic traders have also been accused of some
fairly old-school nefarious behaviour.</p>
            <p>Eric Hunsader, of the US data analysis firm Nanex, says
miniature versions of the Flash Crash happen in individual stocks
many times a day, and he alleges that a lot of it is outright
manipulation.</p>
            <p>He has produced charts <a href="http://www.nanex.net/FlashCrash/OngoingResearch.html">depicting
the weird and wonderful behaviour of markets</a>, as computers seek
to outfox one another by rapidly generating and then cancelling
thousands of orders a second.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68432000/jpg/_68432019_178bb998-f08b-4fad-a03a-66d8c2c2bd0d.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Nanex chart showing trading during the Google flash crash"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">A Nanex chart illustrating the Google
mini-flash crash of 22 April this year</span>
            </div>
            <p>"We allow people with faster connections to place and remove
offers or bids faster than the speed of light can deliver that
information to the other market participants."</p>
            <p>And he is not the only one concerned that some computerised
traders might be up to no good.</p>
            <p>"Unfortunately the nature of markets is that there always is
potential for abusive activity, and with very, very fast trading,
these things can happen very, very fast," says Martin Wheatley,
head of the UK's newly created Financial Conduct Authority.</p>
            <p>"Frankly, for the regulator, it creates a problem trying to pick
out from the vast amount of data trades that potentially might be
abusive."</p>
            <p>
               <strong>
                  <em>A Dark Magic, presented by BBC Business Editor
Robert Peston, will be broadcast on Radio 4 at 0900 on 8 July 2013,
and</em>
               </strong>
               <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/radio/bbc_radio_four/20130708">will
be available on the BBC iPlayer
afterwards</a>
               <strong>
                  <em>.</em>
               </strong>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1344642443998"
                  href="/news/magazine-19214294">The $440m computer glitch</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1330884572855"
                  href="/news/business-17034801">Business turns to algorithms</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1316769273180"
                  href="/news/business-14860424">What is
electronic trading? <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68512000/jpg/_68512352_68512351.jpg"
              width="144"
              height="81"
              alt="Remco Lenterman"/>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">They operate algos that effectively are
mimicking what traders used to do”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Remco Lenterman</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Director of trading firm IMC</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Race to zero</h2>
            <p>The options available late last year for anyone wanting to send
an electronic trade order between New York and Chicago:</p>
            <div class="data-table-outer">
               <table class="data-table">
                  <colgroup>
                     <col width="1*"/>
                     <col width="1*"/>
                     <col width="1*"/>
                     <col width="1*"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                     <tr class="colheading">
                        <th class="left">Route</th>
                        <th class="left">Complete</th>
                        <th class="left">Length (miles)</th>
                        <th class="left">Speed* (milli- secs)</th>
                     </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Original fibre optic cable</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="right">
                           <p>1980s</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="right">
                           <p>c1,000</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="right">
                           <p>14.5</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr class="row2">
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Spread Networks fibre optic cable</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="right">
                           <p>August</p>
                           <p>2010</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="right">
                           <p>825</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="right">
                           <p>13.1</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>McKay Brothers microwave beams</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="right">
                           <p>July</p>
                           <p>2012</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="right">
                           <p>744</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="right">
                           <p>9</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr class="row2">
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Tradeworx microwave beams</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="right">
                           <p>Late</p>
                           <p>2012</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="right">
                           <p>c731</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="right">
                           <p>c8.5</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
            </div>
            <p>*time required for a complete round-trip</p>
            <p>
               <a href="http://www.wired.com/business/2012/08/ff_wallstreet_trading/2/">Source:
Wired Magazine</a>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
