<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23141396"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Business confidence in the UK is at its highest level since 2007 and the economy is slowly strengthening, a survey from a leading business group suggests."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T10:41:40"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68494000/jpg/_68494487_cargo2.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Firms' confidence 'at six-year high'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23141396"/>
         <title>BBC News - UK business confidence 'at six-year high'</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">11:41</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">UK business confidence 'at six-year
high'</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68493000/jpg/_68493942_cargo2.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Cargo port"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Export sales have boosted the UK's economic
prospects, the BCC says</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Business confidence
in the UK is at its highest level since 2007, the latest economic
survey from a leading business group has suggested.</p>
            <p>The quarterly survey from the British Chambers of Commerce (BCC)
is the latest indication that the UK's economic recovery is
strengthening.</p>
            <p>There was further good news from a survey of the UK's
construction sector.</p>
            <p>The Markit/CIPS purchasing managers' index indicated the sector
grew for the second month in a row in June.</p>
            <p>"The UK upturn is slowly strengthening," said David Kern, the
BCC's chief economist.</p>
            <p>The BCC said export sales had grown by their fastest rate since
it began publishing its survey in 1989.</p>
            <p>It now expects GDP to grow by 0.6% in the
second quarter of 2013.</p>
            <p>That is significantly more positive than its previous forecast,
where it predicted growth of 0.9% for the whole year.</p>
            <p>The survey adds to a slew of recent positive data suggesting the
UK economy is beginning to strengthen after a long and slow
recovery from the global financial crisis.</p>
            <p>On Monday, PMI data also suggested UK manufacturing is growing
at its fastest rate in two years, while Bank of England figures
showed that mortgage approvals hit a three-and-a-half-year high in
May.</p>
            <p>Last week, official data showed the services sector, which
accounts for about three-quarters of the economy, was continuing to
grow.</p>
            <p>Mr Kern said the services sector in particular was benefitting
from rising exports.</p>
            <p>"The remarkable export balances show that the service sector is
capable of increasing its trade surplus over time and can work to
reduce our overall trade deficit," he said.</p>
            <p>"Developing the export potential of this sector is critical to
long-term prosperity."</p>
            <p>The BCC said the number of businesses looking to export had
increased in the face of a flat domestic market, and exporters were
increasingly looking to the rest of the world outside Europe.</p>
            <p>However, there are still concerns that the recovery could yet be
derailed.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68499000/jpg/_68499279_68499278.jpg"
                 alt="John Longworth"/>
               <p class="caption">John Longworth, BCC, warns the UK's economic
recovery is "not in the bag yet"</p>
            </div>
            <p>Speaking on BBC Radio 4's Today programme, BCC director general
John Longworth said there had been "false dawns" of recovery
before, where business expansion had been choked off by banks being
unwilling to lend the money required.</p>
            <p>He also said inflation remained a worry among businesses.</p>
            <p>But UK businessman Luke Johnson, the former chairman of Pizza
Express, told the BBC he believed there was a "real recovery" under
way.</p>
            <p>"I think the consistency of all the surveys and statistics
coming through over the last six to 12 months is pretty
compelling," he said.</p>
            <p>"I sense a rising tide of animal spirits. Of course there are
always threats and challenges ahead [but] sentiment is now much
better, and this is now a real recovery."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/in_depth/business/2010/uk_economy/default.stm">
UK Economy</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1366878650633"
                     href="/news/business-22277954">GDP explained</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1295026445854"
                     href="/news/business-12196322">What is inflation?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1317896067946"
                     href="/news/business-15198789">What is quantitative easing?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story" rel="published-1273786194505" href="/news/10108284">What is a rating agency?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/48701000/jpg/_48701041_hughpym.jpg"
                    alt="image of Hugh Pym"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Hugh
Pym</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Chief economics
correspondent, BBC News</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>Two swallows don't make a summer and two positive economic
indicators don't guarantee a sustainable recovery.</p>
            <p>But the upbeat noises from the British Chambers of Commerce and
construction purchasing managers today (and manufacturing
yesterday) reinforce the assumption amongst many economists that
growth picked up in the second quarter of this year.</p>
            <p>It adds up to a brighter background to Mark Carney's first
Monetary Policy Committee meeting at the Bank of England.</p>
            <p>On Thursday he will have to cast his first vote alongside
colleagues who have voted against a further loosening of policy in
recent months.</p>
            <p>There is little in recent data which might persuade the six out
of nine on the committee who have voted against more money creation
(quantitative easing) to change their minds.</p>
            <p>So Mr Carney will have to decide whether to go along with them
or start off his tenure in a minority favouring more quantitative
easing, as his predecessor Sir Mervyn King was.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
