<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23267381"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="China agrees to resume talks on a bilateral investment treaty with the US which could open up new opportunities for businesses in both the countries."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-12T01:38:41"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68687000/jpg/_68687374_173212826-1.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="China to resume US investment talks"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23267381"/>
         <title>BBC News - China agrees to resume US investment treaty
talks</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">12 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:38</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">China agrees to resume US investment
treaty talks</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68687000/jpg/_68687122_china.notes.jpg"
                 alt="Yuan notes"/>
               <p class="caption">The proposed investment treaty is likely to make
it easier for US companies to invest in China.</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">China has agreed to
resume talks on a bilateral investment treaty with the US which
could open up new opportunities for businesses in both
countries.</p>
            <p>Chinese officials have agreed to include all sectors in the
treaty, the first time Beijing has done so.</p>
            <p>The US has been pushing for such a deal as American firms have
been keen to get more access to the Chinese market amid growing
consumer demand there.</p>
            <p>A deal could see key sectors in China open up to investment by
US firms.</p>
            <p>"A high standard US-China bilateral investment treaty is a
priority for the United States and would work to level the playing
field for American workers and businesses by opening markets for
fair competition,'' Treasury Secretary Jacob Lew said in a
statement.</p>
            <p>"The commitment made today stands to be a significant
breakthrough and marks the first time China has agreed to negotiate
a Bilateral Investment Treaty, to include all sectors and stages of
investment, with another country," he added.</p>
            <p>The decision to restart the talks was reached at high-level
negotiations between the two countries held in the US.</p>
            <p>China's Vice Premier Wang Yang said that US had agreed to accept
investment by Chinese state-owned enterprises and sovereign wealth
funds.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68687000/jpg/_68687350_173313556.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="US and Chinese official at bi-lateral talks held in Washington"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The world's two largest economies have
been looking to boost bi-lateral ties</span>
            </div>
            <p>"The United States pledges to treat Chinese investment equally
and fairly," Mr Wang was quoted as saying by the Associated Press
news agency.</p>
            <p>Boosted by their success back home, Chinese firms have been keen
to boost their presence in the US - the world's largest economy.
However, some of the moves by Chinese companies into the US market
have faced close scrutiny.</p>
            <p>Earlier this week, members of the Senate Agriculture Committee
in the US expressed concerns over the China's Shuanghui
International deal to buy Virginia-based Smithfield Foods, the
biggest US pork firm.</p>
            <p>Last year, a US Congressional panel warned Chinese telecom firms
Huawei and ZTE pose a security threat to the US, adding that the
two firms should be barred from any US mergers and
acquisitions.</p>
            <p>The two firms have defended themselves and denied those
claims.</p>
            <p>In September, President Barack Obama blocked a move by Chinese
company, Ralls Corp, to build wind turbines in the US state of
Oregon, citing national security concerns.</p>
            <p>It was the first foreign investment to be blocked in the US for
22 years.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373422869070"
                  href="/news/business-23251089">China's exports and imports
decline</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1369079036267"
                  href="/news/business-22601503">China 'can't be free rider on
trade'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1352184948457"
                  href="/news/business-20177210">US - China: Trade flashpoints</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
