<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23140774"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Our correspondents around Asia have been finding out how the recent big currency movements are affecting people and businesses."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-09T23:52:34"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68567000/jpg/_68567356_637.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Who is affected by big currency movements?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23140774"/>
         <title>BBC News - Who is affected by big currency
movements?</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">10 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:52</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Who is affected by big currency
movements?</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68538000/jpg/_68538793_637.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Notes"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Some of the largest
economies in Asia have seen big movements in the value of their
currencies in recent months.</p>
            <p>Other than domestic factors, the potential tapering off of the
US Federal Reserve's cheap cash injections is partly responsible
for the volatility.</p>
            <p>The US central bank's moves had allowed billions of dollars of
inflows into emerging economies, and now that money is leaving and
it is having an impact on their economies.</p>
            <p>For some countries in the region which rely on exports to drive
growth, it helps to have a weaker currency. For others that have to
import a lot of what the country needs, it is not beneficial.</p>
            <p>Our correspondents around the region have been finding out how
the currency movements are affecting people and businesses.</p>
            <h2 class="section-header" id="heading-1">Indian rupee - Yogita
Limaye, Mumbai</h2>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68493000/jpg/_68493303_india.jpg"
                 alt="Worker at Indian drug company"/>
               <p class="caption">Yogita Limaye on the fall in the value of the
rupee</p>
            </div>
            <p>India's currency has been in freefall recently. Over the past
few months the rupee has fallen nearly 15% touching record lows and
crossing the psychological level of 60 to the US dollar. Stock
markets have been in disarray due to the currency's poor
performance.</p>
            <p>India's finance minister, P Chidambaram, has indicated that this
is a global trend and so there isn't any reason to panic, but the
Indian rupee has been among the worst performing currencies in
Asia.</p>
            <p>Some economists say that the recent slide has been due to global
factors, particularly because of the strengthening of the dollar
and signals from the US that it may start cutting down on stimulus
spending.</p>
            <p>Several sectors are being badly affected,
prime among these, are petroleum companies and automotive
manufacturers who rely heavily on imports. The falling rupee could
widen India's current account deficit, which has already been a big
concern for the country.</p>
            <p>Analysts say what is more worrying than the weak level of the
currency is how volatile it's been over the last few months.</p>
            <p>Many firms have put a hold on business, waiting for some
stability. "I'm not taking any new imports, any new consignments
until there is some stabilisation. We fear that the dollar may even
go to 65 rupees," says Lal Hazari, an electrical goods dealer in
Mumbai.</p>
            <p>The currency fall comes at a bad time for India. The country has
just begun to recover from the slowest growth in a decade, and a
weakening rupee may hurt any recent improvements in the country's
economic situation.</p>
            <p>Inflation, which has been easing in recent months could rise
again. Gas and oil prices have already been hiked. Experts say the
currency depreciation could also have an impact on the fiscal
deficit, which has been narrowing over the past few months.</p>
            <p>While India's central bank has stepped in a few times to sell
dollars and stem the slide, experts say that these are only
short-term measures and what the country needs are long-term
solutions like kickstarting the investment cycle in India and
increasing foreign cash inflows.</p>
            <h3 class="section-header" id="heading-1-1">Philippine peso -
Jennifer Pak, Hong Kong</h3>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68515000/jpg/_68515704_filipino.jpg"
                 alt="Filipino maid in Hong Kong"/>
               <p class="caption">Jennifer Pak meets Filipino maids who are
finding that they can send less back home</p>
            </div>
            <p>Capital flows into Asia have pushed up the Philippine peso
against the US dollar and one of the groups feeling the pinch the
most is overseas workers.</p>
            <p>Domestic helpers in Hong Kong may earn less than half of the
average salary in the Chinese territory, but they are able to boost
local consumption and support their families back in the
Philippines.</p>
            <p>Myrna Nejar is one of the 159,000 Filipino maids in Hong Kong
feeling the pressure. The wage she earns supports her daughter,
granddaughter and elderly mother back in the Philippines.</p>
            <p>Just before the global financial crisis
hit in 2008, Ms Nejar sent three-quarters of her salary back home.
Since the local currency is pegged to the US dollar it amounted to
roughly 16,700 Philippine pesos.</p>
            <p>But after successive rounds of quantitative easing by the US
Federal Reserve, the US dollar has weakened and investment flowing
into the Philippines has diluted the value of Ms Nejar's wage.</p>
            <p>She is now sending roughly 20% less Philippine pesos back
home.</p>
            <p>It's a big adjustment for her 79-year-old mother Sophia Nejar.
"I have to budget very carefully now. I eat less meat so that I can
still buy my medicine and milk," she tells the BBC through an
internet-based video call from her home in the Philippine province
of Antique.</p>
            <p>Filipino maids try to find ways to send home the same amount of
Philippine peso as before. Many resort to borrowing. Others cut
back on their own spending in Hong Kong on food and clothing.</p>
            <p>The sacrifices made by domestic helpers worked. Last year, they
were among the millions of overseas Filipinos who sent a record
$21bn to the Philippines. It has moved families out of slums and
helped them join the emerging middle class.</p>
            <p>For many domestic helpers in Hong Kong though, it's a struggle
to keep up the momentum.</p>
            <h3 class="section-header" id="heading-1-2">Chinese yuan - John
Sudworth, Shanghai</h3>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68538000/jpg/_68538403_china.jpg"
                 alt="Worker in Chinese metal factory"/>
               <p class="caption">John Sudworth on the strengthening yuan</p>
            </div>
            <p>Ten years ago this month a group of senators wrote a letter to
the US Treasury Secretary urging him to stop China cheating on its
currency, and they've been at it ever since.</p>
            <p>Just last month yet another attempt was made to introduce a law
designed, in large part, to punish China for keeping the yuan, or
renminbi, artificially weak.</p>
            <p>It may have appreciated some 35% since 2003, the argument goes,
but it is still too weak. Just look at the growing trade
deficit.</p>
            <p>A trip to the EAE Automotive Equipment Company factory in
Suzhou, in eastern China, suggests Washington might have a
point.</p>
            <p>Up to 80% of the hydraulic vehicle lifts made here are for
export.</p>
            <p>The boss, Zhang Shujun, tells me that the rising currency is not
yet causing real pain because much of it has been offset by the
falling price of Chinese steel.</p>
            <p>Nonetheless, they are noticing an effect - this year alone a 3%
dip in profits, she says, directly as a result of the renminbi
price. She is not keen for it to strengthen further, faster.</p>
            <p>The more interesting question though is not about the correct
value of the renminbi right now. Rather, it is about why China has
been allowing it to strengthen, albeit slowly, for the past 10
years.</p>
            <p>The answer might be something to do with the now well-documented
great Chinese rebalancing act - the shifting of priorities away
from an export and investment based economy.</p>
            <p>A stronger currency, of course, helps in this regard, by
boosting consumer demand. So some analysts expect the renminbi to
continue its steady trajectory for a little while longer.</p>
            <p>Maybe all the US needs is a bit more patience.</p>
            <h3 class="section-header" id="heading-1-3">South Korean won - Lucy
Williamson, Seoul</h3>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68560000/jpg/_68560285_68560284.jpg"
                 alt="yen chart"/>
               <p class="caption">Lucy Williamson on the impact of the yen's
weakness on Japanese tourist arrivals in South Korea</p>
            </div>
            <p>South Korea is paying close attention to Japan's new economic
policies.</p>
            <p>Nicknamed "Abenomics" after Japan's new, nationalist prime
minister, the new policies have led to a dramatic shift in the
value of the yen.</p>
            <p>This has made Korean goods more expensive for Japanese consumers
- a worrying trend for South Korea, which relies on exports.</p>
            <p>Trade between the two countries was worth more than $100bn last
year - less than half that between South Korea and China, but
nevertheless still enough to make Tokyo one of Seoul's top trading
partners.</p>
            <p>Some smaller companies say it's they who are bearing the brunt
of that currency volatility, as Korea's big multinationals which
underpin the economy pass on the costs to their contractors.</p>
            <p>But the weakening yen has also made Korea itself more expensive
for the Japanese to visit. South Korea's Tourism Organisation says
the number of Japanese visitors increased by around a third in the
first half of last year, but has since declined, with no sign of a
rebound.</p>
            <p>Seoul's restaurants, shopping malls and popstars are all big
draws for Japanese visitors - many of whom return year after
year.</p>
            <p>"Of course the exchange rate is a problem," says Choi Yoon Jea,
the head of a kimchi-making school set up for tourists in Seoul,
"because the biggest reason Japanese come here is for
shopping."</p>
            <p>But many of those in the industry, including Mr Choi, say
there's more to the drop in visitors than simple economics - and
that politics is playing a part as well, as the ongoing diplomatic
coolness between the two countries continues.</p>
            <h3 class="section-header" id="heading-1-4">Australian dollar -
Phil Mercer, Sydney</h3>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68470000/jpg/_68470863_auz.jpg"
                 alt="Worker in Australian sheet metal factory"/>
               <p class="caption">Phil Mercer on problems caused by Australia's
strong currency</p>
            </div>
            <p>The over-achieving Australian dollar has spent much of the past
three years lording it above its American cousin.</p>
            <p>Life beyond parity with the greenback has been especially
painful for Australian manufacturers and tourism. It has made
imports cheaper, and has sent the price of many exports
soaring.</p>
            <p>"It's largely changed the landscape of the Australian industrial
outlook," says Michael McCarthy, an analyst at CMC Markets. "A high
Australian dollar meant that our rigid labour markets and high cost
of labour has put most of manufacturing into an uncompetitive
position."</p>
            <p>To survive, firms have had to innovate. Competition from China
and Taiwan has forced Lifestyle BBQs, a family-run company in
Sydney, to shift its focus away from the low-cost end of the
market, to premium sales.</p>
            <p>"There are a lot of products available to customers who want to
purchase a barbecue at very low prices, because of the high
Australian dollar," says owner Blair Boaden. "You can walk into a
store and it's available for between 400 and 800 [Australian]
dollars. And it all seems perfectly adequate. Whereas our product
sells in the equivalent form for between 2,500 and 3,500
dollars."</p>
            <p>However, in recent months there have been many pressures on the
Aussie dollar; from the strength of the US and Chinese economies,
to interest rates and the softening of the mining boom.</p>
            <p>And that has provided some much-needed relief for those weighed
down by a muscular currency. The mighty "Aussie" has lost more than
10% of its value since mid-April.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370828146762"
                  href="/news/business-22836198">Impact on
Japan of a volatile yen <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372318344562"
                  href="/news/world-asia-india-23077632">Indian media: Concerns over
rupee's fall</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1340207912720"
                  href="/news/business-18516467">Hong Kong debates currency peg</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">"I'm not taking any new imports, any new
consignments until there is some stabilisation. We fear that the
dollar may even go to 65 rupees”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Lal Hazari</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Electric goods dealer</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">I have to budget very carefully now. I eat
less meat so that I can still buy my medicine and milk”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Sophia Nejar</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Mother of Filipino maid</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
