<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-22954586"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Measures including criminal sanctions to make bankers responsible for their own failings, are called for in a new report."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T14:48:51"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68264000/jpg/_68264209_canarywharfbankingprotest.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Jail reckless bankers, report urges"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-22954586"/>
         <title>BBC News - Jail reckless bankers, standards commission
urges</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">15:48</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Jail reckless bankers, standards
commission urges</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68252000/jpg/_68252085_cityoflondonskyline.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="City of London skyline"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The commission was highly critical of
aspects of the banking industry</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Senior bankers guilty of reckless
misconduct should be jailed, a long-awaited report on banking
commissioned by the government has recommended.</p>
            <p>The cross-party Parliamentary Commission on Banking Standards'
fifth report said bankers should in future be accountable for their
actions.</p>
            <p>It also said some bonuses should be withheld for up to 10
years.</p>
            <p>The Treasury welcomed the report, calling it "a very impressive
piece of work".</p>
            <p>It promised to provide a response before the summer recess.</p>
            <p>The commission was set up by Chancellor
George Osborne last year after a number of scandals involving the
industry.</p>
            <p>
               <a href="http://www.parliament.uk/business/committees/committees-a-z/joint-select/professional-standards-in-the-banking-industry/news/changing-banking-for-good-report/">
The 571-page report also called on the government</a> to review
alternatives for selling off the Royal Bank of Scotland (RBS),
including breaking it up, and demanded action to make the banking
market more competitive.</p>
            <p>The robustly-worded report said: "Too many bankers, especially
at the most senior levels, have operated in an environment with
insufficient personal responsibility.</p>
            <p>"Senior executives were aware that they would not be punished
for what they could not see and promptly donned the blindfolds.</p>
            <p>"Where they could not claim ignorance, they fell back on the
claim that everyone was party to a decision, so that no individual
could be held squarely to blame - the Murder on the Orient Express
defence."</p>
            <p>The report advocated:</p>
            <ul>
               <li>senior bankers should be assigned clear personal
responsibilities, with the legal onus on them to show they have
done all that is reasonably required</li>
               <li>recklessly disregarding these responsibilities should be made a
criminal offence - including a possible prison sentence</li>
               <li>senior bankers should adhere to a new set of banking standards
set by regulators</li>
               <li>bonus pay for bankers should be deferred for up to 10 years and
cancelled if a banker misbehaves</li>
               <li>banks should be legally required to put financial safety ahead
of shareholder interests</li>
            </ul>
            <p>Shadow chancellor Ed Balls said the report offered a blueprint
for the "radical change" needed. He said: "We need our banks
working well in the future - this report shows us what to do."</p>
            <p>Liberal Democrat peer Lord Oakeshott said: "Why are there no
banged-up bankers? That's what most people want to know after the
last five years of scandals and shame."</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68251000/jpg/_68251362_ed.jpg"
                 alt="Ed Balls"/>
               <p class="caption">Ed Balls "This report sets out the blueprint on
pay, transparency and accountability"</p>
            </div>
            <p>However, former RBS chairman and chief executive Sir George
Mathewson questioned the plan to defer bonuses for 10 years.</p>
            <p>He told the BBC: "I find that a little strange. If you are going
to have bonuses, they are to incentivise behaviours. Ten years out
is not an easy way to imagine incentivisation occurring."</p>
            <p>The report called for more to be done to boost competition among
banks, including two further investigations.</p>
            <p>One, by a government panel of experts, would look at how to make
it easier for people to transfer their bank accounts, while the
other would be a full investigation of retail banking and small
business lending by the Competition and Markets Authority
(CMA).</p>
            <p>The CMA is due to be launched next April, and will replace the
Office of Fair Trading (OFT) and the Competition Commission.</p>
            <p>Following the publication of the parliamentary commission's
report, the OFT said it was "bringing forward" an inquiry into the
provision of banking services to small and medium-sized
businesses.</p>
            <p>"Our review of SME banking is part of an ongoing planned
programme of work in this area to allow the Competition and Markets
Authority to decide whether or not to make a market investigation
reference by 2015," said OFT chief executive Clive Maxwell.</p>
            <p>Consumer watchdog Which? welcomed the
proposals, saying it could herald "the big change in banking that
consumers have been crying out for".</p>
            <p>But the group said more needed to be done to change banking
culture and highlighted the male-dominated culture on trading
floors, it said banks should be forced to take action if there was
a significant imbalance.</p>
            <p>
               <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-22966314">On RBS,
the committee only said that the government should</a> formally
consider alternative options for the nationalised bank by
September.</p>
            <p>The report also called for an end to the government's
purportedly "arms-length" ownership of RBS and Lloyds via the
holding company UKFI - an arrangement set up under Gordon Brown and
described as a "fig leaf" disguising the government's increasing
interference in the running of the two banks, especially RBS.</p>
            <p>The committee also criticised the failure of regulators to spot
the risks building up in the financial system prior to 2008,
demanding "the replacement of mechanical data collection and box
ticking by a much greater emphasis on the exercise of
judgement".</p>
            <p>Senior regulators should also be
personally accountable, ultimately to Parliament, for their
oversight of the banks.</p>
            <p>The report recommended that each bank's board should be required
to institute procedures to protect whistle-blowers - employees who
want to flag up misconduct to the regulators.</p>
            <p>The Financial Services Authority, the overall banking regulator
up to and during the financial crisis, has been split into two
separate units - the Financial Conduct Authority, which polices
banker behaviour, and the Bank of England's Prudential Regulation
Authority, which ensures the banks do not take excessive risks.</p>
            <p>If either regulator spots a pattern of shoddy standards at a
bank, the commission said that the two should be able to put the
bank into "special measures".</p>
            <p>The committee repeated its demand that the chancellor allow
regulators to set a more conservative "leverage ratio" for the
banks.</p>
            <p>The leverage ratio is the minimum amount of loss-absorbing
capital that a bank must hold, as a percentage of its total loans
and investments.</p>
            <p>Mr Osborne has said the limit should be set at 3%, in line with
a new international requirement from the Basel committee of central
bankers. But the committee has the figure should be much
higher.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">There is a very lively debate, which the
Banking Commission has stoked up, about whether RBS needs to be
reconstructed”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <div class="correspondent-byline">
               <a href="/news/correspondents/robertpeston/">
                  <span class="byline-picture">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/53409000/jpg/_53409471_peston-112x81.jpg"
                       alt="image of Robert Peston"/>
                  </span>
               </a>
               <a href="/news/correspondents/robertpeston/">
                  <span class="byline-name">Robert Peston</span>
               </a>
               <span class="byline-title">Business editor</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/correspondents/robertpeston/">Read more from
Robert</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">The real game changer in UK retail banking
will be when the likes of Google, Amazon or Apple decide to enter
the market”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Peter Hahn</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Cass Business School</span>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/business-22936948" class="quote-link">When will
banking ever change?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>The commission explained</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>The Parliamentary Commission on Banking Standards was appointed
in July 2012 following the Libor scandal and other episodes that
damaged the reputation of banks in the UK</li>
               <li>It includes MPs and peers and is chaired by Andrew Tyrie, who
also heads the House of Commons' Treasury Committee</li>
               <li>Members include the Archbishop of Canterbury, Justin Welby</li>
               <li>It heard evidence from major figures in the banking sector</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>What the Banking Reform Bill does</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <strong>The Ring-Fence</strong>: The High Street activities of
each UK bank are to be put into a separate subsidiary from its
riskier investment banking.</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>Electrification</strong>: Regulators will be given the
power to split up an individual bank altogether if the regulator
deems that bank to be undermining the purpose of the
ring-fence.</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>Deposit Guarantees</strong>: The Financial Services
Compensation Scheme currently guarantees up to
Ã‚Â£85,000 of every deposit in a UK bank.
Under the bill, if a bank goes bust, the FSCS will be paid out
ahead of other people owed money by the bank.</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>Loss Absorbency</strong>: The bill gives the Treasury
the power to impose tougher requirements on banks to increase their
ability to absorb losses, in particular by requiring a bank to
borrow money from markets in a form that allows the bank to impose
losses on the lenders if it gets into trouble.</li>
               <li>The Treasury has said the bill may be amended to include
recommendations in the Banking Standards Commission's latest
report</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/press_06_13.htm">Source:
Treasury</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
