<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23076541"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="EU finance ministers agree an outline plan on how to rescue troubled banks in any future crisis - without leaving taxpayers to face the bill."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T03:44:04"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68403000/jpg/_68403922_gqy695et.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="EU in draft deal on bank bailouts"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23076541"/>
         <title>BBC News - EU finance ministers reach draft deal on bank
bailouts</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">04:44</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">EU finance ministers reach draft deal on
bank bailouts</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68296000/jpg/_68296657_3fpk1adq.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="German Finance Minister Wolfgang Schaeuble"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">German Finance Minister Wolfgang Schaeuble: "The
talks were lengthy, quite difficult and intense"</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">European Union (EU)
finance ministers have agreed an outline plan on how to rescue
troubled banks - without leaving taxpayers to face the bill.</p>
            <p>The banks' creditors and shareholders will take the first hits,
followed by savers with deposits of more than 100,000 euros
(Ã‚Â£85,000).</p>
            <p>If that is not enough, government help will be called upon and
taxpayers will be among the last to shoulder losses.</p>
            <p>EU taxpayers have had to pay for a series of bank rescues in
recent years.</p>
            <p>Dutch Finance Minister Jeroen Dijsselbloem said the outline deal
marked a big change in the way that troubled banks are bailed
out.</p>
            <p>"If a bank gets in trouble we will now, throughout Europe, have
one set of rules on who pays the bill," he said.</p>
            <p>"The financial sector itself will now to a very, very large
extent become responsible for dealing with its own problems."</p>
            <p>The next step is for EU governments to negotiate over the
legislation with the European parliament.</p>
            <p>The global financial crisis coupled with the sovereign debt
crisis in the eurozone has hit the region's banking sector
severely.</p>
            <p>Countries from across the EU - such as Cyprus, Spain and Ireland
- have pumped tens of billions of euros in to try and prop up their
ailing banks over the past few years.</p>
            <p>In each case, the national government had
to foot the bill for rescuing its banks, leading to market fears
that the losses at the banks may be more than the government could
absorb.</p>
            <p>The problem was compounded by the fact that most eurozone
governments rely on their own banks to lend them the money they
need.</p>
            <p>However, things changed earlier this year after Cyprus was asked
to raise money through a levy on all Cypriot bank deposits -
including those below 100,000 euros - as a condition for securing a
loan package worth 10bn euros (Ã‚Â£8.4bn;
$13bn) from its EU partners and the International Monetary
Fund.</p>
            <p>But that proposal caused panic in financial markets and was
quickly withdrawn.</p>
            <p>On Thursday Ireland's Finance Minister Michael Noonan, who
chaired the latest talks, said that the new plan aimed to establish
clarity on who paid to rescue ailing banks.</p>
            <p>"Our aim is to have a common approach throughout Europe so our
taxpayers no longer have to shoulder the burden," he said.</p>
            <p>"This establishes 'bail-ins' as the new rule," he added,
referring to a term used to describe losses being shouldered by a
bank and its stakeholders instead of "bailouts" which use public
funds.</p>
            <p>Earlier this month, ministers agreed guidelines on how the
eurozone's emergency bailout fund can inject money directly into
struggling banks.</p>
            <p>The fund will be able to inject a total of 60bn euros into
troubled lenders but the bank's national government, and its
lenders and depositors, will still have to share the burden of any
rescue.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-18094883">Eurozone
crisis</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1365204978521"
                     href="/news/magazine-22042727">Bank staff fear for jobs and
savings</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1365030846536"
                     href="/news/business-22002153">Is Cyprus's euro membership
viable?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1364205392214"
                     href="/news/business-21922110">Q&amp;A: Cyprus deal</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1363964556893"
                     href="/news/world-21899515">German gamble</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">This establishes 'bail-ins' as the new
rule”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Michael Noonan</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Finance Minister, Ireland</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
