<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23282840"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="International football transfer numbers fall slightly but the income they generate has risen sharply in the past six months, says governing body Fifa."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-12T06:51:56"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68688000/jpg/_68688334_68688259.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Steep rise in football transfer fees"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Business"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-23282840"/>
         <title>BBC News - Football transfer income in steep global
increase</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">12 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">07:51</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Football transfer income in steep global
increase</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Bill
Wilson</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Business reporter, BBC
News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68688000/jpg/_68688341_68688257.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Nacho Monreal celebrates scoring for Arsenal against Swansea"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">One of the big January moves was of
Nacho Monreal from Malaga to Arsenal</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">International
football transfer numbers have remained steady but fees paid for
players have risen sharply worldwide in the past six months, says
Fifa.</p>
            <p>Completed player deals fell by 2% in the first six months of
2012, but their total financial value soared by 39%.</p>
            <p>The total income from 5,204 transfers around the globe was
$928.8m (Â£612m).</p>
            <p>Fifa's transfer unit said the increase could be down to some
economies recovering. The top seller was Brazil and the biggest
buyer was England.</p>
            <p>The data was revealed by Fifa's Transfer Matching System (TMS)
organisation, which uses modern electronic technology with the aim
of making international football transfers more transparent and
legally compliant.</p>
            <p>TMS head Kimberly Morris said sales revenues were "trending up
considerably", and had been helped by the improvement in some
countries' economic fortunes.</p>
            <p>She also said the increase might also be down to clubs becoming
more accurate and diligent in the filing of financial information
within the TMS system.</p>
            <p>Ms Morris, who had been speaking at a World Sports Law Report
conference into football player contracts, also said the vast
majority of player moves so far this year had been free
transfers.</p>
            <p>The total of $928.8m income generated in the first half of the
year came from just 12% of all transfer deals.</p>
            <p>The figures refer to international transfers and do not cover
"domestic" transfers between two clubs in the same country.</p>
            <p>With a month-long period to register transfer details in the TMS
system, it means the final figure for the first half of the year
may increase slightly, as some other moves that took place in June
filter through.</p>
            <p>There were a handful of high-profile incoming international
deals into English football earlier this year, including Zeki
Fryers from Standard Liege to Spurs for
Â£3m, Mathieu Debuchy from Lille to
Newcastle United for Â£5m, Nacho Monreal
from Malaga to Arsenal for Â£10m, and
Philippe Coutinho from Inter Milan to Liverpool for
Â£8.5m.</p>
            <p>Relegated QPR spent a total of Â£20m on
the duo of Loic Remy and Chris Samba, from Marseille and Anzi
Makhachkala.</p>
            <p>Most of the deals done in the first half of the year take place
during the January transfer windows in Europe, and July and August
are the two months when most global trading in the second half of
the year will take place.</p>
            <p>The big five European leagues - England, Germany, France, Italy
and Spain - have transfer windows that run from 1 July to 31
August. Scotland has a similar transfer window.</p>
            <p>However, despite the ever-growing amounts of TV money that have
flowed into the coffers of English Premier League clubs, the
biggest names have been keeping their powder dry so far this summer
when it comes to making marquee purchases.</p>
            <p>The TMS is an online system for registering international
transfers and has replaced the old set-up of documents based on
paper.</p>
            <p>In order for a transfer to be validated, the two clubs involved
must enter the relevant information on the deal into the TMS
system.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="/news/business/business_of_sport/">Business of
Sport</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373569031812"
                     href="/sport/0/football/23276952">Battle for TV football
viewers</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story" rel="published-1373324461453" href="/news/23226229">Le Tour climbs economic mountains</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373324453980"
                     href="/news/business-23226079">Andy Murray is minted</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372982506019"
                     href="/news/business-23183734">Tour de France fans follow
heroes</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
