<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/education-23270715"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="An official review of school food suggests schools in England should ban packed lunches and lower the price of cooked dinners to promote healthy eating."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-12T06:40:39"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68687000/jpg/_68687905_lunch.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Ban packed lunches, schools urged"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Education"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/education-23270715"/>
         <title>BBC News - Ban packed lunches, head teachers urged</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">12 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">07:40</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Ban packed lunches, head teachers
urged</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Hannah
Richardson</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News education
reporter</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68687000/jpg/_68687904_lunch.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="School dinners"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The review found most schools provide good quality
meals</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Head teachers in
England are being urged to ban packed lunches to increase the
take-up of school dinners and promote healthy eating.</p>
            <p>A government-commissioned school food review by two founders of
the Leon restaurant chain says take-up is low at 43% despite huge
quality improvements.</p>
            <p>The authors of the School Food Plan say packed lunches are
nearly always less nutritious than a cooked meal.</p>
            <p>And heads are being urged to lower the price of lunches to boost
take-up.</p>
            <p>This might include providing subsidised meals for reception
classes in primary schools and Year 7 classes in secondary schools,
the report says.</p>
            <p>The Department for Education ordered the review by restaurateurs
Henry Dimbleby and John Vincent into the state of school meals in
2012 following strong criticism from Jamie Oliver.</p>
            <p>Seven years earlier, the chef had led a successful campaign to
ban junk and processed food from school canteens. This resulted in
tight nutritional guidelines and healthy eating policies for those
bringing packed lunches.</p>
            <p>But in 2011 he claimed that standards were being eroded because
academies and free schools were exempt from national nutritional
guidelines.</p>
            <p>Mr Dimbleby told BBC Radio 4's Today programme that school food
had improved since the "dark days of the turkey twizzler", but that
the proportion of children eating school meals was not high
enough.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68688000/jpg/_68688136_68688135.jpg"
                 alt="Bramley Sunnyside headteacher Helen Headleand"/>
               <p class="caption">Pupils at Bramley Sunnyside primary school in
Rotherham are encouraged to grow their own food as part of their
learning</p>
            </div>
            <p>"Packed lunches, and more than half of our children bring packed
lunches into schools, two-thirds of those have crisps in them and
two-thirds have confectionery in them," he said.</p>
            <p>"The best schools, the schools with good food, find ways of
making packed lunches the least exciting option."</p>
            <p>He said if packed lunches were banned, schools would be able to
provide better meals at a cheaper price and this would help boost
children's performance.</p>
            <p>"We did a survey of 400 head teachers - over 90% believe
strongly that food has a direct effect on both academic achievement
and behaviour."</p>
            <p>The review suggests that items such as sugary drinks, crisps and
confectionery be forbidden from lunch boxes. In reality many
schools already have healthy packed lunch policies banning such
items.</p>
            <p>And heads are being warned to watch what is being served at
mid-morning break, when some children are said to fill up on
pizzas, panini or cake.</p>
            <p>Packed lunches are understood to be banned in just a very small
number of schools, but the DfE insists it is possible.</p>
            <p>General secretary of the National Association of Head Teachers
Russell Hobby said he felt it probably was not feasible for schools
to ban packed lunches.</p>
            <p>He thought it was right, instead, to focus on making school
meals more attractive in terms of cost and access as well as
nutritional content, taste and presentation.</p>
            <p>He added: "It is hard for students to concentrate on learning
when they haven't eaten enough or when they've eaten the wrong
things. The benefits from investing in decent cooked meals are
huge: better learning and better habits later in life; a calm and
sociable lunch hall also sets a tone for the rest of the day.</p>
            <p>"In addition, increasing numbers of
schools are growing part of their own food, and this can have a big
impact on the children."</p>
            <p>The Association of School and College Leaders said it was
important the plan related to academy schools as well as regular
state schools.</p>
            <p>Its general secretary Brian Lightman added: "While encouraging
all students to eat a nutritious hot lunch is the right aim, it is
not always feasible. Many hardworking families on relatively low
incomes give their children packed lunches because they don't
qualify for free school meals and the cost of a school dinner would
be prohibitive."</p>
            <p>Labour said exempting academies had allowed junk food "creep
back" into schools and it urged the government to enforce food
standards across the board.</p>
            <p>Shadow children's minister Sharon Hodgson said when the country
is in the middle of a childhood obesity crisis, it is important
that schools are doing their part to improve diets.</p>
            <p>"Labour vastly improved the quality of school food after Jamie
Oliver's important campaign. David Cameron and Michael Gove have
deliberately undermined that progress by exempting academies and
free schools from Labour's rules, and junk food has crept back into
canteens and vending machines.</p>
            <p>"Parents deserve to have confidence in the quality of school
meals. Labour's food standards should apply in all schools, and
Michael Gove needs to perform another U-turn to ensure they
do."</p>
            <p>Other recommendations include: after-school cooking lessons for
parents and children, more schools to have stay-on-site rules for
break and lunch time, and for teachers to be encouraged to sit in
the dining hall with children.</p>
            <p>The report comes as the obesity rate among children at the end
of primary school has risen to almost one in five.</p>
            <p>It claims only 1% of packed lunches meet the nutritional
standards that currently apply to school food.</p>
            <p>Rob Rees, chairman of the Children's Food Trust, said his own
children preferred school dinners, but added some parents feel they
are expensive.</p>
            <p>"They absolutely love it. It's not the school meals of the past.
It's wonderful fish pies, bologneses, lasagnes.</p>
            <p>"Knowing I'm investing my money wisely and my child is happy is
giving me peace of mind, so absolutely it is a barrier, but there's
not many things where you can get such good value for money."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373601991629"
                  href="/news/education-23181389">Parents' angst over packed
lunches</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372175324623"
                  href="/news/education-23052805">Pupils missing out on free
lunches</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1361793624674"
                  href="/news/education-21573630">'Cold chips' in pupil
lunchboxes</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Knowing I'm investing my money wisely and my
child is happy is giving me peace of mind”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Rob Rees</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Children's Food Trust</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
