<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23097092"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Famed US photographer, Bert Stern, best known for his images of Marilyn Monroe in what became known as The Last Sitting, dies at the age of 83."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T10:52:29"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68432000/jpg/_68432951_stern.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Monroe photographer Bert Stern dies"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Entertainment and Arts"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23097092"/>
         <title>BBC News - Bert Stern, Monroe photographer, dies in New
York</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">11:52</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Bert Stern, Monroe photographer, dies in
New York</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68429000/jpg/_68429342_stern.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Bert Stern"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Stern photographed Monroe in a Los Angeles hotel
room during a three-day shoot</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Famed US
photographer, Bert Stern, best known for his images of Marilyn
Monroe in what became known as The Last Sitting, has died at the
age of 83.</p>
            <p>Film-maker Shannah Laumeister, 43, who said the two were
secretly married in 2009, confirmed he died at his home in New York
on Wednesday.</p>
            <p>Stern photographed Monroe for Vogue magazine, just weeks before
she died from a drug overdose in 1962.</p>
            <p>Other celebrities he photographed included Audrey Hepburn and
Twiggy.</p>
            <p>Laumeister said: "He'll be remembered as someone who loved women
and loved taking pictures and putting things he felt strongly about
in the camera.</p>
            <p>"His images will live forever and wow generations to come," she
said, adding that the Monroe images "go beyond the photograph and
become a work of art".</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68432000/jpg/_68432720_68432719.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="John Vassos and Bert Stern"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">In 1981, John Vassos (r) returned
missing pictures of Monroe to Stern, which the photographer
believed to be stolen</span>
            </div>
            <p>Stern took more than 2,500 photographs of Monroe during the
intimate three-day shoot at the Bel Air Hotel in Los Angeles, six
weeks before her death in 1962.</p>
            <p>The nude and semi-nude images - including several which Monroe
rejected for magazine publication - were published in a 1982 book
titled The Last Sitting, and a second book, Marilyn Monroe: The
Complete Last Sitting, that came out in 2000.</p>
            <p>In a documentary about the photographer made by Laumeister,
Stern said: "It was a one-time-in-a-lifetime experience to have
Marilyn Monroe in a hotel room, even though it was turned into a
studio."</p>
            <p>A collection of 36 photographs taken during The Last Sitting
were auctioned in New York for nearly $150,000
(Â£102,581) in 2008.</p>
            <p>Born in Brooklyn, Stern photographed a host of celebrities such
as such as Sophia Loren, Elizabeth Taylor and Truman Capote during
a career that spanned 50 years.</p>
            <p>He was also highly regarded as an advertising photographer,
launching his career with a campaign for Smirnoff Vodka.</p>
            <p>The image showed a V-shaped glass of vodka set in the front of
an Egyptian pyramid.</p>
            <p>Along with contemporaries Irving Penn and Richard Avedon, he is
credited with transforming commercial photographs into conceptual
art. He also took the publicity shots for Stanley Kubrick's 1962
drama, Lolita.</p>
            <p>Bruce Barnes, director of the George Eastman House, a museum of
photography and film in Rochester, New York, said: "He was an
enormously innovative photographer, both as a commercial
photographer and a photographer of celebrities and fashion models.
And one of the great people in his field."</p>
            <p>The museum is preparing to present Stern's only documentary
film, Jazz on a Summer's Day, which he made in the late 1950s,
about the Newport Jazz Festival.</p>
            <p>Stern and Laumeister had been scheduled to attend a screening of
Laumeister's documentary in August, Barnes said.</p>
            <p>Stern's funeral is due to take place in New York on Friday.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1229509373000"
                  href="/1/hi/entertainment/7787325.stm">Monroe photos sold for
thousands</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1231840181000"
                  href="/1/hi/entertainment/7825827.stm">Deal reached over Monroe
photos</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1254950262000"
                  href="/1/hi/world/americas/8296030.stm">American photographer Penn
dies</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
