<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23094281"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The Arctic Monkeys close the first night of the 2013 Glastonbury Festival, after a day which also featured performances from Jake Bugg, Rita Ora and Dizzee Rascal."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T23:46:13"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68451000/jpg/_68451113_68451103.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Arctic Monkeys headline Glastonbury"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Entertainment and Arts"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23094281"/>
         <title>BBC News - Glastonbury Festival: Arctic Monkeys
headline</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">29 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:46</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Glastonbury Festival: Arctic Monkeys
headline</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Mark
Savage</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News entertainment
reporter, at Glastonbury</span>
            </span>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68453000/jpg/_68453454_68453453.jpg"
                 alt="Alex Turner of the Arctic Monkeys performs live on the Pyramid Stage at day 2 of the 2013 Glastonbury Festival "/>
               <p class="caption">Lizo Mzimba looks at the highlights from day
one, and ahead to day two</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The Arctic Monkeys
have closed the Glastonbury Festival's first night, playing to more
than 90,000 fans.</p>
            <p>Opening with a brand new song, Do I Wanna Know, they also
rattled through crowd-pleasing hits like I Bet You Look Good On The
Dancefloor.</p>
            <p>Frontman Alex Turner also led the crowd in a chorus of Happy
Birthday to his mum, Penny, who was at the festival.</p>
            <p>They were joined on the bill by Jake Bugg, Rita Ora and Dizzee
Rascal, as the weather largely stayed dry.</p>
            <p>LA trio Haim also played the main stage, but bassist Este Haim
was taken ill during their set.</p>
            <p>The 24-year-old had to sit on a stool after nearly collapsing on
stage.</p>
            <p>"I'm not going to let this get the better of me, especially when
there are so many beautiful people here," she told the
audience.</p>
            <p>"If I pass out, will someone give me mouth to mouth."</p>
            <p>Later, she told the NME she had "nearly died" and blamed the
incident on diabetes.</p>
            <p>"I didn't eat before my set like a smart, good diabetic does and
I remember not being able to feel my arms," she said.</p>
            <p>The Arctic Monkeys made a low-key entrance on the Pyramid Stage
- with none of the pyrotechnics or showbiz affectations of the
festival's last headliner, Beyonce, two years ago.</p>
            <p>In keeping with the slow-burning groove of their new single, the
band set opened with subdued lighting and darkened video screens,
before crashing straight into the heavier, faster Brianstorm, a
single from 2007.</p>
            <p>More confident as a frontman than the last time the band
headlined Glastonbury in 2007, Alex Turner squared up to the mic
and adopted an exaggerated Elvis swagger when addressing the
crowd.</p>
            <p>"We're gonna play all night long," he informed them. "Does that
sound good to you?"</p>
            <p>Songs from their first two albums - I Bet You Look Good On The
Dancefloor, Fluorescent Adolescent, Sun Goes Down - received the
warmest response, while new material was tolerated with good
humour.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68438000/jpg/_68438625_68438624.jpg"
                 alt="Liam Gallagher"/>
               <p class="caption">Liam Gallagher helped open the festival with a
surprise early morning appearance</p>
            </div>
            <p>A string quartet, arranged by Elbow's Guy Garvey, joined the
band for the encore, playing Mardy Bum and Cornerstone.</p>
            <p>The set ended with early track 505 and a wall of feedback.</p>
            <p>Earlier, Liam Gallagher's band Beady Eye kicked off the action
with an unscheduled appearance on The Other Stage at 11:00 BST.</p>
            <p>The early morning set was something of a turnaround for the
singer, who previously headlined the event with Oasis in 1995 and
2004.</p>
            <p>The latter appearance was particularly flat, and Gallagher
claimed the festival was "full of idiots".</p>
            <p>But after Friday's show, the singer told the BBC: "Glastonbury's
back in the good books. I just had a bad experience but now it's
cool again.</p>
            <p>"It's always been cool, it's just me. I'm
full of it."</p>
            <p>He added that playing before lunchtime had been something of a
risk.</p>
            <p>"I thought 11 o'clock could be really ropey but I thought we
done well, man."</p>
            <p>Musical legends could be found dotted around the site on Friday,
with Sinead O'Connor headlining the acoustic stage and Nile Rodgers
of disco pioneers Chic on the West Holts Stage.</p>
            <p>The musician, whose hits include Chic's Le Freak, Diana Ross's
Upside Down and Madonna's Like A Virgin, was playing his first ever
Glastonbury.</p>
            <p>"I think it's sort of mythical," he told the BBC.</p>
            <p>"I come from America, right, so in our
heads it all started with Woodstock and Monterey Pop - and
Glastonbury has kept that tradition alive.</p>
            <p>"Now I'm actually here I can come home and either dispel the
myth or say 'wow, it's everything I thought'."</p>
            <p>Mercury Prize-winners Alt-J also drew a large audience to The
Other Stage, and surprised them all by ditching their smart,
intricate rock songs for a cover of Kylie Minogue's Slow.</p>
            <p>Jake Bugg pulled off an early "Glastonbury moment" with an
energetic set that climaxed with his hit Lightning Bolt; while
Dizzee Rascal provided a canny mix of crowd-pleasing hits and new
material, including his Robbie Williams-featuring single Going
Crazy.</p>
            <p>With an audience of 180,000 music fans, many artists look
forward to Glastonbury as the pinnacle of the festival season - and
anticipation was particularly high after the event took a year off
in 2012.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68434000/jpg/_68434761_68434760.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Glastonbury"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The sun came out in time for fans to watch Jake
Bugg's afternoon set</span>
            </div>
            <p>"I'm never going to forget this," declared pop star Rita Ora as
she left the stage. "You have changed my life."</p>
            <p>Rapper Professor Green, who followed her on the Pyramid Stage,
said he was similarly amazed to be part of the line-up.</p>
            <p>Describing himself as "some little toerag from Hackney who
samples INXS", he described his booking as "mental".</p>
            <p>The 29-year-old, whose hits include Read All About It and the
INXS-based I Need You Tonight was also aware of the opportunity the
stage - and the accompanying TV coverage - presented.</p>
            <p>"I think a lot of people that are here
won't know my music, bar the singles, so this is a good opportunity
to show the musicality of what we do when we play live," he
said.</p>
            <p>With more than 2,000 performers over the weekend, rumours of
"secret appearances" are always rife at Glastonbury, and this
year's crop range from the likely (Fatboy Slim and Radiohead's Thom
Yorke) to the fanciful (Daft Punk and David Bowie).</p>
            <p>Definitely confirmed for the weekend are co-headliners Mumford
and Sons and The Rolling Stones.</p>
            <p>Speaking to Radio 1's Newsbeat, Stones guitarist Keith Richards
said the band had a few reservations about their set.</p>
            <p>"I think the only pressure we feel is that it is the first time
we've done an outdoor show for yonks and English weather," he
said.</p>
            <p>"Throwing in those two equations, yeah there is maybe a little
apprehension."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>GLASTONBURY 2013</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372511712988"
                     href="/news/entertainment-arts-23111268">Stones triumph in Glastonbury
debut</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372535328100"
                     href="/news/uk-23115057">In pictures: Glastonbury on Saturday</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372503286682"
                     href="/news/uk-23110802">John Humphrys at his first festival</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372481888501"
                     href="/news/entertainment-arts-23095490">Jagger: 'I wanted to be a
journalist'</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Festival forecast</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68434000/jpg/_68434783_171606407.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="96"
                 alt="sunrise"/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://bbc.in/ucbJEL">What's the weather like in
Glastonbury?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68268000/jpg/_68268199_glastonbury_logo.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="84"
                 alt="BBC Glastonbury Logo"/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/events/ej58q9">BBC Glastonbury
Festival - 2013</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/events/ej58q9/stages/s2jc6q">The
Introducing Stage</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/events/ej58q9/performances">Line-up by
day</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">I think the only pressure we feel is that it
is the first time we've done an outdoor show for yonks and English
weather”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Keith Richards, Rolling Stones</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
