<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23246871"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A new work by acclaimed British composer Julian Anderson will open the two-month BBC Proms season later."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-12T02:01:08"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68637000/jpg/_68637151_bbc-proms-launch.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Proms to launch with world premiere"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Entertainment and Arts"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23246871"/>
         <title>BBC News - BBC Proms set to launch with 'calm' world
premiere</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">12 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">03:01</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">BBC Proms set to launch with 'calm' world
premiere</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Tim
Masters</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Entertainment and arts
correspondent, BBC News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68637000/jpg/_68637031_bbc-proms-launch.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="BBC Proms promo pic "/>
               <span style="width:624px;">Trumpeter Tine Thing Helseth, sitar player Nishat
Khan, Proms presenter Katie Derham and singer and broadcaster Cerys
Matthews flanked by Daleks at the launch of the BBC Proms
2013</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A new work by
acclaimed British composer Julian Anderson will launch the
two-month BBC Proms season later.</p>
            <p>The music festival - the world's largest - begins on Friday
evening and ends with the world-famous Last Night of the proms on 7
September.</p>
            <p>Anderson describes Harmony, a piece for chorus and orchestra, as
"a short piece about eternity".</p>
            <p>The world premiere of his work is accompanied by sea-inspired
works by Britten and Vaughan Williams.</p>
            <p>"It's very exciting - I've always loved the Proms," Anderson
told the BBC.</p>
            <p>"When you're writing a piece to open a concert series, it seems
to me there are two options: one is to write a piece that's very
loud and rather like a fanfare, and the other is to write a quiet
and more meditative piece.</p>
            <p>"I've chosen the second option which is perhaps the less obvious
of the two."</p>
            <p>He added: "One of the things the Proms audience is famous for,
is their ability to listen to sometimes very long works of
classical music - and this piece celebrates their ability to do
that because it is calm and focused."</p>
            <p>Anderson's work, however, is the shortest of the opening Prom
night. At around four minutes long, it draws on material from the
composer's first opera, Thebans, which will premiere at the ENO in
May 2014.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/67558000/jpg/_67558510_marinalsop.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Marin Alsop conducts the Sao Paulo Symphony Orchestra "/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Marin Alsop will make history as the
first female conductor for the Last Night of the Proms</span>
            </div>
            <p>Sakari Oramo will conduct the First Night of the Proms, marking
the beginning of his tenure as chief conductor of the BBC Symphony
Orchestra.</p>
            <p>Other leading conductors include Sir Andrew Davis, Sir Mark
Elder, Sir John Eliot Gardiner, Valery Gergiev and Sir Antonio
Pappano.</p>
            <p>A special concert dedicated to Sir Colin Davis, who died in
April aged 85, will be held on 20 August - when he was due to lead
the London Symphony Orchestra with tenor Ian Bostridge.</p>
            <p>This years Proms features 75 concerts at London's Royal Albert
Hall, 13 in the Cadogan Hall and four Proms in the Park events
around the UK.</p>
            <p>Highlights include a celebration of the 200th year of Wagner's
birth with a complete performance of his Ring cycle conducted by
Daniel Barenboim.</p>
            <p>The Doctor Who Proms return this weekend, as part of the TV
show's 50th anniversary celebrations.</p>
            <p>Among the Proms firsts are an Urban Classic featuring Fazer,
Laura Mvula and Maverick Sabre and a 6 Music Prom with Cerys
Matthews, Laura Marling and punk heroes The Stranglers.</p>
            <p>Marin Alsop makes Proms history by becoming the first woman to
conduct the Last Night of the Proms. She will be joined by
mezzo-soprano Joyce DiDonato and British violinist Nigel Kennedy,
who will also direct a performance of Vivaldi's The Four Seasons
during the festival.</p>
            <p>Speaking about his opening work, Anderson said he had chosen to
set it to a brief text by 19th Century nature writer Richard
Jefferies about time and eternity.</p>
            <p>"It's a text I've loved for many years because when you go to a
concert, you forget the everyday time of the world outside and you
enter the time of the music," he said.</p>
            <p>Every Prom is broadcast live on BBC Radio 3<em>.</em> The full
list of events can be found at the <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/proms">BBC Proms</a> website.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1368373516871"
                  href="/news/entertainment-arts-22503535">Record ticket sales for BBC
Proms</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1367589951763"
                  href="/news/entertainment-arts-22395057">Prom dedicated to Sir Colin
Davis</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1366290115764"
                  href="/news/entertainment-arts-22188201">Female conductor makes Proms
history</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
