<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23111268"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Organiser Michael Eavis hails &#34;the high spot of 43 years of Glastonbury&#34; after The Rolling Stones make their debut at the festival with a hit-packed set."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-29T23:51:44"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68460000/jpg/_68460890_68460823.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Stones triumph in Glastonbury debut"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Entertainment and Arts"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23111268"/>
         <title>BBC News - Glastonbury Festival: Rolling Stones make
debut</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">30 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:51</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Glastonbury Festival: Rolling Stones make
debut</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Mark
Savage</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News entertainment
reporter, at Glastonbury</span>
            </span>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68461000/jpg/_68461767_68461766.jpg"
                 alt="Sir Mick Jagger and Keith Richards of The Rolling Stones perform on the Pyramid Stage"/>
               <p class="caption">The BBC's Lizo Mzimba reports from Glastonbury
on the Stones' historic set</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The Rolling Stones'
hit-packed Glastonbury debut has been hailed as "the high spot of
43 years" of the festival by organiser Michael Eavis.</p>
            <p>The band opened with Jumpin' Jack Flash, with Mick Jagger
prowling the stage in a green sequinned jacket.</p>
            <p>He repeatedly thanked the crowd and, after It's Only Rock 'N'
Roll (But I Like It), joked organisers had "finally got round to
asking us" to play.</p>
            <p>Tens of thousands of fans cheered on the two-hour set featuring
20 songs.</p>
            <p>Speaking immediately after the band came off stage, festival
boss Eavis called it "the high spot of 43 years of
Glastonbury".</p>
            <p>"They finally did it, and it was
fantastic. My God, did they deliver."</p>
            <p>Eavis also said he had bumped into Prince Harry at the festival
during the day, "and I recommended he stay the night".</p>
            <p>The Stones had arrived on stage after an intro tape featuring
the sounds of Worthy Farm's usual residents, 350 dairy cows.</p>
            <p>Eavis was heard saying "we waited a long time" as the
unmistakable rhythm track of Sympathy For The Devil played and the
crowd spontaneously broke into the familiar "whoo whoo" backing
vocals.</p>
            <p>"It's great to be here doing this show,
doing this festival," said Jagger after It's Only Rock 'N' Roll
(But I Like It).</p>
            <p>"After all these years they finally got round to asking us," he
added. Drummer Charlie Watts gave the joke a desultory cymbal
crash.</p>
            <p>The band had modified the Pyramid stage with three catwalks,
allowing Jagger to bridge the cavernous gap that separates most
Glastonbury performers from the audience.</p>
            <p>It was in almost constant use as the 69-year-old strutted back
and forth, clapping his hands thrusting his thick-lipped pout into
the air.</p>
            <p>Five songs into the set, Jagger introduced a new song, written
for a girl "in cut-off jeans" he claimed to have met at the
festival on Friday night.</p>
            <p>A swampy country-rock number, it featured the refrain "Waiting
for my Glastonbury girl".</p>
            <p>Keith Richards, his guitar slung low around his skinny jeans,
was handed the microphone for a couple of songs, and former Stones'
guitarist Mick Taylor joined the band to layer an intricate blues
solo over 1969's Midnight Rambler.</p>
            <p>He was the only surprise guest of the night, despite rumours
that Adele or even Bruce Springsteen would make an appearance.</p>
            <p>After 90 minutes, Sympathy For The Devil got a full airing, as
flares turned the sky red and a mechanical phoenix rose from atop
the Pyramid stage.</p>
            <p>Jagger said: "We've been doing this for
50 years or something. And if this is the first time you've seen a
band, please come again."</p>
            <p>The encore was You Can't Always Get What You Want, and an
extended, hyperactive take on (I Can't Get No) Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>"Thank you very much Glastonbury," sang Jagger as the song
reached its climax.</p>
            <p>Fireworks lit up the farm and the band took a series of bows,
while the audience continued to chant the riff to Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile, at the Acoustic tent, the Bootleg Beatles played a
Stones riff and commented: "Sign of a good band - you've got to
know when to split up."</p>
            <p>Earlier on Saturday proceedings had started with Malian musician
Rokia Traore, whose upbeat blend of African roots, blues and jazz
gave early risers a chance to dance off the fug of a late
night.</p>
            <p>A headliner at this year's Womad festival, Traore was offered a
Glastonbury slot as a gesture of solidarity with Mali, where
Islamist militants all but banned music in some areas.</p>
            <p>Billy Bragg got into the spirit of the day by playing classic
Stones track Dead Flowers during his set, while soul singer Laura
Mvula welcomed the sun by breaking into a sing-a-long rendition of
Bob Marley's One Love.</p>
            <p>Speaking to the BBC afterwards, she said the cover had been
suggested by her musical director, Troy Miller "whose last
appearance here was with Amy Winehouse, so he knows what he's
talking about".</p>
            <p>Mvula, who only released her debut album
Sing To The Moon, in March, said stepping out on the festival's
main stage was overwhelming.</p>
            <p>"Let me tell you something, there's nothing like it. A sort of
nervousness I've never experienced before.</p>
            <p>"It was like a mental battle - the goal was to get through it
and enjoy as many moments as possible."</p>
            <p>Other acts on Saturday's line-up included Elvis Costello, rap
pioneers Public Enemy and psychedelic rockers Primal Scream.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>GLASTONBURY 2013</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372535328100"
                     href="/news/uk-23115057">In pictures: Glastonbury on Saturday</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372400002721"
                     href="/news/entertainment-arts-23094281">Arctic Monkeys headline
Glastonbury</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372503286682"
                     href="/news/uk-23110802">John Humphrys at his first festival</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372481888501"
                     href="/news/entertainment-arts-23095490">Jagger: 'I wanted to be a
journalist'</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68268000/jpg/_68268199_glastonbury_logo.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="84"
                 alt="BBC Glastonbury Logo"/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/events/ej58q9">BBC Glastonbury
Festival - 2013</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/events/ej58q9/stages/s2jc6q">The
Introducing Stage</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/events/ej58q9/performances">Line-up by
day</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>At the scene</h2>
            <p>For two hours and 20 songs The Rolling Stones were a crossfire
hurricane sweeping across the fields of Glastonbury.</p>
            <p>Mick Jagger was in particularly fine form, his hands flailing
and hips jutting like a Thunderbirds puppet trying to belly
dance.</p>
            <p>But it was the musicality of the night - a long, intricate solo
on Midnight Rambler, or the extended coda of Satisfaction - that
really hit home.</p>
            <p>The band's power is to be simultaneously the biggest rock group
in the world and four old mates playing the blues in their
shed.</p>
            <p>This was live music, raw and unpolished. From the comfort of
your settee, it's easy to criticise Jagger's hammy stage moves and
frequently out-of-breath vocals but that's what it takes to connect
to an audience of this size.</p>
            <p>Mumford and Sons, who headline on Sunday, must be quaking in
their boots.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Rolling Stones set list</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Jumpin' Jack Flash</li>
               <li>It's Only Rock 'n' Roll (But I Like It)</li>
               <li>Paint It Black</li>
               <li>Gimme Shelter</li>
               <li>Glastonbury Girl</li>
               <li>Wild Horses</li>
               <li>Doom and Gloom</li>
               <li>Can't You Hear Me Knocking</li>
               <li>Honky Tonk Women</li>
               <li>You Got the Silver</li>
               <li>Happy</li>
               <li>Miss You</li>
               <li>Midnight Rambler</li>
               <li>2,000 Light Years from Home</li>
               <li>Sympathy for the Devil</li>
               <li>Start Me Up</li>
               <li>Tumbling Dice</li>
               <li>Brown Sugar</li>
            </ul>
            <p>Encore</p>
            <ul>
               <li>You Can't Always Get What You Want</li>
               <li>(I Can't Get No) Satisfaction</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Festival forecast</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68434000/jpg/_68434783_171606407.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="96"
                 alt="Sunrise"/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://bbc.in/ucbJEL">What's the weather like in
Glastonbury?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
