<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23180456"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Actress and singer Bernie Nolan has died at the age of 52, following a long battle with breast cancer."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T14:26:11"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68548000/jpg/_68548852_nolans_getty2010.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Singer Bernie Nolan dies aged 52"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Entertainment and Arts"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23180456"/>
         <title>BBC News - Singer Bernie Nolan dies aged 52</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">15:26</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Singer Bernie Nolan dies aged 52</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68548000/jpg/_68548468_nolans_getty2010.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Bernie Nolan"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Bernie Nolan spent 20 years as lead singer of the
hit Irish girl group</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Actress and singer
Bernie Nolan has died at the age of 52, following a long battle
with breast cancer.</p>
            <p>The former lead singer of The Nolans was first diagnosed in
2010, and had chemotherapy and a mastectomy, receiving an all-clear
in 2012.</p>
            <p>However, months later the disease returned and spread to her
brain, bones, lungs and liver.</p>
            <p>In recent years she was best known for her acting roles in The
Bill and Channel 4 soap Brookside.</p>
            <p>"Bernie passed away peacefully this morning with all of her
family around her," said a spokesperson for the family.</p>
            <p>"The entire family are devastated to have lost beloved Bernie, a
wonderful wife, adoring mother and loving sister, she is
irreplaceable."</p>
            <p>Born on 17 October 1960, she grew up in Ireland, performing as a
family troupe with her five sisters and two brothers. Her father
Tommy would go on to be the Nolans' manager - but after his death,
eldest sister Anne revealed he had sexually abused her from the age
of 11.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68544000/jpg/_68544973_68544971.jpg"
                 alt="The Nolan Sisters: Linda, Anne, Bernie and Maureen"/>
               <p class="caption">Archive: The Nolan sisters 1979 appearance on
Top of the Pops</p>
            </div>
            <p>Nolan turned to acting following 20 years fronting the Irish
all-girl group and a string of hits including 1979's I'm in the
Mood for Dancing and Don't Make Waves.</p>
            <p>She left the group in 1994, and took to the stage, performing in
productions including Blood Brothers in London's West End,
Flashdance and a UK tour of Chicago the Musical.</p>
            <p>She moved into television playing hairdresser Diane Murray in
Brookside from 2000-02 and joining ITV's police drama The Bill in
2003, as Sergeant Sheelagh Murphy.</p>
            <p>"So sad to hear Bernie Nolan has passed away," tweeted Nolan's
Brookside co-star Jennifer Ellison, after hearing the news of her
death. "Such an amazing lady, had the honour of working with her
twice will cherish the memories."</p>
            <p>Bill co-star Gary Lucy tweeted: "RIP Bernie Nolan - our thoughts
are with her family."</p>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68548000/jpg/_68548894_nlwbkfbf.jpg"
                 width="224"
                 height="299"
                 alt="Bernie Nolan, in 2010"/>
               <span style="width:224px;">Nolan wrote about her battle with cancer
in her autobiography, released in May</span>
            </div>
            <p>Nolan also took part in ITV's talent show Popstar to Operastar
in 2010, reaching the final but losing to Pop Idol's Darius.</p>
            <p>In 2008, Bernie, Maureen, Linda and Coleen agreed to a
multi-million pound reunion tour of The Nolans with Universal
Records, prompting a feud between the two remaining sisters, Denise
and Anne.</p>
            <p>Anne, who was in the original line-up but left the group for two
years at the height of their mainstream success, was not included
by the tour's producers and it caused a bitter rift. Denise had
left the group before any of the group's chart hits.</p>
            <p>"Despite all the drama around it, doing the show was one of the
best things I've ever done. It gave us all something to remember
for ever," Bernie said in her autobiography Now &amp; Forever,
which was published in May this year.</p>
            <p>In the book, she claimed she had made her peace with all five of
her sisters over the last few years - and urged her sisters to do
the same. Two of her five sisters, Anne and Linda, were previously
diagnosed with breast cancer but overcame the disease.</p>
            <p>Presenter Lorraine Kelly paid tribute on Thursday, tweeting:
"Bernie Nolan was a very special woman. Brave, funny and hugely
talented. She will be sorely missed. Thoughts with her family and
friends."</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68550000/jpg/_68550744_v167xy00.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="The Nolan sisters performing in the 1980s"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Some of the sisters fell out amid plans for a
reunion tour in 2008</span>
            </div>
            <p>Sherrie Hewson, who works with Bernie's sister Coleen on Loose
Women, tweeted: "RIP the wonderfully talented Bernie Nolan. A
beautiful person that brightened up this sometimes dark world of
ours! Sing forever Bernie."</p>
            <p>"Very sad to hear of the passing of Bernie Nolan," added
commentator Gary Lineker on Twitter. "A fabulous and fabulously
talented lady. Thoughts are with the family."</p>
            <p>Bernie married Steve Doneathy in 1996 and leaves one daughter,
Erin.</p>
            <p>Speaking to BBC Breakfast in May this year, Mr Doneathy said she
had stopped chemotherapy and entered palliative care.</p>
            <p>"But she's still being as positive as you can be under those
circumstances. You get up every day, face the day, and make that
day the best it can be."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1272154082000"
                  href="/1/hi/entertainment/8642438.stm">Nolan sister gets breast
cancer</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1245059986000"
                  href="/1/hi/entertainment/8100350.stm">The Nolans to reunite for UK
tour</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
