<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23119254"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Glastonbury echoes to the sounds of folk-rock group Mumford and Sons, who closed the 2013 festival with their first-ever headline performance there."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T01:34:54"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68471000/jpg/_68471024_68470661.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Mumfords close Glastonbury festival"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Entertainment and Arts"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23119254"/>
         <title>BBC News - Mumford and Sons close Glastonbury
festival</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:34</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Mumford and Sons close Glastonbury
festival</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Mark
Savage</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News entertainment
reporter</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68471000/jpg/_68471020_68470661.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Marcus Mumford of Mumford and Sons "/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Mumford and Sons rounded off the festival in front
of 80,000 people</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Glastonbury is
echoing to the sounds of folk-rock group Mumford and Sons, who
closed the 2013 festival with their first-ever headline performance
there.</p>
            <p>"We came for a party," said frontman Marcus Mumford, as the band
triggered a mass hoedown on Somerset's Worthy Farm.</p>
            <p>An estimated 80,000 people watched the set. When they first
played the festival in 2008, only 200 turned up.</p>
            <p>The 90-minute performance ended with an all-star cover of A
Little Help From My Friends.</p>
            <p>This featured Vampire Weekend, The Vaccines and The Staves.</p>
            <p>Earlier songs, including The Cave and I Will Wait - their only
UK top 20 hit - saw the audience bounce in unison from the front of
the Pyramid Stage to end of the fields.</p>
            <p>The show caps the band's meteoric rise from west London to the
global stage, with multiple Grammy awards, US album sales of four
million and appearances with Bob Dylan and Bruce Springsteen.</p>
            <p>Mumford, 26, said he felt the band had done "nothing special" to
earn the prestigious Glastonbury slot, and put their success down
to the audience.</p>
            <p>"We truly feel you got us here. Thank you
so much."</p>
            <p>In contrast to The Rolling Stones' bullish set the night before,
the Londoners had appeared on stage quietly, playing the
slow-burning Lovers' Eyes on a pitch-black stage.</p>
            <p>But the band's otherwise ebullient set embodied the Glastonbury
spirit - generous, warm-hearted and inclusive.</p>
            <p>It carried further emotional weight as it marked the band's
return to the stage after bass player Ted Dwane had surgery for a
blood clot on his brain this month.</p>
            <p>They said they would have pulled out of the headline slot if
their 28-year-old bass player had not made a full recovery.</p>
            <p>"Was the show ever in doubt? I think it's fair to say it was,"
keyboard player Ben Lovett told the BBC.</p>
            <p>"Nothing was more important than Ted's health," said Lovett.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68461000/jpg/_68461767_68461766.jpg"
                 alt="Sir Mick Jagger and Keith Richards of The Rolling Stones perform on the Pyramid Stage"/>
               <p class="caption">The BBC's Lizo Mzimba reports on The Rolling
Stones historic debut</p>
            </div>
            <p>This year's festival has seen 180,000 people descend on Michael
Eavis's Somerset farmstead.</p>
            <p>The music has catered to a wide range of tastes with sets from
artists such as The Proclaimers, dance act Chase and Status, pop
star Rita Ora and disco pioneers Chic.</p>
            <p>Sunday's line-up included Vampire Weekend, Smashing Pumpkins,
Jessie Ware, Bobby Womack and Sir Bruce Forsyth.</p>
            <p>The turn-out for Sir Bruce was so large that security officers
shut down the Avalon field for 20 minutes, as hundreds of fans
clamoured to see the Generation Game star.</p>
            <p>He emerged on the Avalon Stage to the Strictly Come Dancing
theme and introduced himself as "The Rolling Stones Two", before
playing a set of music hall standards, including Gershwin's Funny
Face.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68467000/jpg/_68467872_68467272.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Sir Bruce Forsyth"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Sir Bruce is one of the oldest performers ever at
Glastonbury</span>
            </div>
            <p>"He's a legend," said Victoria, an audience member from New
Zealand. "I thought I'd be able to get front row but I'm stuck out
in the back and can't see him."</p>
            <p>"You're seeing one man who's got multiple skills all coalesced
into one perfect presenter," said Taylor, a young, tattooed fan
from Middlesbrough. "Everyone wants to be like this guy. To be that
energetic when you're about 107 is just inspirational."</p>
            <p>An emotional Sir Bruce later told the BBC the experience was
"something I will treasure forever".</p>
            <p>The Sunday afternoon "Glastonbury legend" slot - which has
played host to the likes of Shirley Bassey and Johnny Cash - was
filled by country star Kenny Rogers.</p>
            <p>"I was told it was a special slot but I don't always believe
everything my manager says when he's trying to get me to do
something," admitted the singer.</p>
            <p>The 74-year-old struggled initially. He attempted to get the
crowd to sing along to Ruby, Don't Take Your Love To Town, only to
discover they didn't know the words.</p>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68467000/jpg/_68467871_68467276.jpg"
                 width="224"
                 height="299"
                 alt="Kenny Rogers"/>
               <span style="width:224px;">Rogers is also making his Glastonbury
debut</span>
            </div>
            <p>"They sang that better in Morocco," he scolded. "And they don't
even speak English in Morocco."</p>
            <p>But the set regained momentum when he played The Gambler and
Islands In The Stream. So much so that he sang them both again.</p>
            <p>Rogers, who is the seventh-biggest selling artist in US history,
also lent his support to Mumford and Sons.</p>
            <p>"You know, my first 10 years, I played upright bass and sang in
a jazz group - so I can really appreciate what they're doing
melody-wise and time-wise," he told the BBC.</p>
            <p>"It's great to hear a group like that be so successful."</p>
            <p>The mass exodus from Glastonbury began on Sunday, with coaches
leaving throughout the night.</p>
            <p>Although the festival took a year off in 2012, it will return
next year. Organiser Michael Eavis said the headliners had already
been booked.</p>
            <p>"There aren't many left," he said, "There were maybe a dozen
headliner potentials so we're running out of headliners but we got
the last three for next year."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>GLASTONBURY 2013</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372511712988"
                     href="/news/entertainment-arts-23111268">Stones triumph in Glastonbury
debut</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372535328100"
                     href="/news/uk-23115057">In pictures: Glastonbury on Saturday</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372400002721"
                     href="/news/entertainment-arts-23094281">Arctic Monkeys headline
Glastonbury</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372503286682"
                     href="/news/uk-23110802">John Humphrys at his first festival</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68268000/jpg/_68268199_glastonbury_logo.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="84"
                 alt="BBC Glastonbury Logo"/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/events/ej58q9">BBC Glastonbury
Festival - 2013</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/events/ej58q9/stages/s2jc6q">The
Introducing Stage</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/events/ej58q9/performances">Line-up by
day</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
