<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23143063"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Ballet star Mikhail Baryshnikov is back on stage, acting alongside Willem Dafoe in an avant-garde play by one of the world's most acclaimed directors."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T01:21:39"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68531000/jpg/_68531044_theoldwomanrehearsals01creditluciejansch.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Dancer Baryshnikov back on stage"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Entertainment and Arts"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-23143063"/>
         <title>BBC News - Mikhail Baryshnikov back on stage with Willem
Dafoe</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:21</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Mikhail Baryshnikov back on stage with
Willem Dafoe</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Ian Youngs</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Arts reporter, BBC News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68526000/jpg/_68526480_theoldwomanrehearsals01creditluciejansch.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Willem Dafoe and Mikhail Baryshnikov in The Old Woman"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Willem Dafoe (left) stars with Mikhail
Baryshnikov in The Old Woman</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Mikhail Baryshnikov
was one of the world's greatest ballet dancers. He is back on
stage, this time acting alongside US star Willem Dafoe in a play
based on an absurd Russian novella.</p>
            <p>Depending on your age and interests, you will know Mikhail
Baryshnikov either as one of the most graceful creatures that ever
set foot on a stage, in the same league as Nureyev and Nijinsky, or
as that Russian bloke from Sex and the City.</p>
            <p>Either way, you will not have seen him as he is in The Old Woman
at the Palace Theatre in Manchester - ghostly white face, with
mouth and eyes highlighted in black, and a protruding horn of
moulded hair. He is clown, cartoon character and ghoul rolled into
one.</p>
            <p>The Old Woman is adapted from a work by Russian short story
author Daniil Kharms, about a writer who lets a woman into his
house before she promptly dies.</p>
            <p>Kharms died in 1942 at the age of 36 in a prison psychiatric
hospital.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68527000/jpg/_68527461_ap.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="405"
                 alt="Mikhail Baryshnikov in 1978"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Baryshnikov defected from the USSR in
1974</span>
            </div>
            <p>"He wrote from very short paragraphs to small vignettes - very
abstract in many cases and very bizarre and obscene," Baryshnikov
says.</p>
            <p>On stage, there is some dancing and all of the parts are shared
between Baryshnikov and Willem Dafoe, whose appearance has been
similarly transformed.</p>
            <p>For Baryshnikov, it is the latest step in a career that has
evolved through classical ballet, contemporary dance, Broadway,
films and New York-based girly TV comedies.</p>
            <p>The Old Woman, part of the Manchester International Festival, is
the "most difficult and the most challenging" role of his career,
the 65-year-old says.</p>
            <p>The challenge has been increased by the demands of director
Robert Wilson, a visionary of avant-garde theatre who is best-known
for creating the opera Einstein on the Beach with composer Philip
Glass.</p>
            <p>With most directors, an actor knows how they work and what to
expect, Baryshnikov says.</p>
            <p>"With Bob, every day is an adventure," he explains with a
weariness in his thick Russian drawl. Almost 40 years since he
defected from the USSR, his English is still a little bent, if not
broken.</p>
            <p>"He asks you to do things which you never dreamt in your
life.</p>
            <p>"I sing in this, a little bit, but I never sang on stage. He
forced me to choreograph, which I refused many times. I did little
things in my past career, but I'm not a choreographer.</p>
            <p>"First we were doing [the play] in English of course, and then
he said, 'I think you should do it in both languages, Russian and
English. You should switch from one sentence in Russian, to one
sentence in English.'</p>
            <p>"It was already in the middle of rehearsal process. And then he
said, 'You put it in rhyme and then you sing it, and let's do it,
maybe tomorrow.'</p>
            <p>"I mean... Hello," he adds sarcastically.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68531000/jpg/_68531037_2779829.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Mikhail Baryshnikov and Sarah Jessica Parker in Sex and the City"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Baryshnikov played Russian artist
Aleksandr Petrovsky in Sex and the City</span>
            </div>
            <p>Wilson is known to be a perfectionist. "It is exhausting process
and it doesn't let you go 24/7," Baryshnikov says. "For me it's
much more exhausting than dancing all day."</p>
            <p>Baryshnikov became beloved of ballet audiences in the 1970s, and
settled in New York after his defection. Not content (and a little
slight) as a romantic lead, he embraced more experimental
choreographers and moved behind the scenes as an artistic
director.</p>
            <p>He appeared on the big screen in 1977's The Turning Point,
earning an Oscar nomination for best supporting actor. In 1989, he
made his Broadway acting debut in Metamorphosis, and received a
Tony Award nomination.</p>
            <p>If people stop him in the street, I ask what they recognise him
for. "Sex and the City, of course," he replies.</p>
            <p>He played Carrie Bradshaw's suave Russian boyfriend Aleksandr
Petrovsky in the hit TV series.</p>
            <p>"Of course. It's funny. From Peru to Israel. It's always
'Trovsky? Trotsky? Petrotsky? Petrovsky? Oh yeah, that's right.'
They think it's my name." He is animated now and struggles to talk
through laughter.</p>
            <p>"You know how the people, they think it's a reality show. It's a
sad testament of attachment to television. People, they don't have
real serious life in them. They live life of somebody else. That's
what it is. That's what television's designed to do.</p>
            <p>"I'm guilty. I love, do you know this programme Mad Men? This
extraordinary programme."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68527000/jpg/_68527465_theoldwomanrehearsals03creditluciejansch.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Willem Dafoe and Mikhail Baryshnikov in The Old Woman"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Theatre director Robert Wilson is known
for his striking visual style</span>
            </div>
            <p>The Old Woman is Baryshnikov's third recent stage part in
adaptations of Russian stories, after plays based on works by
Chekhov and Bunin. He has also run the Baryshnikov Arts Centre in
New York since 2005.</p>
            <p>Does he miss classical ballet? "No," comes the immediate reply.
"No," he repeats with a dismissive chuckle. "Not at all.</p>
            <p>"I rarely go. When my children were small, I used to take them
to see the classical heritage and tradition of the Sleeping
Beauties and Swan Lakes. But three hours of this, this time would
never come back."</p>
            <p>Did he not enjoy those parts when he was dancing them? "Very
much. I loved performing Giselle and... The classical repertoire
for me didn't quite perfect fit because I was on smallish side, it
was difficult to find the perfect partner.</p>
            <p>"I was not a very capable partner. I was not very strong. People
like Natalia Makarova, Gelsey Kirkland and a few others, when it
was really perfect match, it was a pleasure and a lot of fun."</p>
            <p>But he adds: "There was a natural progression in my quest for
something different."</p>
            <p>
               <em>The Old Woman is at the Palace Theatre in Manchester from
4-7 July.</em>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1362057230902"
                  href="/news/entertainment-arts-21613955">Maxine Peake for Manchester
festival</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1352930900767"
                  href="/news/entertainment-arts-20325381">Branagh heads Manchester
festival</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1310026161480"
                  href="/news/entertainment-arts-14022297">Abramovic stages life and
death</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
