<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-22963499"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Ballet dancer David Wall, who became the youngest male principal in the history of the Royal Ballet, dies of cancer, aged 67."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T11:20:21"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68251000/jpg/_68251528_wall_bbc.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Ballet dancer David Wall dies at 67"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Entertainment and Arts"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-22963499"/>
         <title>BBC News - Ballet dancer David Wall dies aged 67</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">12:20</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Ballet dancer David Wall dies aged 67</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68251000/jpg/_68251431_018360017-1.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="David Wall speaks to Princess Margaret after the Royal Ballet premiere of Mayerling in 1978"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">David Wall, pictured with Princess
Margaret after the Royal Ballet premiere of Mayerling in 1978, was
awarded the CBE</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Ballet dancer David
Wall, who became the youngest male principal in the history of the
Royal Ballet at the age of 21, has died of cancer.</p>
            <p>Wall, who was awarded the CBE, was a regular partner to Dame
Margot Fonteyn.</p>
            <p>He studied at the Royal Ballet School and joined the ballet's
touring company in 1963, becoming principal in 1966.</p>
            <p>Wall, who was 67, died at his family home in Croydon, south
London, on Tuesday. Friend Christopher Price paid tribute to "a
great dancer and artist".</p>
            <p>"It has been an honour to know him and he has brought the world
and his family so much joy and happiness during his lifetime," said
Mr Price.</p>
            <p>"His passing will be an enormous loss to
us all."</p>
            <p>Daria Klimentova, senior principal ballerina with the English
National Ballet (ENB), said she would dedicate her Wednesday
performance in Swan Lake at the Royal Albert Hall to her former
teacher and friend.</p>
            <p>She said <a href="https://twitter.com/DKlimentova/status/347072317358211072">she
would not be at the ENB without him</a> and that she did not know
how she was going to be able to perform after hearing the news.</p>
            <p>Gary Avis, ballet master and principal character artist at the
Royal Ballet, said he would be raising a glass to his friend.</p>
            <p>"With admiration, gratitude and respect I thank you David Wall
for being a friend, mentor and gentleman!" he said on <a href="https://twitter.com/balletboy09/status/347067537504210944">Twitter</a>.</p>
            <p>He said his passing was "unbelievably sad" but called him "a
brave and courageous man" adding he was "inspirational but above
all a real gent with an amazing sense of humour".</p>
            <p>David Wall was accepted into the Royal Ballet school at the age
of 10. A school teacher persuaded his mother to let him audition
after seeing his potential in the compulsory ballroom dancing
lessons at his primary school in Windsor.</p>
            <p>But he said he did not always know he wanted to dance
professionally. He told <a href="http://www.ballet.co.uk/magazines/yr_05/jun05/interview_wall.htm&#34;">
Ballet Magazine</a> it was not until he completed his training, at
the age of 16 that he decided.</p>
            <p>"At that point, we were witness to two
really great ballets: La Fille mal gardee had just been created,
and Cranko's Antigone, in which the males took on the leading
roles. Also, Nureyev had just defected, so seeing the male get more
prominence in the art form spurred me on," he said.</p>
            <p>In 1963, Wall joined the Royal Ballet Touring Company and in
1970, he joined the main Royal Ballet company as principal.</p>
            <p>It was a golden age of classical ballet and Wall danced all the
leading roles with some of the greatest ballerinas, including
Doreen Wells and Lynn Seymour.</p>
            <p>He admitted at first he felt most comfortable dancing onstage
with his wife Alfreda Thorogood, who was a principal dancer at the
Royal Ballet.</p>
            <p>He was 17 the first time he danced with Dame Margot Fonteyn.</p>
            <p>Appearing on <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p009myx2">Radio 4's Desert Island
Discs</a>, in 1978, Wall remembered feeling nervous when Dame
Margot picked him to be her partner.</p>
            <p>"I was doubting and questioning my ability very much for three
weeks," he said.</p>
            <p>"But as soon as I got into the rehearsal room, she put me
totally at my ease and we really started to enjoy working."</p>
            <p>Wall was renowned for his acting ability, which he said was due
to his first artistic director, John Field, who encouraged his
dancers to see plays and watch actors perform.</p>
            <p>Wall retired from dancing in 1984, deciding not to continue as a
character dancer.</p>
            <p>"I had created Rudolf in Mayerling, I think that was the
pinnacle of my career, and I probably would have just become
complacent doing character roles. I needed other challenges," he
told Ballet Magazine.</p>
            <p>He became associate director of the Royal Academy and went on to
become director.</p>
            <p>In 1995, he joined the ENB as ballet master because he felt
strongly about the importance of teaching ballet.</p>
            <p>Gregory Nash, director of arts for the British Council, <a href="http://https://twitter.com/gregorynash_bc/status/347219814554673152">
said on Wednesday</a> that in 1981 Wall heard about the first
National Festival of Youth Dance on the radio and immediately drove
straight to Leicester to join them.</p>
            <p>Many of his <a href="https://twitter.com/pdconnaughton/status/347247994925617152">former
students</a> have paid tribute to his legacy.</p>
            <p>He is survived by his wife, two children and a number of
grandchildren.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371602183404"
                  href="/news/entertainment-arts-22963499">Ballet dancer David Wall dies
at 67</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">As soon as I got into the rehearsal room,
she put me totally at my ease and we really started to enjoy
working”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">David Wall on dancing with Dame Margot
Fonteyn</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>David Wall's Legacy</h2>
            <p>"David Wall came at a particular time in British Ballet. If you
think that British ballet started in 1931. So when David was
dancing in the 1960s that was really when it grew up.</p>
            <p>We had this generation of home-grown male talent that hadn't had
to take time out to do national service.</p>
            <p>So it really was the first time there was this coterie of male
principals and David was at the forefront of that.</p>
            <p>I think he combined incredible technical facility and strength
but with real acting ability, real interpretive skills.</p>
            <p>If you went to see David perform it was akin to really seeing
someone at the National Theatre.</p>
            <p>You felt you were going into the character, you were not just
seeing the steps you were living the life of the character and that
was his particular skill.</p>
            <p>David had an incredibly masculine presence, he had a real
physicality.</p>
            <p>When he danced a pas de deux with Lynn Seymour or Alfreda
Thorogood, his wife who he danced with, you had no doubt there was
that chemistry between them. Because he managed to have this
sensuality and real masculinity in his work."</p>
            <p>
               <em>Deborah Bull is a former Royal Ballet dancer and Creative
Director at The Royal Opera House.</em>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
