<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-23205638"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A baby has been born in the US using a new method for screening embryos during IVF which could dramatically reduce costs, researchers report."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-07T23:02:03"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68579000/jpg/_68579323_baby.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Baby success for new IVF screen"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Health"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-23205638"/>
         <title>BBC News - Baby born using new IVF screening
technique</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">8 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:02</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Baby born using new IVF screening
technique</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By James
Gallagher</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Health and science
reporter, BBC News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68579000/jpg/_68579219_baby.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Connor Levy"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Connor Levy's parents had been trying to conceive
naturally for four years.</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A baby has been born
in the US using a new method for screening embryos during IVF which
could dramatically reduce costs, researchers report.</p>
            <p>Connor Levy was born in May after the test, devised at Oxford
University, helped doctors pick an embryo with the best chance of
success.</p>
            <p>Only one in three attempts at IVF results in a baby as
abnormalities in an embryo's DNA are common.</p>
            <p>Large trials are now needed to see how effective the method is,
experts say.</p>
            <p>If there are abnormalities with the packages of DNA, called
chromosomes, in the embryo then it will not implant in the womb or
if it does the foetus will not reach term.</p>
            <p>It is a problem which increases rapidly
with age. One quarter of embryos are abnormal in a woman's early
30s, but this soars to three quarters by the time a woman reaches
her late 30s and early 40s.</p>
            <p>Some clinics already offer a form of chromosome screening, but
it can add between Ã‚Â£2,000 and
Ã‚Â£3,000 to the cost of IVF in the UK.
Connor's mother, Marybeth Scheidts, said it would have cost her
$6,000 (Ã‚Â£4,100) for the test in
Pennsylvania.</p>
            <p>The new test takes advantage of the dramatic advances in
sequencing the human genome. Within 24 hours it can ensure the
correct number of chromosomes are present.</p>
            <p>Dr Dagan Wells from Oxford University told the BBC: "Current
tests are adding a significant amount of money on to an already
expensive procedure and that is limiting access; most patients are
having to pay for this out of pocket themselves.</p>
            <p>"What our technique does is it gives you the number of
chromosomes and other biological information about the embryo at a
low cost - probably about two thirds of the price of existing
methods of screening."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68576000/jpg/_68576861_c0104963-ivf_embryo,_light_micrograph-spl.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Embryo"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">How to pick the right embryo to implant is a major
issue in fertility clinics</span>
            </div>
            <p>He says trials are now needed to see if it could improve IVF
success rates.</p>
            <p>The baby and a further pregnancy resulting from the screening
method will be announced at the European Society of Human
Reproduction and Embryology conference.</p>
            <p>Marybeth Scheidts, 36, and her husband David Levy, 41, had been
trying to conceive naturally for four years and also tried
artificial insemination.</p>
            <p>In the screening three of the 13 embryos produced were healthy.
Without chromosome screening, picking the right embryo would have
been down to luck. Instead they were successful on their first
attempt.</p>
            <p>Marybeth told BBC News Online that the years of trying were
tough: "It takes its toll, there were some days I would break down
and cry, I wanted to hide in my bedroom and say stop.</p>
            <p>"Then to see him... all this hard work
and we have finally got our little tiny human being named
Connor."</p>
            <p>Dr Michael Glassner, the fertility doctor at Main Line Health
System where the IVF took place, said such techniques would become
more common.</p>
            <p>"If you have ever sat across the desk from a patient that has
failed or is in that crossroads of thinking of another cycle and
you look in their eyes where they are barely able to hold on to
their hopes and dreams - anything that is so significantly going to
impact pregnancy rates is going to become standard.</p>
            <p>"So I think five years from now you fast forward - yes I think
it will be standard."</p>
            <p>Commenting on the study, Stuart Lavery, a consultant
gynaecologist and director of IVF at Hammersmith Hospital, said:
"This is amazing science.</p>
            <p>"They done the work in humans, they've pregnancies - so it's a
pretty powerful proof of concept study using an exciting
technique."</p>
            <p>He also praised the researchers for saying proper trials needed
to be conducted before it was used widely.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373241406926"
                  href="/news/health-23181620">Viewpoints: The way forward for
IVF</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1341192159346"
                  href="/news/health-18649582">Five millionth 'test tube baby'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371518374298"
                  href="/news/health-22935211">Baby success for new 'safer' IVF</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">All this hard work and we have finally got
our little tiny human being named Connor”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Marybeth Scheidts</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Mother</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">They done the work in humans, they've
pregnancies - so it's a pretty powerful proof of concept study
using an exciting technique”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Stuart Lavery</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Director of IVF at Hammersmith
Hospital</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
