<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-23156403"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Non-EU nationals who come to England for more than six months could be charged at least Ã‚Â£200 a year to access the NHS."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-03T14:41:42"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68515000/jpg/_68515689_97768746.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Foreigners to face more NHS charges"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Politics"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-23156403"/>
         <title>BBC News - Foreigners face more charges to access
NHS</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">3 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">15:41</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Foreigners face more charges to access
NHS</h1>
            <div class="has-icon-comment dna-comment-count-simple"> </div>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68516000/jpg/_68516777_68516776.jpg"
                 alt="Health Secretary Jeremy Hunt"/>
               <p class="caption">Health Secretary Jeremy Hunt: "It is a national
health service not an international health service"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Proposals to charge
more foreigners for using NHS services in England and to fix the
"flawed" system for recovering costs have been unveiled.</p>
            <p>People from outside Europe staying for up to five years would
face an annual charge of at least Ã‚Â£200.</p>
            <p>Residency rules would be tightened on free treatment and more
services, such as access to GPs, would be chargeable.</p>
            <p>Ministers say the NHS cannot be an international service but
doctors say plans could pose a public health risk.</p>
            <p>The <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/210438/Sustaining_services__ensuring_fairness_consultation_document.pdf">
consultation document</a>, published on Wednesday, outlines
proposals aimed at cutting the cost of migrants' NHS healthcare in
England.</p>
            <p>They include:</p>
            <ul>
               <li>Restricting free treatment for people from outside the European
Economic Area citizens to those with indefinite leave to remain in
the UK</li>
               <li>Allowing anyone living abroad who has paid National Insurance
for at least seven years in the past to get free treatment while on
UK visits</li>
               <li>A "health levy" on migrants from outside the EEA staying for up
to five years of at least Ã‚Â£200 a year -
unless they have private health cover</li>
               <li>Improving how non-EEA short-term visitors are identified and
charged for hospital treatment</li>
               <li>Extending hospital charges to GP practices and other NHS
treatment for non-permanent residents</li>
               <li>Treatment for infectious diseases and sexually transmitted
infections to remain free for all</li>
               <li>Improving current "flawed" systems for enforcing current
charging rules</li>
               <li>Considering sharing personal information relevant to NHS
charges between the NHS, government departments and other
agencies</li>
            </ul>
            <p>The government says the NHS is one of the most generous systems
in the world and is also "open to abuse by those intent on cheating
the system".</p>
            <p>It does not know how much so-called "health tourism" costs the
NHS - estimates range from Ã‚Â£12m to
Ã‚Â£200m a year - but is to carry out an
"audit" to work out the extent of the problem.</p>
            <p>The Department of Health said the cost of treating foreigners is
at least Ã‚Â£30m a year for the NHS in England
alone - although Dr Clare Gerada, chairwoman of the Royal College
of GPs, said that was the equivalent of just two hours of the NHS's
annual spending.</p>
            <p>The health levy would largely affect foreign students and the
Ã‚Â£200 figure was considered competitive with
what other countries charged foreign students, Health Secretary
Jeremy Hunt told the BBC. But it could be set higher and might
exclude certain treatments like IVF, cosmetic surgery, organ
transplants and antenatal care for pre-existing pregnancies.</p>
            <p>Under existing rules, visitors from
outside the EEA should pay for hospital treatment - but the
government says only a fraction of charges are collected.</p>
            <p>It says it will work on improving the system, possibly through
"improved technology" to track patients, and stop hospitals being
discouraged from identifying foreign patients because they are
liable for unrecoverable debts.</p>
            <p>It also says it will extend charges to GP surgeries and other
primary care for those not eligible for free treatment.</p>
            <p>Mr Hunt said the government needed to "ensure that those
residing or visiting the UK are contributing to the system in the
same way as British taxpayers and ensure we do as much as possible
to target illegal migration".</p>
            <p>"We have been clear that we are a national health service not an
international health service and I am determined to wipe out abuse
in the system," he added.</p>
            <p>Some doctors have warned they fear being turned into "a form of
immigration control" over plans to charge visitors for GP
access.</p>
            <div class="audioInStoryC">
               <div id="emp-23160057-22112" class="emp">
                  <noscript>
                     <div class="warning">
                        <img class="holding"
                          src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68519000/jpg/_68519370_018508752.jpg"
                          alt="A stethoscope around a man's neck"/>
                        <p>
                           <strong>Please turn on JavaScript.</strong> Media requires
JavaScript to play.</p>
                     </div>
                  </noscript>
                  <object width="0" height="0">
                     <param name="id" value="embeddedPlayer_23160057"/>
                     <param name="width" value="304"/>
                     <param name="height" value="71"/>
                     <param name="size" value="Small"/>
                     <param name="externalIdentifier" value="p01c7r7x"/>
                     <param name="playlist"
                         value="http://playlists.bbc.co.uk/news/health-23160057A/playlist.sxml"/>
                     <param name="config_settings_autoPlay" value="false"/>
                     <param name="config_settings_showPopoutButton" value="false"/>
                     <param name="config_plugin_fmtjLiveStats_pageType" value="eav2"/>
                     <param name="config_plugin_fmtjLiveStats_edition" value="Domestic"/>
                     <param name="fmtjDocURI" value="/news/health-23156403"/>
                     <param name="config_settings_suppressItemKind" value="advert, ident"/>
                     <param name="config_settings_showShareButton" value="true"/>
                     <param name="config_settings_showUpdatedInFooter" value="true"/>
                  </object>
               </div>
            </div>
            <p>Royal College of GPs chairwoman Dr Gerada said: "My first duty
is to my patient - I don't ask where they're from or whether
they've got a credit card or whether they can pay."</p>
            <p>For Labour, shadow health minister Liz Kendall said people who
were not entitled to free NHS care should be made to pay for it but
added: "We will have many questions to ask about the details when
they are published but the key tests for their proposals are: can
they be properly enforced and will they save more money than they
cost to put in place?"</p>
            <p>She also said plans must "protect the public's health as well as
taxpayers' money".</p>
            <p>On Twitter, shadow public health minister Diane Abbott said:
"What price xenophobia? Stigmatising foreigners accessing NHS
creates a public health risk."</p>
            <p>The National Aids Trust said the policies would "undermine years
of work to encourage marginalised at-risk groups to access HIV
testing and treatment".</p>
            <p>Chief executive Deborah Jack said "limiting access to primary
care for some migrants" would cut off "the only place many of them
will get an HIV diagnosis - short of presenting at A&amp;E many
years after they were infected once they are very seriously
ill".</p>
            <p>She added: "If they go ahead, they risk putting lives at risk
and accelerating the spread of HIV in the general population."</p>
            <p>The Department of Health said people with HIV would still
receive free healthcare if the scheme was introduced and Mr Hunt
told the BBC there would be an "exemption on all public health
grounds" and pointed to other countries which charge for healthcare
but did not suffer higher rates of, for example TB, as a
result.</p>
            <p>The government has previously said a government-wide push to cut
"benefit tourism" was being considered in response to "widespread
public concern".</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372851133333"
                  href="/news/health-23159485">Reaction to 'health tourism' plans</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1362375816815"
                  href="/news/uk-politics-21651631">No 10 'considering EU benefit
curbs'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1349255277623"
                  href="/news/health-19789397">Health tourists cost NHS millions</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <div class="correspondent-byline">
               <a href="/news/correspondents/nicktriggle/">
                  <span class="byline-picture">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/63731000/jpg/_63731542_triggle-112x81.jpg"
                       alt="image of Nick Triggle"/>
                  </span>
               </a>
               <span class="byline-heading">ANALYSIS</span>
               <a href="/news/correspondents/nicktriggle/">
                  <span class="byline-name">Nick
Triggle</span>
               </a>
               <span class="byline-title">Health
correspondent</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>Those working in the NHS are much less exercised about the
health tourism "problem" than politicians.</p>
            <p>There are good public health and moral reasons why the health
service provides treatment for infectious diseases such as TB and
in emergencies.</p>
            <p>Non-emergency care is a much greyer issue - and that is why
ministers are now talking about applying a levy for that.</p>
            <p>But the major obstacle is how it can be applied.</p>
            <p>GPs have already made it clear they will not be "border guards"
and without a simple system to check eligibility there is a risk
the crackdown will cost more than it saves.</p>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/correspondents/nicktriggle/">Read more from
Nick</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
