<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-22949211"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="There should be &#34;no hiding place&#34; for anyone involved in a cover-up by England's NHS regulator after baby deaths at a Cumbria hospital, the health secretary says."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T18:18:21"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68257000/jpg/_68257403_titcombe_sis.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="NHS 'cover-up' unacceptable - Hunt"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Health"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-22949211"/>
         <title>BBC News - NHS 'cover-up' unacceptable, says health
secretary</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">19:18</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">NHS 'cover-up' unacceptable, says health
secretary</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68254000/jpg/_68254038_titcombe_pa.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Joshua Titcombe"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Joshua Titcombe died nine days after being born at
Furness General Hospital</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A cover-up by
England's NHS regulatory body after a series of baby deaths at a
Cumbria hospital is unacceptable, the health secretary says.</p>
            <p>Jeremy Hunt was speaking after a review of the Care Quality
Commission's (CQC) response to complaints about several deaths at
Furness General Hospital.</p>
            <p>The <a href="http://www.cqc.org.uk/sites/default/files/media/documents/grant_thornton_uk_llp_morecambe_bay.pdf">
review</a> has shown a senior manager may have ordered the deletion
of a report critical of the CQC last year.</p>
            <p>Mr Hunt promised there would be "no hiding place" for those
responsible.</p>
            <p>In a statement to the House of Commons, he said the CQC was
already introducing a tougher inspection regime and had just
appointed a chief inspector of hospitals.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile, he said the government was introducing measures to
make the NHS more transparent, including a duty of candour to
compel the health service to be open and honest about mistakes.</p>
            <p>But Mr Hunt said the attempt to cover up as described in the
report was "completely unacceptable" and the truth must come
out.</p>
            <p>"There should be no anonymity, no hiding place, no opportunity
to get off Scot-free for anyone at all who was responsible for
this."</p>
            <p>And he added: "What happened at Morecambe Bay is above all a
terrible personal tragedy for all the families involved.</p>
            <p>"I want to apologise on behalf of the government and the NHS for
all the appalling suffering they have endured."</p>
            <p>In total, more than 30 families have
taken legal action against Furness General Hospital relating to
baby and maternal deaths and injuries from 2008.</p>
            <p>The CQC asked consultants Grant Thornton to investigate its
failure to spot the problems - Morecambe Bay NHS Trust, which ran
the hospital, had been given a clean bill of health in 2010.</p>
            <p>The consultants found a year after this, with more concerns
emerging, an internal review had been ordered into how the problems
had gone unnoticed.</p>
            <p>But in March 2012 it was decided the findings should not be made
public as the review was so critical of the CQC. The order is said
to have come from a senior manager who has not been named for data
protection reasons. The individual denies the allegations.</p>
            <p>The latest report said this "might well have constituted a
deliberate cover-up".</p>
            <p>But it also acknowledged the CQC had been hampered in its work
because the trust and regional health bosses had failed to share
information about the problems.</p>
            <p>CQC chairman David Prior said the report was "shocking" and
showed the regulator was "not fit for purpose".</p>
            <p>"This is a shocking state of affairs. I am desperately sorry
this has happened," he said.</p>
            <p>But he said publication "draws a line in the sand for us".</p>
            <p>"The report confirms our view that at a senior level the
organisation was dysfunctional. The board and the senior executive
team have been radically changed."</p>
            <p>However, at a CQC meeting on Wednesday non-executive director
Kay Sheldon said she had been treated in an "appalling" manner when
she tried to raise the alarm about what was going on.</p>
            <p>The trust has said that, given the continuing investigation, it
would be "inappropriate to comment on individual cases".</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68261000/jpg/_68261958_68261957.jpg"
                 alt="Jeremy Hunt"/>
               <p class="caption">Jeremy Hunt statement in full</p>
            </div>
            <p>But it has said there is "no denying that the trust has let
women and their families down in the past" and that the new trust
board is "determined to learn from it".</p>
            <p>James Titcombe, whose nine-day old son, Joshua, died in 2008
from a treatable infection after being born in the hospital's
maternity ward, said: "The report lays bare a number of extremely
serious failures [that are] quite hard to believe."</p>
            <p>The publication of Wednesday's report comes four months after a
public inquiry into the failings at another hospital - Stafford -
criticised the culture of the NHS as more concerned with protecting
"corporate self-interest" than patient care.</p>
            <p>Shadow health minister Jamie Reed called on ministers "to order
an urgent investigation into the questions raised by this
report".</p>
            <p>"It would be indefensible for the CQC, the regulator charged
with keeping our hospitals safe, to attempt a cover-up designed to
mask its own failings," he said.</p>
            <p>"My constituents who use this hospital deserve much better and
the government needs to provide answers on every aspect of this
serious allegation."</p>
            <p>Tim Farron, Liberal Democrat MP for Westmorland and Lonsdale,
has asked the police to investigate the issue.</p>
            <p>"It's quite clear as well that the CQC attempted to subvert the
Freedom of Information Act. That's come out today as well and that
means this is potentially a criminal issue and I've written to the
constabulary this afternoon to ask them to open that inquiry."</p>
            <p>It is not the first time the regulator has come under fire since
its creation in 2009.</p>
            <div class="audioInStoryC">
               <div id="emp-22964981-119918" class="emp">
                  <noscript>
                     <div class="warning">
                        <img class="holding"
                          src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68253000/jpg/_68253306_68253305.jpg"
                          alt="Health check results, inc blood test results with stethoscope"/>
                        <p>
                           <strong>Please turn on JavaScript.</strong> Media requires
JavaScript to play.</p>
                     </div>
                  </noscript>
                  <object width="0" height="0">
                     <param name="id" value="embeddedPlayer_22964981"/>
                     <param name="width" value="304"/>
                     <param name="height" value="71"/>
                     <param name="size" value="Small"/>
                     <param name="externalIdentifier" value="p01blw70"/>
                     <param name="playlist"
                         value="http://playlists.bbc.co.uk/news/health-22964981A/playlist.sxml"/>
                     <param name="config_settings_autoPlay" value="false"/>
                     <param name="config_settings_showPopoutButton" value="false"/>
                     <param name="config_plugin_fmtjLiveStats_pageType" value="eav2"/>
                     <param name="config_plugin_fmtjLiveStats_edition" value="Domestic"/>
                     <param name="fmtjDocURI" value="/news/health-22949211"/>
                     <param name="config_settings_suppressItemKind" value="advert, ident"/>
                     <param name="config_settings_showShareButton" value="true"/>
                     <param name="config_settings_showUpdatedInFooter" value="true"/>
                  </object>
               </div>
            </div>
            <p>Widespread concerns prompted ministers to scrutinise the CQC's
performance and recommend a raft of changes including the creation
of a new hospitals chief inspector post and a ratings system.</p>
            <p>Action against Medical Accidents chief executive Peter Walsh
said the report was "a vindication of what local people affected by
failings by the trust and by regulators have been saying".</p>
            <p>"It underlines the need for a fully independent and wide-ranging
inquiry into how, even in the aftermath of Mid Staffordshire, the
regulatory system utterly failed to protect patients and sought to
cover up," he added.</p>
            <p>"It is vital that the new leaders of the CQC ensure it is a
robust, proactive and honest regulator."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371642736998"
                  href="/news/health-22968167">The rotten side of the NHS</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedlisten">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371629441771"
                  href="/news/health-22964981">CQC chair
'desperately sorry' <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedlisten">Listen</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371651061071"
                  href="/news/health-22973382">Jeremy Hunt
statement <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Case study</h2>
            <p>James Titcombe is the father of newborn Joshua, who died at
Furness General Hospital in 2008.</p>
            <p>"Shortly after Joshua was born, my wife collapsed with a very
high temperature and she was given antibiotics.</p>
            <p>"We had very serious concerns for Joshua, but we were repeatedly
reassured he was OK. He was not seen by a doctor.</p>
            <p>"He collapsed at 24 hours of age through the same infection my
wife had, and he died in quite horrible circumstances nine days
later.</p>
            <p>"We wanted an investigation. We were not happy with the trust's
initial investigation and we went to the ombudsman to request an
investigation.</p>
            <p>"One of the shocking things about the CQC's failures was the CQC
repeatedly told the ombudsman that they were the organisation that
would deal with these issues, and on that basis, the report says,
the ombudsman was persuaded not to investigate Joshua's death."</p>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/health-22968167">The rotten side of the
NHS</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
