<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-23068423"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="In a pioneering experiment, scientists in Japan clone a mouse from white blood cells collected from the tail of a living donor."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T02:02:45"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68391000/jpg/_68391990_58170.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Mouse cloned from drop of blood"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Health"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-23068423"/>
         <title>BBC News - Mouse cloned from drop of blood</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">03:02</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Mouse cloned from drop of blood</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Helen
Briggs</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68384000/jpg/_68384834_58170.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="cloned mouse"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The mouse was cloned from a blood cell</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Scientists in Japan
have cloned a mouse from a single drop of blood.</p>
            <p>Circulating blood cells collected from the tail of a donor mouse
were used to produce the clone, a team at the Riken BioResource
Center <a href="http://www.biolreprod.org/content/early/2013/06/25/biolreprod.113.110098.abstract">
reports in the journal Biology of Reproduction</a>.</p>
            <p>The female mouse lived a normal lifespan and could give birth to
young, say the researchers.</p>
            <p>Scientists at a linked institute recently created nearly 600
exact genetic copies of one mouse.</p>
            <p>Mice have been cloned from several different sources of donor
cells, including white blood cells found in the lymph nodes, bone
marrow and liver.</p>
            <p>The Japanese research group investigated
whether circulating blood cells could also be used for cloning.</p>
            <p>Their aim was to find an easily available source of donor cells
to clone scientifically valuable strains of laboratory mice.</p>
            <p>The team, led by Atsuo Ogura, of Riken BioResource Center in
Tsukuba, took blood from the tail of a donor mouse, isolated the
white blood cells, and used the nuclei for cloning experiments,
using the same technique that produced Dolly the sheep in
Edinburgh.</p>
            <p>The process, known as somatic cell nuclear transfer, involves
transferring the nucleus from an adult body cell - such as a blood
or skin cell - into an unfertilised egg that has had its nucleus
removed.</p>
            <p>Reporting their findings in the US journal, <a href="http://www.biolreprod.org/">Biology of Reproduction</a>, the
scientists said the study "demonstrated for the first time that
mice could be cloned using the nuclei of peripheral blood
cells".</p>
            <p>They added: "These cells could be used for cloning immediately
after collection and no donor animals need to be euthanised.</p>
            <p>"This technique would be applicable for
generating genetic copies of invaluable strains of mice, which
cannot be preserved by other assisted reproductive techniques such
as conventional in vitro fertilisation or intracytoplasmic sperm
injection."</p>
            <p>Scientists in Japan have years of experience in cloning
mice.</p>
            <p>A team at a linked institute recently revealed they had produced
almost 600 mice from one donor mouse after 25 consecutive rounds of
cloning.</p>
            <p>The research is aimed at large-scale production of high-quality
animals for farming or conservation purposes, they say.</p>
            <p>Commenting on the study, Professor Robin Lovell-Badge of the MRC
National Institute of Medical Research in London, said it was a
useful small advance on previous work showing that it is possible
to clone mice from a variety of adult cell types, including white
blood cells.</p>
            <p>He told BBC News: "The efficiency of cloning from these cell
types was very good, suggesting that even a small drop of blood
will contain sufficient numbers...this is helpful if the intention
is to use cloning to propagate and expand numbers of rare or
valuable types of individual or species."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1349121243994"
                  href="/news/health-19785006">GM cows make 'low allergy' milk</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1280940972031"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-10871737">US confidence in clone
food</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">This technique would be applicable for
generating genetic copies of invaluable strains of mice”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Research team</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Riken BioResource Center, Tsukuba</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>The cloning method - somatic cell nuclear transfer</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Clones of adult animals are produced by a method called somatic
cell nuclear transfer, which refers to the transfer of the nucleus
from a somatic cell into an egg cell</li>
               <li>A somatic cell is any cell of the body apart from a germ (sex)
cell</li>
               <li>In cloning, the nucleus of a somatic cell is removed and
inserted into a donor unfertilised egg that has had its own nucleus
(containing the genetic material) removed</li>
               <li>The embryo is then placed inside a surrogate mother.</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
