<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-23132561"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Two patients have been taken off their HIV drugs after a bone marrow transplant seems to have cleared the virus from their bodies, doctors report."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-03T08:32:15"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68485000/jpg/_68485324_c0121956-hiv_particles,_artwork-spl.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Bone marrow 'frees men of HIV drugs'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Health"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-23132561"/>
         <title>BBC News - Bone marrow 'frees men of HIV drugs'</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">3 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">09:32</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Bone marrow 'frees men of HIV drugs'</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By James
Gallagher</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Health and science
reporter, BBC News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68485000/jpg/_68485318_c0121956-hiv_particles,_artwork-spl.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="HIV "/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Two patients have
been taken off their HIV drugs after bone-marrow transplants seemed
to clear the virus from their bodies, doctors report.</p>
            <p>One of the patients has spent nearly four months without taking
medication with no sign of the virus returning.</p>
            <p>The team at Brigham and Women's Hospital, in the US, caution
that it is far too soon to talk about a cure as the virus could
return at any point.</p>
            <p>The findings were presented at the <a href="http://www.iasociety.org/Default.aspx?pageId=3">International Aids
Society Conference</a>.</p>
            <p>It is difficult to get rid of an HIV infection because it hides
inside human DNA, forming untouchable "reservoirs" in body.</p>
            <p>Anti-retroviral drugs keep the virus in check within the
bloodstream - but when the drugs stop, the virus comes back.</p>
            <p>The two men, who have not been identified, had lived with HIV
for about 30 years.</p>
            <p>They both developed a cancer, lymphoma, which required a
bone-marrow transplant.</p>
            <p>Bone marrow is where new blood cells are made and it is thought
to be a major reservoir for HIV.</p>
            <p>After the transplant, there was no detectable HIV in the blood
for two years in one patient and four in the other.</p>
            <p>The pair came off their anti-retroviral
drugs earlier this year.</p>
            <p>One has gone 15 weeks, and the other seven, since stopping
treatment, and no signs of the virus have been detected so far.</p>
            <p>Dr Timothy Henrich told the BBC the results were exciting. But
he added: "We have not demonstrated cure, we're going to need
longer follow-up.</p>
            <p>"What we can say is if the virus does stay away for a year or
even two years after we stopped the treatment, that the chances of
the virus rebounding are going to be extremely low.</p>
            <p>"It's much too early at this point to use the C-word
[cure]."</p>
            <p>It is thought that the transplanted bone marrow was initially
protected from infection by the course of anti-retrovirals.
Meanwhile the transplant also attacked the remaining bone marrow,
which was harbouring the virus.</p>
            <p>However Dr Henrich cautioned that the virus could be still be
hiding inside brain tissue or the gastrointestinal track.</p>
            <p>"If [the] virus does return, it would suggest that these other
sites are an important reservoir of infectious virus and new
approaches to measuring the reservoir at relevant sites will be
needed to guide the development of HIV curative strategies," he
said.</p>
            <p>Timothy Brown, also known as the "Berlin patient" is thought to
be the first person cured of Aids. He had a bone marrow transplant
from a rare donor who was resistant to HIV.</p>
            <p>The two US cases both received bone marrow from normal
donors.</p>
            <p>There was also a report of an HIV cure in a baby born in
Mississippi, US. She was treated with anti-retroviral drugs at
birth so it is thought the virus was cleared from the body before
reservoirs were established.</p>
            <p>Dr Michael Brady, the medical director of the Terrence Higgins
Trust, said: "It is too early to know whether HIV has been
eradicated from these men's bodies or whether it might return.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68522000/jpg/_68522436_hivvirus.jpg"
                 alt="HIV virus"/>
               <p class="caption">Doctors say it is far too soon to talk about a
cure for HIV, as James Gallagher reports</p>
            </div>
            <p>"However, the case suggests that what happened to Timothy Brown,
the Berlin Patient was perhaps not a one-off.</p>
            <p>"A bone marrow transplant is a complex and expensive procedure,
which comes with significant risks.</p>
            <p>"For most people with HIV, it would be more dangerous to undergo
a transplant than to continue managing the virus with daily
medication.</p>
            <p>"So while this is by no means a workable cure, it does give
researchers another signpost in the direction of one."</p>
            <p>The head of the Foundation for AIDS Research, Kevin Frost, said:
"These findings clearly provide important new information that
might well alter the current thinking about HIV and gene
therapy.</p>
            <p>"While stem-cell transplantation is not a viable option for
people with HIV on a broad scale because of its costs and
complexity, these new cases could lead us to new approaches to
treating, and ultimately even eradicating, HIV."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1226555836000"
                  href="/1/hi/health/7726118.stm">Bone marrow 'cures HIV patient'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1362350200780"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-21651225">HIV baby 'cured' by
treatment</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1365008407017"
                  href="/news/health-22002455">Body's 'anti-HIV manual' recorded</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <p>It is far too early to call this a cure for HIV. And even if it
was a cure, it wouldn't be a very good one.</p>
            <p>It is very expensive and often leads to "graft-v-host" disease.
There is a 15-20% mortality rate within the first few years after
the transplant.</p>
            <p>This occurs when new immune cells produced by the graft treat
the rest of the body as foreign and attack it.</p>
            <p>The two patients in this study have replaced their regimen of
anti-retroviral drugs, with those to suppress the immune
system.</p>
            <p>The procedure was carried out in these patients only because
they had cancer that needed to be treated.</p>
            <p>The real value of this research for the majority of people with
HIV will come from a deeper understanding of the virus and HIV
reservoirs.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
