<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23029814"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The Edward Snowden affair shows how complicated the international web of extradition treaties are."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-26T23:29:07"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68376000/jpg/_68376119_ramses.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="10 things about extradition"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Magazine"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23029814"/>
         <title>BBC News - 10 things about extradition</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:29</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">10 things about extradition</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Kathryn Westcott
and Vanessa Barford</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68344000/jpg/_68344215_trail2.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="230"
                 alt="Vapour trail"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The Edward Snowden affair shows how
complicated the international web of extradition treaties is. Here
are 10 quirks of the system.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>1. The world's oldest</strong> surviving written
extradition agreement - and peace treaty - was made by <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/ancient/egyptians/ramesses_01.shtml">Ramesses
II of Egypt</a> and the neighbouring Hittites in about 1259 BC.
Sometimes known as the Treaty of Kadesh (following a battle there
some years earlier), the agreement bound both sides to repatriate
criminals and political refugees from the other side.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68365000/jpg/_68365351_ramses.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="308"
                 alt="Temple of Ramesses II, Abu Simbel"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The temple of Ramesses II at Abu Simbel
in Egypt</span>
            </div>
            <p>The Egyptian version of the treaty is preserved at Karnak. Its
counterpart was discovered at Hattusa - site of the Hittite royal
palace - in Turkey in 1916. A copy of that version now hangs on the
walls of the UN headquarters in New York.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>2. The first US</strong> extradition agreement was with
Great Britain in 1794. It was not a full treaty but a single
article in a broader treaty which sought to settle outstanding
issues between the two countries that had been left unresolved
since American independence. It only mentions the crimes of murder
and forgery. The US's first modern treaty was signed with Ecuador
in 1872, according to Douglas McNabb, an expert in US federal
criminal law and international extradition.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68360000/jpg/_68360492_ecuador.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="319"
                 alt="Ecuadorean flag"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Ecuador was co-signatory of the US's first
extradition treaty</span>
            </div>
            <p>Early treaties often recite a "laundry list" of crimes, while
modern ones tend to specify crimes that have a minimum sentence of
a year in prison says McNabb. Early treaties such as those with
Ecuador, Venezuela and Cuba include murder, assassination, piracy,
mutiny and revolt, bigamy, counterfeiting and unlawful destruction
of property such as railroads and bridges. Abortion was added in
later updates.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>3. Ingrained in most</strong>
international extradition laws is the "political offence"
exception, says McNabb. It allows the requested state to refuse
extradition of those accused of political crimes or where that
state believes the real motivation for the request is political
rather than criminal.</p>
            <p>The first British Extradition Act of 1870 declared that no-one
could be surrendered if their offence was one of a political
character. Many refugees fleeing Europe at the time - including
Karl Marx - were offered shelter in the UK.</p>
            <p>The European Convention on the Suppression of Terrorism (1977)
limited the scope of the political offence exception.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>4. The former reputation</strong> of parts of Spain as
the Costa del Crime rested largely on the collapse of a
100-year-old treaty, which Benjamin Disraeli had a hand in
negotiating. When it ran out in 1978, Spain did not hurry to renew
it because it felt that it had not benefitted, with only a few
extradition applications being accepted by the UK. "Spain uses
civil law, and the UK has common law, and Spain didn't really
understand how to make successful extradition treaty requests,
which at that time required prima facie evidence, to the UK and so
the relationship wasn't working," says Anand Doobay, an extradition
expert at law firm Peters &amp; Peters. "So during this period,
practically every criminal in the UK went to Spain." A new
bilateral agreement was signed in 1985.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68360000/jpg/_68360498_sexybeast.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="312"
                 alt="Ray Winstone in Sexy Beast"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Life on the Costa del Crime, as
portrayed in the film Sexy Beast</span>
            </div>
            <p>
               <strong>5. The revival of</strong> the extradition treaty with
Spain forced criminals from the UK to look for somewhere else to
hide. The self-styled Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus (TRNC)
beckoned, being the closest place to the UK with no extradition
treaty. Separated from the Republic of Cyprus, it is only
recognised by Turkey. In 2012, the Serious Organised Crime Agency
(Soca) said Northern Cyprus was emerging as a growing centre for
fugitive criminals.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68365000/jpg/_68365346_nadir.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="316"
                 alt="Asil Nadir"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Asil Nadir was eventually sentenced to 10 years in
jail in 2012</span>
            </div>
            <p>It was home to Asil Nadir for 17 years after he fled the UK
while facing trial over the collapse of the company he headed,
Polly Peck International. But recently, the authorities have been
cooperating with British police to apprehend and deport suspected
wrongdoers. Dubai also became a bolthole for British fugitives, but
an extradition treaty signed between the UK and the United Arab
Emirates in 2008 has made it less of a draw.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>6. Brazil had no</strong> extradition treaty with the UK
before the late 1990s, allowing Great Train Robber Ronnie Biggs -
who had escaped from Wandsworth Prison in 1965 - to enjoy the sun
and sand of Rio for decades. Even if there had been a reciprocal
treaty, Brazilian law prohibits the father of a Brazilian child
from being extradited. In 1981, Biggs was kidnapped in Rio by a
group of former British soldiers working for a security firm and
ended up in the Bahamas, where it was hoped the government would
extradite him to the UK. The country's high court, however, sent
him back to Brazil. In 1997, Brazil and the UK signed a treaty, but
Brazil still rejected a request to extradite Biggs. They also cited
a statute of limitations that discounted crimes committed more than
two decades previously.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68360000/jpg/_68360496_biggsy.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="322"
                 alt="ronald biggs"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Police mug shots of Ronald Biggs</span>
            </div>
            <p>
               <strong>7. Many countries will</strong> not extradite their own
citizens to stand trial - some have this enshrined in their
constitutions. Russia, for example, argued that its constitution
prohibited it from extraditing Andrei Lugovoi, wanted for the
poisoning of dissident Alexander Litvinenko in London in 2006.</p>
            <p>Germany also has a very strong
constitutional law. If a court feels the request is not
proportionate - perhaps being for a minor offence - the
Constitutional Court can block the extradition, says Jodie
Blackstock, director of criminal and EU justice policy at charity
Justice. "The Netherlands also usually seeks to request that a
national accused of crimes committed abroad is tried, or serves a
sentence, in the Netherlands," she says.</p>
            <p>France has provided refuge to director Roman Polanski, wanted by
the US after fleeing before he could be sentenced for having sex
with a minor in 1977, because of his French citizenship,.</p>
            <p>Former counter-culture leader Ira Einhorn - who was convicted in
the US in absentia for the murder of his girlfriend in 1977 -
enjoyed the protection of the French legal system for a number of
years, not because of French citizenship, but because France holds
that trial in absentia is an abuse of human rights.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>8. The UK is</strong> a "bit unique" in not making the
protection of nationals from extradition a feature of UK law, says
Blackstock.</p>
            <p>"I think it goes back to empire days when Britons were regularly
travelling everywhere and establishing new lives.</p>
            <p>"But even now, with the European Arrest Warrant in place, and
where there is a provision in the EU framework decision that member
states can seek for criminals to serve the sentence in their own
country, we haven't transcribed that into UK law," she says.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>9. Embassies have long</strong>
given refuge to those fighting extradition. Under international
law, diplomatic posts are considered the territory of the foreign
nation. But authorities take different views on this. When Julian
Assange took refuge in Ecuador's embassy a year ago, the British
government considered invoking the Diplomatic and Consular Premises
Act (1987) allowing for the revocation of a building's diplomatic
status if the foreign power occupying it "ceases to use land for
the purposes of its mission or exclusively for the purposes of a
consular post".</p>
            <p>"Diplomatic immunity exists to allow embassies and diplomats to
exercise proper diplomatic functions and the harbouring of alleged
criminals, or frustrating the due legal process in a country, is
not a permitted function," William Hague said at the time.</p>
            <p>"Seeking asylum within an embassy - like Assange has done - is
much more prevalent within South America, where there are
agreements between governments which recognise this. If a Peruvian
opposition leader unsuccessfully attempts to overthrow the
government then they can go to the Colombian embassy in Peru and
seek asylum, for example. It's much more common and recognised,
whereas the UK government has never recognised the principle that
you can grant asylum in an embassy," says Doobay.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>10. Xenophobia and illicit</strong> trafficking in
hormonal substances are among the categories of offences a European
Arrest Warrant (EAW) can be sought for which do not require the
conduct to be a crime in the country receiving the EAW. The system,
which has been in effect since 2004, was designed to simplify
extradition procedures and has been signed up to by the 27 EU
member states.</p>
            <p>Other offences on the list of 32 include terrorism, trafficking
in human beings, corruption and fraud, murder, kidnapping and
hostage-taking.</p>
            <p>
               <em>You can follow the Magazine on</em>
               <a href="https://twitter.com/BBCNewsMagazine">Twitter</a>
               <em>and on</em>
               <a href="http://www.facebook.com/BBCMagazine"
               title="Facebook - BBC Magazine">Facebook</a>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68365000/jpg/_68365350_92845892.jpg"
              width="144"
              height="144"
              alt="Karl Marx"/>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Many refugees fleeing Europe - including
Karl Marx - were offered shelter in the UK”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Roman Polanski</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68360000/jpg/_68360494_169454430.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="191"
                 alt="Roman Polanski"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>Polish director, born 1933 - acclaimed for films including
Rosemary's Baby, Chinatown and The Pianist</li>
               <li>Fled US in 1977 after pleading guilty to sex with 13-year-old
girl</li>
               <li>Has lived in France ever since; US failed to extradite Polanski
<a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/10601930">from Switzerland in
2010</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>More from the Magazine</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/66945000/jpg/_66945366_assange-in-embassy.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="214"
                 alt="Julian Assange at the Ecuadorean Embassy"/>
            </div>
            <p>What's day-to-day life like for Wikileaks founder Julian Assange
in London's Ecuadorean embassy - and for his diplomatic hosts?
<a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-20026480">(At home with
Julian Assange)</a>
            </p>
            <p>There is a long tradition of dissidents seeking sanctuary in
embassies. But is it legal or not? <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-17905985">(Who, What, Why: Is
it legal to hide in an embassy?)</a>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
