<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-22946672"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="He is often called the &#34;worst US president&#34;. But as a new book reignites the debate, does James Buchanan really deserve the title?"/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T00:42:16"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68417000/jpg/_68417537_00051u.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Was James Buchanan really the worst president?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Magazine"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-22946672"/>
         <title>BBC News - James Buchanan: Worst US president?</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:42</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">James Buchanan: Worst US president?</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Tom
Geoghegan</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News,
Washington</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68397000/jpg/_68397796_buchanan-comp.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="James Buchanan"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">James Buchanan is
often saddled with the title of "the worst US president", blamed
for not averting the Civil War - but efforts are being made to
reassess his legacy. How bad was he really?</p>
            <p>"My dear sir, if you are as happy in entering the White House as
I shall feel on returning to [my home ] Wheatland, you are a happy
man indeed."</p>
            <p>Buchanan made this remark to his successor, Abraham Lincoln in
1861, as he led him to the podium where he would be inaugurated as
US president. Buchanan was leaving Washington with his reputation
in tatters and was looking forward to a peaceful retirement at his
Pennsylvania home. Yet it was anything but.</p>
            <p>Such was the animosity directed towards him in public, he could
no longer drink in his favourite local taverns and spent much of
his post-presidency holed up at home. Outside, the nation tore
itself apart in a bloody conflict that became known as "Buchanan's
War".</p>
            <p>The intervening years have not been any kinder. Buchanan
consistently ranks bottom in lists of "best presidents".</p>
            <p>In January, Nate Silver, the star statistician whose election
predictions have gained mythical status, revealed <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/01/23/contemplating-obamas-place-in-history-statistically/?_r=0"
               title="New York Times">a poll of polls</a> that placed Buchanan
43rd out of 43 presidents.</p>
            <p>For his critics, who say he caused both his country and the
Democratic Party to fall apart, that's where he belongs.</p>
            <p>But a new book, James Buchanan and the
Coming of the Civil War, hopes to reignite the debate.</p>
            <p>It's not an attempt to contradict the standard portrayal of
Buchanan as one of the least effective presidents, says co-author
Michael Birkner. But it does try to get people to argue about him a
bit more, and reassess what he did well and did badly.</p>
            <p>"You have to bear in mind that popular history in the late 19th
and early 20th Century was written by conservative nationalists
like James Ford Rhodes, James Schouler, and Theodore Roosevelt.</p>
            <p>"Buchanan failed as president in their view because he did not
head off secession by taking strong measures against the southern
fire-eaters who backed it."</p>
            <p>The other point of view is that he exercised prudence in not
provoking war, because like Lincoln he understood it would be
easier to rouse the North to fight if the South started it.</p>
            <p>Buchanan was born in Cove Gap, Pennsylvania, in 1791, but aged
18 settled in Lancaster, where the city still takes great pride in
his achievements.</p>
            <p>Some of his possessions, including his presidential desk, were
<a href="http://lancasteronline.com/article/local/858359_James-Buchanan-s-desk-returns-to-Wheatland.html"
               title="Lancaster Online">recently returned to Wheatland</a>, just
outside Lancaster, where Buchanan lived before and after his
single-term presidency.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68379000/jpg/_68379383_wheatland_getty.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Wheatland, Pennsylvania"/>
            </div>
            <p>"It is time to reassess him, absolutely," says Patrick Clarke,
director of Wheatland. "We don't only learn from the victorious and
successful."</p>
            <p>Buchanan made his fair share of mistakes but Congress and the
judiciary did too, says Clarke, who nominates Warren G Harding as
the worst US president, because of the corruption scandals that
plagued his term of office.</p>
            <p>One of the main criticisms of Buchanan concerns his attitude to
slavery. He supported a Supreme Court decision that denied
African-Americans were citizens, and he backed the admittance of
Kansas to the Union with a pro-slavery constitution, to the disgust
of many Democratic colleagues..</p>
            <p>Civil War was inevitable, says Birkner,
professor of history at Gettysburg College. But the blunders of
politicians like Buchanan - and Kansas was his biggest - made it
happen sooner.</p>
            <p>Lincoln, whose election triggered the break-up of the Union,
would not have been elected if Buchanan had not split his own
party, he adds. But Andrew Johnson, who followed Lincoln, was a
worse president than Buchanan, Birkner says, because he squandered
the opportunity to take the country forward after the war.</p>
            <p>The majority view, that Lincoln was the best and Buchanan was
the worst, results from shortcomings in the way US historians rate
presidents, says Ivan Eland, author of Recarving Rushmore.</p>
            <p>Eland thinks presidential ratings are too easily swayed by
charisma, activism and service during a crisis. In his book, he
ranks the White House occupants according to how much they
fulfilled the aims of the Founding Fathers to bring peace,
prosperity and liberty to the country.</p>
            <p>At the top he puts the relatively unknown John Tyler, for ending
the longest Indian war in US history and avoiding one with Britain
over Canada.</p>
            <p>But Woodrow Wilson is at the bottom for taking the US into World
War I, an action that Eland thinks was avoidable.</p>
            <p>"I don't think [Buchanan] was a great president but he's
probably better than people give him credit for. He was trying to
avoid the war and it ended up being a catastrophe," says Eland.</p>
            <p>"Buchanan was right in that he thought it was illegal for the
South to secede but illegal to do anything militarily unless the
South started the fight."</p>
            <div class="data-table-outer">
               <table class="data-table">
                  <colgroup>
                     <col width="1*"/>
                     <col width="33.333%"/>
                     <col width="33.333%"/>
                     <col width="33.333%"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                     <tr class="heading">
                        <th colspan="4" class="left">
                           <h2>Top and bottom presidents</h2>
                        </th>
                     </tr>
                     <tr class="colheading">
                        <th class="left"/>
                        <th class="left">Poll of polls</th>
                        <th class="left">Peace, prosperity, liberty</th>
                        <th class="left">UK academics</th>
                     </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tfoot>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="4" class="left">
                           <p>Sources: Nate Silver (poll of polls), Ivan Eland (peace,
prosperity, liberty), Iwan Morgan (British academics)</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                  </tfoot>
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Best</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left"/>
                        <td class="left"/>
                        <td class="left"/>
                     </tr>
                     <tr class="row2">
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>1</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Abraham Lincoln</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>John Tyler</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Franklin D Roosevelt</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>2</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Franklin D Roosevelt</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Grover Cleveland</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Abraham Lincoln</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr class="row2">
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>3</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>George Washington</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Martin Van Buren</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>George Washington</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>4</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Teddy Roosevelt</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Rutherford B Hayes</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Thomas Jefferson</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr class="row2">
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>5</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Thomas Jefferson</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Chester A Arthur</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Theodore Roosevelt</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Worst</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left"/>
                        <td class="left"/>
                        <td class="left"/>
                     </tr>
                     <tr class="row2">
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>1</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>James Buchanan</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Woodrow Wilson</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>James Buchanan</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>2</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Franklin Pierce</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Harry Truman</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Franklin Pierce</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr class="row2">
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>3</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Warren Harding</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>William McKinley</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Warren Harding</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>4</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>WH Harrison</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>James Polk</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>John Tyler</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr class="row2">
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>5</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Andrew Johnson</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>George W Bush</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Andrew Johnson</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
            </div>
            <p>The perception of what makes a good and bad president can be
very different outside the US.</p>
            <p>In 2011, Franklin D Roosevelt topped the <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-12195111"
               title="BBC website">first ever UK academic poll</a> rating the
performance of US presidents.</p>
            <p>"I think we rated FDR higher because he dealt with issues that
had huge global significance - the Great Depression and World War
II," says Iwan Morgan, professor of US Studies at the University of
London, one of the 47 British contributors to the poll.</p>
            <p>"For Americans, however, he is a more divisive figure as the
architect of big government."</p>
            <p>The British have an excessively high estimate of Obama because
we want him to succeed, says Morgan, while Bush Jr is generally
disliked because of the wars.</p>
            <p>"But we don't appreciate that he deployed presidential influence
very effectively to get his policies enacted.</p>
            <p>"Here's the problem with presidential rating - are you rating
leadership or what they did?"</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine">In today's
Magazine</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373253012577"
                     href="/news/magazine-22971177">Revolution in the royal nursery</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373240476495"
                     href="/news/magazine-23179862">The sad life of a circus lion</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373066350296"
                     href="/news/magazine-23146086">10x10 things about 10 years of the
Magazine</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372980521482"
                     href="/news/magazine-23137492">Will there ever be another massive tank
battle?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Who was James Buchanan?</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Nicknamed "Doughface" for being a Northerner with Southern
sympathies</li>
               <li>The only president from Pennsylvania</li>
               <li>And the only one to be a lifelong bachelor</li>
               <li>Engaged to Anne Coleman in his 20s but she broke it off and
later died</li>
               <li>In retirement, his friend William R King, later vice-president,
lived with him at Wheatland, the two known as "Miss Nancy and Aunt
Fancy"</li>
               <li>Buchanan defended his presidency in his memoir, published in
1866</li>
               <li>Two years later, he died, aged 77</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Was he the first gay president?</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68419000/jpg/_68419505_buch_king_comp.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="110"
                 alt="Buchanan and King"/>
            </div>
            <p>We don't have any convincing evidence that he and William Rufus
King were sexually intimate, says Professor Michael Birkner.</p>
            <p>They were emotionally intimate and lived together for a number
of years, although not consecutively. I would be sceptical that he
had a sexual relationship with anyone, let alone King. I think he
was asexual. He tried to make his early relationship with Anne
Coleman into more than it really was because it gave him the doomed
love story.</p>
            <p>He was undoubtedly our only bachelor president but I'd hold the
argument about our only gay president.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
