<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23126814"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Thousands of elderly people are missing. The last UK census found far fewer people in their 90s than expected, and the same thing happened in the US with people over 100."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T00:39:15"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68493000/jpg/_68493375_dancinghands_afp624.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Where are the missing 90-year-olds?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Magazine"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23126814"/>
         <title>BBC News - Where are the missing 90-year-olds?</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:39</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Where are the missing 90-year-olds?</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Ruth
Alexander</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68489000/jpg/_68489047_dancinghands_afp624.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Elderly people dancing"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Thousands of elderly
people are missing. The last UK census found far fewer people in
their 90s than expected, and the same thing happened in the US with
people over 100. Could this be an early sign that gains in life
expectancy made in recent decades will not be repeated in
future?</p>
            <p>We've seen amazing improvements in life expectancy over the past
few decades.</p>
            <p>Six years have been added to global average life expectancy at
birth, over the past two decades.</p>
            <p>Much of this increase has been down to improvements in child
mortality in low- and middle- income countries.</p>
            <p>But in countries like the UK, post-retirement life expectancy
has also increased rapidly.</p>
            <p>"Life expectancy of a man aged 65 has increased from 14 years in
the early 1980s to 21 years now - so that's a 50% jump in just
three decades," says Richard Willets, director of longevity at
insurance company Partnership.</p>
            <p>Which is why, when the 2011 census was published, he went
straight to the statistics about elderly populations.</p>
            <p>And there the data revealed a
surprise.</p>
            <p>"There were 30,000 fewer people aged in their 90s than
previously believed," he says - 429,000 instead of 457,000.</p>
            <p>"That was about 15% fewer men; 5% fewer females. There were also
fewer centenarians than previously believed - the number of female
centenarians was [out] by about 10%."</p>
            <p>Something similar has happened in the United States.</p>
            <p>A projection made in 2004 suggested that by 2010, there would be
around 114,000 people aged 100 or over, Willets says.</p>
            <p>But, in reality, the 2010 census counted less than half that
number.</p>
            <p>Where have they all gone?</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68479000/jpg/_68479437_oldwoman_think624.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="elderly woman"/>
            </div>
            <p>Sadly, they've already died. They just didn't live as long as
statisticians had predicted.</p>
            <p>Between censuses, annual population estimates are made by taking
the numbers from the last census (which are, in part, estimates),
and applying mortality tables, information from registered deaths
and immigration data.</p>
            <p>None of that information is perfect. So
the further you get from the census year, the fuzzier the numbers
become.</p>
            <p>And because the numbers of people aged 90 and above are so
small, any small estimation errors in how many people have died
result in large discrepancies between the estimated number of
people still alive - and the actual number.</p>
            <p>"When I looked into why this may have happened, it quickly
became apparent that the previous estimates of the number of people
alive at different ages was subject to considerable uncertainty
because of the approach that's taken to produce those estimates,"
says Willets, who has written about his discovery <a href="http://www.theactuary.com/features/2012/11/longevity-and-our-missing-90-year-olds/">
in The Actuary.</a>
            </p>
            <p>In other words, the mortality and life expectancy calculations
actuaries and statisticians rely on have been too optimistic.</p>
            <p>Willets expects to see some revisions made in the light of his
find.</p>
            <p>"I think it's not inconceivable that we move from a situation
where we're adding an extra year of life expectancy in retirement
every three or maybe four years, to one where it takes five, six,
seven, eight years, perhaps, to add that extra year of life
expectancy," he says.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68489000/gif/_68489044_life_expectency_624.gif"
                 width="624"
                 height="391"
                 alt="graphic showing rising life expectancy"/>
            </div>
            <p>This would break an incredible long-running trend for the
world's richest countries.</p>
            <p>"Life expectancy has been increasing in the past in countries
doing well by 2.5 years per decade, three months per year, which is
really quite remarkable - six hours per day," according to
Professor James Vaupel, director of the Max Planck Institute for
Demographic Research in Germany, who's been tracking it.</p>
            <p>This trend has been constant over the past 200 years - but for
changing reasons. First, child and maternal mortality started
improving, then, in the second half of the 20th Century, smoking
rates began to drop.</p>
            <p>"The last couple of years on that graph, there is a possible
slowdown," says Colin Mathers a senior scientist at the World
Health Organization (WHO) says.</p>
            <p>"But it's hard to tell - we need a few more years of data to
see. It's possible that some of the reductions - particularly in
cardiovascular disease associated with reductions in smoking, in
control of blood pressure particularly - have reached a saturation
point.</p>
            <p>"In Australia or California, for example, smoking rates are
quite low - they could go lower, but it might not have much more
impact on death rates. Perhaps control of cholesterol or blood
sugar might kick in and start to further improve life expectancy.
On the other hand, we're seeing increasing levels of obesity and
less exercising at population level."</p>
            <p>But the expert view is that the story of fast-increasing life
expectancy certainly isn't over for the world's low- and middle-
income countries. In fact, it's probably just beginning.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68489000/jpg/_68489041_oldmansmoking624.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Smoking a hookah in Gujarat"/>
            </div>
            <p>Over the past two decades, substantial improvements have been
made to health in Africa, Asia, Latin America and the eastern
Mediterranean region in particular, Mathers says.</p>
            <p>Life expectancy at birth in Asia has increased by about seven
years since 1990. India, China, Indonesia, the Philippines and
Malaysia are all stand-out countries. Average life expectancy at
birth has also increased by seven years in Eastern Mediterranean
countries.</p>
            <p>"In some of the poorest countries we are
seeing reductions in child and maternal death rates and these are
contributing to improvements in life expectancy," Mathers says.</p>
            <p>"In some of the middle income countries, and countries which are
developing very fast like China and some of the South American
countries, we're seeing improvements in living conditions and
medical care which are starting to contribute to very substantial
reductions in adult mortality rates as well."</p>
            <p>Africa is also a success story: life expectancy at birth has
increased by six years from 50 years to 56 years in the short
period, 1990-2011.</p>
            <p>But these averages hide individual tales of tragedy at a country
level: going against this trend, there are a number of African
countries where life expectancy has fallen over the same period,
largely due to HIV/Aids.</p>
            <p>"In South Africa, for example, over the past 20 years, life
expectancy has decreased by five years, almost entirely due to the
HIV epidemic. And in Zimbabwe also, life expectancy has decreased
by six years," Mathers says.</p>
            <p>"In Nigeria on the other hand, life expectancy was much lower in
1990, at 46 years - there were very high levels of child, and
adult, mortality. And that has improved to 53 years. So that's a
seven-year increase for Nigeria, compared to a five-year decrease
for South Africa."</p>
            <p>But Nigerian life expectancy is still five years lower than that
in South Africa, he points out.</p>
            <p>
               <em>You can follow the Magazine on</em>
               <a href="https://twitter.com/BBCNewsMagazine">Twitter</a>
               <em>and on</em>
               <a href="http://www.facebook.com/BBCMagazine">Facebook</a>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine">In today's
Magazine</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373253012577"
                     href="/news/magazine-22971177">Revolution in the royal nursery</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373240476495"
                     href="/news/magazine-23179862">The sad life of a circus lion</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373066350296"
                     href="/news/magazine-23146086">10x10 things about 10 years of the
Magazine</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372980521482"
                     href="/news/magazine-23137492">Will there ever be another massive tank
battle?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">In countries doing well, life expectancy has
been increasing by 2.5 years per decade, three months per year -
six hours per day”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Professor James Vaupel</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Max Planck Institute</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>More or Less: Behind the stats</h2>
            <p>Listen to More or Less on BBC Radio 4 and the World Service, or
download the free podcast</p>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/moreorless">Download the More
or Less podcast</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-17707410"
                  title="BBC News - More or Less">More stories from More or Less</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">In South Africa, for example, over the past
20 years, life expectancy has decreased five years, almost entirely
due to the HIV epidemic”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Colin Mathers</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">WHO</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
