<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-22803975"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Despite decades of decline and mismanagement, there are signs of life in Detroit's private sector companies try to rebuild the city. But is it too late?"/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T01:14:22"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68251000/jpg/_68251606_autoparts624getty.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Glimmers of hope in Detroit"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Magazine"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-22803975"/>
         <title>BBC News - Glimmers of hope in Detroit</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:14</span>
            </span>
            <div class="correspondent-byline">
               <div class="correspondent-byline-inner">
                  <a href="/news/correspondents/jonnydymond">
                     <span class="correspondent-portrait">
                        <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/63719000/jpg/_63719305_dymond_144x104_gray.jpg"
                          alt="Jonny Dymond"
                          width="144"
                          height="104"/>
                     </span>
                     <span class="byline-lead-in">Article written by</span>
                     <span class="name">Jonny
Dymond</span>
                  </a>
                  <span class="bbc-role">Washington
correspondent</span>
                  <ul class="social-links">
                     <li>
                        <a rel="me" href="/news/correspondents/jonnydymond">More from
Jonny</a>
                     </li>
                     <li>Follow <a rel="me" href="http://twitter.com/JonnyDymond">Jonny
on Twitter</a>
                     </li>
                  </ul>
               </div>
            </div>
            <h1 class="story-header">Glimmers of hope in Detroit</h1>
            <div class="has-icon-comment dna-comment-count-simple"> </div>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68187000/jpg/_68187364_autoparts624getty.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="401"
                 alt="Boarded-up auto parts business in Detroit"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Despite decades of decline and
mismanagement, there are signs of life in Detroit as private sector
companies try to rebuild the city. But is it too late?</p>
            <p>Outside the baseball stadium in Detroit the other week a man
sold T-shirts printed with white capital letters on a black
background: Detroit vs Everybody.</p>
            <p>Being a journalist in need of a metaphor, it stuck in my
mind.</p>
            <p>Later, I met with Matt Cullen, the chief executive of Rock
Ventures, which has invested in a number of Detroit-based
businesses.</p>
            <p>He's a native Detroiter who has spent almost three decades
working for General Motors. He's now part of the huge
revitalisation effort that's going on in the city's centre.</p>
            <p>I told him about the T-shirt slogan and I asked, is that part of
the deal, too, the Detroit spirit?</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68226000/jpg/_68226971_challengedetroitindexpic.jpg"
                 alt="Abandoned home in Detroit"/>
               <p class="caption">The BBC's Matt Danzico meets young innovators in
Detroit</p>
            </div>
            <p>He laughed, but also winced, because there are at least two ways
to read the slogan. One is a plucky, never-say-die,
it-will-rise-from-the-ashes kind of attitude. And the other is a
late night, very drunk,
who-wants-a-fight-before-falling-asleep-in-the-gutter kind of
pose.</p>
            <p>The latter is probably not how you want to sell America's most
troubled city.</p>
            <p>There's no escaping the fascination of Detroit. The first time I
went, in early 2011, I was quite literally open-mouthed at the
devastation. Outside the city's abandoned central railway station,
on a bitterly cold winter's day, I gawped at the incomprehensibly
large building.</p>
            <p>The station is part of <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/in-pictures-17095523"
               title="In pictures">Detroit's decaying majesty</a>, what is accurately
and painfully called "ruin porn".</p>
            <p>At one point a limo pulled up and disgorged a couple, he in
tuxedo, she in a wedding gown, who spent 20 minutes or so being
artfully photographed in front of the monument to the fall of a
city. I really thought I'd seen it all.</p>
            <p>But I had not. This last visit I headed out from my downtown
hotel, down the vast, empty Michigan Avenue to get some food.</p>
            <p>In the Corktown neighbourhood there's a funky burger bar, an
artisanal coffee shop, a bustling barbecue joint.</p>
            <p>There are startlingly few black customers - often none at all -
which feels more than a little odd in a city that is overwhelmingly
African-American.</p>
            <p>But it seems churlish to grumble. That there is somewhere nice
to eat and drink and meet a few minutes from the city centre,
somewhere the young professionals who are now electing to live in
the area might want to spend their start-up dollars, is a triumph
in a city short of such things.</p>
            <p>As I left, I looked up, and there looming over me in the warm
night was the huge, beautiful, abandoned central railway
station.</p>
            <p>I had a wildly over-romantic surge of hope for the city that so
much of the US so enjoys giving a good kicking.</p>
            <p>There are unmistakeable signs of revival in the private sector,
just as the city faces the final showdown with the creditors to
whom it owes $15bn (Ã‚Â£10bn).</p>
            <p>A good deal of this is due to one man, Dan Gilbert, the founder
of the Quicken Loans mortgage empire. He has gone against the trend
of half a century by moving his white-collar staff into the
city.</p>
            <p>He and his colleagues have set up venture capital companies and
tech start-up incubators.</p>
            <p>He and his staff - their eyes ablaze with Motor-City-evangelism
- organise design competitions for vacant lots, and spread the word
far and wide that, in the immortal lyric of rock musician Ted
Nugent, "Detroit City, she's the place to be".</p>
            <p>The city centre is buzzing - there is a sense of purpose in the
air, of momentum, of money, of enterprise.</p>
            <p>Ross Sanders runs Bizdom, a tech start-up incubator that has
recently outgrown the building that housed it and has had to move
to another office.</p>
            <p>At Bizdom I chatted to a couple of start-up 20-somethings, Erik
Torenberg of Rapt.fm, and Michael Sharber of Greenlancer.</p>
            <p>Mr Torenberg, a skinny rap enthusiast from New Jersey, said that
the first thing his relatives asked when he told them that he was
moving to Detroit was: "Is it safe?"</p>
            <p>He bursts with enthusiasm for the city.</p>
            <p>Mr Torenberg studied at the nearby University of Michigan, but
not once ventured into Detroit. Now he can't get enough of the
place. And Mr Sharber, who grew up in Detroit, invites me to watch
his volleyball game, played in the shadow of a vast abandoned
factory.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68188000/jpg/_68188937_83780432.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="331"
                 alt="Aerial view of derelict factory in Detroit"/>
            </div>
            <p>But if Detroit is to rise again it will need more than the
enthusiasm of the private sector. It will need a properly
functioning public sector.</p>
            <p>There is no sign of that coming along anytime soon.</p>
            <p>"We go into buildings," the fire chief told me, "and grapple
with the devil."</p>
            <p>He was standing outside his station on a warm summer's evening
as a smell of herbs wafted out from the kitchen. Dinner time was
coming for his 12-man company.</p>
            <div class="data-table-outer">
               <table class="data-table">
                  <colgroup>
                     <col width="1*"/>
                     <col width="1*"/>
                     <col width="1*"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                     <tr class="heading">
                        <th colspan="3" class="left">
                           <h2>Detroit's declining fortunes</h2>
                        </th>
                     </tr>
                     <tr class="colheading">
                        <th class="left">In numbers</th>
                        <th class="left">2008</th>
                        <th class="left">2012</th>
                     </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tfoot>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="3" class="left">
                           <p>Source: <a href="http://www.detroitmi.gov/Portals/0/docs/EM/Reports/City%20of%20Detroit%20Proposal%20for%20Creditors1.pdf"
                              title="Local government">City of Detroit Proposal for Creditors
2013</a>
                           </p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                  </tfoot>
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Population</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>912,062</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>684,799</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr class="row2">
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Unemployment</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>15%</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>18%</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Property tax collection rate</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>76%</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>68.3%</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr class="row2">
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>Budget deficits</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>$217m</p>
                        </td>
                        <td class="left">
                           <p>$652m</p>
                        </td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
            </div>
            <p>The station was in better nick than the immediate neighbourhood.
Across the way, waist-high grass grew untended. A long-closed
supermarket was covered with graffiti, its green awning torn and
hanging at a crazy angle.</p>
            <p>Upstairs, huge noisy fans battled with the summer heat in the
company's dormitories. The fire chief had an office out of the
1970s - clipboards and to-do lists covering one wall, a beaten-up
desk, an old TV opposite with a washed-out screen.</p>
            <p>I thought of the shiny new offices of downtown, all glass and
steel, climate controlled with flat-screen TVs and famous-name
coffee machines.</p>
            <p>Apart from the odd computer, nothing in the station that had
been purchased in the last 20 or so years. And, with all due
respect to the company, there was no-one new in it either. Apart
from one recent transfer all the men were middle-aged or more.</p>
            <p>How long can it go on like this?</p>
            <p>In his first report a few weeks ago, the city's new emergency
manager wrote of <a href="http://www.freep.com/assets/freep/pdf/C4206913614.PDF">Detroit's
public sector being</a> "dysfunctional and wasteful after years of
budgetary restriction, mismanagement, crippling operational
practices and, in some cases, indifference or corruption".</p>
            <p>For 50 years Detroit meant mass assembly, it meant the
automobile, opportunity for an uneducated - often black -
workforce.</p>
            <p>Then it came to represent the decline of the Great City, the
collapse of urban government, even the end of the American
dream.</p>
            <p>There is huge energy in the city. But saving Detroit is not a
done deal.</p>
            <p>"We hope for better things; it shall rise from the ashes," goes
the city motto.</p>
            <p>Or, more pithily, Detroit v Everybody.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1330012772570"
                  href="/news/in-pictures-17095523">In pictures: The ruins of
Detroit</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1305291528173"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-13384255">In pictures: Detroit's abandoned
buildings</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1324681708632"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-16323753">Detroit 'savaged' by economic
problems <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>'It's like the Wild West'</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68248000/jpg/_68248413_msharber.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Michael Sharber"/>
            </div>
            <p>"I was born in Detroit and I moved away to pursue work
opportunities, but I came back by chance and was blown away by what
I saw. In places like New York or California, I'm just one of
millions of other faces trying to make it.</p>
            <p>"It's a lot easier to get recognised here. There are business
leaders who are willing to share advice, people who want to invest
in your ideas.</p>
            <p>"Detroit was built on innovation and creativity, from Thomas
Edison to the auto industry and you now see all these new college
graduates moving here looking to turn their ideas into reality -
this city is full of opportunity. People are looking at Detroit as
the new frontier. It's like the Wild West and it's being
rebuilt."</p>
            <p>
               <em>Michael Sharber is co-founder of</em>
               <a href="http://www.greenlancer.com/home">Greenlancer</a>
               <em>,</em>
               <em>which</em>
               <em>pairs</em>
               <em>engineers with solar energy
companies - part of</em>
               <a href="http://www.bizdom.com">Bizdom's</a>
               <em>start-up accelerator
programme</em>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>AUDIO: Soup and sympathy</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68249000/png/_68249952_detroitsoup.jpg.png"
                 width="304"
                 height="250"
                 alt="Composite of images from Detroit Soup"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>The BBC's Jonny Dymond attends a Detroit Soup event, where
soup, salad and community are the ingredients one group hopes can
help fix the city</li>
               <li>The community events help raise money to support worthy
projects in Detroit</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-us-canada-22900004" class="listen">How
soup and salad can save Detroit</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Start-ups and serious money</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68249000/jpg/_68249950_img_1106copy.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Erik Torenberg"/>
            </div>
            <p>"I came to Detroit for three months, with the idea of seeing how
it went - that was 15 months ago and I am now here indefinitely,
because we see ourselves as part of this city's revival.</p>
            <p>"We've got a lot of love from people here and Detroit already
has such a great hip-hop history, from Eminem to J Dilla. When you
combine that with the burgeoning tech scene here, it's the perfect
place for our company.</p>
            <p>"The main thing Detroit needs right now is some success stories
- it needs one or two start-ups to blow up and make some serious
money to get people talking about the city."</p>
            <p>
               <em>Erik Torenberg is co-founder of</em>
               <a href="http://rapt.fm/">rapt.fm</a>
               <em>, which enables rappers across the
world to battle each other online - he is sponsored by</em>
               <a href="http://bizdom.com/">Bizdom</a>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
