<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23108807"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Talk of immigration reform in the US often focuses on Hispanic immigrants, but a small group of Irish activists may have a louder voice in some important circles."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T00:48:26"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68493000/jpg/_68493284_166236946(1).jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Can the Irish help reform US immigration?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Magazine"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23108807"/>
         <title>BBC News - Can the Irish help reform US immigration?</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:48</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Can the Irish help reform US
immigration?</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Kate
Dailey</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News
Magazine</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68493000/jpg/_68493274_166236946(1).jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Tens of thousands of immigration reform supporters march in the 'Rally for Citizenship' on the West Lawn of the US Capitol in Washington, DC"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Talk of immigration
reform in the US often focuses on Hispanic immigrants, but a small
group of Irish activists may have a louder voice in some important
circles.</p>
            <p>Advocates for US immigration had cause for celebration last week
when the Senate passed a pro-immigration bill by a vote of 68 to
32.</p>
            <p>The legislation heads next to the House of Representatives.</p>
            <p>"The House is controlled by the Republicans, and we have to
convince Republicans that this is a good idea," says Ciaran
Staunton, who has been lobbying for reform.</p>
            <p>He says it in such a matter-of-fact way that it sounds easy -
never mind that Republican Senator Rand Paul, who voted against the
bill, promised it would be "dead on arrival" once it reached the
House.</p>
            <p>Never mind that Tennessee Representative Scott DesJarlais says
he'll "fight to make sure this bill never reaches the floor".</p>
            <p>Never mind that relations between the House and the Senate, and
Democrats and Republicans are so fractured it's difficult to get
anything done on any topic.</p>
            <p>Staunton, president of the Irish Lobby
for Immigration Reform, thinks he has a good shot of drumming up
support. Other activists think so too, thanks in large part to
Staunton's thick brogue and Irish background.</p>
            <p>"Ciaran and his merry band of warriors do what others can't,"
says Frank Sharry, executive director of America's Voice, an
immigration reform advocacy group.</p>
            <p>"They can be fearless, and go where other activists might have
trouble connecting, and they punch above their weight."</p>
            <p>Staunton, who has worked closely with New York Democratic
Senator Charles Schumer during the development of the immigration
bill, has also had productive meetings with conservative
politicians such as Senator Lindsey Graham, and Representatives
Peter King and Paul Ryan - all of whom have Irish roots.</p>
            <p>Many conservatives, citing the rapid growth of Hispanic voters
in the US, say the bill is necessary to keep the Republican Party
relevant. But the Irish connection can add an additional level of
persuasion.</p>
            <p>"We're meeting with people whose grandparents were immigrants,
and I tell them that under the regulations today, their
grandparents wouldn't get in," says Staunton, an Irish immigrant
who has been in the US for 31 years.</p>
            <p>"We were fit to get a message out there, that this isn't just a
Hispanic issue."</p>
            <p>Though Ireland and America have a long
immigration history, legal avenues for Irish immigrants vastly
diminished after a 1965 bill was passed.</p>
            <p>The legislation eliminated country-based immigration quotas that
benefited Europeans, and focused instead on offering entry to those
with family connections and employment offers.</p>
            <p>"The unintended effect of it was that it virtually eliminated
immigration from Ireland," says Sharry. "After the 1965 criteria,
most immigration came from Latin America and Asia."</p>
            <p>Given the "historic closeness" of the US and Ireland, says
Sharry, lawmakers and activists have tried to increase the
opportunity for Irish to emigrate to the US, including adding
10,000 visas for Irish citizens in the 1990s - language that is
also included in the current bill.</p>
            <p>Only Ireland and parts of the African diaspora have such visas
set aside in the bill.</p>
            <p>But Siobhan Lyon, executive director of the Irish Immigration
Center of Philadelphia, says it's important that the Irish support
the bill to help all immigrants.</p>
            <p>"I've heard people say terrible things about immigrants, and I
call them out and say, 'I'm an immigrant.' They say, 'Oh, we
weren't talking about you Siobhan!' But yet they are," she
says.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68493000/jpg/_68493291_ciaranryan.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Mark Daly, Paul Ryan and Ciaran Staunton"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Ciaran Staunton, right, met with US Congressman Paul
Ryan, centre, and Republic of Ireland Senator Mark Daly to discuss
immigration reform</span>
            </div>
            <p>"It's important that the Irish stand firm alongside our Hispanic
brethren. Sometimes we do have access to people and we do have the
ability to change some people's mind," she says.</p>
            <p>For instance, she often talks to Irish Americans about how
immigration reform is needed so that an Irish worker living here on
an expired visa can go back to Ireland to attend his mother's
funeral - an issue that resonates with the Irish-American
community, but is also applicable to immigrants from all
countries.</p>
            <p>At the same time, she'll discuss how the
current anti-immigration atmosphere in the US has slowed Irish
arrivals to the country.</p>
            <p>"This is a big problem for the Irish community - for first time
in the history of our two countries we don't have a flow of Irish
coming to the US," she says.</p>
            <p>Opponents of the bill say all immigrants - Irish or otherwise -
have to wait their turn.</p>
            <p>"The US has the most liberal immigration policy in the world,"
says Jack Martin, a spokesperson for the Federation for American
Immigration Reform.</p>
            <p>"We are admitting at the present time under the current law more
than a million people a year for legal, permanent residence.</p>
            <p>"In addition to which we are allowing close to a million people
a year coming into the country as temporary workers.</p>
            <p>"We think that it is a mistake to offer legalisation or amnesty
to people from any country or ethnicity, religion for whatever
reason. It weakens respect for the law and encourages future law
breakers."</p>
            <p>Despite the outspoken opposition by many in the House, Staunton
and his colleagues feel optimistic about the bill's future.</p>
            <p>And when the House returns to session next week, he and his team
will be there, making the case for immigration reform.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine">In today's
Magazine</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373253012577"
                     href="/news/magazine-22971177">Revolution in the royal nursery</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373240476495"
                     href="/news/magazine-23179862">The sad life of a circus lion</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373066350296"
                     href="/news/magazine-23146086">10x10 things about 10 years of the
Magazine</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372980521482"
                     href="/news/magazine-23137492">Will there ever be another massive tank
battle?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">For first time in the history of our two
countries, we don't have a flow of Irish coming to the
US”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Siobhan Lyons</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Immigration activist</span>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-us-canada-23091302" class="quote-link">US
Senate passes immigration reform</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>What's in Senate immigration bill?</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Path to citizenship for immigrants who arrived illegally before
31 December 2011</li>
               <li>Billions in funding for border security, including 20,000 new
Border Patrol agents, 700 miles of fencing, unmanned drones and
electronic surveillance. Border security goals must be met before
undocumented immigrants can become permanent residents</li>
               <li>A start-up visa for foreign entrepreneurs; new visa programmes
for low-skilled workers and the agricultural sector</li>
               <li>All employers must use E-Verify, a programme to verify
electronically each employee's legal status within four years</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/z?c113:S.744:">Full text of
the bill</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Irish undocumented</h2>
            <p>According to Ciaran Staunton, there are about 50,000
undocumented Irish immigrants living in the US.</p>
            <p>That's just a small fraction of the estimated 11m immigrants
living in the US without permission.</p>
            <p>But Staunton says it doesn't matter to him if it's "50 or 50,000
Irish".</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
