<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23184816"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="For six years in the last 1950s and early 60s, the British military conducted nuclear tests from Christmas Island. Fifty years on, what signs are left of its dramatic history?"/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-07T23:56:20"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68578000/jpg/_68578877_kiribati_reuters.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Christmas Island's nuclear legacy"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Magazine"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23184816"/>
         <title>BBC News - Christmas Island: In search of Britain's nuclear
legacy</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">8 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:56</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Christmas Island: In search of Britain's
nuclear legacy</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By John
Pickford</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News,
Kiritimati</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68578000/jpg/_68578166_christmasisland_bbc.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="400"
                 alt="Chrismas Island"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">In 1957, the British military began
conducting nuclear tests in the Pacific Ocean and based themselves
on Christmas Island. The tests ended six years later and parts of
the island were sealed off for decades. What signs are left of its
dramatic history?</p>
            <p>Main Camp: The name is all that is left of the British military
headquarters of 50 years ago. Christmas Island's only hotel, the
Captain Cook, stands there now.</p>
            <p>The searing east wind blows and the ocean
swell booms ceaselessly on the reef, like a distant train in a
tunnel. There is a ruined church of coral rock close by. An
inscription, etched in cement, invites Church Notices. Who pinned
up the last one and what did it say?</p>
            <p>Christmas Island has gone through a lot of change. It is now
part of the Oceanic state of Kiribati (pronounced Kiribas) with a
capital in distant Tarawa, a day's flight away via Fiji. And it has
a new name, Kiritimati.</p>
            <p>The people of Kiribati, formerly the Gilbert Islands, have
difficulty pronouncing the letter S. So Christmas becomes Kritmat,
and then Kiritimati - a new name is born.</p>
            <p>Most significant is the increase in the human population, now
approaching 10,000. There are more vehicles today than there were
people in 1958.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68571000/jpg/_68571835_church_christmasisland_bbc.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="400"
                 alt="Ruined church on Christmas Island"/>
            </div>
            <p>Concerns have been raised about the island's carrying capacity
due to its unreliable water supply, but the Kiribati government has
continued to encourage resettlement from overcrowded Tarawa. Some
fear this poses a 21st Century threat to Christmas Island's
environment.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68571000/jpg/_68571830_christmasisland_ap.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="405"
                 alt="Christmas Island tests 1962"/>
            </div>
            <p>There are new schools, a bank and even a small hospital. I spoke
to a tired looking doctor, the island's obstetrician. How many
babies in a week? "Oh not many, about 10," she says. That is 500 in
a year.</p>
            <p>But for others connected with this island, time has stood still.
Trevor Butler, now 75, went out aged 20 as a sapper with the Royal
Engineers.</p>
            <p>After his return he developed a cataract in his right eye and
for much of his life he has been trying, and failing, to get
compensation from the Ministry of Defence for what he alleges was
harmful exposure to radiation during his military service. He is a
vigorous, determined man and still fascinated by the island. Before
my departure he asked me if I would see if there was anything left
of the structures he had helped build during his time there.</p>
            <p>A few weeks later I am on Kiritimati in a lorry heading south.
To my left is the deep blue of the ocean and to my right mile after
mile of salt-bush scrub, a rich green after recent rain. The road
is remarkably good, considering it is 50 years old. Then I remember
Trevor telling me they added cement to the tarmacadam to help it
set.</p>
            <p>I am with William from the Wildlife Department and we are
driving to the remote south-east tip of the island, once ominously
called the Forward Zone. It was high in the atmosphere over this
area or just offshore that the bombs were detonated, and for
decades it was sealed off.</p>
            <p>William traps feral cats out here because they are a threat to
the sea bird colonies and he says he has seen something I might
find interesting.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68578000/jpg/_68578868_birds.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Thousands of tern teeming over the island"/>
            </div>
            <p>We have driven fast for two hours - this is the biggest coral
atoll on earth - but now slow to a walking pace.</p>
            <p>It is the birds. Sooty terns. Tens of thousands of them, in the
air and on the ground. A glorious, teeming, deafening cacophony.
Did they really explode an atom bomb over this? Well they did, and
there must have been a moment after the flash when there was
silence.</p>
            <p>William stops the lorry and we begin walking into the scrub. It
is taller than we are so it is like entering a maze.</p>
            <p>What we are looking for has something to do with the giant
tethers that were constructed for a couple of the atom bombs which
were suspended from balloons and detonated, rather than dropped as
air bursts from planes.</p>
            <p>The sun is setting and I am beginning to get worried we are
lost, when William calls out: "Here!"</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68578000/jpg/_68578426_concrete_christmasisland.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Rusted steel rings in concrete"/>
            </div>
            <p>It is a massive slab of concrete about 50 metres square with
huge rusted steel rings set into it. In the middle there are six
bigger rings close together.</p>
            <p>I suddenly think of Trevor with his shovel, stripped to the
waist in his army shorts like in the photos he showed me.</p>
            <p>There was a major clean-up of remaining military debris in 2006
but this looks unmoveable. The thing is so extraordinary and in
some respects so bizarre in that wild, bleak place that you cannot
help but be impressed.</p>
            <p>You wonder what a visitor from space might make of it or an
archaeologist in 500 years with no knowledge of our civilisation.
You would have to explain so much: that there was something called
a Cold War going on and a once great imperial power was struggling
to keep up.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>How to listen to</strong>
               <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/default.stm">
From Our Own Correspondent</a>
               <strong>: BBC Radio 4:</strong>
Saturdays at 11:30 and some Thursdays at 11:00. You can also
<a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qjlq">listen
online</a> or <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/fooc">download the
podcast</a>.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>BBC World Service:</strong> Short editions Monday-Friday
- see the World Service <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldserviceradio/programmes/schedules">programme
schedule</a>.</p>
            <p>
               <em>You can follow the Magazine on</em>
               <a href="https://twitter.com/BBCNewsMagazine">Twitter</a>
               <em>and on</em>
               <a href="http://www.facebook.com/BBCMagazine"
               title="Facebook - BBC Magazine">Facebook</a>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>From Our Own Correspondent</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68571000/jpg/_68571833_churchnotices_bbc.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Stone sign: Church notices"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>Insight and analysis from BBC correspondents, journalists and
writers from around the world</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li>Broadcast on Radio 4 and BBC World Service</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qjlq">Listen to
the programme</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/fooc">Download
the programme</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine/">More from
Magazine</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
