<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23064490"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Emma Jane Kirby reports from Torre del Mar in Spain where many under-25s are emigrating because they see little prospect of work at home."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-30T23:49:34"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68430000/jpg/_68430328_spain_thinkstock.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Why has Spain fallen out of love with Europe?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Magazine"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23064490"/>
         <title>BBC News - Why has Spain fallen out of love with the
European Union?</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:49</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Why has Spain fallen out of love with the
European Union?</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Emma Jane
Kirby</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68412000/jpg/_68412020_149865260getty.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Spanish beach"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Since 2007, Spanish
approval of the EU has almost halved. On an Andalusian beach, one
hard-pressed couple explain why their attitudes have shifted so
dramatically.</p>
            <p>It is already 30C (86F) on the beach at Torre del Mar and Maria
Dolores and her husband Jose are getting a little crabby with each
other as they un-stack the plastic sun loungers from the shed.</p>
            <p>Jose stumbles backwards into the dog's water bowl and
curses.</p>
            <p>He is tired and hot and he does not want to be Jose The Sun Bed
Man today - he prefers being Jose The Civil Servant in the coolness
of an air-conditioned office - but since his hours and wages were
slashed two years ago, he needs this sideline to make ends
meet.</p>
            <p>"Why can't they cut jobs at the top rather than the bottom?" he
mutters as he unchains the loungers.</p>
            <p>"It's always cuts, cuts, cuts. I know we have a big debt in
Spain but the pressure we're under to pay it back so quickly is
crippling us."</p>
            <p>Maria Dolores takes money from a tanned,
bikini-clad tourist and speaks loudly and slowly to her, pointing
to the sun and making signs to show the woman that it is very, very
hot today and she must not get burnt.</p>
            <p>"She is a nice lady, that one," she tells me. "Even if she is
German. Not like that Merkel woman."</p>
            <p>Jose snorts. He is not a fan of the German Chancellor either, he
says - and nor is he a fan of that European Union she runs.</p>
            <p>Torre del Mar, like the rest of Andalusia, has greatly benefited
from Spain's entry into the EU in the mid-1980s.</p>
            <p>The long, paved promenade with its palm trees, cycle lanes and
beach bars was paid for largely through EU grants - EU money is
behind countless schools, roads and restoration projects in the
region.</p>
            <p>As Spain emerged, under-developed and economically weak, from
the isolation of the Franco dictatorship, the EU was seen as its
benevolent benefactor.</p>
            <p>Now, six years into an economic crisis which has left 27% of the
population unemployed, it is viewed as the belligerent bully which
is forcing Spain to its knees with austerity measures.</p>
            <p>Since 2007, Spanish approval of the EU has almost halved.</p>
            <p>Just down the coast in a nearby park, a group of elderly men
play petanca, a form of boules, in the shade.</p>
            <p>The heavy silver balls flash sparks of
sunlight as they roll towards the dusty jack and smack against each
other with a satisfying thock.</p>
            <p>A rumble of irritation goes round the group as the big, wheezing
Antonio wins again, spitting on his handkerchief and wiping his
flushed face.</p>
            <p>"Oh, give someone else a bit of the glory," chides Miguel, a
white-haired and sprightly man of 70.</p>
            <p>These men remember what it was like to live under Franco - and
subsequently the boom times that followed, as the Spanish economy,
fuelled by EU structural funds and a decade-long property bonanza,
went from strength to strength.</p>
            <p>"In those days, everything seemed possible," says Miguel sadly,
"but now where has the all that money gone? The problem is the EU
is no longer a collective, it's just different rules for each and
every country."</p>
            <p>Antonio smacks the silver balls against each other in
irritation. "We are in crisis," he snaps.</p>
            <p>"We need help but all Chancellor Merkel does is tell our Prime
Minister to cut our deficit and our pensions." He lifts his arm and
prepares to throw.</p>
            <p>"Give me half a chance," he mutters, and I would cut the damn
lot of those EU politicians - we did not elect them."</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68433000/jpg/_68433230_147356125getty.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Chancellor Angela Merkel and Greek President Karolos Papoulias"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">European leaders meeting in Brussels
have agreed to spend over Ã‚Â£7bn on job
creation</span>
            </div>
            <p>The heat has intensified as I leave the park and seems to have
taken the locals by surprise.</p>
            <p>Many bear angry red stripes of sunburn down their legs and backs
and everyone looks sticky and a little fractious.</p>
            <p>Back on the beach, Maria Dolores is cutting a piece of ham to
offer to the couple of scraggy dogs, which are skulking under the
picnic table.</p>
            <p>One of them, smelling the meat, jumps up quickly, sending a
gritty cloud of grey sand onto Jose's feet. He curses irritably and
Maria tuts at him reproachfully.</p>
            <p>"They are our children's dogs," she explains. "Both our boys
have gone to England to find jobs - they are working there as
waiters now.</p>
            <p>"When I speak to my sons on the phone I can hear they're
homesick but of course they can't come back here because there's
nothing for them in Spain."</p>
            <p>She pats the dog's head and says quietly: "This is all I've got
left of my family."</p>
            <p class="transmission-info">
               <strong>How to listen to</strong>
               <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/default.stm">
From Our Own Correspondent</a>
               <strong>:</strong>
            </p>
            <p>
               <strong>BBC Radio 4:</strong> Saturdays at 11:30 and some
Thursdays at 11:00</p>
            <p>
               <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qjlq">Listen
online</a> or <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/fooc">download the
podcast</a>.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>BBC World Service:</strong> Short editions Monday-Friday
- see World Service <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldserviceradio/programmes/schedules">programme
schedule</a>.</p>
            <p>
               <em>You can follow the Magazine on</em>
               <a href="https://twitter.com/BBCNewsMagazine">Twitter</a>
               <em>and on</em>
               <a href="http://www.facebook.com/BBCMagazine"
               title="Facebook - BBC Magazine">Facebook</a>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine">In today's
Magazine</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373253012577"
                     href="/news/magazine-22971177">Revolution in the royal nursery</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373240476495"
                     href="/news/magazine-23179862">The sad life of a circus lion</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373066350296"
                     href="/news/magazine-23146086">10x10 things about 10 years of the
Magazine</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372980521482"
                     href="/news/magazine-23137492">Will there ever be another massive tank
battle?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>From Our Own Correspondent</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68432000/jpg/_68432567_162493229.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Spanish beach"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>Insight and analysis from BBC correspondents, journalists and
writers from around the world</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li>Broadcast on Radio 4 and BBC World Service</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qjlq">Listen to
the programme</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/fooc">Download
the programme</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">The problem is the EU is no longer a
collective, it's just different rules for every country”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
