<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23179862"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="More used to seeing animals on the plains of Africa when working with wildlife TV crews, Natasha Breed is shocked to see the state of one of her beloved lions at a circus in France."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-07T23:41:16"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68603000/jpg/_68603095_lion_think624.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="The sad life of a circus lion"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Magazine"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23179862"/>
         <title>BBC News - The sad life of a circus lion</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">8 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:41</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">The sad life of a circus lion</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Natasha
Breed</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Normandy,
France</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68579000/jpg/_68579191_cagelion_highres_breed.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="464"
                 alt="Lion in a cage outside the circus"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The circus continues
to roll into various towns in Britain at this time of year, but
increasingly it does so without the lions and tigers which were
once synonymous with it. In some parts of Europe however, the days
of performing animals are not over.</p>
            <p>At the southern tip of Normandy lies the Parc Naturel du Perche.
A picturesque patchwork of French countryside, seamed by winding
streams and ramblers' footpaths, quilted with extensive forests and
dotted with farms and orchards. Known for its tall Norman barns,
local cider, and the sturdy Percheron draft horses used to pull
heavy loads, it is a bucolic setting very different from the
savannahs of Kenya that I am used to.</p>
            <p>Yet here I am, in the middle of the Perche, and less than ten
metres away is an adult lion. He's about four years old, with a
thick blonde mane and a nose that is still a youthful pale pink.
And he is lying like a sphinx, with his head up, looking at me.</p>
            <p>How many times have I seen a lion lie like this before, in the
shade of a tree gazing out lazily over the plains? Or, waiting
expectantly as a lioness approaches to rub faces with him, in that
wonderful tactile way lions greet each other? Or, closing his eyes
in paternal indulgence, while his small cubs clamber over his
hindquarters and pounce on the tassel of his tail, as his upper lip
twitches into a gentle sneer?</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68579000/jpg/_68579064_lionafrica_breed.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="232"
                 alt="A lion in the wild in Africa"/>
            </div>
            <p>I have spent years working with wildlife film crews following
lions in Africa, and I have learned to read the big cats' moods in
their eyes. Meeting the gaze of a lion, I have experienced that
stomach-lurching intuition that tells me if I make one wrong move I
am toast.</p>
            <p>The pupils dilate, and the gaze becomes
100% focused - and suddenly I have felt what it might be like to be
a wildebeest coming face to face with his nemesis.</p>
            <p>But this lion's eyes barely flicker as I approach him. There is
no gleam of interest, no unwavering intent, no spark of fun.
Usually, for any cat, a moving target is always going to be fun to
chase - whether it ends in a meal or not.</p>
            <p>He is not even wary of me, as any self-respecting lion in Africa
has learned to be, when a human approaches on foot. This animal is
weary, dispirited, and - something I have never seen before - he is
bored.</p>
            <p>I had been driving to the local market town when I noticed the
circus. Across a busy road, a McDonalds, a car wash and a DIY
centre face a sprawling disused supermarket allotment. But today, a
huge candy-striped Big Top, and a semi-circle of trailers are
ranged around the car park of the abandoned store.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68579000/jpg/_68579183_lioncircus_breed_light.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="300"
                 alt="Circus entrance"/>
            </div>
            <p>Some of the trailers have barred sides and I glimpse the
familiar form of a lion standing in one of the cages. Then I notice
the roadside posters - on street lamps, bus shelters and
litterbins.</p>
            <p>Beneath the headline "Visit the Zoo", white tigers and lions
leap through rings of fire, or pose majestically for their
portraits. I read that the circus will be in town for five days. I
park, cross the road and approach the circus.</p>
            <p>A man is uncoupling a trailer from a
truck and I ask if I can walk around. Squinting at me through a
curl of blue smoke from the cigarette clamped between his lips, he
nods.</p>
            <p>Four shaggy Bactrian camels stand in a roped-off area of tarmac.
No grass, no trees. Just white lines where shoppers once parked and
a single lamppost casting a narrow shadow - below which, pitiably,
the camels have congregated.</p>
            <p>Beyond is another trailer with more lions and tigers in it -
yes, there are white ones there. The two-by-12-metre carriage,
partitioned into stalls, holds at least six big cats. Some sleep,
others sit or stand up, staring out at passing traffic and
pedestrians, with dull eyes.</p>
            <p>The UK government recently announced that a ban prohibiting the
use of wild animals in circuses in Britain would come into effect
in 2015.</p>
            <p>How many big cats, elephants and other animals watch the world
through the bars of cages, without ever having known the infinity
of wilderness? Knowing, instead, the blurred scenery of tarred
roads, as they travel in gaudy procession from town to town.</p>
            <p>The frightening, flickering flames of fire as they leap, night
after night, through burning rings, or dance or perform headstands,
to the crack of whips and the clamour of applause.</p>
            <p>The tedium of their dreadful prisons. And the hopeless monotony
of interminable exile.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>How to listen to</strong>
               <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/default.stm">
From Our Own Correspondent</a>
               <strong>:</strong>
            </p>
            <p>
               <strong>BBC Radio 4:</strong> Saturdays at 11:30 and some
Thursdays at 11:00</p>
            <p>
               <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qjlq">Listen
online</a> or <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/fooc">download the
podcast</a>.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>BBC World Service:</strong> Short editions Monday-Friday
- see World Service <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldserviceradio/programmes/schedules">programme
schedule</a>.</p>
            <p>
               <em>You can follow the Magazine on</em>
               <a href="https://twitter.com/BBCNewsMagazine">Twitter</a>
               <em>and on</em>
               <a href="http://www.facebook.com/BBCMagazine"
               title="Facebook - BBC Magazine">Facebook</a>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine">In today's
Magazine</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373253012577"
                     href="/news/magazine-22971177">Revolution in the royal nursery</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373066350296"
                     href="/news/magazine-23146086">10x10 things about 10 years of the
Magazine</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372980521482"
                     href="/news/magazine-23137492">Will there ever be another massive tank
battle?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372948988913"
                     href="/news/blogs-magazine-monitor-23182920">Paper Monitor: Patching up
a prince</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>About the author</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68602000/jpg/_68602159_natashabreed.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Natasha Breed"/>
            </div>
            <p>Natasha Breed has worked as field assistant in Africa to
wildlife crews from the BBC Natural History Unit for 20 years</p>
            <p>She is the author of From Ox Cart to Email, the story of the
Lewa Wildlife Conservancy in Kenya</p>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-1909657">Why do
lions roar?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/nature/life/Lion#p00fpt2z">Watch
female lions protect their young</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>From Our Own Correspondent</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68542000/jpg/_68542503_lion3.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Lion"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>Insight and analysis from BBC correspondents, journalists and
writers from around the world</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li>Broadcast on Radio 4 and BBC World Service</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qjlq">Listen to
the programme</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/podcasts/series/fooc">Download
the programme</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
