<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23037957"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Malcolm Gladwell on the little-known defence analyst who might have changed the course of the Vietnam War - if only people had listened to him."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-08T23:58:05"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68617000/jpg/_68617430_68613829.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Could one man have shortened the Vietnam War?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Magazine"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23037957"/>
         <title>BBC News - Viewpoint: Could one man have shortened the
Vietnam War?</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">9 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:58</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Viewpoint: Could one man have shortened
the Vietnam War?</h1>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68613000/jpg/_68613427_vietnam_ap.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="401"
                 alt="US soldier guards Route 7 as Vietnamese women and school children return home "/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Konrad Kellen was an
unknown defence analyst who might have changed the course of the
Vietnam War if only people had listened to him, argues Malcolm
Gladwell.</p>
            <p>Listening well is a gift. The ability to hear what someone says
and not filter it through your own biases is an instinctive ability
similar to having a photographic memory.</p>
            <p>And I think we have a great deal of trouble with people who have
this gift. There is something about all of us that likes the fact
that what we hear is filtered through someone's biases.</p>
            <p>There are many examples of this phenomenon, but I want to focus
on the story of Konrad Kellen, a truly great listener.</p>
            <p>During the Vietnam War, he heard something that should have
changed the course of history. Only it didn't. And today no-one
really knows who Kellen was - which is a shame because his statue
should be in the middle of the Vietnam Memorial in Washington
DC.</p>
            <p>Kellen was born in 1913. His full name
was Katzenellenbogen - one of the great Jewish families of Europe.
They lived in splendour near Berlin's Tiergarten. His father was a
prominent industrialist and his stepmother was painted by Renoir, a
family friend.</p>
            <p>Kellen was tall, handsome and charismatic. He loved Ferraris. He
could quote long sections of Thucydides from memory. One of his
cousins was the great economist Albert O Hirshman. Another was
Albert Einstein.</p>
            <p>He lived one of those extraordinary 20th Century lives. When he
was quite young, he left Berlin and moved to Paris where he became
friends with Jean Cocteau. On a ship, the America, he was offered a
job by the gangster Dutch Schultz. And when he got to the US, he
met the author Thomas Mann and became his private secretary. Then
he joined the US Army during World War II.</p>
            <p>After the war was over, a young woman came up to him in a Paris
cafe and asked if he'd do her a favour: "My father is an artist and
I need someone to take his work back to America." He agreed. The
woman was Marc Chagall's daughter.</p>
            <p>Kellen was the kind of person that people went up to unannounced
in cafes and asked great favours of. He had that gift.</p>
            <p>After the war, the army sent him back to
Berlin where his job was to interview German soldiers to find out
why they kept fighting for Hitler long after it was clear that the
war was lost. Then he went to work for Radio Free Europe. Again he
had the job of a listener, asked to interview defectors from behind
the Iron Curtain to get a flavour of what life was like under the
Soviet regime.</p>
            <p>And finally, in the early 1960s, he joined the Rand Corporation,
a prestigious think tank in California started by the Pentagon
after the war to do top-level defence analysis. And there he faced
the greatest challenge of his career - the Vietnam Motivation and
Morale Project.</p>
            <p>The morale project was started by Leon Goure, who was also an
immigrant. His parents were Mensheviks. They escaped from the
Soviet Union during one of Stalin's purges. Goure was brilliant,
charismatic, incredibly charming and absolutely ruthless, and he
was Kellen's great nemesis.</p>
            <p>The morale project grew out of the Pentagon's great problem in
the early part of the Vietnam War. The US Air Force was bombing
North Vietnam because they wanted to stop the North Vietnamese
communists from supporting the insurgency in South Vietnam led by
the Viet Cong.</p>
            <p>The idea was to break the will of the North Vietnamese. But the
Pentagon didn't know anything about the North Vietnamese. They knew
nothing about Vietnamese culture, Vietnamese history, Vietnamese
language. It was just this little speck in the world, in their
view.</p>
            <p>How do you know that you're breaking the will of a country if
you know nothing about the country? So Goure's job was to figure
out what the North Vietnamese were thinking.</p>
            <p>He came into Saigon and took over an old French villa on Rue
Pasteur in the old part of the city. He hired Vietnamese
interviewers and sent them out into the countryside.</p>
            <p>The job was to find captured Viet Cong guerrillas and to
interview them. Over the next few years, they came up with 61,000
pages of transcripts. Those transcripts were translated into
English and summarised and analysed.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68417000/jpg/_68417148_leongoure.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="300"
                 alt="Leon Goure speaking at Miami-Dade Community College south campus - Kendall, Florida"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Leon Goure was Kellen's greatest
nemesis</span>
            </div>
            <p>Goure took those analyses and he gave briefings to all the top
military brass in the American military establishment. And every
time he gave a presentation on the Vietnam Motivation and Morale
Project, he said the same things:</p>
            <ul>
               <li>that the Vietcong were utterly demoralised</li>
               <li>that they were about to give up</li>
               <li>that if pushed a little bit more, if bombed just a little bit
more, they'll throw up their hands in despair and run screaming
back to Hanoi</li>
            </ul>
            <p>It's hard to overestimate just how seriously Goure was taken in
those years. He was the only man who understood the mind of the
enemy. When dignitaries came to Saigon, their first stop would be
the villa in Rue Pasteur, where Goure would hold forth at cocktail
parties with insights into this strange, mysterious enemy they were
fighting.</p>
            <p>He'd be picked up by helicopter and
whisked to aircraft carriers off the coast of Vietnam, so he could
brief the top military brass who had flown in from Washington. They
used to say that Lyndon Johnson would walk around with a copy of
Goure's findings in his back pocket. What Goure said formed the
justification for US policy in Vietnam.</p>
            <p>Everyone believed what Goure said, with one exception - Konrad
Kellen. He read the same interviews and reached the exact opposite
conclusion.</p>
            <p>Years later, he would say that his rethinking began with one
memorable interview with a senior Vietcong captain. He was asked
very early in the interview if he thought the Vietcong could win
the war, and he said no.</p>
            <p>But pages later, he was asked if he thought that the US could
win the war, and he said no.</p>
            <p>The second answer profoundly changes the meaning of the first.
He didn't think in terms of winning or losing at all, which is a
very different proposition. An enemy who is indifferent to the
outcome of a battle is the most dangerous enemy of all.</p>
            <p>Now why did Kellen see this and Goure did not? Because Goure
didn't have the gift.</p>
            <p>Goure was someone who filtered what he heard through his own
biases. His biases were that this was 1965. The US was the most
powerful country in the history of the world. North Vietnam was a
speck that had barely entered the Industrial Revolution.</p>
            <p>In just the first bombing campaign of the war, Operation Rolling
Thunder, the US dropped as many bombs on this tiny speck as the RAF
dropped on all of Germany throughout WWII.</p>
            <p>Goure looked at the numbers and he could not believe that anyone
could stand up in the face of that kind of assault. So he read that
second sentence in the interview and he stopped listening.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68606000/jpg/_68606681_fire_vietcong_afp.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="300"
                 alt="A Viet Cong base being burned in My Tho, Vietnam on 05 April, 1968."/>
            </div>
            <p>Kellen was different. He had the gift. He was 20 when Hitler
took over in Germany and he immediately packed his bags and didn't
return until after the war was over. When asked why he left when he
did, he would always say the same thing: "I had a feeling."</p>
            <p>Hitler made it perfectly plain what his
attitude towards the Jews was in those years, but most people
didn't listen. Kellen did. That doesn't sound like a great
accomplishment, but it was.</p>
            <p>Listening is hard because the more you listen, the more
unsettling the world becomes. It's a lot easier just to place your
hands over your ears and not listen at all.</p>
            <p>So Kellen stood up and said that Goure was wrong, that the
Vietcong were not giving up and were not demoralised. It was not,
he said, a battle the US could win - not today, not tomorrow and
not the day after tomorrow.</p>
            <p>Nothing happened. Goure had cocktail parties and entertained
visiting dignitaries and helicopters whisked him off to aircraft
carriers, and Kellen wrote long, detailed reports that were ignored
and then forgotten. The war went on and things got worse and
worse.</p>
            <p>In 1968, a colleague of his went to see Henry Kissinger, who was
then the incoming architect of the Vietnam War, and he urged
Kissinger to meet Kellen.</p>
            <p>But Kissinger never did. Maybe if he had, the course of history
would be different. But that's the great irony of being a great
listener. The better listener you are, the less people want to
listen to you.</p>
            <p>Kellen retired to a small cliff-top house overlooking the ocean
in Los Angeles with a Chagall on the wall. He had a long and sad
decline.</p>
            <p>In his old age, he would wake up in the middle of the night and
imagine that the Nazis were coming up the hill to get him. It was
the only time he was ever wrong.</p>
            <p class="transmission-info">
               <em>This piece is based on an edited
version of</em>
               <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b036k7d0">Malcolm Gladwell:
Listening in Vietnam</a>
               <em>on BBC Radio 4</em>
            </p>
            <p>
               <em>You can follow the Magazine on</em>
               <a href="https://twitter.com/BBCNewsMagazine">Twitter</a>
               <em>and on</em>
               <a href="http://www.facebook.com/BBCMagazine"
               title="Facebook - BBC Magazine">Facebook</a>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine">In today's
Magazine</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373287989791"
                     href="/news/blogs-magazine-monitor-23224705">10 very, very long waits
for sporting glory</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373253012577"
                     href="/news/magazine-22971177">Revolution in the royal nursery</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373240476495"
                     href="/news/magazine-23179862">The sad life of a circus lion</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373066350296"
                     href="/news/magazine-23146086">10x10 things about 10 years of the
Magazine</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>About the author</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68387000/jpg/_68387163_gladwell.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Malcolm Gladwell"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>Malcolm Gladwell is a journalist and author</li>
               <li>Hear more on this story in Radio 4's Pop-Up Ideas, broadcast on
Tuesday 9 July at 09:30 BST and repeated on 10 July at 20:45
BST</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b036k7d0">Or catch up
with iPlayer</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Konrad Kellen</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68606000/jpg/_68606683_kellan_konrad.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="228"
                 alt="Konrad Kellen"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>Born 1913 in Germany</li>
               <li>Fled Nazi Germany for New York aged 20</li>
               <li>Worked for US Army intelligence unit in WWII and awarded the
Legion of Merit</li>
               <li>Policy analyst at Rand Corporation in California</li>
               <li>In 1969, he and Rand colleagues wrote an open letter to the US
government recommending US troops be withdrawn from Vietnam within
a year</li>
               <li>Died aged 93 in 2007</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Vietnam War 1955-75</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68387000/jpg/_68387165_2695678(1).jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="American napalm bombs exploding in fields south of Saigon during the Vietnam War"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>Called the American War in Vietnam</li>
               <li>Claimed millions of lives</li>
               <li>US was driven by Cold War concerns about the spread of
communism</li>
               <li>US and South Vietnam failed to stop communist-led
unification</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/shared/spl/hi/asia_pac/05/vietnam_war/html/build_up.stm">
The war in brief</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-pacific-16568035">Vietnam:
chronology of key events</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">An enemy who is indifferent to the outcome
of a battle is the most dangerous enemy of all”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
