<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23129242"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The riots in Sweden that broke out in May shocked the world. A shortage of community police has been diagnosed - police officers like Togo-born Rissa Seidou who know the area and its residents."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-03T00:19:40"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68486000/jpg/_68486158_rissaseidou3.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="An African on the beat in Sweden"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Magazine"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23129242"/>
         <title>BBC News - An African on the beat in Sweden</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">3 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:19</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">An African on the beat in Sweden</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Tim Mansel</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC World Service,
Stockholm</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68505000/jpg/_68505297_rissaseidou2.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Rissa Seidou"/>
            </div>
            <p>
               <strong>The riots in Sweden that broke
out in May shocked the world. Sweden was the last place most people
expected scenes of this kind. More community police officers are
needed, a minister says, officers like Togo-born Rissa Seidou who
know the area and its residents.</strong>
            </p>
            <p>Rissa Seidou cuts a striking figure in Husby, a suburb of
Stockholm. She wears baggy trousers and a navy blue polo shirt, big
boots and a pistol on her hip.</p>
            <p>Husby is where the riots began, riots that spread first to other
Stockholm suburbs and then into the provinces. Cars and buildings
burned for several nights and young men pelted the police and
firefighters with stones.</p>
            <p>The disturbances exposed Sweden's reputation for tolerance and
equality to international scrutiny. They also exposed fragile
relations between the police and some of the residents of Sweden's
more deprived communities, some of whom complained of racism.</p>
            <p>"I cannot say there are not racist police officers," says Rissa.
"If I say that, I am lying to you."</p>
            <p>And did she think, as was widely reported, that police officers
had used racial insults during the riots?</p>
            <p>"Yeah," she says, "I think it's
possible."</p>
            <p>Rissa is a neighbourhood police officer, based in Kista, a
suburb adjacent to Husby, north of Stockholm city centre. Nearly
85% of Husby's population of 12,000 are either first or
second-generation immigrants. Unemployment is high, particularly
among men under 25, and educational achievement is low.</p>
            <p>The reasons for the riots are disputed. Some people in Husby
connect them to an incident a few days earlier in which a police
officer had shot an elderly man dead in his flat in Oslogatan. The
police said he had been threatening people with a knife.</p>
            <p>"The people in Husby thought the police reacted wrong and they
did this to punish the police," says one local teenager about the
riots.</p>
            <p>Another young man points to more general dissatisfaction. "The
people are tired," he says. "They are stopped by the police three
or four times a day. People who are not from Sweden have a lot of
trouble with the police here."</p>
            <p>"It's not acceptable to throw stones at the police," says Jamil,
a 25-year-old gardener of Iraqi origin, who is smoking and chatting
to friends in the central square. "But it is understandable."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68500000/jpg/_68500649_rinkeby_afp.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="300"
                 alt="Bystanders take photos of a row of burning cars in the Stockholm suburb of Rinkeby (May 23, 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The riots spread around the city, with
groups of youths stoning police</span>
            </div>
            <p>Rissa Seidou has been a police officer for eight years. Now in
her late thirties, she was born in Togo in West Africa and grew up
in France. When she was 20 her parents brought her to Sweden.
Sweden had yet to join the European Union and didn't recognise her
French education. So she had to go back to high school, into a
class of 16-year-olds.</p>
            <p>Her father would come down to the school every day to talk to
the teachers and to inspect her work.</p>
            <p>At the time she thought it was embarrassing, but now she is
grateful.</p>
            <p>"I thank them every day." she says, "They were so concerned,
they were so engaged because they knew it was a new country."</p>
            <p>Rissa ended up working as a youth leader. She would sometimes be
asked to accompany young people down to the police station for
interrogations.</p>
            <p>"A lot of young people said the police
were unfair, that they were treated very badly by the police. I
wanted to be there myself and be a witness and then make my own
conclusions," she says.</p>
            <p>Her conclusion was that the Swedish police were too nice. "They
were not rude at all. They were very, very kind. I found it very
strange."</p>
            <p>Despite opposition from friends and family, Rissa decided she
wanted to join the police.</p>
            <p>"My family laughed at me and said it wouldn't be possible,
because they'd never seen a police officer with African parents.
But I wasn't going to give up."</p>
            <p>Rissa says she is the first Swedish police officer with two
African parents.</p>
            <p>She chooses her words carefully when asked if she has
experienced racism from her police colleagues.</p>
            <p>"I had a little bit of a tough time at the police training
school. And when I left, I think the police, I mean the
institution, was not so prepared to receive a woman with an African
background. I didn't fit. I was a little bit different.</p>
            <p>"There are always some people who don't believe that a foreigner
can also be a police officer.</p>
            <p>"If I said there was no racism, then, as I said, I'm lying to
you. Yes of course it's happened. If it's happened it's because
they're not so used to foreigners. Of course some people have said
some bad words, but I see it as normal behaviour."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68511000/jpg/_68511930_rissaseidou.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="300"
                 alt="Rissa Seidou"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Rissa says she and her colleagues are neighbourhood
police on paper only</span>
            </div>
            <p>As Rissa walks through Husby she stops frequently to talk to
passers-by. She chats to three young girls on their way to an
after-school club, a member of the local neighbourhood watch and a
young man from Algeria who tells her that the cops in Sweden are
nice compared to those in France or Germany. She smiles.</p>
            <p>But she also expresses regret: "This is the first time we've
been down here since the riots," she says, referring to herself and
her colleague who is accompanying her.</p>
            <p>Rissa says they are neighbourhood police on paper only, that
they are too often called away to other duties.</p>
            <p>"I think if they call us neighbourhood police then where should
we be? Here, in our area, making contacts with people who are
living here," she says, explaining that she will be spending the
whole summer in another police district.</p>
            <p>"The people here pay their taxes like every other Swede and they
need us. We should be building relationships so they know who we
are. They recognise me because I'm black, and they know there's
only one black woman. But they don't know any of the other police
officers."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68486000/jpg/_68486197_demo_afp.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="300"
                 alt="People stand in front of a banner reading 'Stop police violence for an independent investigation' during a demonstration against police violence in the Stockholm suburb of Husby (22 May 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Community activists have accused the
police of using racist language during the unrest</span>
            </div>
            <p>The Swedish minister for integration, Erik Ullenhag, appears to
have got the message. After visiting Husby last week, he said that
he thought more police were needed on the beat.</p>
            <p>At the moment, around one Swedish police officer in 20 comes
from an immigrant family, but Rissa is not enthusiastic about the
suggestion that the Swedish police should be recruiting more people
from ethnic minorities.</p>
            <p>"The police in Sweden have to get used to people from other
countries, and try to learn more and understand more about them. I
think the police need to learn more about other cultures. The
solution is not to recruit more people from other countries."</p>
            <p>As Rissa stands outside the metro station in Husby, Jamil, the
gardener, drives up in a small electric truck.</p>
            <p>"Rissa is a very good police officer," says Jamil. "She's the
only one who is good."</p>
            <p>"That's not what you said the first time I came down here," she
laughs.</p>
            <p>Jamil acknowledges that he was aggressive the first time they
met. "But when she talked good to me then I started to be good with
her."</p>
            <p>"He calmed down," Rissa explains. "I said, 'Why are you so
angry? You don't know me, you've never met me. This is the first
time, so let's talk.' And now we're friends."</p>
            <p>"It's the person, not the uniform," says Jamil. "I like the
person."</p>
            <p>"But you hate the uniform," says Rissa.</p>
            <p>Jamil agrees. "But if every police officer were like her," he
adds, "I swear to God we don't have a problem with the police."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine">In today's
Magazine</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373253012577"
                     href="/news/magazine-22971177">Revolution in the royal nursery</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373240476495"
                     href="/news/magazine-23179862">The sad life of a circus lion</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373066350296"
                     href="/news/magazine-23146086">10x10 things about 10 years of the
Magazine</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372980521482"
                     href="/news/magazine-23137492">Will there ever be another massive tank
battle?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Find out more</h2>
            <p>
               <strong>Assignment: Sweden's angry suburbs</strong> is broadcast
on the BBC World Service on Thursday 4 July 2013 at 08:06 GMT,
14:32 GMT and 19:06 GMT, or listen again on iPlayer</p>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p01bbvjh">Assignment:
Sweden's angry suburbs</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>In her words</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68510000/jpg/_68510205_rissaseidou3.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Rissa Seidou"/>
            </div>
            <p>
               <strong>"I think the police need to learn more about other
cultures. The solution is not to recruit more people from other
countries."</strong>
            </p>
            <p>Rissa Seidou</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
