<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-22957099"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The quality of a performance does not drive the amount of applause an audience gives, a study suggests."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T00:04:34"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68248000/jpg/_68248554_img_2602.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Applause is a 'social contagion'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Science and Environment"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-22957099"/>
         <title>BBC News - Clapping reveals applause is a 'social
contagion'</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:04</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Clapping reveals applause is a 'social
contagion'</h1>
            <div class="has-icon-comment dna-comment-count-simple"> </div>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Rebecca
Morelle</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Science reporter, BBC
World Service</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68248000/jpg/_68248492_img_2602.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="hand clap"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Researchers found that it takes one or two people to
start - and end - a round of applause</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The quality of a
performance does not drive the amount of applause an audience
gives, a study suggests.</p>
            <p>Instead scientists have found that clapping is contagious, and
the length of an ovation is influenced by how other members of the
crowd behave.</p>
            <p>They say it takes a few people to start clapping for applause to
spread through a group, and then just one or two individuals to
stop for it to die out.</p>
            <p>The Swedish study <a href="http://rsif.royalsocietypublishing.org/lookup/doi/10.1098/rsif.2013.0466">
is published in the Journal of the Royal Society Interface</a>.</p>
            <p>Lead author Dr Richard Mann, from the University of Uppsala,
said: "You can get quite different lengths of applause - even if
you have the same quality of performance. This is purely coming
form the dynamics of the people in the crowd."</p>
            <p>
               <strong>Chain reaction</strong>
            </p>
            <p>The research was carried out by studying video footage of groups
of undergraduates as they watched a presentation.</p>
            <p>The scientists found that it took just
one or two people to put their hands together for a ripple of
applause to spread through the crowd.</p>
            <p>These claps sparked a chain reaction, where, spurred on by the
noise, other audience members joined in.</p>
            <p>"The pressure comes from the volume of clapping in the room
rather than what your neighbour sitting next to you is doing,"
explained Dr Mann.</p>
            <p>But the performance that had been witnessed - no matter how
brilliant - had little effect on the duration of the noisy
acclaim.</p>
            <p>In fact, the researchers found the duration of applause varied
greatly.</p>
            <p>Dr Mann told BBC News: "In one case an audience might clap on
average 10 times per person. Another time they might clap three
times as long.</p>
            <p>"And all that comes from is that you have this social pressure
to start (clapping), but once you've started there's an equally
strong social pressure not to stop, until someone initiates that
stopping."</p>
            <p>The scientists believe that clapping is a form of "social
contagion", which reveals how how ideas and actions gain and lose
momentum.</p>
            <p>Studying this, they say, could shed light on other areas, such
as how trends come in and go out of fashion or how ideas spread on
the internet.</p>
            <p>Dr Mann said: "Here we tested whether you are more driven by the
total number of people in the room or the people sitting next to
you.</p>
            <p>"And the equivalent on Facebook or Twitter would be whether you
are more likely to join in a trend if you see lots of people in the
wider world mentioning it or if just your closer friends mention
it."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1248168879000"
                  href="/1/hi/magazine/8160543.stm">To clap or not to clap?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1189507820000"
                  href="/1/hi/magazine/6986935.stm">A respectful round of...
applause?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">An audience might clap on average 10 times
per person. Another time they might clap three times as
long”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Dr Richard Mann</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">University of Uppsala</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
