<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-23229097"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Growing opposition to wind energy in the heart of Germany could damage ambitious targets for renewables."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-11T02:05:39"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68660000/jpg/_68660130_castle.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Wind power battle in fairy tale land"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Science and Environment"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-23229097"/>
         <title>BBC News - Battle over wind turbines in the land of Sleeping
Beauty</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">11 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">03:05</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Battle over wind turbines in the land of
Sleeping Beauty</h1>
            <span class="byline byline-photo">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/64370000/jpg/_64370744_matt2.jpg"
                 alt="Matt McGrath"/>
               <span class="byline-name">By Matt
McGrath</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Environment
correspondent, BBC News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68623000/jpg/_68623168_sleepingbeautycomp.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="sleeping beauty comp"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Plans to expand wind
energy into the most scenic parts of Germany are fuelling
increasing opposition across the country.</p>
            <p>Anti-wind campaigners are angry that areas including the forests
made famous by the tales of the brothers Grimm are among the
targets for new turbines.</p>
            <p>For the first time they have formed a national opposition group
to thwart the expansion.</p>
            <p>They say the growth of wind will damage forests and tourism
across the country.</p>
            <p>Germany has embarked on a massive
expansion of renewable energy in the wake of the Fukushima nuclear
disaster in 2011. Chancellor Merkel's government decided to phase
out atomic plants more rapidly and instead increased the
opportunities for green power.</p>
            <p>With guaranteed prices for 20 years thanks to feed-in tariffs
enshrined in law, solar farms, biogas plants and wind parks have
boomed. There are now 1.3 million small co-operatives and
households supplying renewable energy to the grid.</p>
            <p>This <em>Energiewende</em> or energy transformation has been
remarkably successful, with 22% of Germany's electricity being
generated by renewables in 2012. Wind has played a major part in
this change, and the public has been generally supportive, despite
rapidly increasing energy bills.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68608000/jpg/_68608620_img_5593.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Castle"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Sleeping Beauty reputedly slept for 100 years in
this castle in Sababurg, just across the valley from the home of
Rapunzel</span>
            </div>
            <p>To date, a majority of the 23,000 wind turbines in the country
have been built in the flatter north and eastern parts of the
country. But now the focus of expansion is on the picture postcard
areas of dark forest and lush green hills in the central and
southern areas of Germany.</p>
            <p>One such region is the Rheinhardswald in the northern part of
the state of Hesse. This is the home of the magical tales of
Sleeping Beauty, Rapunzel and others, made famous in the books of
the brothers Grimm.</p>
            <p>This quiet, scenic place is a magnet for tourists from all over
the world.</p>
            <p>But now there are also plans to build up to 200 turbines on the
surrounding hills.</p>
            <p>Ann-Kathrin Blankenberg is a PhD student and a vocal opponent of
the plans.</p>
            <p>"It is not because this is the area of Sleeping Beauty," she
says.</p>
            <p>"I want the green movement, I want green technology, I don't
want nuclear power - but they should be made in the right way and
not by destroying the forest.</p>
            <p>"We have here special, old growth forest and some species just
live in this area and are in danger because of the turbines."</p>
            <p>The campaigners argue that putting wind turbines in this area
makes no sense. The wind speeds are low and the area is home to
some extremely rare birds including the endangered black stork.</p>
            <p>Across Germany, the plans for expansion have pitted green
against green - the potential damage to natural resources from the
building of turbines seems to be the biggest concern for
opponents.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68636000/jpg/_68636907_img_5552.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="T-shirt"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Campaigners say the building of turbines here would
be disastrous for tourism</span>
            </div>
            <p>About 170 regional groups opposed to wind energy have now formed
a national organisation called Vernunftkraft, to fight the
expansion of turbines. They are trying to get enough signatures on
a petition to force the German parliament to debate the future
direction of the <em>Energiewende</em>, especially the subsidies
for wind energy.</p>
            <p>Some of those involved believe that unlike solar power, which
has been adopted by many individual householders, wind parks are
essentially speculative investments with electricity consumers
guaranteeing a return for developers.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68652000/jpg/_68652757_pop3.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="comp4"/>
            </div>
            <p>At his sleek workshop near Wiesbaden, several hundred kilometres
away from the fairytale forests of Sleeping Beauty, Markus Storck
designs some of the greenest machines on the planet.</p>
            <p>His crafted, lightweight bicycles have won dozens of awards. His
products sell all over the world and he has also experimented with
electric bikes.</p>
            <p>But he is now vehemently opposing the expansion of wind energy
in Germany, and is highly critical of developers and the subsidies
that bolster their projects.</p>
            <p>"They are getting people to invest by telling them they can make
money with it, but people will also lose like with the internet. I
would call it a wind bubble," he says.</p>
            <p>"There is nobody who stands up and tells the truth, we have to
stop now."</p>
            <p>While the protestors are becoming more organised, they still
represent a relatively small section of society.</p>
            <p>Opinion polls continue to show widespread political support for
the energy transformation and for wind energy as well. There is a
common belief that opponents of wind are "nimbys" - short for "Not
In My Back Yard" - who only complain because the turbines are
coming to their local areas.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68646000/jpg/_68646547_img_5606.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="wedding"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Sleeping Beauty's castle is a popular place for
weddings and celebrations</span>
            </div>
            <p>Hans-Josef Fell is the Green MP who is sometimes called the
father of the feed-in tariff. In 2000, he wrote the draft of the
Renewable Energy Source Act that kick-started the energy
transformation. He characterises the opponents of wind as small,
aggressive groups.</p>
            <p>"They don't bother to have an honest discussion, because they
want to prohibit a wind turbine in their backyard," he says.</p>
            <p>"They don't recognise that by doing so, other people have to
deal with the consequences of an opencast coal mine or radioactive
waste storage."</p>
            <p>There are other issues associated with the energy transformation
that are troubling environmentalists. The shutdown of nuclear
reactors in the south of the country means there is a need to
transfer energy from the north. New, high voltage cables are needed
to link onshore and offshore wind parks to consumers and
industry.</p>
            <p>But critics are worried that these new cables will not only
damage the landscape, they could also be a risk to public
health.</p>
            <p>There are demands from the Green party that the wires be buried
where possible. But many landowners are unwilling to, quite
literally, give ground for the projects.</p>
            <p>In the central university town of Goettingen, local Green party
councillor Harald Wiedemann has concerns about how these plans will
work.</p>
            <p>"The problem is, on the one hand the cost, and on the other is
the electro-magnetic field - no one has said they will have 1,000kw
cables here but in future it is possible", he says.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68637000/jpg/_68637995_img_5574.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="campaigner against turbines"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Local residents say their opposition is
founded on science and is not "nimbyism"</span>
            </div>
            <p>"We have to build these cables really far away from towns - it
is too expensive to put them underground for such a long distance,
no-one can pay."</p>
            <p>Whether people are objecting to electricity pylons or the
building of wind turbines, much of the opposition appears to be
practical and not grounded in climate change scepticism. A majority
accept that rising temperatures and the need for secure,
sustainable energy sources means the energy transition must go
ahead.</p>
            <p>Back at the home of Sleeping Beauty, the opponents of turbines
insist that they are open to compromise.</p>
            <p>Guenter Koseck, the owner of the castle at Sababurg that is
reputed to have been the home of the slumbering princess, says this
is not an ideological fight.</p>
            <p>"This area is owned by the state, so if we get turbines here
only because it is the easiest place to locate them and not because
it is the most efficient area, then I would object," he says.</p>
            <p>"We want to move to green energy, and it has to be located
somewhere. Without any question I would accept it here, as long as
the arguments are right."</p>
            <p>Follow Matt on <a href="http://twitter.com/mattmcgrathbbc">Twitter</a>.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373418713010"
                  href="/news/science-environment-23127175">German 'energy bender' in
trouble?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1361923407053"
                  href="/news/business-21575288">Who pays for the greening of
Germany?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1353542508348"
                  href="/news/business-20002801">Coal resurgence calls undermine clean
energy commitments</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">There is nobody who stands up and tells the
truth, we have to stop now”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Markus Storck</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Bicycle designer</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
