<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-23096068"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The atmospheric carbon left over from nuclear bomb tests could help scientists track illegally poached ivory, new research finds."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T20:00:01"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68469000/jpg/_68469099_elehpants_afp_getty158835724.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Nuclear carbon to fight poaching"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Science and Environment"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-23096068"/>
         <title>BBC News - Carbon from nuclear tests could help fight
poachers</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">21:00</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Carbon from nuclear tests could help fight
poachers</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Melissa
Hogenboom</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Science reporter, BBC
News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68470000/jpg/_68470241_elehpants_afp_getty158835724.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Mother and baby elephant"/>
               <span style="width:624px;">Poaching is now at the highest it has
been for two decades, according to conservation groups</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The atmospheric
carbon left over from nuclear bomb testing could help scientists
track poached ivory, new research has found.</p>
            <p>These bomb tests changed the level of carbon in the atmosphere,
which can be traced to date elephant tusks.</p>
            <p>Trafficking poached ivory is increasingly being used to fund
civil wars, groups warn.</p>
            <p>Scientists say the findings, <a href="http://www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.1302226110">published in
PNAS</a>, could make it easier to enforce the ivory ban.</p>
            <p>The number of elephants being poached is now at the highest it
has been for two decades, according to a UN backed report.</p>
            <p>This was highlighted in January when a family of <a href="/news/world-africa-20944859"
               title="Kenya elephant family slaughtered">11 elephants was slaughtered in
Kenya</a>, their tusks hacked off with machetes.</p>
            <p>In the 1980s, more than half of Africa's
elephants are thought to have been wiped out by poachers. This led
to an international ban on trading ivory in 1989. As public
awareness of the threat of extinction increased, the global demand
for ivory dwindled.</p>
            <p>But today conservationists believe that a growing demand for
ivory in China and other Asian countries is responsible for a huge
increase in the number of animals being poached.</p>
            <p>Many governments have huge stockpiles of ivory, and it is often
unclear when this ivory was acquired and whether or not some of it
is leaking into the illegal market.</p>
            <p>Now scientists have found that radioactive carbon in the
atmosphere emitted during the Cold War bomb tests will make it
easier to distinguish between illegal ivory to that which was
acquired before the trade ban.</p>
            <p>The amount of radiocarbon in the atmosphere nearly doubled
during nuclear weapons tests from 1952 to 1962, which steadily
dropped after tests were restricted to underground. This has been
dubbed "the bomb-curve".</p>
            <p>The levels have declined since but as they are still absorbed by
plant, they enter the food chain and are measurable in plant and
animal tissues.</p>
            <p>The concentration of radiocarbon found in tiny samples of animal
tissue can accurately determine the year of an animals death, from
1955 until today, explained lead author Kevin Uno from Columbia
University's Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, US.</p>
            <p>"This is different to the traditional dating technique which
takes advantage of the loss of radiocarbon through time."</p>
            <div id="slideshow_container" class="storybody-halfwide-include">
               <div id="ss_slides">
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68474000/jpg/_68474362_154220648.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Dehorned rhino and calf"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">Rhinos are increasingly being targeted
as countries like China and Vietnam believe powdered rhino horn has
medicinal powers. One preventative tactic is dehorning rhinos
safely</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68478000/jpg/_68478173_seizedivory_april_2013_167520701.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Elephant tusks seized in the Zakouma National Park, Chad"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">An Asian appetite for ivory is believed
to have fuelled poaching in recent years and highly organised crime
groups increasingly put the lives of park rangers at
risk</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68474000/jpg/_68474364_167520707.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Guards exercising during a parade in Zakouma National"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">Zakouma National Park in Chad has hired
a military unit to protect its Elephants, 90% of which have been
poached in the last decade</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68474000/jpg/_68474363_171854903.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Kenya Wildlife Service rangers carrying placards in Nairobi"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">Conservationists warn that unless the
demand is curtailed, poaching is edging the African elephant ever
closer to extinction</span>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="ss_controls">
                  <a href="#prev" class="ss_prev ss_button ss_button_disabled">
                     <span>previous
slide</span>
                  </a>
                  <a href="#next" class="ss_next ss_button ss_button_disabled">
                     <span>next
slide</span>
                  </a>
               </div>
            </div>
            <p>Traditional radiocarbon dating would only
be able to pick up an "imperceptible amount of decay" added Dr Uno,
but because the bomb spike doubled the concentration or carbon,
they were able to find huge variations over the last 60 years,
which enabled accurate dating.</p>
            <p>Dr Uno said this technique "would
dovetail very nicely with DNA testing which tells you the region of
origin, but not the date".</p>
            <p>As anti-poaching funding is extremely limited, understanding
where the poaching hotspots are, as well as how old the tusks are,
could help the international community to direct funding to the
places most at risk, he added.</p>
            <p>"The year an elephant died plays a big role in whether or not
the trade [of ivory] is legal. Poached ivory makes it to market
relatively quickly, so by measuring the age of a tusk we can say
what year it's from. This will help us pinpoint the source of the
ivory and how it's getting to market."</p>
            <p>Big government organisations like the UN and Interpol have also
recently increased efforts looking into the problem.</p>
            <p>"Saving elephants - majestic and wonderful species - is
priceless. These wildlife forensics are ready to roll, now we need
to speak to the organisations who can set up a programme to make it
happen."</p>
            <p>Poaching is a problem closely linked to poverty, politics and
conflict. Poachers include poor opportunistic individuals and
increasingly heavily armed militia groups who use ivory to fund
conflicts.</p>
            <p>WWF's regional East Africa manager Drew McVey welcomed the new
research, and said any help in securing convictions could reduce
ivory trafficking.</p>
            <p>"The key thing to note is that ivory has been smuggled so far
and wide, we've got to cut down the loopholes as much as we can.
Though the amount of seizures [of illegal ivory] is increasing each
year, we don't know how much we're catching, it's realistic to
think we're not catching all the big ones."</p>
            <p>He added that poaching is not easy to prevent as "one thing
Africa isn't short of is poor people" which is why it's important
to cut down the ways people are moving ivory around.</p>
            <p>"Rather than targeting people on the ground, we need to reduce
the demand from middle men and the consumers," Mr McVey told BBC
News.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68484000/jpg/_68484755_img_1823(2).jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Cutting a tusk in preparation for sampling "/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The researchers analysed tusk samples smaller than a
pinch of salt</span>
            </div>
            <p>As for the scientific process involved, Paula Raimer from
Queen's University Belfast, said the study removes doubt that the
C14 emitted from bombs can be used to date ivory.</p>
            <p>"The work is of particular importance for forensics use in
endangered species because the authors show that C14 can be used to
determine the age of death or collection of ivory as well as
establishing growth rates, so that other data from the teeth can
also be put on a calendar time scale."</p>
            <p>The study has wider implications for crime forensics, she added,
as bomb carbon could be used to date human bones as well as to
detect art forgeries.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1366981886404"
                  href="/news/world-africa-22308960">CAR elephant poaching 'on the
rise'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1358218162300"
                  href="/news/world-africa-21018429">African elephant poaching threatens
wildlife future</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1357852817491"
                  href="/news/science-environment-20971182">SA rhino poaching at record
level</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Bomb carbon dating</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68478000/jpg/_68478174_68474355.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Elephant tusks "/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>Traditional radiocarbon dating determines the age of ancient
objects by measuring the amount of carbon-14 (C14)</li>
               <li>The approximate time since an organism died can be measured
from the amount of C14 left in its remains</li>
               <li>But remains from after the Cold War contain higher levels of
C14 due to the nuclear bombs</li>
               <li>In a new study Dr Uno and colleagues used this increase in
carbon to date herbivore samples, which they matched to
corresponding points on the bomb-curve</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">These wildlife forensics are ready to roll,
now we need to speak to people who can set up a programme to make
it happen”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Dr Kevin Uno</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Columbia University, US</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
