<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-23143430"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The world's largest rat eradication campaign has now laid toxic bait on a further 580 sq km of South Georgia, reaching its target."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T00:01:26"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68530000/png/_68530915_brownratonsouthgeorgia2_creditpaulaosullivan.png"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="South Georgia rat removal hits mark"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Science and Environment"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-23143430"/>
         <title>BBC News - South Georgia rat removal hits milestone</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:01</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">South Georgia rat removal hits
milestone</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Melissa
Hogenboom</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Science reporter, BBC
News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68530000/png/_68530992_brownratonsouthgeorgia2_creditpaulaosullivan.png"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Brown rat on South Georgia"/>
               <span style="width:624px;">The brown rat was introduced to South
Georgia on sealing and whaling ships over 200 years ago. It's a
ferocious predator and feasts on the chicks and eggs of
ground-nesting seabirds</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The world's largest
rat eradication campaign has now laid toxic bait on a further 580
sq km of South Georgia, reaching its target.</p>
            <p>These poisonous pellets have now been spread on 70% of the
rat-infested island.</p>
            <p>First introduced on sealing and whaling ships in the late 18th
Century, millions of invasive rats have long been a threat to local
wildlife.</p>
            <p>The team is confident they will eradicate the rodents within two
years.</p>
            <p>South Georgia is famous for its rich wildlife but as sailors
plundered the ocean for seals and whales, they unknowingly brought
with them the common brown rat.</p>
            <p>The unwelcome visitors multiplied quickly as they bred and for
over 200 years have feasted on the chicks and eggs of
ground-nesting seabirds, which include ducks, diving petrels and
prions.</p>
            <p>Species like the South Georgia Pipit and the South Georgia
Pintail are unique to the island and there is now a growing concern
that many local birds are at danger of extinction.</p>
            <p>The island is separated by several glaciers, so once rats have
been eradicated from a region, they cannot repopulate it.</p>
            <p>But as the climate warms the island's natural glaciers are
slowly melting. As this continues, there will no longer be a
natural barrier preventing the rats from spreading.</p>
            <div id="slideshow_container" class="storybody-halfwide-include">
               <div id="ss_slides">
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68534000/jpg/_68534315_southgeorgiapintailstonymartin(15).jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="South Georgia pintails"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">South Georgia is home to the South
Georgia Pintail which are unique to the island but wildlife groups
are worried it's at danger of extinction</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68534000/jpg/_68534293_southgeorgiapipit_creditewanedwards.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="South Georgia pipit"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">The South Georgia Pipit is also indigenous to the
island but rats have vastly reduced its numbers</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68534000/jpg/_68534318_rateatingabaitpellet_creditrolandgockel.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Rat eating a toxic bait pellet"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">The latest mission saw 183 tonnes of
toxic pellets distributed thinly across the island to reach every
rodent territory from sea level to mountain top</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68534000/jpg/_68534292_nordenskjoldglacier_credittonymartin.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Nordenskjold glacier"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">As the island is separated by glaciers, once rats
have been eradicated from a region they cannot repopulate it, but
these glaciers are receding due to climate change</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68534000/jpg/_68534319_helicopterinflightovervalley_creditrolandgockel.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Helicopter in fight over valley"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">The team had to be ready to move at
first light as the wind was calmest immediately after
dawn</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68534000/jpg/_68534289_handbaitingwhalingstationamongstelephantseals_creditrolandgockel.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Handbaiting a whaling station amongst resting elephant seals"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">Areas which could not be reached by
helicopter were hand baited, such as old whaling stations - areas
where elephant seals now rest</span>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="ss_controls">
                  <a href="#prev" class="ss_prev ss_button ss_button_disabled">
                     <span>previous
slide</span>
                  </a>
                  <a href="#next" class="ss_next ss_button ss_button_disabled">
                     <span>next
slide</span>
                  </a>
               </div>
            </div>
            <p>Tony Martin, the project's director from
the University of Dundee, described the mission as "a race against
time", as the melting glaciers could make the task of removing them
nearly impossible.</p>
            <p>"What's there today is but a shadow of what was there when
Captain Cook discovered [the island] in 1775.</p>
            <p>He explained that species like the fabulous Wilson Storm Petrel,
which were once present in the millions have all left the main
island.</p>
            <p>"There are still a few rodent-free islands around the coast from
which the main island can be re-colonised. We are trying to allow
the sea birds to reclaim their ancestral home.</p>
            <p>"The ecosystem of South Georgia evolved in the absence of any
terrestrial mammals, so when man came along... and introduced these
furry rodents, they were completely naive. This is a man induced
problem and it's about time that man put right earlier errors,"
Prof Martin said.</p>
            <p>"Team rat", as they call themselves, embarked on the first phase
of the eradication project in 2011, and <a href="/news/science-environment-13282806"
               title="'Success' in island rat campaign">successfully removed rats from a
tenth of the island</a>.</p>
            <p>The team purposely left time between missions to observe if any
survivors had managed to reproduce but, two years on, the area
remains rat free.</p>
            <p>For the latest mission the team spread nearly 200 tonnes of
pellets using helicopters which enabled them to cover large areas
very quickly.</p>
            <p>They dropped pellets in every area mice or rats occupied and
areas which cannot be reached by helicopter were baited by hand -
this included former whaling stations which are now industrial
heritage sites.</p>
            <p>Prof Martin explained that to be successful meant total
eradication.. Killing 99.9% would be a failure.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68534000/jpg/_68534287_helicopterlasheddowninsnowstorm_creditrolandgockel.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Helicopter in snowstorm"/>
               <span style="width:624px;">The team encountered days of terrible
weather, including blizzards and gale force winds</span>
            </div>
            <p>"If you leave one pregnant female - we all know how quickly rats
breed - we would be back to where we were."</p>
            <p>For this latest phase, for which the team had spent 21 months in
preparation, they faced the harshest weather conditions experienced
in a decade and were often unable to fly.</p>
            <p>The bait was attached underneath the helicopters which meant
strong wind could easily strain the aircraft. They encountered
turbulence "virtually every single day", helicopter pilot George
Phillips told BBC News.</p>
            <p>"It was very difficult to tell when the turbulence was coming,
that's why it took such a long time. On one particular period we
had eight wind-free days where the helicopters were able to fly
continuously.</p>
            <p>"In those days, the pilots did as much flying as you would do in
the UK in two months."</p>
            <p>Mr Phillips recalled how after four days at sea, he was stunned
by the beautiful terrain of the island.</p>
            <p>"It's a completely natural uninhabited environment that is so
extreme with high mountains, glaciers and seals that are so wild
they come up to you like little Alsatian puppies."</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68534000/jpg/_68534290_kingpenguins_creditgeorgelemann.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="King penguins"/>
               <span style="width:624px;">South Georgia's abundant wildlife includes four
species of penguin who nest on the island</span>
            </div>
            <p>The project will need to raise a further
Â£2m in order to bait the remaining area at
the southern end of the island, which they aim to complete in
2015.</p>
            <p>Even when rat free, the wildlife is not expected to return
immediately as to re-colonise the island could take decades if not
centuries, said Prof Martin.</p>
            <p>"Man managed to mess up South Georgia in the space of very few
years but it's going to take centuries before it gets back to where
it was."</p>
            <p>Though challenges remain - not least to find the additional
funding needed, Prof Martin said his team is confident they can win
this race against time</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1362152242421"
                  href="/news/science-environment-21629737">South Georgia rat cull begins
again</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1354190925786"
                  href="/news/science-environment-20539068">South Georgia rat cull to
resume</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1304552374393"
                  href="/news/science-environment-13282806">'Success' in island rat
campaign</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
