<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-23135934"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The last creatures to survive on Earth as our Sun reaches the end of its life will be tiny organisms living deep underground, according to scientists."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T00:49:14"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68489000/jpg/_68489468_om-j_thermophile_bacteria.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Bugs to be Earth's 'last survivors'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Science and Environment"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-23135934"/>
         <title>BBC News - Microbes to be 'last survivors' on future
Earth</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:49</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Microbes to be 'last survivors' on future
Earth</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Rebecca
Morelle</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Science reporter, BBC
World Service</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68489000/jpg/_68489376_om-j_thermophile_bacteria.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Extremophile"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Microbes that can withstand tough conditions could
be the last life on Earth</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The last surviving
creatures on Earth will be tiny organisms living deep underground,
according to scientists.</p>
            <p>Researchers used a computer model to assess our planet's fate
billions of years from now.</p>
            <p>They found that as the Sun becomes hotter and brighter, only
microbes would be able cope with the extreme conditions that the
solar changes would bring.</p>
            <p>The research <a href="http://www.nam2013.co.uk/">is being
presented at the National Astronomy Meeting</a>.</p>
            <p>Jack O'Malley James, from the University of St Andrews in
Scotland, said: "There won't be very much oxygen present, so they
need to be able to survive in low or zero-oxygen environments, high
pressures, and high salinities because of evaporating oceans."</p>
            <p>
               <strong>Mass extinction</strong>
            </p>
            <p>The future of life on Earth is tied to that of the Sun, and over
time, our star will become more and more luminous.</p>
            <p>Scientists from the universities of St Andrews, Dundee and
Edinburgh used this fact to create a forecast for our planet's
future environment.</p>
            <p>In a billion years' time, the heat from the Sun will become so
intense, that the oceans start to evaporate.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68489000/jpg/_68489382_om-j_yellowstone.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Yellowstone Park"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Extremophiles are found in hostile environments such
as the Geyser Basin region of Yellowstone Park</span>
            </div>
            <p>"Once you get to this tipping point, you get a lot more water in
the atmosphere and because water vapour is a greenhouse gas, that
sets this runaway greenhouse effect... and you end up with the
Earth heating up to 100C or more plus what we experience today,"
explained Mr O'Malley James, a PhD student.</p>
            <p>This, he said, combined with falling levels of oxygen, would
lead to the rapid loss of plants and larger animals.</p>
            <p>Soon after, a group of microbes called extremophiles would be
the only life forms left.</p>
            <p>These tiny organisms are found on Earth today, and can cope with
hostile environments.</p>
            <p>These, the scientists said, would be the only creatures that
could withstand the heat, aridity and poisonous atmosphere of this
future Earth. They believe that they would probably be clustered
around the last drops of water deep underground.</p>
            <p>Eventually as conditions worsen they too will vanish, and in
about 2.8 billion years, Earth will be devoid of all life.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>'Microbial worlds'</strong>
            </p>
            <p>The researchers said that studying the rise and fall of life on
our planet could give us an insight into how life might survive
elsewhere in the Universe.</p>
            <p>Mr O'Malley James told the BBC: "If you were to find an
Earth-like planet and to take a snapshot in time of the life living
on the surface, it's more likely that you would find microbial life
than you would the more complex life like we see on Earth
today."</p>
            <p>The researchers said that microbes cause subtle changes to the
ratios of gasses in the atmosphere, and this could enable
astronomers to one day detect their presence on other Earth-like
planets.</p>
            <p>"One of the best candidates is methane. This could be used to
indicate the presence of life, although it depends on how much is
produced and whether it builds up to a detectable level in the
atmosphere... If we can pick up all these subtle levels of gasses
on remote planets - maybe we could detect it," Mr O'Malley James
said.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1234809337000"
                  href="/1/hi/sci/tech/7893414.stm">Alien life 'may exist among
us'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story" rel="published-1364263484601" href="/nature/21923937">Living life to the extreme</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1218736866000"
                  href="/1/hi/sci/tech/7558448.stm">Arsenic-munching bacteria
found</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
