<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-23076324"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The European Space Agency (Esa) appoints Thales Alenia Space of Italy to build the Euclid dark energy-hunting space telescope."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T15:45:32"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68420000/jpg/_68420348_photo.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Thales takes lead on 'dark explorer'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Science and Environment"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-23076324"/>
         <title>BBC News - Euclid spacecraft to be built by Thales Alenia
Space</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">16:45</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Euclid spacecraft to be built by Thales
Alenia Space</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Jonathan
Amos</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Science correspondent, BBC
News, Toulouse</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68416000/jpg/_68416024_photo.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="304"
                 alt="Euclid concept"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Euclid will conduct its surveys 1.5 million
kilometres from Earth on its "night side"</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The European Space
Agency (Esa) has appointed Thales Alenia Space (TAS) of Italy to
lead the construction of its "dark explorer", Euclid.</p>
            <p>The organisation's Industrial Policy Committee has approved the
issuing of a contract worth 322m euros
(Â£275m).</p>
            <p>Euclid will launch in 2020 and look deep into the cosmos for
clues to the nature of dark energy and dark matter.</p>
            <p>These phenomena dominate the Universe, and yet scientists
concede they know virtually nothing about them.</p>
            <p>"Euclid will be so impressive; it will be a cosmologist's dream,
and we are making it happen step by step," Prof Alvaro Gimenez,
Esa's director of science, told BBC News.</p>
            <p>The TAS contract, which will be signed in the coming weeks,
completes the sourcing of the two major elements that make up
Euclid.</p>
            <p>A contract to build the payload module, which will hold the 1.2m
telescope and two instruments, has already been awarded to Europe's
other big space company, Astrium.</p>
            <p>Its value, some 72m euros, will come out of the global sum that
will now go to TAS as prime contractor.</p>
            <p>Thales Alenia's job will be to direct the industrial project,
constructing the spacecraft's basic structure and then integrating
all other parts.</p>
            <p>As is often the case with Esa science missions, the instruments
will be delivered direct, and paid for, by individual member
states.</p>
            <p>Euclid will make its observations using a visible-light camera
from the UK and a near-infrared camera/spectrometer from
France.</p>
            <p>The latter needs particular detectors that will be acquired from
a US specialist, Teledyne.</p>
            <p>"As you know, we will be paying for the development of the
infrared detectors but it is Nasa who will pay for the flight
models," said Prof Gimenez.</p>
            <p>By picking up this bill, in the region of 30m euros, the US
space agency is effectively buying positions in the Euclid science
consortium for 40 American researchers.</p>
            <p>Dark energy and dark matter are two of the most pressing
problems in science.</p>
            <p>Together, they <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-21866464">account
for about 95% of the energy density in the cosmos</a>, but
researchers are nowhere near a description for either.</p>
            <p>Dark energy is the name given to the "force" that appears to be
driving the Universe apart at an accelerating rate.</p>
            <p>Dark matter is the extra material that is unseen but which
astronomers know to be there because of its gravitational effects
on the matter we can observe. Galaxies, for example, could not hold
their shape were it not for the presence of some additional
"scaffolding".</p>
            <p>Euclid will try to plot dark matter's distribution by looking
for the subtle way its mass distorts the light coming from distant
galaxies. It will do this over a third of the sky.</p>
            <p>The mission will go after dark energy by mapping the
three-dimensional distribution of galaxies. The patterns in the
great voids that exist between these objects can be used as a kind
of "yardstick" to measure the expansion through time.</p>
            <p>Ground-based surveys have done this for small volumes of the
sky; Euclid however will measure the precise positions of some two
billion galaxies out to about 10 billion light-years from
Earth.</p>
            <p>And American involvement raises the prospect of an additional
method being used to study dark energy. Many US scientists have
used exploding stars, or supernovae, as the distance measure
instead of galaxies. Euclid would be well equipped to try this
approach also.</p>
            <p>"It could happen. It would be a bonus, but first we intend to
measure the galaxies to get at dark energy," Prof Gimenez told BBC
News.</p>
            <p>Euclid will launch on a Soyuz rocket and make its observations
at a position about 1.5 million km from Earth.</p>
            <p>Esa expects its total expenditure over the lifetime of the
project to be just over 600m euros.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/61001000/gif/_61001522_hist_universe464.gif"
                 width="464"
                 height="313"
                 alt="History of the Universe"/>
            </div>
            <p>
               <a href="mailto:Jonathan.Amos-INTERNET@bbc.co.uk">Jonathan.Amos-INTERNET@bbc.co.uk</a>
and follow me on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/BBCAmos">@BBCAmos</a>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1340179228617"
                  href="/news/science-environment-18503703">Telescope to probe dark
universe</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1335464053987"
                  href="/news/science-environment-17743190">UK company to build Sun
satellite</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1333151586596"
                  href="/news/science-environment-17559286">Survey gets a grip on dark
energy</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Dark energy and dark matter mysteries</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68419000/jpg/_68419738_c0049665-galaxy_cluster_collision,_x-ray_image-spl.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Galaxy cluster MACS J0025.4-1222 collision"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>Gravity acting across vast distances does not seem to explain
what astronomers see</li>
               <li>Galaxies, for example, should fly apart; some other mass must
be there holding them together</li>
               <li>Astrophysicists have thus postulated "dark matter" - invisible
to us but clearly acting on galactic scales</li>
               <li>At the greatest distances, the Universe's expansion is
accelerating</li>
               <li>Thus we have also "dark energy" which acts to drive the
expansion, in opposition to gravity</li>
               <li>The current theory holds that 68% of the Universe is dark
energy, 27% is dark matter, and just 5% the kind of matter we know
well</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/science/space/universe/questions_and_ideas/dark_matter">
BBC Universe: Dark matter</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/science/space/universe/questions_and_ideas/dark_energy">
BBC Universe: Dark energy</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
