<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-23173157"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The government's rollout of &#34;superfast&#34; broadband to rural areas is about two years behind its original schedule, the National Audit Office says."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-05T09:00:06"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68558000/jpg/_68558374__58404025_cable12234-1.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Rural broadband rollout criticised"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Technology"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-23173157"/>
         <title>BBC News - UK rural broadband rollout criticised by
auditors</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">5 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">10:00</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">UK rural broadband rollout criticised by
auditors</h1>
            <div class="has-icon-comment dna-comment-count-simple"> </div>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Leo Kelion</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Technology reporter</span>
            </span>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68579000/jpg/_68579253_68579181.jpg"
                 alt="Man with laptop in Cotswolds garden"/>
               <p class="caption">The BBC's Rory Cellan-Jones visits the
Cotswolds, which is still waiting</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The government's
rollout of "superfast" broadband to rural areas is about two years
behind its original schedule, an official audit has found.</p>
            <p>The report said only nine of 44 rural areas would reach targets
for high-speed internet by 2015, and four areas could also miss a
revised 2017 target.</p>
            <p>The National Audit Office also raised concerns that BT would be
the only firm likely to win contracts.</p>
            <p>It said the company would benefit from
Ã‚Â£1.2bn of public funds as a result.</p>
            <p>"The rural broadband project is moving forward late and without
the benefit of strong competition to protect public value," said
auditor general Amyas Morse.</p>
            <p>"For this we will have to rely on [the Department for Culture
Media and Sport's] active use of the controls it has negotiated and
strong supervision by [the regulator] Ofcom."</p>
            <p>He added the scheme was also expected to cost the taxpayer more
than first thought.</p>
            <p>In 2011, then Culture Secretary <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/government-aims-for-superfast-broadband-to-reach-90-per-cent-of-homes-and-businesses">
Jeremy Hunt announced</a> that 90% of premises in every local
authority area of the UK should have access to internet speeds
above 24 megabits per second by May 2015 and a minimum of 2Mbps for
others.</p>
            <p>To do this he pledged
Ã‚Â£530m of cash for rural broadband projects
which would become available to councils if they also provided
funds.</p>
            <p>He said this would give the country the "best superfast
broadband network in Europe".</p>
            <p>However, the scheme was hit by delays, in part because it took
longer than expected to get approval from the EU.</p>
            <p>The NAO said once officials revised their projections, they
found it was going to take 22 months longer than first envisaged
for 40 of the areas to reach the goal.</p>
            <p>Last week the Treasury revised its target, saying it now wanted
95% of UK properties to have access to superfast broadband by the
end of 2017, effectively shifting the goal until after the next
general election.</p>
            <p>The NAO warned four areas - Highlands and Islands, Cumbria,
Norfolk and Suffolk - might still miss this new deadline because
the local authorities had failed to request sufficient funds.</p>
            <p>A spokesperson for Cumbria County Council told the BBC that
since the report was compiled it had signed a contract with BT to
deliver superfast broadband to 93% of Cumbrian homes by 2015.</p>
            <p>The DCMS said that a pledge to invest an extra
Ã‚Â£250m meant it would meet the goal.</p>
            <p>However, the NAO said that past experience suggested the
"government is not strong at taking remedial action to guard
against further slippage".</p>
            <p>The revelations prompted claims that DCMS did not have a "good
enough grip" on its programme and that BT had been "cagey" about
its costs.</p>
            <p>"Opaque data and limited benchmarks for comparison means the
department has no idea if BT is being reasonable or adding in big
mark ups," said Labour MP Margaret Hodge, who is the chair of
Parliament's Public Accounts Committee.</p>
            <p>However, a spokesman for the DCMS said its efforts to deliver
value-for-money were "strong and robust".</p>
            <p>"We agree that effective enforcement of the contracts is
important and are working with local authorities to ensure this,"
he said.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68558000/jpg/_68558369_laptop.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Person on laptop"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Faster speeds let users stream higher quality video
and download documents more quickly</span>
            </div>
            <p>"As the NAO report makes clear, the project's funding model
greatly reduced the cost and financial risk to the taxpayer."</p>
            <p>BT also defended its record.</p>
            <p>"There was strong competition when prices were set at the start
of the process and that has ensured counties have benefited from
the best possible terms," it said.</p>
            <p>"Deploying fibre broadband is an expensive long-term business
and so it was no surprise that others dropped out as the going got
tough."</p>
            <p>Sixteen organisations had originally shown interest in competing
for the rural broadband projects.</p>
            <p>The NAO noted that "competition was envisaged to be a key
value-for-money safeguard".</p>
            <p>However, it said suppliers had complained the bidding process
was "difficult and complicated" and that the process favoured large
companies with secure revenue streams.</p>
            <p>By early 2013 only BT and Fujitsu were left in the running, and
in March Fujitsu dropped out after it said various factors had made
winning the work unattractive.</p>
            <p>The audit highlighted that officials only scored BT's financial
model eight out of 20 - the minimum pass rate.</p>
            <p>It said it remained unclear how much of the firm's bids covered
"contingency costs" - a safety-cushion to protect it against
unexpected charges.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68561000/jpg/_68561085_68561084.jpg"
                 alt="David Corner, from the National Audit Office"/>
               <p class="caption">David Corner, from the National Audit Office,
said the delay was due to a high number of negotiations around the
country</p>
            </div>
            <p>It also raised concern that BT said 40% of its costs would be on
staffing - a figure the NAO said was hard to verify.</p>
            <p>The report revealed that there had already been one instance
when BT had been caught overcharging for management costs by
Ã‚Â£3m.</p>
            <p>It also pointed out that BT's figures were based on the
assumption that only 20% of properties would sign up to superfast
broadband within seven years of it being enabled.</p>
            <p>The study said this was lower than the figure suggested by both
industry experts and international comparisons.</p>
            <p>A clawback rule is supposed to ensure that if uptake is higher
the firm should share the extra profits with the public.</p>
            <p>However, the NAO said government workers would have to
scrutinise hundreds of thousands of invoices to make sure this
happened, and that some councils have already said they might not
have enough resources to do this.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373014063706"
                  href="/news/technology-23194287">Rural broadband verdict - too little,
too late</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372256866343"
                  href="/news/technology-23062545">UK broadband voucher scheme
attacked</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372179379579"
                  href="/news/uk-politics-23055573">Councils 'yet to get' broadband
cash</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Superfast broadband availability</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68564000/gif/_68564894_broadband_speed_304.gif"
                 width="304"
                 height="380"
                 alt="Ofcom map of Superfast broadband availability"/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://maps.ofcom.org.uk/broadband/">See Ofcom's
detailed maps of broadband availability, speeds and
performance</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
