<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-23271125"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Changes wrought by social media and mobile gadgets look set to make life more difficult for game makers and creators."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-12T01:54:31"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68675000/jpg/_68675011_68668427.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Changing times for games makers"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Technology"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-23271125"/>
         <title>BBC News - Indie video games developers face an uncertain
future</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">12 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:54</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Indie video games developers face an
uncertain future</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Mark Ward</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Technology correspondent, BBC
News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68684000/png/_68684390_eon.png"
                 width="512"
                 height="288"
                 alt="Surgeon Simulator 2013"/>
               <span style="width:512px;">Surgeon Simulator 2013 requires players
to complete a heart transplant with inappropriate
tools</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">If you want an
object lesson in how the gaming world has changed, then the runaway
success of Surgeon Simulator 2013 is probably as good a guide as
you are going to get.</p>
            <p>Coded in just four days in January by developers from Bossa
Games as part of the 2013 Global Game Jam event, it casts the
player in the role of a surgeon who has to perform a series of
delicate surgical procedures.</p>
            <p>The game's gimmick is that the player must carry out these
procedures via simulated arms that are clumsy and hard to control.
This makes delicate movement impossible and success has more to do
with luck and blunt force than skill.</p>
            <p>The demo of the game was uploaded to the
Game Jam site and proved a big hit. Not only did people want to
play it, they took videos of themselves playing and shared them
online.</p>
            <p>In only a few days the videos had racked up millions of views
and the hilarity of the demo was being talked about everywhere
online.</p>
            <p>"All of a sudden this thing went out of control and we knew we
had to move fast," said Henrique Olifiers, co-founder of Bossa
during a presentation about Surgeon Simulator at the Develop
conference in Brighton. The conference brings together the UK's
games makers to talk about how their industry is changing.</p>
            <p>For Bossa, moving fast meant pledging to produce an entire
Surgeon Simulator game in 48 days and then working very hard on
social media to maintain interest in what was supposed to be a
spare-time project.</p>
            <p>That led to "six figure sales" when the full game emerged and
gave Bossa its biggest hit to date.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68679000/jpg/_68679121_68679120.jpg"
                 alt="Brighton Develop"/>
               <p class="caption">WATCH: Delegates give their views on the rise of
mobile gaming</p>
            </div>
            <p>What is significant about the Surgeon Simulator story is the way
that success came about.</p>
            <p>"It used to be about who shouted the loudest," said Lee
Schuneman, head of Microsoft's Lift London studio. The title with
the biggest marketing spend tended to get the biggest audience.</p>
            <p>But not any more.</p>
            <p>"Now it's about conversations between developers and players
and, more importantly, between the players themselves," he
said.</p>
            <p>"The initial success of a game is down to how it is received by
players and how that audience is cared for once it has
launched."</p>
            <p>Alongside the rise of social media and the growing chatter among
gamers about what they play have come structural changes in where
and on what people play games.</p>
            <p>While blockbuster "AAA" titles are still being made, increasing
numbers of people are playing games on mobile devices such as
phones, tablets and portable game gadgets.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68680000/jpg/_68680607_ecb777cb-f727-433f-9d0a-0b1936029d62.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="228"
                 alt="Screengrab of Slamjet Stadium"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Games played on portable gadgets are
becoming more popular</span>
            </div>
            <p>The relatively limited capabilities of those devices has led to
a huge rise in casual games written by independent developers, be
they gathered in small studios or working alone.</p>
            <p>"The bigger studios are breaking up and there are definitely
more indie and smaller studios around now," said Will Freeman,
editor of Develop magazine which writes about the UK game developer
scene.</p>
            <p>"Those smaller studios are great for the creative output of the
industry," he said, adding that they tended to take more risks than
the larger studios which had become more conservative as the
budgets required to make top flight titles grew and grew.</p>
            <p>However, he said, that did not mean that indie developers had it
easy. In a hit-driven industry, said Mr Freeman, many of them had
struggled to prosper because it was hard for them to get noticed
and sell enough copies to pay the rent.</p>
            <p>Solo game maker Alistair Aitcheson solved some of those problems
by moving in with his parents and using their home as his
development HQ. That left him more time to worry about how to get
his two titles, Greedy Bankers and Slamjet Stadium, noticed and
into the hands of gamers.</p>
            <p>"There was a lovely period on the iPhone when it was easier to
get exposure," he said. "But that's gone now because there are so
many titles out there it's hard to get spotted."</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68680000/jpg/_68680605_kungfu.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="304"
                 alt="Kung Fu Superstar Kickstarter page"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Kickstarter can be a frustrating place to try to
raise funds</span>
            </div>
            <p>Good reviews, networking on social media and hard work to get a
game in front of potential players can help, said Mr Aitcheson, but
there was no doubt that it remained the toughest problem any indie
developer had to tackle.</p>
            <p>The experience of Kostas Zarifis showed just how tough it can
be. Mr Zarifis gave up a good job at the high profile Lionhead
Studios to go it alone and bring to fruition a personal project
called Kung Fu Superstar.</p>
            <p>The game put the player in the position of a martial artist who
used real Kung Fu moves to defeat foes in the game world.</p>
            <p>A video of what it might look like was a big hit on YouTube and
won thousands of "likes" on Facebook. That success led to a
Kickstarter campaign that aimed to raise
Ã‚Â£200,000 to produce a prototype. Sadly, the
project was not fully funded.</p>
            <p>"We got about half of what we asked for, which was nice, but we
needed all of it to get anything," he said. "Liking something on
Facebook is not the same as pledging money."</p>
            <p>Despite this, he said, he has no regrets about going it
alone.</p>
            <p>"I stuck to my guns and it paid off in the end," he said. "I do
not think there's any scenario where you do this kind of thing and
work on something you really believe in that does not pay off in
the end."</p>
            <p>Mr Zarifis is now doing gaming work on other titles while he
looks for ways to get Kung Fu Superstar funded and made.</p>
            <p>"I set out to challenge my limits," he said, " and the challenge
has not broken me yet."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373411579110"
                  href="/news/technology-23240971">App Store 'dominated by
zombies'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370560333533"
                  href="/news/technology-22807205">Virtual reality treadmill gets
cash</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1369639430726"
                  href="/news/technology-22657667">Gamestick console set for launch
<span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">There are so many titles out there it's hard
to get spotted”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Alistair Aitcheson</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Video games developer</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
