<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-23137754"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Live streaming of child sex abuse via webcams is an emerging threat, experts warn, as they say the number of indecent images reported has doubled in a year."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T10:44:40"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68496000/jpg/_68496667_018482227.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Children 'abused to order' warning"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="UK"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-23137754"/>
         <title>BBC News - Live streaming of child sex abuse an 'emerging
threat'</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">11:44</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Live streaming of child sex abuse an
'emerging threat'</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68493000/jpg/_68493830_68493829.jpg"
                 alt="Peter Davies, Ceop"/>
               <p class="caption">Peter Davies, Ceop, says online offending is
just as harmful as physical sexual abuse and has led to children
attempting suicide</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Live streaming of
child sex abuse via webcams is an emerging threat, experts have
warned, amid a doubling of reported indecent images.</p>
            <p>The Child Exploitation and Online Protection Centre said
children were being "abused to order".</p>
            <p>Offenders targeted vulnerable families overseas, paying them to
facilitate child abuse, according to its report.</p>
            <p>Ceop said those carrying out abuse used a "hidden internet" to
disguise their identity and avoid detection.</p>
            <p>
               <a href="http://ceop.police.uk/Documents/ceopdocs/CEOP_TACSEA2013_240613%20FINAL.pdf">
The report found</a> the number of still and moving child abuse
images reported to Ceop had doubled in the last year to 70,000 -
although this includes a "substantial" number of duplicated
images.</p>
            <p>The child protection body - part of Home Office's Serious
Organised Crime Agency - said it received 8,000 reports of indecent
images of children being shared last year.</p>
            <p>It said live streaming emerged in 2012 as a means of producing
and distributing images.</p>
            <p>"We're seeing cases where they're effectively being abused to
order for paying customers," chief executive Peter Davies told the
BBC.</p>
            <p>He said some of those exploiting children via the internet were
in the UK, adding: "At every level an absolutely appalling kind of
crime."</p>
            <p>Children were forced to engage in sexual activity on live
webcams in exchange for payment to the family or organised crime
gangs, according to Ceop's annual threat assessment of child
exploitation and abuse .</p>
            <p>Online video services such as Skype were identified as among
those being exploited to transmit live images of abuse.</p>
            <p>Ceop said many abusers were hiding their
actions deep in the "hidden internet" by using <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-22754061">encrypted networks
and other secure methods</a> to distribute images. These methods
made it harder for law enforcement agencies to trace abusers.</p>
            <p>"The use of the hidden internet in the UK and beyond is expected
to continue increasing throughout 2013, possibly reaching 20,000
daily UK users by the end of the year," said the report.</p>
            <p>"Ceop assesses that the networking and sense of 'safe' community
that occurs within the hidden internet and the relative
sophistication of offenders within that environment stimulates the
production of [indecent images of children] on both a commercial
and non-commercial basis."</p>
            <p>An NSPCC spokeswoman said evidence from police in England and
Wales indicated there were 20,000 sexual offences against children
every year.</p>
            <p>"However, we believe this is far from the true situation as many
cases are never revealed," said the spokesman.</p>
            <p>Independent charity Victim Support, meanwhile, said the police
service must "ask itself some searching questions".</p>
            <p>"Its first priority is to prevent and detect crime," chief
executive Javed Khan said.</p>
            <p>There were "inconsistencies in the way forces collect, record
and categorise child sex abuse offences", he added.</p>
            <p>"It is essential that every dot is joined up if the most
vulnerable in our society are to be protected.</p>
            <p>"Every police force must therefore
contribute fully and consistently to the national intelligence
picture - only then will we have a true picture of the scale of the
problem."</p>
            <p>Policing and Criminal Justice Minister Damian Green said: "These
figures are deeply troubling and show how our understanding of
child sexual exploitation has greatly improved in recent years.</p>
            <p>"But more needs to be done. Ceop is doing excellent work and we
will see its capability strengthened when it is transferred to the
National Crime Agency later this year.</p>
            <p>"I am leading a new Home Office group which is urgently looking
at how we better identify those at risk."</p>
            <p>An estimated 50,000 UK web users are involved in distributing
abuse images.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371683629379"
                  href="/news/technology-22754061">Do dark networks aid
criminals?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370507581691"
                  href="/news/technology-22794498">Government demands action on web
safety</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370748025234"
                  href="/news/uk-22831219">PM wants web 'action' on child porn</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>What is the hidden internet?</h2>
            <p>When information moves online, each computer's individual IP
address is widely logged, potentially giving police a start in any
investigation.</p>
            <p>But some in the industry say tech-savvy paedophiles have turned
to networks specifically designed to conceal the identity and
location of their users.</p>
            <p>Using a variety of technological tricks, so-called "dark nets" -
Tor, I2P, Freenet and many others - hide the giveaway identifiers
while allowing people to go on using the web.</p>
            <p>Drugs, guns and credit card skimmers are openly on sale on these
networks.</p>
            <p>They are places where paedophiles, criminal hackers and
professional thieves advertise their services.</p>
            <p>However some see the hidden web as a force for good because it
is used to avoid detection in many places where political protests
are harshly suppressed.</p>
            <p>
               <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-22754061">Do dark
networks aid cyberthieves and abusers?</a>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">It is essential that every dot is joined up
if the most vulnerable in our society are to be
protected”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Javed Khan</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Victim Support</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
