<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-23099582"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Moors Murderer Ian Brady loses his legal bid to be transferred from a hospital back to prison as a tribunal rules he needs continuing medical care for chronic mental illness."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T12:56:37"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68436000/jpg/_68436352_sketch_brady_pa.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Ian Brady told to stay in hospital"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="UK"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-23099582"/>
         <title>BBC News - Moors Murderer Ian Brady loses prison move
bid</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">13:56</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Moors Murderer Ian Brady loses prison move
bid</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68365000/jpg/_68365693_quenzler.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Court artist sketch of Ian Brady. By Julia Quenzler"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Ian Brady gave evidence at the
tribunal</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Moors Murderer Ian
Brady has lost his legal bid to be transferred from a psychiatric
hospital back to prison.</p>
            <p>He wanted a tribunal to approve a move to a Scottish prison, but
Ashworth Hospital said he had chronic mental illness and needed
continued care at the Merseyside top-security facility.</p>
            <p>Brady, now 75, and Myra Hindley, who died in prison in 2002,
tortured and murdered five children.</p>
            <p>He was jailed for three murders in 1966 and has been at Ashworth
since 1985.</p>
            <p>He and Hindley later confessed to another two murders.</p>
            <p>Judge Robert Atherton, who headed the three-person mental health
tribunal at Ashworth, said: "The tribunal has concluded that Mr Ian
Stewart Brady continues to suffer from a mental disorder which is
of a nature and degree which makes it appropriate for him to
continue to receive medical treatment, and that it is necessary for
his health and safety and for the protection of other persons that
he should receive such treatment in hospital, and that appropriate
medical treatment is available for him."</p>
            <p>The reasons for the tribunal's decision will be released
later.</p>
            <p>Brady, whose legal costs are estimated to
be around Â£250,000 and paid by the
taxpayer, as he gets legal aid, has the right to challenge the
decision.</p>
            <p>Dr David Fearnley, medical director at Ashworth, said: "We
appreciate the time and effort the mental health tribunal has given
to this case and its judgment is consistent with the expert
opinions of our clinicians.</p>
            <p>"Mr Brady suffers from a severe personality disorder and a
mental illness which still require high-quality care.</p>
            <p>"It is a testament to the staff of Ashworth Hospital that we
have been able to stabilise his schizophrenia to the degree we
have. However, his condition is chronic and will require this
support for the foreseeable future."</p>
            <p>Asked if the tribunal, which was held in public at Brady's
request, may have exacerbated the illness, Dr Fearnley said: "I
think the difficulty with an individual such as Ian Brady is that
he has a complex mental disorder and for many years has been able
to publicise his concerns.</p>
            <p>"However, we see this as part of an overall problem which our
experts are looking into and will continue to provide expert
care."</p>
            <p>Brady has been on a hunger strike since 1999, and appeared at
the tribunal with his feeding tube in place. The tribunal heard
that he also eats some food on "most days".</p>
            <p>Dr Fearnley said his treatment was under review by the
specialist team, including the issue of feeding.</p>
            <p>Brady and Hindley's crimes of sexual abuse, torture and murder
of children shocked the nation.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68431000/jpg/_68431556_68431555.jpg"
                 alt="Dr David Fearnley"/>
               <p class="caption">Dr David Fearnley: Ian Brady is "in the right
place to receive the right treatment by the right people"</p>
            </div>
            <p>Lesley Ann Downey, 10, John Kilbride, 12, Keith Bennett, 12, and
Pauline Reade, 16, were all sexually assaulted before their deaths
at the hands of the couple.</p>
            <p>Their bodies were buried on Saddleworth Moor, near Manchester,
although Keith Bennett's body was never found.</p>
            <p>Their final victim, Edward Evans, 17, was murdered in front of
Hindley's 17-year-old brother-in-law, who alerted the police.</p>
            <p>Keith's mother, Winnie Johnson, made repeated calls for Brady to
reveal the location of his grave. She died last year, aged 78,
without knowing where her son's remains are.</p>
            <p>Her solicitor John Ainley said he thought she would have been
"satisfied" by the tribunal's decision.</p>
            <p>"She always felt that Ian Brady did not give the children any
choice and consequently he should not have the choice to leave the
hospital environment."</p>
            <p>Terry Kilbride, the brother of John, said Brady should stay in
hospital.</p>
            <p>"I don't believe he's going to kill himself, that's just a ploy,
just another wind-up.</p>
            <p>"I think to be honest he should go back to hospital, I think
that's where he belongs, in the hospital, and keep him alive as
long as possible because it's only him that knows where Keith
Bennett is."</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68448000/jpg/_68448081_de01.jpg"
                 alt="Alan West, stepfather of Lesley Ann Downey"/>
               <p class="caption">Stepfather of Lesley Ann Downey, Alan West, says
the tribunal was well worth it</p>
            </div>
            <p>Brady gave evidence for more than four hours at the tribunal,
which sat at Ashworth psychiatric hospital in Maghull. It was the
first time he had spoken in public for 47 years.</p>
            <p>Brady had told the tribunal he used "method acting" to trick
doctors into classing him as insane so he could be transferred from
prison to hospital.</p>
            <p>But he said he now wanted to leave Ashworth because he hated it
and "the regime has changed to a penal warehouse".</p>
            <p>The tribunal heard from Brady's lawyer that Brady had a severe
personality disorder but was not mentally ill and could be treated
in prison rather than hospital.</p>
            <p>During his evidence, Brady refused to answer a question from his
own lawyer about whether he intended to take his own life if he was
declared fit to return to prison.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372198230555"
                  href="/news/uk-23057892">Witnessing Brady's tribunal evidence</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1341324167380"
                  href="/news/uk-18690303">Profile: Ian Brady</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372326541927"
                  href="/news/magazine-23063124">How easy is it to fake mental
illness?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <div class="correspondent-byline">
               <a href="/news/correspondents/dominiccasciani/">
                  <span class="byline-picture">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/55243000/jpg/_55243840_casciani-112x81-white.jpg"
                       alt="image of Dominic Casciani"/>
                  </span>
               </a>
               <span class="byline-heading">Analysis</span>
               <a href="/news/correspondents/dominiccasciani/">
                  <span class="byline-name">Dominic Casciani</span>
               </a>
               <span class="byline-title">Home affairs correspondent</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>Ashworth Hospital argued that Brady was after "a win" over the
authorities. This decision, which denies him that victory, comes
down to the very narrow legal remit that had to be fulfilled by his
mental health tribunal.</p>
            <p>The panel had one simple duty: to assess the patient's health
and what would be clinically right for him.</p>
            <p>So although we have not yet seen the full reasons, the
tribunal's decision means it has decided that Brady is still
suffering from paranoid schizophrenia or another treatable
disorder.</p>
            <p>Once it had come to that conclusion, it could further rule that
it would be appropriate to keep Brady at Ashworth, either to
receive treatment or because it would be necessary for his own
safety or those of others.</p>
            <p>It's going to be very difficult for him to challenge the
decision because he can only launch an appeal if he can show that
the tribunal got the law wrong.</p>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/correspondents/dominiccasciani/">Read more from
Dominic</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
