<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-23213740"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Radical cleric Abu Qatada is held in a high security jail near the Jordanian capital Amman, after being deported from the UK."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-07T20:21:35"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68595000/jpg/_68595101_68595096.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Abu Qatada deported from Britain"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="UK"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-23213740"/>
         <title>BBC News - Abu Qatada deported from UK to stand trial in
Jordan</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">7 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">21:21</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Abu Qatada deported from UK to stand trial
in Jordan</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68597000/jpg/_68597941_68590113.jpg"
                 alt="Abu Qatada arrives in Jordan from UK"/>
               <p class="caption">The BBC's Yolande Knell in Amman: "He was rushed
very quickly to the state security court"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Radical cleric Abu
Qatada is being held in a high security jail near the Jordanian
capital Amman, after being deported from the UK.</p>
            <p>His plane left RAF Northolt at 02:46 BST for his home country,
where he appeared in court to be charged with terror offences,
which he denies.</p>
            <p>Prime Minister David Cameron said he was "delighted" at his
removal.</p>
            <p>Abu Qatada was first arrested in the UK over alleged terror
connections in 2001 and has fought deportation since 2005.</p>
            <p>The Palestinian-Jordanian cleric's deportation was finally able
to proceed after the UK and Jordan signed a treaty agreeing that
evidence obtained through torture would not be used against
him.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68590000/jpg/_68590114_68590113.jpg"
                 alt="Radical cleric Abu Qatada looks out the window of the plane"/>
               <p class="caption">The BBC's Dominic Casciani describes the scene
at RAF Northolt as the flight takes off</p>
            </div>
            <p>Home Secretary Theresa May said she was glad that the
government's determination to remove him had been "vindicated".</p>
            <p>"This dangerous man has now been removed from our shores to face
the courts in his own country," she said.</p>
            <p>She added that she wanted to streamline such deportation
processes in future.</p>
            <p>"I am also clear that we need to make sense of our human rights
laws and remove the many layers of appeals available to foreign
nationals we want to deport.</p>
            <p>"We are taking steps - including through the new Immigration
Bill - to put this right."</p>
            <p>Changes to the bill would affect cases like Abu Qatada's, she
said, and also cases in which people facing deportation claim they
have a right to respect for their private and family life in the
UK, as set out in article eight of the European Convention on Human
Rights.</p>
            <p>Mrs May said she hoped to reform the convention, and would not
rule out the possibility of the UK withdrawing from it
altogether.</p>
            <p>"Nothing is off the table," she said.</p>
            <p>"We're working on that at the moment," the home secretary told
the BBC, adding that the Conservative manifesto for the 2015
general election would "set out clearly what we would do in
relation to these issues".</p>
            <p>Abu Qatada was accompanied on the flight of around five hours by
six people from Jordan, comprising three security officials, a
psychologist, a medical examiner and his Jordanian lawyer, the BBC
understands.</p>
            <p>The 53-year-old had been held at Belmarsh
prison in south-east London, from where a convoy of three police
vehicles left at midnight.</p>
            <p>After arriving at Jordan's Marka military airport he was driven
in a green SUV, escorted by a 12-car convoy, to the sealed off
state security court in Amman.</p>
            <p>Military prosecutors charged him with conspiracy to carry out
terrorist acts - relating to a plot to bomb American and Israeli
tourists during Jordan's millennium celebrations.</p>
            <p>The cleric was remanded in custody for 15 days and taken to
eastern Jordan's Muwaqqar prison, a judicial official said.</p>
            <p>After the hearing his lawyer Tayseer Diab said: "The attorney
general interrogated him today, and he directed a series of
accusations towards him - he accused him of conspiracy to take part
in terrorist acts.</p>
            <p>"My client denied all the allegations, and he asserts that his
return to Jordan was out of his own free will, in order to be with
his family. The procedure was carried out well, and he received
good treatment."</p>
            <p>Speaking outside the court, Abu Qatada's father Mahmoud said:
"His spirits are high and the officials are good people - they
might allow him to obtain bail after a few days."</p>
            <p>BBC home affairs correspondent Dominic Casciani said Home Office
officials were "incredibly relieved" after "one of the most tense
weeks in the department's recent history".</p>
            <p>"They were so concerned about the possibility that the cleric
could change his mind at the last minute that they were leaving
nothing to chance."</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68591000/jpg/_68591707_68591706.jpg"
                 alt="Home Secretary Theresa May"/>
               <p class="caption">Home Secretary Theresa May: "I was deeply
frustrated how long it took"</p>
            </div>
            <p>Speaking on BBC Breakfast, Mrs May said she had been provided
with updates on the deportation throughout the night.</p>
            <p>She said she had been "as frustrated as the public" about the
estimated Â£1.7m cost and length of time it
had taken to remove Abu Qatada, but that people would welcome the
end result.</p>
            <p>She said she did not have any concerns about the treatment of
Abu Qatada in Jordan.</p>
            <p>She said: "The treaty we've signed ensures that there are proper
processes of exchange of evidence and will insure the treatment of
Abu Qatada and others deported to Jordan."</p>
            <p>Asked on Sky News whether Abu Qatada's wife and children would
have the right to stay in the UK, Mrs May said they would have to
decide what they want their future to be before the government gets
involved.</p>
            <p>Mr Cameron criticised a "caravan of lawyers" over the case,
adding that it had "made my blood boil that this man who has no
right to be in our country, who is a threat to our country and that
it took so long and it was so difficult to deport him, but we've
done it, he is back in Jordan that is excellent news."</p>
            <p>Abu Qatada, whose real name is Omar Othman, was granted asylum
in the UK in 1994 but the Security Service came to view him as a
threat as his views hardened.</p>
            <p>Richard Reid, the would-be mid-Atlantic
shoe bomber, and Zacarias Moussaoui, both jailed for involvement in
terrorism, are said to have sought religious advice from him.</p>
            <p>The cleric's sermons were also found in a flat in the German
city of Hamburg used by some of those involved in 9/11.</p>
            <p>He vowed to fight the UK's 2005 decision to deport him to Jordan
to face retrial over bomb plot allegations - setting in motion an
eight-year legal battle.</p>
            <p>The dispute continued until May this year, when the cleric
accepted that his right to a fair trial there was protected by the
new treaty between Jordan and the UK.</p>
            <p>Labour's shadow home secretary Yvette Cooper welcomed the
deportation and backed Mrs May's call for a more streamlined
process in future.</p>
            <p>She said: "The home secretary has been right to get further
guarantees from Jordan and we should welcome the series of
agreements from the Jordanian government too.</p>
            <p>"We must ensure that delays like this do not last for so long in
future and that the system is reformed to make it faster."</p>
            <p>Keith Vaz, chairman of Parliament's Home Affairs Select
Committee, questioned why the government had not started work on a
treaty with Jordan at an earlier stage in the process.</p>
            <p>"The home secretary's legal advisers will have questions to
answer as to why they didn't conceive of this scheme earlier which
would have prevented a cost to the taxpayer of
Â£1.7m."</p>
            <p>
               <a href="/news/uk-16584923">Profile: Abu Qatada</a>
            </p>
            <p>
               <a href="/news/uk-23197677">The security problem Jordan
doesnât need?</a>
            </p>
            <p>
               <a href="/news/uk-22909465">Abu Qatada case has cost UK
Â£1.7m</a>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373172336030"
                  href="/news/uk-23215592">As it happened: Abu Qatada deported</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1326787641373"
                  href="/news/uk-16584923">Profile: Abu Qatada</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371551425628"
                  href="/news/uk-22953531">Abu Qatada treaty endorsed by King</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/63416000/jpg/_63416834_yolande.jpg"
                    alt="image of Yolande Knell"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Yolande Knell</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
News, Amman</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>There was tight security as Abu Qatada arrived back in Jordan -
where he grew up - for the first time in more than 20 years. He was
immediately driven from Marka airbase to the state security court -
a journey that would have taken just a few minutes.</p>
            <p>While the cleric has become a household name in the UK, when I
did an informal survey in Amman remarkably few people had heard of
him. Some people who had thought he should not have been sent back
here.</p>
            <p>"I'm a Muslim but I don't like extremists. I wish he hadn't
come," an old man said. "Why should the UK export its problems to
us? He was resident in London for so many years, you should have
tried him if he's guilty of anything," added another.</p>
            <p>One woman believed Abu Qatada was misunderstood. She told me the
preacher was "very good for Islam" and that "his followers will be
very glad for him to be back."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/50693000/jpg/_50693810_ross.jpg"
                    alt="image of Ross Hawkins"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Ross Hawkins</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Political correspondent</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>In deporting Abu Qatada, Theresa May has succeeded where many
other home secretaries failed - and she is trying to press home the
advantage.</p>
            <p>The government intends to change the law to ensure fewer
deportation appeals. But Conservatives want to go further and alter
the UK's relationship with the European Court of Human Rights.</p>
            <p>They cannot do that in government because the Liberal Democrats
would stop them. So they are promising the policy - the details of
which are yet to be announced - for their manifesto.</p>
            <p>And Theresa May, who many Tories suspect fancies herself as a
future party leader, is likely to be one of its more prominent
champions.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
