<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-23230419"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The European Court of Human Rights is due to rule on whether murderer Jeremy Bamber and two other killers should have their life sentences reviewed."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-09T06:49:22"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68611000/jpg/_68611167_jeremynov10.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Court to rule on Bamber life term"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="UK"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-23230419"/>
         <title>BBC News - European Court to rule on Jeremy Bamber life
term</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">9 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">07:49</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">European Court to rule on Jeremy Bamber
life term</h1>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/51203000/jpg/_51203512_jeremynov10.jpg"
                 width="224"
                 height="224"
                 alt="Jeremy Bamber, photographed in 2010. Copyright: Andrew Hunter - Jeremy Bamber Campaign "/>
               <span style="width:224px;">Jeremy Bamber's appeal is being heard
with that of two other men</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The European Court
of Human Rights is due to rule on whether murderer Jeremy Bamber
and two other killers should have their life sentences
reviewed.</p>
            <p>Bamber, along with serial killer Peter Moore and Douglas Vinter,
argue that the whole life tariff is "inhuman".</p>
            <p>The court has previously ruled that such sentences do not
violate a prisoner's human rights, but the matter was referred to
its grand chamber for the final say.</p>
            <p>The ruling is expected at 09:30 BST.</p>
            <p>The three men are among a group of 49 people in England and
Wales who are serving whole life tariffs.</p>
            <p>This means they cannot be released other than at the discretion
of the justice secretary on compassionate grounds - for example, if
they are terminally ill or seriously incapacitated.</p>
            <p>They claim that being denied any prospect of release amounts to
"inhuman and degrading" treatment and this is a violation of
Article 3 of the European Convention on Human Rights.</p>
            <p>They say they should be entitled to have their tariffs
reviewed.</p>
            <p>The case was referred to the grand
chamber after the men narrowly lost their first European Court
hearing in 2012: three of the seven judges ruled in their
favour.</p>
            <p>The court's first ruling concluded that the men's sentences were
not "grossly disproportionate".</p>
            <p>Bamber was jailed for murdering five members of his family in
Essex in 1985.</p>
            <p>He has always protested his innocence and claims his
schizophrenic sister Sheila Caffell shot her family before turning
the gun on herself.</p>
            <p>Moore killed four gay men for his sexual gratification in north
Wales in 1995.</p>
            <p>In 2008, Vinter, from Middlesbrough, admitted killing his wife
Anne White. He had been released from prison in 2005 after serving
nine years for murdering a colleague.</p>
            <p>Last year, the Court of Appeal in London upheld the principle of
whole life sentences for the most dangerous of offenders, saying it
did not breach human rights.</p>
            <p>At the time, the Lord Chief Justice said jail without the
possibility of release should be "reserved for the few
exceptionally serious offences".</p>
            <p>He said judges must be convinced those sentenced to whole life
need to be held forever for punishment and retribution.</p>
            <p>Eric Allison, a former prisoner and the Guardian's prison
correspondent, told BBC Radio 5 live that the UK did not have the
death penalty and the prison system was about rehabilitation and
reform.</p>
            <p>He said whole life tariffs were about "pure punishment and pure
revenge and we are better than that".</p>
            <p>"We are human beings and we are capable of change. I spent time
in prison. I did not kill anybody but I have seen people who did
kill turn their lives around and that's the aim of the system. That
should apply to all prisoners."</p>
            <p>Rape victim Helen Stockford's attacker was a convicted murder
and she has been campaigning to ensure he now stays in prison for
life. She says some criminals do not deserve a second chance.</p>
            <p>"They are given chances after chances, and it seems they cannot
live in society normally," she told BBC Radio 5 live.</p>
            <p>"I feel I am doing the life sentence, not him," she said.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1354064527079"
                  href="/news/uk-20520372">Bamber appeals against life term</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1353508722272"
                  href="/news/uk-20433191">Whole life prison terms upheld</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>What is a whole life tariff?</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Offenders who receive a whole life tariff cannot be released
other than at the discretion of the justice secretary on
compassionate grounds - for example, if they are terminally ill or
seriously incapacitated</li>
               <li>They are not eligible for a parole review or release</li>
               <li>However, prisoners can have their sentence reduced on
appeal</li>
               <li>The sentence is reserved for offenders judged to be the most
dangerous to society</li>
               <li>49 people are currently serving whole life tariffs</li>
               <li>These include the Yorkshire Ripper Peter Sutcliffe and Moors
Murderer Ian Brady</li>
               <li>Serial killer Rosemary West is the only women currently serving
a whole life sentence</li>
               <li>The most recent murderers to receive the sentence are Mark
Bridger, who killed five-year-old April Jones, and Dale Cregan who
murdered two police officers</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
