<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-23179230"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Scotland Yard says it has &#34;new evidence and new witnesses&#34; in the Madeleine McCann case as it opens a formal investigation into her disappearance."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T17:09:29"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68546000/jpg/_68546083_hi003991608.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="UK police pursue new Madeleine leads"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="UK"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-23179230"/>
         <title>BBC News - Madeleine McCann: New leads spark Met formal
inquiry</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">18:09</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Madeleine McCann: New leads spark Met
formal inquiry</h1>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68191000/jpg/_68191797__59848778_014594406-1.jpg"
                 width="224"
                 height="299"
                 alt="Madeleine McCann"/>
               <span style="width:224px;">Madeleine was almost four years old when she
disappeared</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Scotland Yard says
it has "new evidence and new witnesses" in the Madeleine McCann
case and has opened a formal investigation into her
disappearance.</p>
            <p>The Met Police said it still believed there was a chance
Madeleine was alive and it was investigating 38 "persons of
interest" after reviewing the evidence.</p>
            <p>Madeleine's parents, Gerry and Kate McCann, said the shift from
review to investigation was "a big step forward".</p>
            <p>Madeleine was almost four when she disappeared in Portugal in
May 2007.</p>
            <p>She went missing from her family's holiday flat in the Algarve
resort of Praia da Luz, as her parents dined out with friends at a
nearby restaurant.</p>
            <p>Portuguese authorities dropped their investigation into her
disappearance in 2008, but Scotland Yard started a review in May
2011, after Prime Minister David Cameron had responded to a plea
from the McCanns, of Rothley, Leicestershire.</p>
            <p>Det Ch Insp Andy Redwood, who is heading what has been called
Operation Grange, said: "The review has given us new thinking, new
theories, new evidence and new witnesses."</p>
            <p>His 37-strong police team is two-thirds
of the way through examining 30,500 documents from files held by
the Portuguese, private investigators and British police. Some
fresh interviews have also taken place.</p>
            <p>"Over the last two years what the review has told me is that
there is no clear, definitive proof that Madeleine McCann is dead,"
Det Ch Insp Redwood said.</p>
            <p>"So on that basis, I still genuinely believe that there is a
possibility that she is alive."</p>
            <p>He added: "It is a positive step in our hunt for Madeleine that
our understanding of the evidence has enabled us to shift from
review to investigation."</p>
            <p>Scotland Yard's decision to formally open its own investigation
- which, like the review, will be funded by the Home Office -
follows extensive discussions with UK prosecutors and the
Portuguese.</p>
            <p>BBC home affairs correspondent Danny Shaw said: "It's highly
unusual - although not unprecedented - for a British police force
to launch its own inquiry into an incident abroad."</p>
            <p>In a statement, the McCanns said: "Kate and Gerry warmly welcome
the shift in the Met's emphasis from review to investigation.</p>
            <p>"It is clearly a big step forward in establishing what happened
and, hopefully, towards bringing whoever is responsible for
Madeleine's abduction to justice."</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68545000/jpg/_68545453_68545452.jpg"
                 alt="Detective Chief Inspector Andy Redwood"/>
               <p class="caption">Det Ch Insp Andy Redwood: "There is no clear,
definitive proof that Madeleine McCann is dead"</p>
            </div>
            <p>The Met said the 38 "persons of interest," who include 12
British nationals, are from five European countries - Portugal, the
UK and three unnamed others.</p>
            <p>Detectives say they need to find out more information and
collect evidence on them and are not anticipating any immediate
arrests.</p>
            <p>The 12 UK nationals, who are not all currently in the UK, are
believed to have been in Portugal at the time of Madeleine's
disappearance.</p>
            <p>The Met said it was "at an advanced stage of dialogue" with the
other countries involved, and enquiries would be continuing with
their assistance in the months ahead "to establish more information
about the individuals concerned and any potential involvement".</p>
            <p>A foreign national resident abroad could not be prosecuted in
the UK for any possible crime that may be linked to Madeleine's
disappearance.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/59847000/jpg/_59847328_newimage_bbc.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Madeleine McCann when she disappeared and how she might have looked aged nine"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The Metropolitan Police issued a
computer-generated image (r) of how Madeleine might have looked
aged nine</span>
            </div>
            <p>Detectives say Madeleine's parents, the friends the McCanns were
with in Portugal and people known to the family before they went
away are not suspects or people they need to investigate.</p>
            <p>The investigation is currently closed in Portugal and as part of
the country's criminal justice system it cannot be reopened unless
judges are convinced there are solid grounds to do so.</p>
            <p>British police have formally asked the Crown Prosecution Service
to submit an international letter of request to Portuguese
authorities for assistance in obtaining evidence relating to their
inquiries.</p>
            <p>The Met has asked for a small number of its officers to be
present in Portugal for the inquiries there.</p>
            <p>As part of the review, a computer-generated image of how
Madeleine might have looked at the age of nine was created with the
help of her family. They marked her 10th birthday on 12 May.</p>
            <p>By May 2012 - one year into the review - the Home Office's costs
had reached Â£1.9m. The Met Police said a
more up-to-date figure for the cost of the review would be released
in due course.</p>
            <p>The former head of the National Police Improvement Agency Peter
Neyroud said it was a difficult investigation because it involved
two countries, possibly more.</p>
            <p>"It was always going to be an expensive inquiry and it is a fine
judgement as to how far you go on but if, as appears, there are
fresh lines of inquiry and a case worth pursuing, there is a young
lady out there who deserves to be reunited with her parents - or a
murder case that deserves to be pursued."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1305280591931"
                  href="/news/uk-13386785">Madeleine McCann inquiry timeline</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1335350249885"
                  href="/news/uk-17838052">'Madeleine at nine' image created</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1331995869526"
                  href="/news/uk-england-leicestershire-17414919">McCanns call review
'huge step'</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/48372000/jpg/_48372269_000105904-1.jpg"
                    alt="image of Danny Shaw"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Danny
Shaw</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Home affairs correspondent,
BBC News</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>A team of Scotland Yard's best detectives, assisted by police
overseas, in an inquiry paid for by the Home Office, offers the
best opportunity to find out what happened to Madeleine McCann. It
may also be the last chance to do so.</p>
            <p>Although the Yard can not put right mistakes made during the
initial inquiry, when the Portuguese were accused of failing to
seal off the area where Madeleine had been staying and gather all
available forensic evidence, the new team has had access to all the
files.</p>
            <p>That has enabled detectives with no prior involvement to look at
the case objectively and form fresh views about what may have
happened to Madeleine. There is a real determination among officers
to solve the mystery - and a quiet optimism that it may be
possible.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
