<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-23132091"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="BSkyB is cleared of breaching the broadcasting code after a reporter on its Sky News channel hacked into the emails of fraudsters John and Anne Darwin."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T17:58:18"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68488000/jpg/_68488142_darwin_pa.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="BSkyB cleared over canoe case hack"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="UK"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-23132091"/>
         <title>BBC News - Ofcom clears BSkyB over canoe case email
hacking</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">18:58</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Ofcom clears BSkyB over canoe case email
hacking</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68486000/jpg/_68486534_darwin_pa.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Anne Darwin, John Darwin"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The Darwins were jailed for fraud in
2008</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">BSkyB has been
cleared of breaching the broadcasting code after a reporter on Sky
News hacked into the emails of fraudsters John and Anne Darwin.</p>
            <p>Ofcom said the actions were "at the boundaries of what is
appropriate" but "warranted in the... circumstances".</p>
            <p>Sky News said the move was "editorially justified and in the
public interest".</p>
            <p>The Darwins were jailed in 2008 after the former prison officer
faked his death in a canoeing accident as his wife cashed in
insurance policies.</p>
            <p>John Darwin, who was reported missing in March 2002, was
arrested after handing himself into police five years later.</p>
            <p>Sky News announced in April 2012 that it had authorised
correspondent Gerard Tubb to "access the email of individuals
suspected of criminal activity".</p>
            <p>It said the decision to approve such a move was a "finely
balanced judgement based on individual circumstances and must
always be subjected to the proper editorial controls".</p>
            <p>The hacking was said to have taken place in the run-up to the
Darwins' trial and the material discovered was later passed on to
police and used as evidence in court.</p>
            <p>
               <a href="http://stakeholders.ofcom.org.uk/binaries/enforcement/broadcast-bulletins/obb233/obb233.pdf">
Regulator Ofcom said</a> neither Mr nor Mrs Darwin had complained
but it had "a general duty" to investigate possible infringements
of privacy.</p>
            <p>It said although there was "current public concern about
unauthorised accessing of voicemail and emails by journalists" the
"exceptional circumstances of this case outweighed Mr and Mrs
Darwin's expectation of privacy".</p>
            <p>"The emails were accessed with a view to detecting or revealing
a serious crime in circumstances where there appears to have been a
real prospect that the relevant evidence would go unnoticed by
investigating authorities...</p>
            <p>"BSkyB behaved responsibly once it had obtained the emails,
passing them to the police and ensuring that there was no
publication until after proceedings had concluded."</p>
            <p>In its response to Ofcom, BSkyB said Mr Tubb decided to access
the email accounts "in order to demonstrate that Mrs Darwin was not
the innocent victim that she portrayed publicly and that she had
been involved in the deception".</p>
            <p>Gaining unauthorised access to an email account is a criminal
offence under the Computer Misuse Act.</p>
            <p>But the Crown Prosecution Service said in March it would not be
bringing any charges.</p>
            <p>"It is not possible to ascertain whether the potential offence
of unlawful interception of a communication was committed in the UK
or the US," said the CPS.</p>
            <p>"Although this may warrant further investigation, it has been
decided... that further investigations are not required as, in
accordance with the DPP's guidelines, we do not consider that any
potential prosecution would be in the public interest."</p>
            <p>BSkyB is 40% owned by News Corp, which decided to close the News
of the World in 2011 over phone hacking by the newspaper's
journalists.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1363633419023"
                  href="/news/uk-england-tees-21835295">Canoe couple 'hacking' case
dropped</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1333629625536"
                  href="/news/uk-17628600">Sky News admits hacking emails</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
