<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-22967853"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Families of soldiers killed in Iraq can sue the government for negligence and bring damages claims under the Human Rights Act, the Supreme Court rules."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T12:42:49"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68257000/jpg/_68257389_army_comp.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Families win Iraq deaths damages bid"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="UK"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-22967853"/>
         <title>BBC News - Iraq damages cases: Supreme Court rules families
can sue</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">13:42</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Iraq damages cases: Supreme Court rules
families can sue</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68255000/jpg/_68255676_68255675.jpg"
                 alt="Susan Smith speaking outside the Supreme Court"/>
               <p class="caption">Susan Smith: "Well, we've won... but to be
honest we didn't expect to"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Families of soldiers
killed in Iraq can pursue damages against the government, the
Supreme Court has ruled.</p>
            <p>Legal action was brought by relatives of three men killed by
roadside bombs while in Snatch Land Rovers and another killed while
in a Challenger tank.</p>
            <p>
               <a href="http://www.supremecourt.gov.uk/decided-cases/docs/UKSC_2012_0249_Judgment.pdf">
The judges ruled</a> the families could make damages claims under
human rights legislation and sue for negligence.</p>
            <p>The defence secretary has said the ruling could make it "more
difficult for troops to carry out operations".</p>
            <p>The ruling comes after a lengthy legal battle and previous
judgements by the High Court and the Court of Appeal.</p>
            <p>At least 37 UK soldiers have died in
conflicts in Iraq and Afghanistan while travelling in the lightly
armoured Snatch Land Rover; its vulnerability has led some soldiers
to call it the "mobile coffin".</p>
            <p>The families of the three soldiers who died in the vehicles
while on duty in Iraq want to make claims for damages under the
European Convention on Human Rights, Article Two of which imposes a
duty on authorities, in this case the Army, to protect the right to
life.</p>
            <p>The soldiers were Pte Phillip Hewett, 21, of Tamworth,
Staffordshire, who was killed in July 2005; Pte Lee Ellis, 23, of
Wythenshawe, Greater Manchester, killed in February 2006; and L/Cpl
Kirk Redpath, 22, of Romford, east London, killed in August
2007.</p>
            <p>The Ministry of Defence had argued the claims should be struck
out because the soldiers were not covered by the legislation once
they had left their British base.</p>
            <p>But the Supreme Court rejected this, concluding the soldiers
were within the UK's jurisdiction at the time of their deaths and
so were subject to human rights legislation.</p>
            <p>BBC legal affairs correspondent Clive Colman described the
ruling as a "major shift", which could now lead to more claims
being made against the MoD.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68265000/jpg/_68265112_68265111.jpg"
                 alt="Defence Secretary Philip Hammond"/>
               <p class="caption">Defence Secretary Phillip Hammond: "We do not
believe that the Ministry of Defence was negligent..."</p>
            </div>
            <p>But he added that the court had been careful to say that certain
things will still not be challengeable under human rights law, such
as high-level policy decisions at the MoD or decisions made in the
heat of battle.</p>
            <p>The families of Cpl Stephen Allbutt, 35, of Sneyd Green,
Stoke-on-Trent - who was killed in a "friendly fire" incident in a
tank in Iraq in March 2003 - and of L/Cpl Daniel Twiddy, of
Stamford, Lincolnshire, and Trooper Andrew Julien, of Bolton,
Greater Manchester, who were both badly injured in the same
incident, brought a second case to the court.</p>
            <p>They argued that the MoD owed a duty of care under the law of
negligence. They said the MoD had failed to properly equip the
tanks and to give soldiers adequate training.</p>
            <p>The MoD had argued that there was "combat
immunity" where troops in action were concerned and it was not
"fair, just or reasonable" to impose a duty of care on the MoD when
soldiers were on the battlefield.</p>
            <p>But during Wednesday's hearing, the Supreme Court justices ruled
that immunity did not apply in this case.</p>
            <p>Defence Secretary Philip Hammond said: "I am very concerned at
the wider implications of this judgement, which could ultimately
make it more difficult for our troops to carry out operations, and
potentially throws open a wide range of military decisions to the
uncertainty of litigation.</p>
            <p>"We will continue to make this point in future legal proceedings
as it can't be right that troops on operations have to put the
European Convention on Human Rights ahead of what is operationally
vital to protect our national security."</p>
            <p>Debi Allbutt, the widow of Cpl Stephen Allbutt, told the BBC she
was pleased with the outcome, but that the families' fight would
continue.</p>
            <p>She said: "We want combat immunity thrown out of the rulebook,
so instead of soldiers having to sue the Ministry of Defence, the
equipment and the training will be in place to stop things like
this happening again."</p>
            <p>Susan Smith, mother of Pte Phillip Hewett, described the
judgement as "absolutely brilliant".</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68256000/jpg/_68256925_army_comp.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Pte Phillip Hewett, Pte Lee Ellis and Lance Cpl Kirk Redpath"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Relatives of Pte Phillip Hewett, Pte Lee
Ellis and L/Cpl Kirk Redpath were among those who brought the
case</span>
            </div>
            <p>"They can no longer treat soldiers as sub-human with no rights,"
she said.</p>
            <p>"Phillip's dead. Nothing is going to bring him back, but this
might help save lives in the future."</p>
            <p>Lawyer Jocelyn Cockburn, who is acting for the Snatch Land Rover
families, said the MoD "can't be given a carte blanche to fail to
equip our troops".</p>
            <p>She said: "I think what they have established is what seems to
many families is common sense - that soldiers have human rights,
and they do remain within the jurisdiction of the UK, and they
don't lose those because they are on the battlefield."</p>
            <p>The families' claims will now be able to proceed to trial to
determine if the MoD owes damages.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1353695387569"
                  href="/news/uk-england-20469279">MoD announces
Â£46m Foxhound contract</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1352568519458"
                  href="/news/uk-20281534">Judges to consider damages ruling</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1350608416195"
                  href="/news/uk-19992082">Soldiers' families can sue MoD</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/48642000/jpg/_48642120_001379846.jpg"
                    alt="image of Caroline Wyatt"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Caroline Wyatt</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Defence correspondent, BBC News</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>This is the result the MoD did not want. It has fought hard
through the courts to limit the extension of human rights and
negligence laws to the battlefield, an unpredictable place where
the enemy is usually trying to kill or maim UK military personnel:
a place which MoD lawyers have long argued is incompatible with the
idea of a 'right to life'.</p>
            <p>But gradually, the European Convention on Human Rights has been
tested in the courts and found to apply to British soldiers while
on British military bases abroad. And now thanks to the Supreme
Court's judgement, human rights have been found to apply to
soldiers on the battlefield, though not without limits.</p>
            <p>Exactly what their judgement means for soldiers and their
families will still have to be tested in the High Court, as the
judgement is not the end of the story. There are likely to be many
more legal skirmishes before it's clear what impact will be,
whether on procurement decisions, devising training or issuing
orders before the UK's soldiers, sailors or air personnel are sent
to war.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Snatch-2 Land Rover</h2>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68234000/jpg/_68234877_snatchlandrover_304.jpg"
                 width="305"
                 height="210"
                 alt="A Snatch Land Rover"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <strong>Role:</strong> Protection Patrol Vehicle</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>Defences:</strong> Armour to protect against explosions
and gunfire; electronic sensors to detect roadside bombs</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>Strengths:</strong> Quick land transport for up to six
troops</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>Weaknesses:</strong> Critics argue the thin-skinned
vehicles offer insufficient protection against roadside bombs</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>Cost:</strong> Approximately
Â£50,000</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
