<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-london-23266281"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Six protesters from Greenpeace are attempting to scale the tallest building in western Europe, The Shard in London."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-11T11:36:16"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68665000/jpg/_68665217_68664171.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Protesters attempt to scale Shard"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="England/London"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-london-23266281"/>
         <title>BBC News - Greenpeace protesters climbing up The Shard in
London</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">11 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">12:36</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Greenpeace protesters climbing up The
Shard in London</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68665000/jpg/_68665783_68665782.jpg"
                 alt="Climbers on side of Shard"/>
               <p class="caption">The six female protesters are scaling the Shard
in central London because it overlooks three offices belonging to
Shell</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Six protesters are
attempting to climb the tallest building in western Europe, The
Shard.</p>
            <p>Police said the group accessed the building in central London by
climbing on to the roof of nearby London Bridge Station. Officers
were called to the scene at 04:25 BST.</p>
            <p>Greenpeace said it was protesting against Shell's Arctic
drilling, which the oil company said was "not new".</p>
            <p>The Shard skyscraper stands at 310m (1,016ft) and has 87
storeys.</p>
            <p>BBC reporter Jonathan Savage, who is at the scene, said the
women were climbing the edge of the building as it has a
ladder-like structure, and were using ropes.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68664000/jpg/_68664164_68664163.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Greenpeace protesters"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Greenpeace said the protesters were
experienced climbers</span>
            </div>
            <p>He said they were about a quarter of the way up and there are
police and ambulance teams at the scene looking up at the
climbers.</p>
            <p>Greenpeace said the location was chosen because it sits in the
middle of the oil company's three headquarters and because the
building was modelled on a shard of ice.</p>
            <p>A spokesman said the climbers were all well trained and it was
not dangerous. If they manage to get to the top of the building,
they plan on installing a piece of art.</p>
            <p>The demonstrators are <a href="https://twitter.com/GreenpeaceUK/status/355220637159129091">live-streaming</a>
the climb from helmet cameras, with birds-eye views of their ascent
being broadcast.</p>
            <p>Greenpeace wants the area around the North Pole to be made a
global sanctuary, off limits to industrialisation.</p>
            <p>One climber, Victoria Henry, 32, a Canadian living in Hackney,
said: "We'll try to hang a huge art installation 310m up that will
make Shell think twice before sending their rigs into the
Arctic.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68665000/jpg/_68665235_68665234.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="People looking up at the Shard"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">A Shard spokesperson said it has a team
advising the protesters</span>
            </div>
            <p>"It's going to be really hard work, it's going to be
nerve-shredding for all of us and we may not succeed, but we're
going to do everything we can to pull it off.</p>
            <p>"Millions of people have called on Shell to get out of the
Arctic but they're still trying to drill there anyway.</p>
            <p>"If we reach the top we'll be able to see all three of Shell's
London offices below us, meaning they'll be able to see us. Maybe
then they'll stop ignoring the movement ranged against them."</p>
            <p>In a statement, Shell said: "We respect the right of individuals
and organisations to engage in a free and frank exchange of views
about our operations.</p>
            <p>"Recognising the right of individuals to express their point of
view, we only ask that they do so with their safety and the safety
of others, including Shell personnel and customers in mind."</p>
            <p>On the Arctic, it said oil and gas production from the Arctic
"was not new".</p>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68666000/jpg/_68666915_68664167.jpg"
                 width="226"
                 height="282"
                 alt="Protesters scaling the Shard"/>
               <span style="width:226px;">The protesters aim to hang an art
installation at the top of the building</span>
            </div>
            <p>"The Arctic region currently produces about 10% of the world's
oil and 25% of its gas.</p>
            <p>"If responsibly developed, Arctic energy resources can help
offset supply constraints and maintain energy security for
consumers throughout the world.</p>
            <p>"Shell has been operating in the Arctic and sub-Arctic since the
early 20th Century, giving us the technical experience and know-how
to explore for and produce oil and gas responsibly."</p>
            <p>The BBC reporter at the scene said the Shard had members of its
high-wire team giving the women a health and safety briefing as
they climbed the building.</p>
            <p>A Shard spokesman said: "Our primary focus is on the safety of
the protestors and the workers and visitors to the building.</p>
            <p>"We are working with the relevant authorities to try to ensure
the safety of those concerned."</p>
            <p>The Qatari-owned building, which was opened in February,
contains offices, restaurants, a hotel and residential
apartments.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1368432553530"
                  href="/news/technology-22478746">At the
summit of the Shard <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1358532793204"
                  href="/news/magazine-21065706">Staring at the Shard</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1357868932702"
                  href="/news/uk-20979547">Take a tour of
The Shard's roof <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
