<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-oxfordshire-23079649"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Two pairs of brothers who were among seven men who abused girls from Oxford in a sadistic sex grooming ring are jailed for life."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T21:00:33"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68415000/jpg/_68415011_bullfinch_brothers_464.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Men get life for sex abuse ring"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="England/Oxford"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-oxfordshire-23079649"/>
         <title>BBC News - Oxford grooming sex case: Brothers jailed for
life</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">22:00</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Oxford grooming sex case: Brothers jailed
for life</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68421000/jpg/_68421975_compguilty.jpg"
                 alt="(Top L-R) Mohammed Karrar, Bassam Karrar, Akhtar Dogar, Anjum Dogar, (Bottom) Kamar Jamil, Assad Hussain, Zeesham Ahmed"/>
               <p class="caption">Thames Valley Police say they are speaking to 50
people in continuing inquiries</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Two pairs of
brothers from Oxford who were among seven men who abused girls as
part of a sadistic sex grooming ring have been jailed for life.</p>
            <p>Mohammed Karrar, 38, and brother Bassam Karrar, 34, will serve a
minimum of 20 years and 15 years respectively.</p>
            <p>Brothers Akhtar Doghar, 32, and Anjum Doghar, 31, were both
given minimum terms of 17 years, at the Old Bailey.</p>
            <p>The men's offences included child rape and trafficking, between
2004 and 2012. A fifth man was also jailed for life.</p>
            <p>Kamar Jamil, 27, who was found guilty of charges including rape
and arranging child prostitution, was told he would serve at least
12 years.</p>
            <p>Jurors heard at the men's trial at the
Old Bailey how six girls, aged at the time between 11 and 15, were
plied with alcohol and drugs before being forced to perform sex
acts.</p>
            <p>Some were beaten and burned.</p>
            <p>The court heard how the men - two of east African origin and
five of Pakistani origin - identified vulnerable girls for abuse
and then groomed each one of them until they were under the control
of the gang.</p>
            <p>They were then each either abused by the men themselves, given
to the men's friends or offered at a price to others who were not
on trial.</p>
            <p>The girls were mostly chosen because their unsettled or troubled
lives made them easier to manipulate.</p>
            <p>Judge Peter Rook, sentencing, said Jamil, the Dogar brothers and
the Karrar brothers abused vulnerable girls in Oxford over a long
period, and on occasions the "depravity was extreme".</p>
            <p>The abuse started in Oxford but some victims were later taken to
other parts of the country to be offered to other men who were in
contact with the gang.</p>
            <p>The court heard the victims were tied up, burnt, suffocated,
beaten and urinated upon, and would return to Oxford bleeding,
injured and carrying sexually-transmitted infections.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68420000/jpg/_68420486_68420484.jpg"
                 alt="Police spokeswoman "/>
               <p class="caption">In a statement read by police, the family
thanked the girl for "finding the strength" to speak out</p>
            </div>
            <p>Judge Rook said the men had blighted their victims' lives and
robbed them of their adolescence.</p>
            <p>He said: "These six girls have shown enormous courage in coming
to the Old Bailey to give evidence, knowing they would be accused
of lying, knowing they would have to relive their ordeals, knowing
they have not been believed in the past."</p>
            <p>Judge Rook said he hoped the victims' courage would act as a
deterrent to other men but also ensure the appropriate authorities
would not fail in future to take action in the face of such
activity.</p>
            <p>Two more men, Assad Hussain, 32, and Zeeshan Ahmed, were each
jailed for seven years for two counts of sexual activity with a
child.</p>
            <p>Talking about the abuse suffered by one of the victims, Judge
Rook told Jamil and the Dogar brothers, who were convicted of
abusing her: "You took her soul. She felt as though it had been
ripped out. You put her parents through years of sheer
torture."</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/67594000/jpg/_67594801_67594800.jpg"
                 alt="Girl Three"/>
               <p class="caption">Victim: "I was scared to say no"</p>
            </div>
            <p>In total, nine men had denied charges including rape, arranging
child prostitution and trafficking between 2004 and 2012. Two were
acquitted of all charges.</p>
            <p>Numerous opportunities to catch members of the gang are believed
to have been missed.</p>
            <p>Thames Valley Police chief constable Sara Thornton has
previously apologised for the delay in securing convictions against
the seven men.</p>
            <p>Ms Thornton admitted a joint investigation did not start until
2011, despite complaints from victims.</p>
            <p>The force has since set up Kingfisher, a specialist unit to deal
with such cases,</p>
            <p>NSPCC chief executive Peter Wanless said there had been a
"systematic failure" by Oxfordshire County Council to stop the gang
earlier and protect the victims, who had raised the alarm on
several occasions.</p>
            <p>Oxfordshire County Council said a serious
case review was being carried out by the Oxfordshire Safeguarding
Children Board.</p>
            <p>A council spokesman said: "We would like to praise the courage
of the victims for giving evidence in court that has led to these
sentences, and we are sorry we did not stop it sooner."</p>
            <p>Javed Khan, of independent charity Victim Support, said the
control exerted by the men amounted to "modern-day slavery".</p>
            <p>Andy Dipper, from Oxford Community Against Trafficking, said the
organisation would apply pressure to ensure changes to the justice
and care systems.</p>
            <p>"Victims are being stigmatised and
discouraged from reporting their horrific abuse because of a system
which is ponderous, accusatory and further traumatises them," he
said.</p>
            <p>Matthew Reed, chief executive of the Children's Society, said:
"Care homes, the police, social workers and health workers all need
to get better at spotting the signs of abuse.</p>
            <p>"And they need to urgently change their attitude to vulnerable,
exploited teenage girls, who are being routinely dismissed as
'troublesome' or 'promiscuous' or as having made lifestyle
choices."</p>
            <p>Sam Monaghan, director of children's services at children's
charity Barnardo's, said: "These men were able to abuse children
for eight years. That can't be allowed to happen again.</p>
            <p>"A fundamental shift in the collective mindset is needed at
every level of the justice system."</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68419000/jpg/_68419270_68419269.jpg"
                 alt="Simon Morton from Thames Valley Police"/>
               <p class="caption">Simon Morton, Thames Valley Police: "This shows
every victim in the country justice can work for them"</p>
            </div>
            <p>Policing and criminal justice minister Damian Green said the
case showed more should be done to protect vulnerable children.</p>
            <p>He said: "A new Home Office-led group will look at how to better
identify those at risk and create a more victim-focused culture
within the police, health and children's services.</p>
            <p>"But our prime responsibility is, of course, stopping abuse
before it starts.</p>
            <p>"The group will be working to target the organised crime
networks that perpetrate the sort of systematic abuse we have seen
in Oxford."</p>
            <ul>
               <li>Kamar Jamil, formerly of Aldrich Road, Oxford, was found guilty
of five counts of rape, two counts of conspiracy to rape and one
count of arranging child prostitution</li>
               <li>Akhtar Dogar, of Tawney Street, Oxford, was found guilty of
five counts of rape, three counts of conspiracy to rape, two counts
of child prostitution and one count of trafficking</li>
               <li>Anjum Dogar, of Tawney Street, Oxford, was found guilty of
three counts of rape, two counts of child prostitution, three
counts of conspiracy to rape and one count of trafficking</li>
               <li>Assad Hussain, of Ashurst Way, Oxford, was found not guilty of
rape and guilty of two counts of sexual activity with a child</li>
               <li>Mohammed Karrar, of Kames Close, Oxford, was found guilty of
two counts of conspiracy to rape, four counts of rape of a child,
one count of using an instrument to procure miscarriage, two counts
of trafficking, one count of assault of a child by penetration, two
counts of child prostitution, three counts of rape, two counts of
conspiracy to rape a child and one count of supplying a class A
drug</li>
               <li>Bassam Karrar, of Hundred Acres Close, Oxford, was found guilty
of two counts of rape, one count of rape of a child, two counts of
conspiracy to rape a child, two counts of child prostitution, one
count of trafficking and one count of conspiracy to rape</li>
               <li>Zeeshan Ahmed, of Palmer Road, Oxford, was found guilty of two
counts of sexual activity with a child</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372346602991"
                  href="/news/uk-england-oxfordshire-23086440">Mother proud of 'brave'
abuse victim <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372266093751"
                  href="/news/uk-england-oxfordshire-23066882">Authorities 'blind' to
Oxford abuse</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1368545202362"
                  href="/news/uk-22467927">Oxford grooming: Girl Three's story</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/64005000/jpg/_64005513_64005512.jpg"
                    alt="image of Alex Forsyth"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Alex Forsyth</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
South Home Affairs Correspondent</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>For the six victims, it's been a long road to justice.</p>
            <p>Some were abused for years, controlled and intimidated by men
they had, at first, trusted.</p>
            <p>Their courage has been praised by all involved in this case.</p>
            <p>They endured the ordeal of giving evidence to a packed
courtroom, recounting intimate details of abuse, some too explicit
to report, then undergoing intense cross examination.</p>
            <p>At the end of the four-month trial they were, at last,
believed.</p>
            <p>For them, this marks the end of a long legal process, but it's
by no means the end of the story.</p>
            <p>The authorities will now examine their own role in this case,
trying to understand how the abuse went on for so long and trying
to ensure it can never happen again.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Find out more</h2>
            <p>On Friday 28 June between 10:00 BST and 13:00 BST the BBC Asian
Network will be holding a live debate from the Cowley Road in
Oxford - a location at the centre of the city's grooming case.
Locals and British Pakistanis will discuss the relevance of the
ethnicity of the men sentenced.</p>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006wqgk">Nihal's
phone-in show on BBC Asian Network</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">A fundamental shift in the collective
mindset is needed at every level of the justice system”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Sam Monaghan</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Barnardo's</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
