<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-birmingham-23123549"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A huge fire involving 100,000 tonnes of plastic recycling, thought to have been sparked by a Chinese lantern, is contained, firefighters say."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T21:18:02"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68475000/jpg/_68475284_firedartmouthrd1.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Lantern 'caused largest blaze'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="England/Birmingham and Black Country"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-birmingham-23123549"/>
         <title>BBC News - Smethwick fire: Chinese lantern 'caused largest
blaze'</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">22:18</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Smethwick fire: Chinese lantern 'caused
largest blaze'</h1>
            <div id="slideshow_container" class="storybody-halfwide-include">
               <div id="ss_slides">
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68473000/jpg/_68473035_firedartmouthrd1.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Firefighters tackle blaze in Smethwick"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">West Midlands Fire Service was called to the fire
late on Sunday night</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68471000/jpg/_68471234_smethwick.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="The fire as seen from Handsworth"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">More than 200 firefighters tackled the
fire off Dartmouth Road</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68476000/jpg/_68476434_68476433.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Smoke seen across Birmingham"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">As dawn broke the smoke could be seen
for miles across the area leading to some dramatic
pictures</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68487000/jpg/_68487194_1a682f41-66fe-4fc3-a14e-7319e06ec6ee.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Firefighters at the scene of the fire on Monday afternoon"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">Fire chiefs said the heat coming off the
fire was "tremendous"</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68473000/jpg/_68473495_de52.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Smethwick fire"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">The fire, believed to be started by a Chinese
lantern, involves 100,000 tonnes of plastic spread across about
90,000 sq m</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68473000/jpg/_68473493_bofacddcuaaw9wn.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Smethwick fire"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">Firefighters have contained the blaze but expect to
be at the fire for a number of days</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68473000/jpg/_68473421_wp_20130701_001.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Smoke is seen drifting over Birmingham city centre"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">The smoke blocked out the early morning
sun in the centre of Birmingham, miles from the fire</span>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="ss_controls">
                  <a href="#prev" class="ss_prev ss_button ss_button_disabled">
                     <span>previous
slide</span>
                  </a>
                  <a href="#next" class="ss_next ss_button ss_button_disabled">
                     <span>next
slide</span>
                  </a>
               </div>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A huge fire
involving 100,000 tonnes of plastic recycling material, thought to
have been sparked by a Chinese lantern, has been contained say
firefighters.</p>
            <p>Crews described the blaze, which also involved a factory unit,
as the largest they had seen in the West Midlands.</p>
            <p>More than 200 firefighters attended the fire in Smethwick. Three
of them have been taken to hospital.</p>
            <p>The fire, which <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-birmingham-23129776">produced
a 6,000ft smoke plume</a>, is said to have caused
Â£6m damage to the Jayplas depot.</p>
            <p>Fire chiefs have now called for an "urgent review" into the use
of Chinese lanterns.</p>
            <p>Chief fire officer Vij Randeniya said it was the 15th fire at a
waste recycling site in the West Midlands this year and said he was
calling for a meeting with plant operators.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68474000/jpg/_68474132_68474131.jpg"
                 alt="Aerial view of fire"/>
               <p class="caption">Aerial footage shows the extent of the fire</p>
            </div>
            <p>Mike Maxwell, the director of Jayplas, said the fire had been "a
tragic accident over which we had no control".</p>
            <p>The blaze in Dartmouth Road, which is expected to take about
three days to fully extinguish, is within an industrial estate, but
the closest residents were being advised to keep windows
closed.</p>
            <p>The fire service said Dartmouth Road, Halfords Lane and
Brasshouse Lane were closed to traffic and that the fire was likely
to cause congestion in the area.</p>
            <p>Nearby Galton Valley Primary School, in Brasshouse Lane, had
been closed because of the road closures.</p>
            <p>Mr Randeniya said the fire, which began at about 23:00 BST on
Sunday, had taken eight minutes to take hold after a lantern landed
in the depot.</p>
            <p>The service has previously campaigned against the use of Chinese
lanterns.</p>
            <p>"What you're doing in an unregulated and uncontrolled way is
putting fire in the sky and every now and again it lands on
something like this and we're here for three days," Mr Randeniya
said.</p>
            <p>In a statement, West Midlands Fire Service urged community
leaders and members of the public to discourage the use of Chinese
lanterns.</p>
            <p>It said there was "wide scope" for limiting the use of such
lanterns and questioned whether event licences would be needed for
anyone wanting to release them.</p>
            <p>The Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs said it
was raising awareness of the risks of sky lanterns and looking to
see what could be done to improve fire safety.</p>
            <p>It is also asking councils to look at the licensing of mass
releases of the lanterns.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68480000/jpg/_68480453_west_midlands_fire_624.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="388"
                 alt="Smethwick fire"/>
            </div>
            <p>Mr Randeniya said they had made "steady progress" on the fire,
although it had caused "Â£6m of
devastation".</p>
            <p>He said: "We can see the seat of the fire, but we can't get to
it at the moment - and that measures about 300m by 300m.</p>
            <p>"Conditions are difficult and it's quite tricky underfoot so
we're having to be extremely careful. We can only take it 100m at a
time but hopefully by tomorrow we will have made substantial
progress."</p>
            <p>About 100 firefighters remained at the site earlier and
officials said their priority was to protect nearby buildings.</p>
            <p>Mr Maxwell, from the recycling plant, apologised to all the
people living nearby for the disruption caused and said they hoped
to "have the site up and running as soon as possible".</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68474000/jpg/_68474629_68474627.jpg"
                 alt="Firefighters tackle blaze in Smethwick"/>
               <p class="caption">Area commander Steve Vincent said there were
reports the smoke was visible 50 miles away</p>
            </div>
            <p>He added: "Jayplas will do everything we can to assist the
emergency services and the Environment Agency to ensure the site
and surrounding areas are made safe and cleaned up as quickly as
possible with minimum impact to the local environment."</p>
            <p>Area commander Steve Vincent described it as the "largest fire
that we've had in the West Midlands".</p>
            <p>The ambulance service said it had treated 13 firefighters "for a
variety of minor injuries, though three were taken to hospital
overnight".</p>
            <p>"Injuries include heat exhaustion, injuries to eyes and an ankle
as well as one minor burn," a spokesman added.</p>
            <p>Public Health England in the West Midlands said smoke from any
source could contain substances to irritate breathing, skin or
eyes.</p>
            <p>"People with asthma and other respiratory conditions may be
particularly susceptible to the smoke and should carry and use
their medication [such as inhalers] as usual," said a
spokesman.</p>
            <p>Witness Jack Awal said he could see the fire from his home two
miles away in Handsworth.</p>
            <p>He said: "I heard a loud bang and went outside to see what it
was.</p>
            <p>"I immediately recognised where the smoke was coming from. I
knew it had to be a factory.</p>
            <p>"It was like a scene from a movie. There were so many large
explosions and loud bangs. It was like a firework display - there
were loud crackles and bangs every few seconds."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372684877262"
                  href="/news/uk-england-birmingham-23129776">Saving wildlife after a huge
fire</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372669908957"
                  href="/news/uk-england-birmingham-23124144">Photographs show largest
fire yet</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372687739151"
                  href="/news/magazine-23129276">Five problems caused by Chinese
lanterns</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
