<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-london-23248433"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A young offender institution is labelled an &#34;unacceptably violent place&#34; by inspectors who found an &#34;unprecedentedly high&#34; use of batons by staff."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-10T07:34:11"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68641000/jpg/_68641810_feltham.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Youth prison 'unacceptably violent'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="England/London"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-london-23248433"/>
         <title>BBC News - Feltham Young Offender Institution 'unacceptably
violent'</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">10 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">08:34</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Feltham Young Offender Institution
'unacceptably violent'</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/59695000/jpg/_59695610_feltham2.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Inside Feltham Young Offenders' Institution"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Feltham Prison and Young Offender Institution, was
labelled 'unacceptably violent'</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A young offender
institution has been labelled "unacceptably violent" by inspectors
who found "unprecedentedly high" use of batons by staff.</p>
            <p>Feltham Prison and Young Offender Institution, in west London,
witnessed on average almost two fights or assaults every day, a
report said.</p>
            <p>Some of the fights were "very serious", HM Inspectorate of
Prisons found.</p>
            <p>The National Offender Management Service said it showed the
"disturbing but accurate" challenges staff face.</p>
            <p>Andrew Neilson, director of campaigns at the Howard League for
Penal Reform, said: "This is the worst inspection report of its
kind we have seen in a decade.</p>
            <p>"If you want to see the effects of keeping hundreds of troubled
boys cooped up in a prison, you need look no further than
Feltham."</p>
            <p>Feltham is divided into two parts - Feltham A holds children and
young people, mostly aged 16 or 17, while Feltham B holds young
adult men aged 18 to 21.</p>
            <p>Chief inspector of prisons Nick Hardwick
said: "Feltham as a whole is an unacceptably violent place.</p>
            <p>"Despite excellent work in some cases, staff were unable to
prevent a high number of very concerning incidents that carried a
significant risk of serious injury.</p>
            <p>"Staff were sometimes overwhelmed by the challenges they faced,"
he added.</p>
            <p>"As a consequence, some of their response, such as the prolonged
use of isolation on the children and young people's side and the
use of batons on the young adult side, were unacceptable."</p>
            <p>Mr Hardwick told the BBC Today programme: "As numbers in custody
of young people has fallen, those that remain are the most troubled
and staff are struggling to cope with that.</p>
            <p>"If you were a parent with a child in Feltham, you'd be
terrified."</p>
            <p>Many young people told inspectors they were frightened and had
little confidence in staff to keep them safe.</p>
            <p>Self-harming behaviour remained high among young adults and
emergency cell bells were not answered quickly, the report
said.</p>
            <p>National Offender Management Service (Noms) chief Michael Spurr
told the programme: "The levels of violence is higher than any of
us would want to see.</p>
            <p>"It paints a disturbing but accurate picture of the challenges
that staff at Feltham are facing on a daily basis."</p>
            <p>He added: "The young people who come into Feltham are troubled.
Half are coming in for violent offences, many have got long
standing gang affiliations and managing that challenging population
has been incredible difficult."</p>
            <p>He said batons were used 25 times last year which was higher
than in any other prison however they were not used on those aged
under 18.</p>
            <p>He said to make the institution safer, those who are on remand
will be moved elsewhere so staff can spend more time with those who
have been convicted.</p>
            <p>"They [inmates] are safe but we want to make them as safe as
possible. You can't remove totally harm from anywhere," he
added.</p>
            <p>Prison Reform Trust director Juliet Lyon said: "Feltham should
frighten us all.</p>
            <p>"Why do we place our most vulnerable and volatile young people
in our most troubled institutions, and expect anything other than
the violence, self-harm and mayhem this report reveals?"</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1359008676220"
                  href="/news/uk-england-london-21159302">Prison attacks 'rise by a
third'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1334811711476"
                  href="/news/uk-england-london-17736704">Criticisms in report 'taken
out'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1330548118343"
                  href="/news/uk-england-london-17214332">Flagship crime scheme will
end</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">If you were a parent with a child in
Feltham, you'd be terrified”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Nick Hardwick</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Chief Inspector of Prisons</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
