<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-23239545"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Rupert Murdoch says he &#34;welcomes&#34; the chance to face MPs over comments he allegedly made about a police probe into corrupt payments by journalists."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-09T20:18:29"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68636000/jpg/_68636144_64904786.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Murdoch prepared to face MPs again"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Politics"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-23239545"/>
         <title>BBC News - Rupert Murdoch 'welcomes' chance to face MPs
again</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">9 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">21:18</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Rupert Murdoch 'welcomes' chance to face
MPs again</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68636000/jpg/_68636138_68636137.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Rupert Murdoch"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Mr Murdoch appeared before MPs in 2011</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Rupert Murdoch has
said he "welcomes" the chance to face MPs over comments he
allegedly made about a police probe into corrupt payments by
journalists.</p>
            <p>The Commons culture committee wants to question the News Corp
boss, who apparently criticised officers and defended reporters in
secretly-recorded conversations with staff on The Sun.</p>
            <p>Mr Murdoch's spokesman said he wanted to clear up "any
misconceptions".</p>
            <p>He previously gave evidence to the committee in 2011.</p>
            <p>The appearance was disrupted when a protester attempted to throw
a foam pie at him.</p>
            <p>Mr Murdoch was secretly recorded in March by Channel 4 News and
the Exaro news agency appearing to criticise the police and
defending his journalists who have been accused of such
payments.</p>
            <p>It was broadcast appearing to show him criticising Operation
Elveden - the probe into alleged illegal payments to public
officials by journalists, mainly from News International.</p>
            <p>In the recording - of a talk Mr Murdoch gave to Sun journalists
- he is heard complaining about "totally incompetent" police
officers and saying he would do "everything in his power to give
you total support, even if you're convicted".</p>
            <p>BBC media correspondent David Sillito said the MPs believed
there were contradictions between the apparent contents of the
recording and Mr Murdoch's evidence to them that they wanted to
explore.</p>
            <p>But he added that with more than 20 arrests so far in the
Elveden inquiry and several people charged, the committee would be
extremely restricted in what questions it could ask.</p>
            <p>A spokesman for News Corporation said: "Mr Murdoch welcomes the
opportunity to return to the select committee and answer their
questions. He looks forward to clearing up any misconceptions as
soon as possible."</p>
            <p>Earlier on Tuesday, Metropolitan Police Assistant Commissioner
Cressida Dick told MPs on the Home Affairs Committee that the force
was seeking a court order to get hold of the tape recording.</p>
            <p>She said voluntary co-operation with News Corp had
"significantly reduced" in the past couple of months and all new
requests for material were now subject to the approval of a judge -
a process she described as "protracted".</p>
            <p>News Corp has said it continues to co-operate with the police
regarding Operation Elveden, and the separate investigation in
allegations of phone hacking, and said Mr Murdoch had been
demonstrating "understandable empathy" with staff.</p>
            <p>Evans Harris, associate director of the Hacked Off campaign,
which calls for tighter regulation of the press, welcomed the move
to recall Mr Murdoch.</p>
            <p>He said: "The victims of press abuse, who Hacked Off represent,
were appalled that Rupert Murdoch told Sun journalists that parts
of the Leveson inquiry were over 'next to nothing'."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372895556966"
                  href="/news/uk-23175564">News Corp defends Murdoch over tapes</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372450858502"
                  href="/news/business-23104822">News Corp officially splits in
two</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
