<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-23186128"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A bill to guarantee a referendum on Britain's EU membership in 2017 clears its first Commons hurdle as 304 mainly Tory MPs back it."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-05T16:01:37"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68563000/jpg/_68563263_68563256.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="MPs urge 'overdue' EU referendum"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Politics"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-23186128"/>
         <title>BBC News - EU referendum: MPs call for public to have their
say</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">5 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">17:01</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">EU referendum: MPs call for public to have
their say</h1>
            <div class="has-icon-comment dna-comment-count-simple"> </div>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68562000/jpg/_68562663_68562662.jpg"
                 alt="James Wharton MP"/>
               <p class="caption">James Wharton: "This has got the full backing of
David Cameron and the Conservative Party leadership"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Conservative MPs
have led calls for the public to have their say in a referendum on
whether Britain should remain in the European Union.</p>
            <p>James Wharton, whose bill proposes a vote by 2017, said he was
"speaking for millions of people" in the country.</p>
            <p>He said "public sentiment" about Europe had changed and fresh
consent for the UK's membership was "long overdue".</p>
            <p>Labour said the Tories were "talking to themselves" while the
Lib Dems branded the bill a "complete stunt".</p>
            <p>MPs backed Mr Wharton's private member's bill at second reading
- the first time it has been debated - by 304 votes to 0 although
only a handful of Labour MPs took part as they and the Lib Dems
boycotted the vote en masse.</p>
            <p>After the unanimous vote, Mr Cameron - who was in the Commons
chamber for much of the debate - <a href="https://twitter.com/David_Cameron">wrote on Twitter:</a>
"Referendum Bill passes first Commons stage, bringing us one step
closer to giving the British people a say on Europe."</p>
            <p>Although it has passed its first parliamentary hurdle, the bill
will face much stronger opposition later and its passage through
Parliament is far from guaranteed.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68570000/jpg/_68570565_68570560.jpg"
                 alt="Douglas Alexander"/>
               <p class="caption">Douglas Alexander: "We do not believe that an
in/out referendum in 2017... is in the national interest"</p>
            </div>
            <p>Only five Conservative MPs - Ken Clarke, Sir Richard Shepherd,
Jason McCartney, Sir Malcolm Rifkind and Gary Streeter - did not
vote.</p>
            <p>Veteran europhile Mr Clarke and eurosceptic Mr McCartney are
away from Westminster for family reasons while Mr Streeter did not
take part as he is chairing the committee which will now scrutinise
the bill in detail.</p>
            <p>Sir Richard spoke during the debate in favour of a referendum
while Sir Malcolm said he would have backed it but choose to focus
on other important parliamentary work as it was "obvious" that it
would pass with a big majority.</p>
            <p>Six Labour MPs - Roger Godsiff, Kate Hoey, Kelvin Hopkins,
Dennis Skinner, Graham Stringer and Gisela Stuart - joined
Conservatives in the yes lobby calling for a referendum.</p>
            <p>Opening the debate, Mr Wharton - MP for Stockton South - said
"power should reside with the people" and that his bill would give
the public a "real choice" on the UK's future in Europe within a
"sensible timeframe".</p>
            <p>"We should trust the British public to have their say," he told
MPs, adding that recent public votes on the electoral system and
devolution for Scotland, Wales showed "we live in the age of the
referendum".</p>
            <p>"We have had so many referendums on so many things," he said.
"It would seem to be farcical to deny a say on such an important
thing which matters to so many people."</p>
            <p>Backing Mr Wharton's call, Conservative backbencher Andrew Tyrie
said the EU was a "fundamentally different creature" than it was
nearly 40 years ago when the public endorsed entry in a
referendum.</p>
            <p>For the government, William Hague called on "everyone who is a
true democrat to unite behind this bill", saying it was "the best
chance currently available" for a referendum and to give people
"the decisive say which is their right".</p>
            <p>There had been four major EU treaties in the past 25 years which
had not been subject to a referendum in the UK, the foreign
secretary told MPs, and "no institution can survive without the
people's support".</p>
            <p>He added: "It is the right bill at the right time to give the
British people their democratic say on the country's future."</p>
            <p>But Mr Alexander said the referendum was predicated on an
"arbitrary date" and an "unrealistic and uncertain negotiating
strategy" and claimed the issue had become an obsession for the
Conservatives.</p>
            <p>"Three years in, this is a party still banging on about Europe,
a party talking to itself and not the country."</p>
            <p>The prime minister's promise of a referendum by the end of 2017,
following a renegotiation of the UK's relationship with Brussels,
cannot be made law in the form of a government bill because of Lib
Dem opposition.</p>
            <p>Mr Wharton - the youngest Conservative in the Commons - agreed
to propose the legislation after he came top in a ballot of MPs and
after Tory MPs pushed for the referendum commitment to be made
binding before the 2015 election.</p>
            <p>Private members bills traditionally have little chance of
becoming law unless they are backed by the government and the BBC's
political editor Nick Robinson said the legislation could easily be
derailed by its opponents in the Commons and the Lords.</p>
            <p>But the Conservatives believed they were making a "powerful
political point", he added.</p>
            <p>Lib Dem leader Nick Clegg, who did not take part in the debate,
told the BBC it was a "complete stunt" and the government had
already passed legislation to guarantee a referendum in the event
of further powers being handed to Brussels.</p>
            <p>He told Radio 2's Jeremy Vine show that the time for a
referendum was when the "rules of the game" changed and when "new
things were asked of the UK" in terms of its relationship with the
EU.</p>
            <p>UK Independence Party leader Nigel Farage said a "passionate"
referendum campaign would "wake up" the country.</p>
            <p>"I want friendship, co-operation and trade (with the EU). I
don't want to be part of a political union," he told the BBC. "I
don't find it acceptable that 75% of our laws are now made by the
institutions of Brussels."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>The UK and the EU</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1358335284589"
                     href="/news/uk-politics-20448450">Better off out v Better off
in</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1368448523282"
                     href="/news/uk-politics-22509588">Q&amp;A: An EU referendum?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1342002312925"
                     href="/news/world-europe-18788906">Profile: European Union</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372767389623"
                     href="/news/uk-politics-23144358">Bid to cut UK rebate
'unacceptable'</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
