<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-23192888"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Labour is to hand a report into allegations of irregularities in the selection of an election candidate to the police, in an escalating row with the party's biggest union backer."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-05T16:42:12"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68570000/jpg/_68570159_68567006.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Labour refers Falkirk row to police"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Politics"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-23192888"/>
         <title>BBC News - Labour to refer Falkirk selection row to
police</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">5 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">17:42</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Labour to refer Falkirk selection row to
police</h1>
            <div class="has-icon-comment dna-comment-count-simple"> </div>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68577000/jpg/_68577372_miliband.jpg"
                 alt="Labour leader Ed Miliband"/>
               <p class="caption">Labour leader Ed Miliband: ''At all times, we
have acted to uphold the integrity of my party''</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Ed Miliband is
refusing to back down in his fight with Labour's biggest union
backer over its influence in the party.</p>
            <p>The Labour leader has asked police to look at alleged
irregularities in a candidate selection race in Falkirk.</p>
            <p>According to an internal Labour report, Unite members were being
signed up to the local party without their knowledge in a bid to
rig the contest.</p>
            <p>Unite leader Len McCluskey said his union had done nothing wrong
and he was disappointed at the turn of events.</p>
            <p>Labour HQ has taken over the selection contest in Falkirk but
has not said why it has involved the police.</p>
            <p>Mr McCluskey denies claims Unite tried to fix the contest to get
its preferred candidate selected and claims the internal Labour is
a "stitch up" designed to smear the union.</p>
            <p>Mr Miliband has dismissed the smear claims as "total nonsense"
and said that, instead of defending these practices, Mr McCluskey
should be "facing up to what happened in Falkirk".</p>
            <p>"The Labour Party I lead will select its
candidates in a fair and transparent way. We will act without fear
or favour," said Mr Miliband.</p>
            <p>"He should not be defending the machine politics involving bad
practice and malpractice that went on there. He should be facing up
to it."</p>
            <p>Mr Miliband said the party's inquiry had shown "people were
being signed up as members of the Labour Party without their
knowledge. It says that bad practices were going on. It says people
were being asked to sign up to the Labour Party on the condition
that they supported particular candidates.</p>
            <p>"We are not having this in the Labour Party."</p>
            <p>Labour's shadow business secretary Chuka Umunna told the BBC:
"We took advice yesterday in relation to the Falkirk matter and as
a result of the advice given, have decided swiftly and strongly to
refer it to the police."</p>
            <p>It is not clear why the party considers it might be a police
matter. Mr Umunna told the BBC he could not comment about why as
legal advice was "subject to prejudice".</p>
            <p>The Conservative MP Henry Smith had also written to the Chief
Constable of Scotland, Sir Stephen House, asking for an inquiry and
suggesting Unite might have committed fraud.</p>
            <p>Mr McCluskey told reporters he was "clearly disappointed at the
developments back in London" adding: "It seems to me that the
Labour leadership has now been caught up in anti-union Tory
hysteria and I'm amazed as everyone else is at this."</p>
            <p>He said he supported Ed Miliband as Labour leader but said: "We
are in the middle of a media storm which is being caused by
Labour's inability to deal with this situation."</p>
            <p>He said he would co-operate with any police inquiry but wanted
an independent inquiry that would be made public: "As far as
Unite's concerned we have done nothing wrong."</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68575000/jpg/_68575825_68575644.jpg"
                 alt="Len McCluskey"/>
               <p class="caption">Len McCluskey: "The way its been handled by the
Labour Party headquarters is nothing short of disgraceful"</p>
            </div>
            <p>The Conservatives said Mr Miliband should have acted sooner.</p>
            <p>A spokesman said: "This is followship, not leadership, from Ed
Miliband. Why didn't he refer Falkirk to the police days ago?"</p>
            <p>He added: "Will Ed Miliband now come clean, and admit that this
scandal goes wider than just Falkirk?</p>
            <p>"Unite have already admitted that they are targeting another 40
Labour selections, as Len McCluskey continues to take over the
Labour Party."</p>
            <p>But Mr Miliband told BBC political editor Nick Robinson the
party had acted "thoroughly and decisively" since allegations were
first raised in May, first suspending the selection process, then
holding its own inquiry and then referring the matter to the
police.</p>
            <p>He also rejected Mr McCluskey's suggestion that he was seeking
his own "Clause IV moment" - a "situation where [Labour leaders]
punch up union leaders" - saying he was acting "to uphold the
integrity of my party".</p>
            <p>The party has already stepped in to run the selection process in
Falkirk centrally, and has suspended the rules under which unions
could sign up members to Labour and pay the fees on their
behalf.</p>
            <p>On Thursday, Labour's general election co-ordinator Tom Watson,
whose office manager Karie Murphy was Unite's preferred candidate
in Falkirk, quit for the "future unity" of the party.</p>
            <p>Mr Watson told BBC Radio WM that he had been thinking about it
for a few months but the "fuss" about the Falkirk selection had
persuaded him it was time to move on.</p>
            <p>But he added: "I think David Cameron's portrayal of the
situation, that everyone is in hock to Len McCluskey, is just not
true."</p>
            <div id="slideshow_container_3a"
              class="slideshow-container storybody-halfwide-include">
               <div class="ss_slides">
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68564000/jpg/_68564213_edmiliband_afp.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Ed Miliband"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">Ed Miliband: In 2011, the Labour leader made Tom
Watson deputy chairman of the Labour Party and 2015 general
election co-ordinator, to oversee the selection of Labour
parliamentary candidates.</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68564000/jpg/_68564212_tomwatsonwide_getty.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Tom Watson"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">Tom Watson MP: The former union official resigned as
election co-ordinator over the Falkirk selection inquiry. He told
Mr Miliband he was also tired of the shadow cabinet
"merry-go-round". He has close ties to Unite's Len
McCluskey.</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68564000/jpg/_68564211_kariemurphy_pa.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Karie Murphy"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">Karie Murphy: Tom Watson's office manager and
Unite's preferred candidate for Falkirk. She has been suspended by
the party along with Falkirk party chairman Stephen
Deans.</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68564000/jpg/_68564891_lenmccluskey_getty.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Len McCluskey"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">Len McCluskey: Unite general secretary and Mr
Watson's former flat mate. He denies that Unite tried to sway the
selection by filling the local party with members. Unions had been
able to sign up members to the party and pay their
fees.</span>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="ss_controls">
                  <a href="#prev" class="ss_prev ss_button ss_button_disabled">
                     <span>previous
slide</span>
                  </a>
                  <a href="#next" class="ss_next ss_button ss_button_disabled">
                     <span>next
slide</span>
                  </a>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372947115094"
                  href="/news/uk-politics-23186851">Watson quits as Labour election
boss</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372956296003"
                  href="/news/uk-politics-23190269">Tom Watson resigns - Labour
bloodsports</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1333549004654"
                  href="/news/uk-politics-17591959">Profile: Len McCluskey, Unite
leader</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">Gary
O'Donoghue</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Chief political
correspondent, BBC Radio 4</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>There are a million questions still to be clarified about what
exactly went on in Falkirk, but there is no doubt that in sending
their evidence to the police, Ed Miliband and Labour have chosen to
escalate this row with Unite to a stratospheric level.</p>
            <p>Now it may be that he had little choice with political opponents
taking similar steps, nevertheless many in the unions will see this
as akin to turning in a family member.</p>
            <p>Nothing may come of it. There may be nothing to find.</p>
            <p>But if you were thinking that this was all shadow boxing up till
now, think again.</p>
            <p>It has without doubt become the biggest test of the Labour
leader's time in charge, and could define the party's future
relationship with the whole union movement.</p>
            <p>Who will blink first?</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
