<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-23234340"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Ed Miliband will promise to make politics more &#34;transparent and trusted&#34; by reforming Labour's relationship with unions after the Falkirk selection row."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-08T22:59:10"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68617000/jpg/_68617393_68617096.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Miliband urges union links overhaul"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Politics"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-23234340"/>
         <title>BBC News - Ed Miliband urges changes to Labour-union
links</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">8 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">23:59</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Ed Miliband urges changes to Labour-union
links</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68617000/jpg/_68617103_68617096.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Ed Miliband"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Ed Miliband will criticise union leaders for
encouraging "machine politics"</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Ed Miliband will
promise to make politics more "open, transparent and trusted" by
reforming Labour's relationship with trade unions.</p>
            <p>The party leader will pledge to abolish the automatic
"affiliation" fee paid by three million union members to
Labour.</p>
            <p>Mr Miliband will also say the selection of parliamentary
candidates should be widened, with the general public helping to
choose them.</p>
            <p>It follows a row with the Unite union over picking a candidate
in Falkirk.</p>
            <p>Unite, one of the party's biggest donors, is accused of signing
up its members to Labour in Falkirk - some without their knowledge
- in an effort to get its preferred candidate selected.</p>
            <p>The union's leader Len McCluskey denies people were recruited
without knowing about it, and says Unite worked within the
rules.</p>
            <p>In his speech on Tuesday, Mr Miliband will call for a system
which is "open, transparent and trusted - exactly the opposite of
the politics we saw in Falkirk. That was a politics closed, a
politics of the machine, a politics hated - and rightly so.</p>
            <p>"What we saw in Falkirk is part of the death throes of the old
politics. It is a symbol of what is wrong with politics. I want to
build a better Labour Party - and build a better politics for
Britain."</p>
            <p>He will call for an end to affiliation
fees - where members of supportive unions pay an automatic levy to
Labour unless they opt out - and instead involve only those who
"deliberately" choose to join the party.</p>
            <p>The fees are worth about Ã‚Â£8m a year to
Labour. Insiders estimate making them non-automatic would cost the
party about Ã‚Â£5m.</p>
            <p>Mr Miliband will say: "We need to do more, not less, to mobilise
individual trade union members to be part of our party: the three
million shop workers, nurses, engineers, bus drivers, construction
workers, people from the public and private sector, that are
affiliated to the Labour Party.</p>
            <p>"The problem is not that these ordinary working men and women
dominate the Labour Party. The problem is that they are not
properly part of all that we do. They are not members of local
parties; they are not active in our campaigns."</p>
            <p>The Labour leader will argue that unions should have political
funds "for all kinds of campaigns and activities as they choose"
but individual members should not pay Labour any fees "unless they
have deliberately chosen to do so".</p>
            <p>He will add: "I believe we need people to be able to make a more
active, individual, choice on whether they affiliate to the Labour
Party.</p>
            <p>"So we need to set a new direction in our relationship with
trade union members in which they choose to join Labour through the
affiliation fee: they would actively choose to be individually
affiliated members of the Labour Party and they would no longer be
automatically affiliated."</p>
            <p>This could raise the current Labour membership from the current
200,000 to a "far higher number", Mr Miliband will say.</p>
            <p>He will also promise to look at the idea of holding open
"primaries", where all adults, not just party members, can vote for
the selection of a candidate in their constituency.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68620000/jpg/_68620344_prescott.jpg"
                 alt="John Prescott"/>
               <p class="caption">Lord Prescott: "It is radical and
courageous"</p>
            </div>
            <p>He will say such a system will be used to select Labour's runner
for the London mayoralty in 2016.</p>
            <p>Mr Miliband will argue the party should impose a code of conduct
for those seeking selection and "strict" spending limits on them
and organisations backing them.</p>
            <p>There must also be "standard constituency agreements with trade
unions so that no-one can be subjected to undue local pressure", he
will say.</p>
            <p>An internal party inquiry found evidence Unite officials had
signed up new members without their knowledge, breaching party
rules, to try and get their favoured candidate elected. Mr
McCluskey has said he has "no trust" in the probe.</p>
            <p>Labour has insisted the episode is a one-off but said it showed
the need for wider reforms to candidate selection.</p>
            <p>The Conservatives have said Labour must publish the Falkirk
report and refuse to take any more money from the unions until an
entirely new system of funding is agreed.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373317795884"
                  href="/news/uk-politics-23234342">Will union plan get Miliband off the
hook?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373274959151"
                  href="/news/uk-politics-23224300">I won't meddle in union row -
Blair</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373192934944"
                  href="/news/uk-politics-23217088">Harman: Falkirk problems a
one-off</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">This speech is designed to get Mr Miliband
off the hook of a row that has caused him real damage”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <div class="correspondent-byline">
               <a href="/news/correspondents/nickrobinson/">
                  <span class="byline-picture">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/53409000/jpg/_53409465_robinson-112x81.jpg"
                       alt="image of Nick Robinson"/>
                  </span>
               </a>
               <a href="/news/correspondents/nickrobinson/">
                  <span class="byline-name">Nick
Robinson</span>
               </a>
               <span class="byline-title">Political
editor</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/correspondents/nickrobinson/">Read more from
Nick</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
