<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-23122628"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg says he would not take any big pay rise for MPs, as speculation grows that a big increase is to be recommended."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T15:41:21"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68478000/jpg/_68478019_68466389.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Clegg: I wouldn't take MP pay rise"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Politics"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-23122628"/>
         <title>BBC News - Nick Clegg: I wouldn't take pay rise for
MPs</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">16:41</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Nick Clegg: I wouldn't take pay rise for
MPs</h1>
            <div class="has-icon-comment dna-comment-count-simple"> </div>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68476000/jpg/_68476525_68466389.jpg"
                 alt="Nick Clegg"/>
               <p class="caption">Nick Clegg: "It would be impossible to explain
to the public why MPs should be treated so differently"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Deputy Prime
Minister Nick Clegg has said he would not take a big pay rise even
if one is recommended for MPs.</p>
            <p>He said people whose living standards were being "remorselessly
squeezed" would find a big rise for MPs "impossible to
understand".</p>
            <p>The Independent Parliamentary Standards Authority is expected to
say backbench MPs' Ã‚Â£66,000 salaries should
increase to more than Ã‚Â£70,000 from the
election.</p>
            <p>Prime Minister David Cameron has said such a plan would be
"unthinkable".</p>
            <p>But the BBC's Nick Robinson said the PM could not block the
recommendations and advisers had warned him MPs would reject any
bid to do so in the Commons.</p>
            <p>The BBC's political editor added that the Independent
Parliamentary Standards Authority's (Ipsa) recommendation would be
"likely to cause outrage from voters at a time when there is
significant pay restraint in the public and private sectors".</p>
            <p>Ipsa, which was set up as an independent body to regulate MPs'
pay and pensions in the wake of the expenses scandal, is expected
to announce its initial recommendations later this month.</p>
            <p>MPs and members of the public will be
able to take part in a consultation before Ipsa publishes its final
plans - expected in the autumn - which would then come into force
without the need for further legislation.</p>
            <p>Reports in several newspapers this weekend suggest its initial
recommendations will call for a rise of about 15% in the basic
salary of a backbench MP from Ã‚Â£66,396 to a
sum closer to Ã‚Â£75,000. MPs would, however,
have to pay much higher contributions towards their pensions.</p>
            <p>Asked about the reports of a proposed pay rise for MPs, Mr
Clegg, the Lib Dem leader, said the recommendations were a matter
for Ipsa and for MPs to decide themselves whether or not to take
any rise.</p>
            <p>Speaking in Pakistan, Mr Cameron said he did not know what Ipsa
would say but added: "Whatever Ipsa recommends, we can't see the
cost of politics or Westminster going up. We should see the cost of
Westminster go down.</p>
            <p>"Anything would be unthinkable unless the cost of politics was
frozen and cut, so I'll wait and see what Ipsa have to say. What I
said to Ipsa was that restraint is necessary."</p>
            <p>The government could propose a motion calling for Ipsa's
recommendations to be ignored, but Nick Robinson said this could
"undermine the independence of the new system" and would be
unlikely to win enough support from MPs.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68474000/jpg/_68474026_68474025.jpg"
                 alt="Keith Vaz"/>
               <p class="caption">Keith Vaz MP: "This has always been a point of
contention"</p>
            </div>
            <p>And <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2351736/Miliband-Ill-scrap-MPs-10-000-pay-rise.html">
the Mail on Sunday reported that a source close to Labour leader Ed
Miliband had said:</a> "We will view any rise for MPs in the light
of the current climate of economic austerity.</p>
            <p>"It has to be seen in the context of the decision to limit
public sector workers' pay increases to 1% and the fact that some
private sector workers have had their pay cut."</p>
            <p>The Commons voted against a 1% pay rise in 2011 and last year
agreed to extend the pay freeze into 2013. MPs' salaries are due to
rise to Ã‚Â£67,060 from April 2014.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68489000/gif/_68489420_mp_salary_comparison3.gif"
                 width="464"
                 height="310"
                 alt="Public sector salary comparison"/>
            </div>
            <p>In an anonymous online survey of 100 MPs conducted for Ipsa -
the results of which were published in January - 69% said they were
underpaid. The average level suggested for the appropriate level of
pay was Ã‚Â£86,250.</p>
            <p>Former Labour minister and chairman of the Home Affairs select
committee Keith Vaz: "The last thing on earth MPs should be talking
about is their own pay."</p>
            <p>Former children's minister and Tory MP
Tim Loughton: "This isn't going to happen. It would be completely
inappropriate for us to accept it at the moment. It sends the wrong
message to the rest of the country going through a tough time."</p>
            <p>Matthew Sinclair, of the Taxpayers' Alliance, which campaigns
for lower taxes, said there would be public outrage should the
rises go ahead.</p>
            <p>He said: "MPs are already very well paid both in terms of
European politicians and the average salary in this country.</p>
            <p>"It would be particularly egregious for politicians to be handed
a whopping great pay rise while hard-pressed taxpayers tighten
their own belts."</p>
            <p>Former Labour minister Tom Harris called for Ipsa to be
abolished and MPs to be given the final say on issues of
parliamentary pay and expenses.</p>
            <p>"If we're going to get the blame for rises in our salary, we
might as well take the responsibility too," he wrote <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/politics/10152505/Ipsa-was-a-colossal-mistake-MPs-should-take-back-control-of-our-pay.html">
in the Daily Telegraph</a>. "The complaints will continue, but at
least they'll be aimed at the right people.<strong>"</strong>
            </p>
            <p>And he suggested efforts to cut the "cost of politics" were
futile. "Running a modern parliament in the 21st Century costs
money. And if it doesn't, you're not doing it right."</p>
            <p>MPs are paid more than their counterparts in Spain and France
but less than legislators in the Republic of Ireland, Germany and
Italy. An Ipsa study in 2012 found the mean average for pay across
major democracies was just over
Ã‚Â£86,000.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372632142778"
                  href="/news/uk-politics-23122630">PM told he can't stop MPs' pay
rise</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1357836662765"
                  href="/news/uk-politics-20978487">MPs call for a '32% pay rise'</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">What must have seemed a good idea at the
time of the MPs' expenses scandal is now giving the prime minister
a political migraine”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <div class="correspondent-byline">
               <a href="/news/correspondents/nickrobinson/">
                  <span class="byline-picture">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/53409000/jpg/_53409465_robinson-112x81.jpg"
                       alt="image of Nick Robinson"/>
                  </span>
               </a>
               <a href="/news/correspondents/nickrobinson/">
                  <span class="byline-name">Nick
Robinson</span>
               </a>
               <span class="byline-title">Political
editor</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/correspondents/nickrobinson/">Read more from
Nick</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Running a modern parliament in the 21st
Century costs money”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Tom Harris</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Labour MP</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
