<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-wales-23199905"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A report written 17 years ago, which has finally been published, identifies &#34;extensive&#34; abuse at children's homes in north Wales in the 1970s and 1980s."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-08T10:19:18"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68569000/jpg/_68569376_8twp8jto.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="'Extensive' abuse at care homes"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="Wales"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-wales-23199905"/>
         <title>BBC News - Jillings report: 'Extensive' abuse at children's
homes</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">8 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">11:19</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Jillings report: 'Extensive' abuse at
children's homes</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68600000/jpg/_68600598_8twp8jto.jpg"
                 alt="Bryn Estyn care home in North Wales in 1992"/>
               <p class="caption">John Jillings says some of the treatment was
'bestial'</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A report written 17
years ago, has finally been published, identifying long-term
"extensive" abuse at children's homes in north Wales during the
1970s and 1980s.</p>
            <p>Abuse allegations at several children's homes, including the
former Bryn Estyn home in Wrexham, emerged in the 1990s.</p>
            <p>An inquiry by <a href="http://7acdffdc682396080ae6-df8bc385e018ac757acdd54508ce5af3.r63.cf3.rackcdn.com/jillings-redacted_part1of2.pdf">
John Jillings</a> was carried out in 1996 but later shelved.</p>
            <p>In response, a joint statement from the councils in north Wales
said the safety of children was a priority.</p>
            <p>The report found:</p>
            <ul>
               <li>Extensive abuse of children over a substantial number of
years</li>
               <li>Children had been severely disturbed by the abuse</li>
               <li>At least 12 children had died</li>
               <li>Responses to reports children had been abused were "too little
and too late"</li>
               <li>Five men working at Bryn Estyn were convicted of serious
offences involving 20 boys and five girls aged 10-16</li>
               <li>Investigating panel were hindered by serious constraints</li>
               <li>There was a "lack of clarity" over accessibility of social
services files and police material</li>
               <li>Report panel considered abandoning the investigation</li>
               <li>Some staff refused to meet investigating panel</li>
               <li>It was not known how many statements made were handed to
CPS</li>
               <li>It was not known how many alleged perpetrators, including
police officers, were named in the statements</li>
               <li>An earlier report into abuse at another home was shelved after
concerns over prejudicing a prosecution and insurance worries</li>
               <li>The report urged a public judicial inquiry</li>
            </ul>
            <p>The 300-page report was initially written in 1996 after it was
commissioned by the former Clwyd County Council, which covered the
areas now represented by Flintshire, Denbighshire and Wrexham
councils.</p>
            <p>It had followed North Wales Police's investigation into abuse
claims in 1991 and the conviction of seven former care workers.</p>
            <p>But as more claims of widespread abuse in almost 40 homes
emerged, the former Clwyd County Council commissioned Mr Jillings
in March 1994 to investigate.</p>
            <p>However, it was never published.</p>
            <p>Mr Jillings, a former director of social services for
Derbyshire, said the council was worried about costly insurance
claims and his report never saw the light of day.</p>
            <p>A redacted [edited] version of the report was finally made
public and published online on Monday following a Freedom of
Information (FoI) request by BBC Wales.</p>
            <p>The report said: "Our investigations have led us to conclude
that the abuse of children and young people in Clwyd residential
units has been extensive, and has taken place over a substantial
number of years."</p>
            <p>It added: "It is clear that, in a significant number of cases,
the lives of young people who have been through the care system in
Clwyd have been severely disrupted and disturbed. At least 12 young
people are dead."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68602000/jpg/_68602040_jillings.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Jillings report"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Sections of the Jillings report were
redacted</span>
            </div>
            <p>The report said of "the many statements" taken, "it is unclear
how many were forwarded to the Crown Prosecution Service [CPS] for
consideration", and "it is also unclear how many other
professionals, including police officers, were named in these
statements as perpetrators of assaults".</p>
            <p>However, the panel concluded they could not hope to address
successfully the wider areas of concern, including that public
figures had been involved in the abuse.</p>
            <p>The report had "frank criticism" for individuals at the council
as well as "aspects of policy and practice," but said they
"nevertheless respect the authority for its determination to
examine what went wrong".</p>
            <p>It said that "the most striking fact to emerge is that five men
who shared in common their employment as residential care workers
at Bryn Estyn were convicted of serious offences involving at least
24 young people."</p>
            <p>According to the Jillings report, another inquiry into abuse at
the Cartrefle children's home was not published because of CPS
concerns it may prejudice a prosecution, as well as concerns over
insurance.</p>
            <p>Summarising, the report said: "Our findings show that time and
again the response to indications that children may have been
abused has been too little and too late.</p>
            <p>"Furthermore the needs and interests of children and young
people have tended to be an incidental, rather than a primary
concern."</p>
            <p>The report urged a public judicial inquiry, and says that the
former residents who made complaints "did not appear to be
motivated out of a desire for financial recompense" and "the
motivation appeared to be a genuine desire to see the situation
improved for children in care".</p>
            <p>It said Clwyd council was particularly vulnerable to criticism
because the local authority was about to cease under a
re-structuring of councils.</p>
            <p>The report went on to say that other
agencies, such as health, education, probation, North Wales Police
and the Welsh Office "require similarly careful and detailed
scrutiny" to put more effective safeguards in place.</p>
            <p>Following the publication of the report, a <a href="http://www.wrexham.gov.uk/english/council/news/jillings.htm">joint
statement from the north Wales councils</a> was released.</p>
            <p>It said: "The North Wales Councils recognise that the release of
the report may bring distress to those affected by historic abuse
and they encourage anyone who is affected by its release to call
one of the numbers below if they need support.</p>
            <p>"All councils have and will continue to support anyone affected
by abuse.</p>
            <p>"In North Wales, the safeguarding of children and young people
is a high priority for today's councils."</p>
            <p>The Jillings inquiry was followed by another investigation by
the late Sir Ronald Waterhouse, which took four years to
complete.</p>
            <p>Sir Ronald found there had been "appalling mistreatment" of
children over a period of 20 years.</p>
            <p>He had gathered evidence from 650 people, with most allegations
focusing on seven homes.</p>
            <p>Last year the scandal re-emerged after a victim claimed the
Waterhouse report in 2000 had not uncovered the full scale of the
abuse.</p>
            <p>Home Secretary Theresa May then launched a new police inquiry
into the abuse allegations.</p>
            <p>And Clwyd council's successor authorities such as Flintshire
County Council and Wrexham County Borough Council began searching
their archives for a copy of that report.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1352226547477"
                  href="/news/uk-20218054">Q&amp;A: North Wales abuse scandal</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1352383964162"
                  href="/news/uk-wales-20251861">'Publish child abuse report' -
MP</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1352227068533"
                  href="/news/uk-wales-politics-20222521">Child abuse: Getting to the
truth</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">The most striking fact to emerge is that
five men who shared in common their employment as residential care
workers at Bryn Estyn were convicted of serious offences
”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Jillings Report</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Separate abuse inquiries</h2>
            <p>In April, <strong>Operation Pallial,</strong> an independent
investigation examining claims of historical child abuse at
children's homes in north Wales found "significant evidence of
systemic and serious sexual and physical abuse".</p>
            <p>Investigators found evidence of 140 allegations of historical
abuse between 1963 and 1992.</p>
            <p>76 new complainants came forward and 84 suspected offenders were
named.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>A separate review by Mrs Justice Macur</strong> is
investigating the terms of the Waterhouse abuse inquiry, which took
place between 1996 and 2000.</p>
            <p>The inquiries followed a victim's claims that Sir Ronald
Waterhouse uncovered only a fraction of the abuse.</p>
            <p>Those claims surfaced in the wake of the Jimmy Savile
scandal.</p>
            <p>Home Secretary Theresa May ordered Operation Pallial following a
Newsnight report last November which - as well as leading to a Tory
peer being falsely accused of paedophilia - alleged that child
abuse in north Wales from the 1970s was more widespread than
reported.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
