<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-23222502"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Nasrun Mir meets Parvez Rasool, first Kashmiri Muslim cricketer to play for India."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-09T01:37:48"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68602000/jpg/_68602073_picturesofkashmiricricketerparvezrasool(13).jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Parvez Rasool: First Kashmiri Muslim cricketer to play for India"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia/India"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-23222502"/>
         <title>BBC News - Parvez Rasool: First Kashmiri Muslim cricketer to
play for India</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">9 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:37</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Parvez Rasool: First Kashmiri Muslim
cricketer to play for India</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Nasrun Mir</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Srinagar</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68602000/jpg/_68602027_picturesofkashmiricricketerparvezrasool(10).jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="300"
                 alt="Parvez Rasool"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Parvez Rasool has been one of the top wicket takers
for Jammu and Kashmir</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">"I find it difficult
to answer when people ask me questions which are political and have
nothing to do with my cricket," says Parvez Rasool.</p>
            <p>Last week, the 24-year-old spinning all-rounder became the first
Muslim cricketer from Indian-administered Kashmir to be selected
for the national team. He earned a call-up for the forthcoming
one-day series against Zimbabwe, beginning on 26 July.</p>
            <p>Rasool has kept his mobile phone mostly switched off ever since
his selection last week as people call him to ask him about his
political beliefs, ideology, and playing for India.</p>
            <p>Kashmir, claimed by both India and Pakistan, has seen an armed
insurgency against Indian rule since 1989.</p>
            <p>Only two international cricket matches have ever been staged in
Indian-administered Kashmir - the cricket pitch was dug up by some
angry locals during the second match against West Indies in 1983.
The home side were booed by supporters of the separatist cause and
lost the game.</p>
            <p>Most cricket fans in the troubled Muslim-dominated valley have
traditionally supported the opposition in cricket matches involving
India.</p>
            <p>"May Rasool perform well, but be on the losing side,
particularly if he plays against Pakistan," says Tariq, a shop
owner from Rasool's native village of Bijbehara, some 44km (27
miles) south of the summer capital, Srinagar.</p>
            <p>Kapil Dev, who captained India during the 1983 match in
Srinagar, however, believes that Rasool's inclusion in the national
team will be a boost to Kashmir.</p>
            <p>"Kashmir has suffered a lot in the last 20 years and hopefully
Rasool's story is the brighter side of things to come," he told the
BBC.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68602000/jpg/_68602034_picturesofkashmiricricketerparvezrasool(3).jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="300"
                 alt="Parvez Rasool"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Rasool has been feted by local people and the
government after his selection</span>
            </div>
            <p>"Players from smaller cities have been dominating Indian cricket
for a decade now. Like [Indian cricket captain] Mahendra Singh
Dhoni was the first from [the eastern city of] Ranchi to play for
and lead India, I hope Rasool repeats [a similar feat] for Jammu
and Kashmir."</p>
            <p>Rasool has already made his mark.</p>
            <p>In the 2012-13 domestic season, he took 33 wickets and scored
549 runs, including two centuries. He was the top scorer and
highest wicket taker for the Jammu and Kashmir team, and the third
highest wicket taking spinner of the season.</p>
            <p>And if this was not all, Rasool also picked up seven wickets
against Australia in a warm up game in February. He was also the
first Kashmiri Muslim to play in the lucrative Indian Premier
League (IPL) tournament, turning up for the Pune Warriors team.</p>
            <p>"His ability to bowl orthodox off spin is his strength. He is a
good all-rounder. He has got a chance in Zimbabwe to do justice
with his talent," says Indian spin legend Bishen Singh Bedi, who
played 67 Test matches for India and picked up 266 wickets.</p>
            <p>Rasool's journey to the national team has been chequered.</p>
            <p>When he was selected for the India A team earlier this tear,
some media reports alleged that the selection was influenced by a
"political motive to bring the people of Kashmir closer to
India".</p>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68602000/jpg/_68602067_picturesofkashmiricricketerparvezrasool(8).jpg"
                 width="224"
                 height="299"
                 alt="Parvez Rasool"/>
               <span style="width:224px;">Rasool is an all-rounder</span>
            </div>
            <p>Omar Abdullah, Chief Minister of Indian-administered Kashmir,
reacted angrily on Twitter, saying such reports were "insulting to
Parvez and his entire life-long effort" and also to the "people of
Kashmir who don't need artificially created icons".</p>
            <p>In 2009, while travelling with the under-22 team, he was
detained at the airport in the southern city of Bangalore for
allegedly carrying explosives in his kitbag.</p>
            <p>Abdul Qayoom Bagow, the team's coach, says it all began after
Rasool and another member of the team objected to sniffer dogs
searching their cricket kit. Both the players, he said, were
carrying the Holy Quran in their bags. They were let off after
questioning.</p>
            <p>As an 11-year-old, Rasool aspired to bat and keep wickets,
remembers Bagow.</p>
            <p>"After seeing him bowl, however, I asked him to practise the art
of spin bowling. The best thing about Rasool is he always listens,"
says Bagow.</p>
            <p>Rasool's father, Ghulam Rasool, a retired government worker,
says he "never thought" of making an international cricketer out of
his son and wanted to keep him away from the violent politics of
the troubled valley.</p>
            <p>"I don't want to talk politics. Some people do politics, some
read books and some play sports. My son is a cricketer and not a
politician. I want people to understand it," he says.</p>
            <p>Rasool says he is working hard to earn a regular place in the
Indian squad.</p>
            <p>"It is a proud feat for me to play at the highest level of the
game for India."</p>
            <p>
               <em>Nasrun Mir is an independent journalist based in
Srinagar</em>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1322657127391"
                  href="/news/world-asia-india-15963873">Kashmir 'pitch diggers'
acquitted</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
