<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23118403"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Israeli-Palestinian peace negotiations could be &#34;within reach with a little more work&#34;, says the US secretary of state after three days of talks."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-30T12:09:56"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68464000/jpg/_68464584_68463572.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Mid-East talks 'within reach' - US"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23118403"/>
         <title>BBC News - Mid-East talks 'within reach' - US secretary of
state</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">30 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">13:09</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Mid-East talks 'within reach' - US
secretary of state</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68466000/jpg/_68466505_018495231.jpg"
                 alt="US Secretary of State John Kerry"/>
               <p class="caption">US Secretary of State John Kerry: "We started
out with very wide gaps, and we have narrowed those
considerably"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The US secretary of
state has said final-status Israeli-Palestinian peace negotiations
could be "within reach... with a little more work".</p>
            <p>John Kerry extended his peace mission on Saturday, cancelling a
scheduled trip to Abu Dhabi.</p>
            <p>For three days he has shuttled between Palestinian President
Mahmoud Abbas and Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu.</p>
            <p>But Palestinian negotiator Saeb Erekat said there had been no
breakthrough.</p>
            <p>He said the latest meeting had been "positive and profound", but
"there is still a gap between the Palestinian and Israeli
positions".</p>
            <p>"I'm pleased to tell you that we have made real progress on this
trip," Mr Kerry told reporters in Tel Aviv, before leaving the
region.</p>
            <p>"And I believe that with a little more work, the start of
final-status negotiations could be within reach. We started out
with very wide gaps, and we have narrowed those considerably."</p>
            <p>"We made progress in every sector," he
went on to say.</p>
            <p>He said he was reluctant to leave and was "leaving people
behind" to continue to try to secure the basis for discussions, and
that both sides had asked him to return to the region soon.</p>
            <p>The main stumbling block to talks has been disagreement over the
issue of Israeli settlement-building in the West Bank, which the
Palestinians want frozen as a precondition to talks. However,
speaking at the start of Sunday's weekly cabinet meeting, Mr
Netanyahu insisted that Israel was not blocking a return to
negotiations.</p>
            <p>"We are not putting up any impediments on the resumption of the
permanent talks for a peace agreement between us and the
Palestinians," he said in remarks quoted by AFP news agency.</p>
            <p>"There are things that we will strongly insist on in the talks
themselves, especially security... there will be no agreement that
will endanger Israelis' security."</p>
            <p>Among other issues, Mr Abbas is said to be pushing Israel to
release the longest-serving Palestinian prisoners.</p>
            <p>Two decades of on-off negotiations between Israel and the
Palestinian Authority (PA) have failed to produce a permanent
settlement, with the latest round of direct negotiations breaking
down in 2010.</p>
            <p>Mr Kerry is on his fifth visit to the region since taking office
in February.</p>
            <p>He is offering the Palestinians the incentive of a major
investment plan, but it is dependent on progress towards a peace
deal.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/in_depth/middle_east/2001/israel_and_the_palestinians/default.stm">
Mid-East crisis</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372407527581"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23081781">'Economic peace'</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1363903688107"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-21886557">Frank words from Obama in
Israel</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1363842975825"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-21850739">Ending the deadlock</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1363880475605"
                     href="/news/world-21877968">Press sees little point in visit</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/55356000/jpg/_55356845_001398161-1.jpg"
                    alt="image of Quentin Sommerville"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Quentin Sommerville</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News, Jerusalem</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>There was an expectation - or perhaps just a hope - that John
Kerry would be able to announce something concrete after his fifth
visit here. There were even rumours of summit, to be held in Amman
at the end of the week.</p>
            <p>As he left, the US secretary of state said talks were "within
reach", but negotiators said privately that there was much to keep
them from easy grasp. And that's despite Mr Kerry having three
meetings each with the Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu
and Palestinian President Mahmoud Abbas in as many days.</p>
            <p>The release of Palestinian prisoners, and the development of
Israeli settlements on the occupied West Bank remain the key
stumbling blocks. Palestinian negotiators, who, in recent days,
were playing down talk of an imminent summit agreement, insist that
Israel must meet its obligations from previous negotiations; Israel
views these demands as preconditions to talks. On these key issues
the two sides don't appear to be any closer.</p>
            <p>Undeterred, Mr Kerry will be back soon - for his sixth trip -
and will attempt to make good on his claim that only a "little more
work" is required to start negotiations.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
