<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23218612"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="People in northern Africa are conflicted over what to make of recent events and the turmoil gripping Egypt, the Arab World's powerhouse, says the BBC's Rana Jawad."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-07T14:34:48"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68594000/jpg/_68594796_68594132.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Tunisia and Libya divided over Morsi ousting"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Africa"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23218612"/>
         <title>BBC News - Tunisia and Libya divided over Morsi
ousting</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">7 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">15:34</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Tunisia and Libya divided over Morsi
ousting</h1>
            <span class="byline byline-photo">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/48807000/jpg/_48807738_007100730.jpg"
                 alt="Rana Jawad"/>
               <span class="byline-name">By Rana Jawad</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News, Cairo</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68594000/jpg/_68594792_68594132.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="A boy holds a sign that reads: &#34;Do not take power with you, Brotherhood&#34; as protesters wave the Libyan flag during a demonstration against the Muslim Brotherhood for interfering in local politics, in Benghazi, Libya, 10 May 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Libyan protesters have rallied against
the Muslim Brotherhood in recent months</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">People in northern
Africa are conflicted over what to make of recent events and the
turmoil gripping the Arab world's powerhouse - Egypt.</p>
            <p>Over in Libya, for the past year-and-a half, I have watched a
young population go from being relatively polite about the Muslim
Brotherhood to being emphatically hostile in their rhetoric against
them.</p>
            <p>Libyans who did not vote for the Islamists have grown equally
suspicious of their intentions in the long-term: They welcomed the
toppling of President Mohammed Morsi.</p>
            <p>I have heard many Libyans claim they need a "second revolution"
in the past year.</p>
            <p>But when Libyans talk like this, you cannot help but wonder who
they will revolt against - they do not have a central figure to get
rid of and no army to speak of.</p>
            <p>They are currently largely unhappy with the legislative body -
the General National Congress they elected more than a year ago -
as well as more brigades and militias than they can count.</p>
            <p>Following the ousting of Mr Morsi, Ibrahim, a Libyan activist
who stood in front of the courts of Benghazi protesting against
Colonel Gaddafi's rule in 2011, says simply: "What happened in
Egypt will happen in Libya."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68401000/jpg/_68401280_tripolidemo.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Pro-government demonstrators rally against violence in Tripoli, May 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Post-revolution Libya has seen
pro-government protests against violence</span>
            </div>
            <p>He does not see the army's intervention in neighbouring Egypt as
a coup.</p>
            <p>"They did it to protect the will of the people," he tells the
BBC in a telephone interview from Benghazi.</p>
            <p>Hanna Ghallal, a lawyer from the birthplace of Libya's
revolution, sees both sides of the coin in Egypt.</p>
            <p>As an activist she feels Egyptians stood against Mr Morsi "for
dignity and real democracy, because that doesn't stop at the ballot
box".</p>
            <p>But as a woman of the law she does not think the army's
intervention was a good idea because "now they are part of the
conflict, and the army should be impartial".</p>
            <p>Ibrahim and Hanna agree on one thing, though - they now see an
ideologically divided Egypt on the brink of civil strife that could
spread to their side of the border.</p>
            <p>"If Egypt is de-stabilized, imagine what will happen in Libya,"
says Ms Ghallal. "We depend on them for our shared border security,
because we have no army to do the job for starters."</p>
            <p>Further west, Tunisians have already taken it a step further:
they seem to have emulated Egypt and started their own Tamarod
("rebellion") campaign like the one created by young Egyptian
activists who managed to rally millions of people to the streets
after months of campaigning.</p>
            <p>Taieb Moalla, a local Tunisian correspondent for a French
newspaper and a long-time opponent of his country's deposed leader,
is perplexed by recent events.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/65770000/jpg/_65770043_65770042.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Tunisian protesters shout slogans during a demonstration after the death of opposition leader Chokri Belaid (pictured on flag), outside the Interior ministry in Tunis on 6 February 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">As Tunisians know, revolutions are
followed by a period of turmoil and confusion over what to do
next</span>
            </div>
            <p>"The situation is not clear," he tells me from Tunis. "It used
to be clear and easy but now it isn't."</p>
            <p>Although Mr Moalla does not see the ousting of Mr Morsi as a
coup in the traditional sense - because millions supported the
army's move - he does not believe the army intervened for
democracy, or to protect the people.</p>
            <p>"There are signs of a civil war," he says. "It's possible
because [the ousting] will make Morsi more popular amongst his
supporters and could further radicalize the Muslim
Brotherhood."</p>
            <p>Although Tunisia's elections also ushered in a moderate Islamist
party - Ennahda - which has caused some limited unease, Mr Moalla
does not envision a repeat of what happened in Egypt in his own
country.</p>
            <p>"Unlike Egypt, our army has no tradition of being politically
involved, we did not have any leaders with a military background,"
he says.</p>
            <p>"Ennahda have also been more reconciliatory in power - there is
a coalition government here. They [Ennahda] were smart because they
understood that they cannot govern alone."</p>
            <p>This is ultimately where Egypt's ousted president failed.</p>
            <p>Revolutions are inextricably linked with a romantic notion of
profound change.</p>
            <p>In reality, they are followed by a period of turmoil and
confusion over what to do next, how to do it and who the best
person is for that task.</p>
            <p>In these three countries, the revolutions have also come with
the rise of political Islam. How all these elements are dealt with
will determine how smooth the transition is.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12315833">Egypt in
crisis</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373156235629"
                     href="/news/magazine-23199377">Shifting sands</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373146727395"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23214054">What now for
Brotherhood?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373020716781"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23197801">Failed experiment</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373067054933"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23205101">Two years in Tahrir
Square</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
