<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23181510"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The BBC's Irene Caselli reports from the Petare slum near Venezuela's capital, where troops have been deployed to fight crime."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-05T00:50:27"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68554000/jpg/_68554548_68554541.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Crime-fighting in Venezuela's toughest slum"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Latin America"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23181510"/>
         <title>BBC News - Fighting crime in Petare, Venezuela's toughest
slum</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">5 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:50</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Fighting crime in Petare, Venezuela's
toughest slum</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Irene
Caselli</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News,
Caracas</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68552000/jpg/_68552002_006.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Soldiers and police in Petare"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">When Venezuela
decided to use the army to fight violent crime, it deployed troops
to the slum of Petare. It is known as one of Venezuela's most
violent areas, but change may finally be coming.</p>
            <p>Carlos was 13 years old when he got involved in crime. Like many
other youths in Petare, Carlos did it because he felt he had no
other option to get what he wanted.</p>
            <p>"I started by stealing," he says. "We would assault people
coming home with their groceries, and we would take everything away
from them. I did it because I wanted a motorbike and there was no
money at home."</p>
            <p>Carlos does not go into details when he explains what crimes he
committed, but now, at the age of 30, he considers himself
lucky.</p>
            <p>"There used to be 16 of us working in the streets. Only three of
us are still alive," he says.</p>
            <p>In places like Petare, young people are the main victims of
crime, and the main perpetrators. They are not involved in
well-established gangs like those in Central America, but they are
organised into small groups that fight for the control of the
territory and of drug sales.</p>
            <p>Being murdered is their biggest risk.</p>
            <p>The United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC) <a href="http://www.unodc.org/documents/data-and-analysis/statistics/Homicide/Globa_study_on_homicide_2011_web.pdf">
labels Venezuela</a> as the country with the fifth-highest murder
rate in the world.</p>
            <p>In response to what has become one of the main worries for
Venezuelans, President Nicolas Maduro has sent soldiers to the
streets to control crime.</p>
            <p>Petare, the city's largest slum that grew on the steep hills
overlooking eastern Caracas, was one of the first places where the
army was deployed as part of the Safe Homeland initiative.</p>
            <p>Soldiers now collaborate with policemen and have set up
checkpoints throughout the neighbourhood.</p>
            <p>Authorities say that since the launch on 13 May, homicides have
gone down by 38% and thefts by 34%.</p>
            <p>"The main aim is for people to feel truly safe and to feel that
we're working for them," says Gen Marco Rojas, vice-minister of
citizen security.</p>
            <p>"This is a not a punitive plan, this is a plan with a very high
social component."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68552000/jpg/_68552088_basketball.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Basketball players in Petare"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The government is promoting sport in its
fight against crime</span>
            </div>
            <p>Representatives of the armed forces have held meetings with
members of the community in recent weeks to hear their needs.</p>
            <p>In Petare, these meetings have been held in pro-government
centres.</p>
            <p>One of them is the Nucleo Antonio Jose de
Sucre, a community centre with large graffiti of President Hugo
Chavez, who died of cancer in March after 14 years in power.</p>
            <p>Keyla de las Rosas, one of the organisers, says she feels more
protected now that the army is active.</p>
            <p>"It's an important grain of sand," she says.</p>
            <p>But critics say the initiative does not represent a shift from
previous security policies carried out by the government.</p>
            <p>Since 1999, the government has implemented 19 security plans,
says Roberto Briceno of the Venezuelan Violence Observatory
(OVV).</p>
            <p>He says murder rates have either doubled or tripled, depending
on which figures are used.</p>
            <p>The OVV collects data from seven universities across Venezuela,
and says murder figures are much higher than government figures
suggest.</p>
            <p>After years of not disclosing murder rates, this year Mr Maduro
said that there were 16,000 murders in 2012. But the OVV says there
were more than 21,000, a record high for Venezuela, which has a
population of 29 million.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68554000/jpg/_68554058_hi017738163.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Venezuelans queue to vote, April file picture"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Nicolas Maduro waged a high-profile campaign for
votes in Petare...</span>
            </div>
            <p>Analysts say the high levels of violence are due to a
combination of factors.</p>
            <p>Some internal factors include corruption among the security
forces, a huge number of weapons available thanks to weak
gun-control laws and high levels of impunity, according to
InsightCrime, a think-tank that researches organised crime in Latin
America.</p>
            <p>When it comes to the wider context, Venezuela has become a
transit point for drug gangs smuggling cocaine from neighbouring
Colombia.</p>
            <p>Mr Briceno says the most worrying aspect of the increasing level
of violence is that the government lacks a coherent security policy
and gives mixed messages.</p>
            <p>He says there has been some progress since Mr Maduro took over
as president in April.</p>
            <p>Mr Maduro made security a priority and deployed the army to the
streets. Thanks to his initiative, the National Assembly approved a
much-awaited disarmament law.</p>
            <p>He also implemented plans to use sport to promote peace.</p>
            <p>But at the same time, he announced the creation of armed,
military-trained pro-government forces known as "workers' militias"
to supplement existing militias founded by Mr Chavez.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68554000/jpg/_68554065_68554061.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Supporters of Venezuelan opposition presidential candidate Henrique Capriles have a poster with his picture at their home in the Petare slum in Caracas on April 13"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">...but his rival Henrique Capriles
controls the province</span>
            </div>
            <p>"There is a difference between the logic of citizen security and
a logic of war," says Mr Briceno.</p>
            <p>"In order to make progress, we need to create a professional
police force, not one that is partisan and backs the
government."</p>
            <p>He says that this is especially important in the current context
of polarisation following the 14 April election, when opposition
leader Henrique Capriles lost by a narrow margin and alleged
electoral fraud.</p>
            <p>Even when it comes to security policy, political divisions are
clear in Petare, which lies in Miranda state, governed by Mr
Capriles. The mayor overseeing Petare is also from the
opposition.</p>
            <p>The government has blamed the high crime statistics on the
opposition, while the opposition says the government has withdrawn
funds from the local police force.</p>
            <p>Youths like Carlos say they are clear as to why crime
proliferates.</p>
            <p>"The economic needs, the lack of access to education," he says.
"The only way we had to get access was by stealing and joining
criminal gangs."</p>
            <p>Carlos left crime behind and has helped set up an organisation
that aims to get more young people out of criminality by giving
them material support as well as educational and psychological
help.</p>
            <p>The organisation, called El Hampa Quiere Cambiar (roughly
translated as "Crime wants to change"), is looking for financial
aid from the government.</p>
            <p>Carlos is unconvinced about the army effectiveness in fighting
crime, but he does not think it is necessarily a bad move.</p>
            <p>"It is a different approach," he says. "We do our work, they do
theirs."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1365998269263"
                  href="/news/world-latin-america-22149202">Chavez heir wins Venezuela
election</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1341100340992"
                  href="/news/world-latin-america-18591390">Venezuela and
violence</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1325099027408"
                  href="/news/world-latin-america-16349118">Venezuela 'highest murder
rate'</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>World's murder capitals</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Honduras - <strong>82.1</strong> (murders per 100,000 people
each year)</li>
               <li>El Salvador - <strong>66</strong>
               </li>
               <li>Ivory coast - <strong>56.9</strong>
               </li>
               <li>Jamaica - <strong>52.1</strong>
               </li>
               <li>Venezuela - <strong>49</strong>
               </li>
               <li>Guatemala - <strong>41.4</strong>
               </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <em>Source: UNODC report</em>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">There is a difference between the logic of
citizen security and a logic of war”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Roberto Briceno</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Venezuelan Violence Observatory</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
