<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-22965779"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Celebrations begin for the 90th birthday of Israel's President Shimon Peres, in the presence of celebrities and world leaders."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T08:50:22"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68255000/jpg/_68255224_68255022.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Israel starts celebrating Peres 90th"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-22965779"/>
         <title>BBC News - Israel starts celebrations for Shimon Peres's
90th</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">09:50</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Israel starts celebrations for Shimon
Peres's 90th</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68255000/jpg/_68255220_68255218.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Israeli President Shimon Peres (centre) with former US President Bill Clinton (left) and Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu (right), 18 June 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Former US President Bill Clinton (l) and
Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu (r) joined the
celebrations</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Israel's President
Shimon Peres has begun celebrations for his upcoming 90th birthday
in the company of celebrities and world leaders.</p>
            <p>British former Prime Minister Tony Blair and US ex-President
Bill Clinton were among guests at Jerusalem's convention centre
late on Tuesday.</p>
            <p>Singer Barbra Streisand performed, with actors Robert De Niro
and Sharon Stone also in attendance.</p>
            <p>A series of events are planned ahead of Mr Peres's birthday in
August.</p>
            <p>Tuesday's gala marked the start of Israel's annual presidential
conference, an event that is funded by individuals and foundations
at a cost $3m (Â£1.9m).</p>
            <p>Some 5,000 people are expected to take part in two days of
discussions on the theme of "Facing Tomorrow".</p>
            <p>The VIP guest list for the opening party showed the high
international esteem in which Mr Peres is held.</p>
            <p>Opening his speech, Mr Blair, now a special envoy to the Middle
East, said: "We in Britain have our Queen, you have your Shimon"
before going on to praise the president's leadership qualities.</p>
            <p>US President Barack Obama, who was in Northern Ireland for a G8
summit, sent a pre-recorded message expressing his birthday wishes
to Mr Peres "on behalf of the American people".</p>
            <p>UN Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon also sent a tribute, as did
German Chancellor Angela Merkel and former Soviet leader Mikhail
Gorbachev.</p>
            <p>When President Peres took to the podium, he called for an end to
the conflict in the Middle East.</p>
            <p>"We want peace with our neighbours," he said. "The yesterday
between us and the Palestinians is full of sorrow."</p>
            <p>"I believe that the Israel of tomorrow and the Palestine of
tomorrow can give our children light and hope."</p>
            <p>The political career of Polish-born Mr Peres spans six decades.
He has served twice as prime minister of Israel.</p>
            <p>He is credited with starting the country's nuclear programme and
was closely involved with the early creation of Jewish settlements
in the occupied West Bank.</p>
            <p>He went on to promote peace between Israel and the
Palestinians.</p>
            <p>In 1994, a year after the signing of the Oslo Accords, he was
awarded the Nobel Peace Prize along with Israel's then-Prime
Minister Yitzhak Rabin and then-Palestinian leader Yasser
Arafat.</p>
            <p>Although he was not popular during much of his political career,
Israelis have built up a deep affection for him that has been
widely expressed during nearly six years as Israel's president.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1314784660824"
                  href="/news/world-middle-east-14628835">Israel profile</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
