<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23176058"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="New Australian Prime Minister Kevin Rudd heads to Indonesia, with talks on asylum policy and people-smuggling set to top the agenda."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T09:04:17"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68538000/jpg/_68538602_018443232.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Rudd set for Indonesia asylum talks"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23176058"/>
         <title>BBC News - Australia PM Rudd heads for Indonesia asylum
talks</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">10:04</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Australia PM Rudd heads for Indonesia
asylum talks</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68403000/jpg/_68403905_018443232.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Kevin Rudd talks to the media on 26 June 2013 "/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Mr Rudd said the talks were about consolidating
ties, not policy announcements</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Australian Prime
Minister Kevin Rudd is heading to Indonesia with talks on asylum
policy set to top the agenda.</p>
            <p>Mr Rudd, who ousted Julia Gillard as Labor Party leader last
week, will meet his Indonesian counterpart Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono
in Bogor.</p>
            <p>Asylum is expected to be one of the key issues in Australia's
general election, due later this year.</p>
            <p>The number of people arriving by boat via Indonesia to seek
asylum has increased sharply in recent months.</p>
            <p>Most come from Iraq, Iran, Sri Lanka and Afghanistan. They make
their way to Indonesia and from there head to Christmas Island, the
closest part of Australian territory to Java.</p>
            <p>Last year, the government reintroduced a controversial policy
under which people arriving by boat in Australia are sent to camps
in Nauru and Papua New Guinea for processing.</p>
            <p>It said the move was needed to prevent people making the
dangerous journey to Australia on overcrowded and rickety boats,
several of which have sunk in recent years.</p>
            <p>But the policy - identical to one which Mr Rudd dismantled in
2008 - has been strongly criticised by rights groups and has so far
failed to deter new arrivals.</p>
            <p>The Indonesia trip is Mr Rudd's first overseas visit since he
became prime minister last week after defeating Ms Gillard - who
ousted him in 2010 - in a party ballot.</p>
            <p>An election had been scheduled for 14
September. Mr Rudd has indicated he will move the date but has not
yet specified when polling will take place.</p>
            <p>Opposition leader Tony Abbott, who leads Mr Rudd in the polls,
says under him boats would be turned back to Indonesia when safe to
do so.</p>
            <p>Mr Rudd has said this risks damaging ties with Indonesia, an
important ally and trading partner.</p>
            <p>Both political parties have argued that some of the arrivals are
economic migrants, not refugees - but this was rejected earlier
this week by Australian Human Rights Commission President Professor
Gillian Triggs, who said 90% of asylum seekers were found to be
genuine refugees.</p>
            <p>Speaking as he set off for Indonesia, Mr Rudd said the meeting
was about consolidating ties rather than reaching a deal on
people-smuggling.</p>
            <p>"It will be completely wrong and I think disrespectful to the
Indonesian president to create any expectation of any immediate
change at all," Mr Rudd said.</p>
            <p>"Don't hold your breath for some sort of bright and breezy
announcement out of Jakarta... that everything is all fixed and
back to normal."</p>
            <p>Indonesian Foreign Minister Marty Natalegawa, meanwhile, said on
Wednesday that the issue of people-smuggling had to be handled on a
multilateral basis.</p>
            <p>"In the history of the issue, we have seen Australia considering
numerous options, such as the so-called Pacific Solution, Malaysia
Solution, Timor Leste Solution and so on," the Jakarta Post quoted
him as saying.</p>
            <p>"But Indonesia will always be adamant that this issue should not
only be a burden for certain countries. This needs co-operation
between the destination countries, the countries of origin and
transit countries such as Indonesia," he said.</p>
            <p>Mr Rudd arrives in Jakarta on Thursday afternoon and will hold
formal talks with Mr Yudhoyono on Friday.</p>
            <p>The issue of live cattle exports is also expected to come up at
the meeting, which is part of an annual dialogue.</p>
            <p>Australia halted shipments to Indonesia in 2011 after footage
showed harsh treatment of animals. These have since been restored
in reduced numbers, hitting Australia's cattle industry hard.</p>
            <p>Mr Rudd has also called for increasing trade ties between the
two nations. "Let's make it bigger. This is a huge emerging
economy. It is next door to us," he said.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372649305354"
                  href="/news/world-asia-23123785">Australia PM Rudd unveils
cabinet</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372291118837"
                  href="/news/world-asia-23076517">Rudd sworn in as new Australian
PM</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371771803901"
                  href="/news/world-asia-22953103">Will Nauru deliver Pacific
Solution?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Australia's irregular maritime arrivals</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>2010: 134 boats carrying 6,535 passengers</li>
               <li>2011: 69 boats, carrying 4,565 passengers</li>
               <li>2012: 278 boats carrying 17,202 passengers</li>
               <li>2013 (figures up to 7 June): 164 boats carrying 11,017
passengers</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <em>Figures from Australia's Department of Immigration;
passenger numbers exclude crew</em>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
