<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23153532"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Chad's former leader Hissene Habre is charged with war crimes, crimes against humanity and torture in Senegal."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T18:37:16"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68511000/jpg/_68511984_habre_afp_1987.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Senegal charges Chad's ex-leader"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Africa"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23153532"/>
         <title>BBC News - Chad ex-leader Habre charged in Senegal with war
crimes</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">19:37</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Chad ex-leader Habre charged in Senegal
with war crimes</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68511000/jpg/_68511980_habre_afp_1987.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Chad's then-President Hissene Habre, in 1987"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Hissene Habre has lived a quiet life in Dakar for
more than 20 years</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Chad's ex-President
Hissene Habre has been charged in Senegal with war crimes, crimes
against humanity and torture by a special court.</p>
            <p>The 70 year old, who was arrested on Sunday in the Senegalese
capital, Dakar, denies killing and torturing tens of thousands of
his opponents.</p>
            <p>He fled to Senegal when he was deposed after eight years in
power in 1990.</p>
            <p>Last year, the UN's International Court of Justice ordered
Senegal to put him on trial or extradite him.</p>
            <p>Mr Habre appeared before a special court set up in Senegal to
investigate the allegations. He will remain in custody pending the
trial.</p>
            <p>Analysts say the case would be a milestone for African justice -
representing the first time an African leader has been tried in a
fellow African country on charges of crimes against humanity.</p>
            <p>The Senegalese authorities and the
African Union had for years failed to make a decision on his fate
despite pressure from human rights groups.</p>
            <p>Mr Habre and his wife kept a low profile in Dakar, where he
lived in relative freedom despite being put under house arrest in
2005 - guarded by two security agents.</p>
            <p>Senegalese MPs passed a law in December allowing a special
African Union tribunal to be created in the country to try the
former leader, who has been dubbed "Africa's Pinochet".</p>
            <p>The BBC's Thomas Fessy in Dakar says the official investigation
will take up to 15 months before a trial can start.</p>
            <p>The charges against him date from 1982, when Mr Habre came to
power in a coup, until 1990, the year he was ousted.</p>
            <p>Jacqueline Moudeina, a lawyer for some of his alleged victims,
told the BBC that the move came as a relief to her clients who had
been seeking justice for years.</p>
            <p>Mr Habre's lawyer El-Hadji Diouf told the BBC he remained
confident the truth would eventually emerge and Mr Habre would be
discharged.</p>
            <p>The former Chadian president was first indicted in Senegal in
2000 - but the country's courts ruled at the time that he could not
be tried there.</p>
            <p>His alleged victims then filed complaints under Belgium's
universal jurisdiction law, which allows the country's judges to
prosecute human rights offences committed anywhere in the
world.</p>
            <p>He was charged by Belgium with crimes against humanity and
torture in 2005, but Senegal has refused four extradition
requests.</p>
            <p>Plans in 2011 to repatriate Mr Habre to Chad, where a court in
2008 sentenced him to death in absentia for planning to overthrow
the government, were stopped following a plea from the UN.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1342787530176"
                  href="/news/world-africa-18927845">Profile: Chad's Hissene
Habre</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1303405994804"
                  href="/news/world-africa-13164686">Chad profile</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1355942699365"
                  href="/news/world-africa-20791090">Senegal MPs pass Habre trial
law</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Who is Hissene Habre?</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Born in 1942 to ethnic Toubou herders in northern Chad</li>
               <li>Given scholarship to study political science in France</li>
               <li>First came to the world's attention in 1974 when his FAN rebels
captured three European hostages to ransom for money and arms</li>
               <li>Seized power in 1982, allegedly with the help of the CIA;
ousted by current President Idriss Deby in 1990</li>
               <li>Accused of systematically persecuting groups he distrusted</li>
               <li>A former swimming pool was used as an underground prison where
survivors say they were subjected to electric shocks, near-asphyxia
and "supplice des baguettes", when their heads were squeezed
between sticks</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-africa-18927845">Profile: Chad's Hissene
Habre</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
