<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23153652"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Christian Fraser sees the work going on to help Western Front war graves defeat the ravages of time."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T09:02:56"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68538000/jpg/_68538479_letouretcem&amp;mem.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="War graves and the ravages of time"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23153652"/>
         <title>BBC News - Shielding Commonwealth war graves from the
ravages of time</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">10:02</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Shielding Commonwealth war graves from the
ravages of time</h1>
            <span class="byline byline-photo">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/48983000/jpg/_48983840_jex_798425_de22-1.jpg"
                 alt="Christian Fraser"/>
               <span class="byline-name">By Christian
Fraser</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68531000/jpg/_68531414_letouretcem&amp;mem.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Le Touret Cemetery and Memorial, France"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">It's remarkable
walking the cemeteries of the old Western Front to see how pristine
and loved they still look.</p>
            <p>A foreign field that is forever England, tended like a cottage
garden.</p>
            <p>Of course the years of wind, rain and sun inevitably take their
toll on the headstones.</p>
            <p>The name of Pte Atkins for instance, of the Royal Warwickshire
Regiment, is looking just a little worn.</p>
            <p>But his memory will never be allowed to fade.</p>
            <p>The Commonwealth War Graves Commission serves no other purpose
but to preserve the honour of every soldier that fell - even those
that were never identified.</p>
            <p>And there are time-honoured traditions on how each of these
headstones must look.</p>
            <p>"Our legibility standards are exacting," says Barry Murphy,
director of the commission's France operations.</p>
            <p>"We aim that they are legible from a range of 2m [6ft 6in],
which is usually where people will stand back to look.</p>
            <p>"And as you walk along the line, they
must also be readable from 45 degrees, so that people can see the
names as they approach."</p>
            <p>Cabaret Rouge is one of the many cemeteries close to the town of
Arras.</p>
            <p>The name derives from a front-line cafe that was destroyed here
during the early stages of the war.</p>
            <p>The cemetery was begun by Commonwealth troops in March 1916.</p>
            <p>It was greatly enlarged after the 11 November 1918 armistice
brought World War I to an end, when thousands of bodies from the
battlefields of Arras were brought in.</p>
            <p>It contains the graves of British, Irish, Australian, New
Zealand, Indian and South African soldiers and airmen, and is the
final resting place of hundreds of Canadians, killed at the Battle
of Vimy Ridge in 1917.</p>
            <p>Today, the lines of white Portland stone stretch as far as the
eye can see.</p>
            <p>But if you visit, it's likely you will see among them a number
of tiny green huts. And there, in front of them, perched in
impossible positions, are the craftsmen who are restoring the
headstones.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68531000/jpg/_68531578_dsc_0222.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="An engraver at work"/>
            </div>
            <p>While they work, the air is filled with the whine of the
engraver's drill.</p>
            <p>Ahead of next year's centenary, each headstone across the
Western Front is being checked, cleaned, where necessary
re-engraved, or, if beyond repair, replaced altogether.</p>
            <p>Among the commission's team is Frenchman Johann Riquoir. As he
worked, his stare was fixed on one of the six tablets he restores
each day.</p>
            <p>"The soldiers left their families and came to fight here in
France without receiving anything in return," he said.</p>
            <p>"This is my way of paying homage to that sacrifice - and I put
the same quality of work into a headstone for an unknown soldier as
I do for those who are named."</p>
            <p>The commission has surveyed in the past year every gravestone
and memorial it manages, not just on the Western Front but in 153
countries. The planning is meticulous.</p>
            <p>And given that 1.7 million men and women of the Commonwealth
forces died in the two world wars, you will appreciate the enormous
scale of their project.</p>
            <p>Last year the commission's workshop in Beaurains near Arras
produced 3,500 new headstones for 153 countries. This year they
will work around the clock, engraving up to 25,000.</p>
            <p>The tablets were once carved by a hand-guided machine, known as
a pantograph. Now they're done by computers.</p>
            <p>The machines, guided by digital images, etch an exact copy of
the original headstone - with regimental shield, name, inscription
- into the new stone.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68531000/jpg/_68531412_engravermachine.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="An engraving machine"/>
            </div>
            <p>Some 80% of the new headstones will go to France and Belgium,
some to Normandy, where the sea-air has damaged a good many of the
World War II graves, and some will be sent in diplomatic bags to
distant cemeteries or to hostile places such as Somalia.</p>
            <p>Barry Murphy, from the commission, says it is also updating
German stones for the shared cemetery in Mons, where the first
shots of the war were fired. It's where world leaders will meet
next August for the first commemorations.</p>
            <p>"We have a number in the workshop at the moment for St
Symphorien, in Mons," he said.</p>
            <p>"It's a significant cemetery because it contains burials from
the first few days of the war, as well as burials from the end of
the war.</p>
            <p>"It was a very circular battle. They ended up where they
started.</p>
            <p>"For us it's one of a number of sites we are trying to ensure
will look as good as possible before the start of the
commemorations next year."</p>
            <p>By 1917 the then "Imperial" War Graves Commission, established
the importance of "eternal brotherhood" among the dead.</p>
            <p>For the first time, everyone that was killed would have an
identical grave, irrespective of rank.</p>
            <p>All the soldiers that fell would be remembered whether or not
they were found or identified - many of the re-engravings that are
being done are for unidentified graves, a "Soldier of the Great War
- Known Unto God".</p>
            <p>It was a colossal undertaking burying the dead of the Great War
- it was only completed in 1938. Just in time for the start of
World War II.</p>
            <p>Today, almost a 100 years on, the visitor numbers are
increasing. Advances in genealogy bring people to the grave of a
distant relatives they didn't previously know existed.</p>
            <p>And what might have seemed distant and remote - suddenly becomes
tangible and immediate.</p>
            <p>Kiera Purdie, 16, from Greenock, Renfrewshire, was on a
battlefield tour the day we visited.</p>
            <p>She had come with her classmates to see for the first time, the
grave of her great-grandmother's husband, Pte Speers, of the Royal
Inniskilling Fusiliers, who was killed on 16 May 1915, aged 31.</p>
            <p>"I am glad I came," she said. "It was a very moving moment for
me. I had expected the stones to look darker. Not as well kept. It
is well worth coming here."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68531000/jpg/_68531643_childath.a.c.cemetery.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="A child at HAC Cemetery, France"/>
            </div>
            <p>The gravestone looked as it would have looked 90 years ago.
Their tour guide, Margaret Hubbard, regularly brings these school
trips to France, only when they stand in front of it, she says,
facing the tragedy of war, do they really understand it.</p>
            <p>"The care they have taken with the graves is something that has
gone on for generations, and it will continue for generations to
come," she said.</p>
            <p>"For me it adds another dimension to the teenage culture, it's
not something they are normally exposed to.</p>
            <p>"But when they come here, when they stand amidst this and they
understand what happened here, it matters."</p>
            <p>A signature feature of the bigger Commonwealth cemeteries, is
the rectangular stone of remembrance. The inscription was chosen by
Rudyard Kipling - an early member of the war graves commission, he
was also a father who grieved, for his own son, John, who went
missing in the Battle of Loos.</p>
            <p>"Their name liveth for evermore," was the inscription
chosen.</p>
            <p>Words that speak to the new generation - just as they did to the
last.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1352508349136"
                  href="/news/magazine-20265393">Stories of love and loss in a desert war
grave</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>The human face of World War I</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/64288000/jpg/_64288267_2664968.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="French and British troops in a trench on the Western Front during World War I"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwone/soldiers_stories_gallery.shtml"
                  title="BBC History: WWI diaries and letters">Listen to actors voice
the letters of soldiers who fought in the trenches</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwone/wardiary_gallery.shtml"
                  title="BBC History: View WWI diaries">From the mundane to
miraculous: Examine the war diaries of the 92nd Infantry
Brigade</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwone/humanfaceofwar_gallery_04.shtml"
                  title="BBC History: German officer's WWI diary">Read a German
officer's account of life on the other side</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
