<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23273309"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="South Africa's former ANC youth leader Julius Malema launches a new political group, calling for land redistribution and mine nationalisation."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-11T15:43:25"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68675000/jpg/_68675596_68673662.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="SA's Malema launches political group"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Africa"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23273309"/>
         <title>BBC News - Julius Malema launches Economic Freedom Fighters
group</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">11 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">16:43</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Julius Malema launches Economic Freedom
Fighters group</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68671000/jpg/_68671678_68671677.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Julius Malema at the launch his Economic Freedom Fighters party in Johannesburg, South Africa on 11 July 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Julius Malema was once a close ally of
President Jacob Zuma</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">South Africa's
former African National Congress Youth League leader, Julius
Malema, has launched a political group called the Economic Freedom
Fighters.</p>
            <p>Mr Malema, who was expelled from the governing ANC in 2012, said
the EFF wanted the redistribution of farm land and the
nationalisation of the mines.</p>
            <p>"We will share, black and white. But failure to share means you
will be forced to share," he said.</p>
            <p>He described his movement's ideology as "anti-capitalist".</p>
            <p>Wearing a red beret inscribed with "Commander In Chief EFF", Mr
Malema told journalists in Johannesburg that the EFF was "inspired
by people's suffering on the ground", the South African Press
Association quotes him as saying.</p>
            <p>"We all belong here, but we all have to show proof that we
belong here," he said.</p>
            <p>"Black people have nothing to show.
Therefore we must give them something to show so they can say
proudly: This is our land, this is our country."</p>
            <p>Once a close ally of President Jacob Zuma, Mr Malema has become
one of his strongest critics and campaigned for his removal from
office at the ANC's national conference in December 2012.</p>
            <p>He has accused the president of not doing enough to help the
poor black voters who had helped to elect him.</p>
            <p>According to South Africa's Mail and Guardian newspaper, he did
not commit to contesting next year's elections, saying such things
would be decided at the organisation's national assembly to be held
at the end of July.</p>
            <p>Analysts say that increasing numbers of South Africans are
losing faith in the ANC, which has dominated the country since
1994, accusing it of corruption and failing to improve the lives of
ordinary people.</p>
            <p>South Africa is the continent's biggest economy, largely based
on its mineral wealth, but it has experienced sluggish growth in
recent years.</p>
            <p>Last month, another new party, Agang, was formed by Mamphela
Ramphele, the former partner of black consciousness leader, Steve
Biko.</p>
            <p>However, Mr Malema said he would not work with either Agang or
the official opposition, the Democratic Alliance.</p>
            <p>Mr Malema became infamous for singing the anti-apartheid song
Shoot the Boer, which South Africa's high court ruled in 2011 was
hate speech and banned the ANC from singing it.</p>
            <p>However, Mr Malema and other ANC leaders objected, arguing that
the song was a celebration of the fight against minority rule.</p>
            <p>He was later expelled from the ANC for provoking party
divisions.</p>
            <p>The 32-year-old also faces a corruption charge relating to a
government tender awarded to a company partly owned by his family
trust.</p>
            <p>He rejects the charge, saying that the case is politically
motivated.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1314710741968"
                  href="/news/world-asia-pacific-14718226">Profile: Julius Malema</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1320944656807"
                  href="/news/world-africa-15678254">Julius Malema in his own
words</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1347544539173"
                  href="/news/world-africa-19585351">Why Julius Malema pulls the
crowds</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/56631000/jpg/_56631705_milton_nkosi_cropped2.jpg"
                    alt="image of Milton Nkosi"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Milton Nkosi</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
News, Johannesburg</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>Julius Malema once told me that his blood was "black, green and
gold" - the colours of the ANC which kicked him out for sowing
divisions and bringing it to disrepute.</p>
            <p>So saying that he is launching his Economic Freedom Fighters to
challenge the oldest liberation movement on the African continent
is quite an about-turn.</p>
            <p>There is no doubt that South Africa is experiencing what some
may call a "winter of discontent".</p>
            <p>A few weeks ago Mamphela Ramphele launched another party, Agang,
also with the intention of unseating the ANC.</p>
            <p>Mr Malema insists that he will not join with Agang or indeed the
official opposition Democratic Alliance.</p>
            <p>He will certainly bring with him some of those disillusioned
youth from the weakened ANC Youth League but he will need to work
much harder to convince South Africans that his policy of
nationalisation is the future of the most powerful economy in
Africa.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
