<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23198540"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A US engineer found hanged in his Singapore apartment killed himself, a Singapore coroner rules, saying there was &#34;no foul play&#34;."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-08T06:23:54"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68599000/jpg/_68599917_67524093.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Singapore rules US death suicide"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23198540"/>
         <title>BBC News - Singapore coroner rules Shane Todd death
suicide</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">8 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">07:23</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Singapore coroner rules Shane Todd death
suicide</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/67524000/jpg/_67524926_67524093.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="File photo: Shane Todd"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Mr Todd worked as an electrical engineer
in Singapore</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A US engineer found
hanged in his Singapore apartment killed himself, a Singapore
coroner has ruled.</p>
            <p>Shane Todd, 31, who had been working for a government research
body, was found dead at his home in June 2012.</p>
            <p>His death was registered as suicide, but his parents alleged he
was killed over a project related to sensitive technology.</p>
            <p>The coroner ruled that "there was no foul play". The US has
described the inquiry as "fair and transparent".</p>
            <p>Mr Todd died of "asphyxia due to hanging", the inquest
concluded.</p>
            <p>The verdict in the case - which attracted considerable attention
after Mr Todd's parents contested police findings and campaigned
for an investigation - is final and cannot be appealed against.</p>
            <p>Mr Todd had just left a job at a state-owned research
organisation, Singapore Institute of Microelectronics (IME), at the
time of his death.</p>
            <p>His parents alleged he was working on a project linked to
China's telecoms giant, Huawei, involving sensitive semiconductor
technology, and that his death was the result of foul play linked
to the project.</p>
            <p>Both Mr Todd's former employer and Huawei
- last year named a potential national security threat by a US
Congressional committee because of fears over links to China's
government and military - rejected this, saying they had been
involved in preliminary talks on a project that did not get off the
ground.</p>
            <p>The court also said that the project had not materialised.</p>
            <p>"Even if it did, which I did not find, the listed specifications
show it would not have violated general export control laws, nor
could it have been used for military applications," District Judge
Chay Yuen Fatt said.</p>
            <p>"The deceased was not in possession of confidential and valuable
classified information in the course of his employment at the IME,"
he added.</p>
            <p>Instead the coroner found that the evidence showed "beyond a
reasonable doubt" that Mr Todd had killed himself.</p>
            <p>Mr Todd, who had suffered from depression in the past, had been
described by witnesses as being under considerable stress in the
weeks leading up to his death.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68541000/jpg/_68541071_018085411-1.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Rick (right) and Mary Todd (centre), parents of Shane Todd, check into their flight back to the US, at Changi Airport in Singapore 23 May 2013"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Shane Todd's parents said they lost
confidence in the investigation</span>
            </div>
            <p>The coroner's inquiry, which convened in May, heard that in the
days before he was found dead analysis of his computer showed he
had visited a number of websites on suicide.</p>
            <p>The Todd family's key witness, a deputy medical examiner from
Missouri in the US, also faced stringent questioning during the
inquiry that saw him revise his position that Shane Todd could have
been garrotted.</p>
            <p>He maintained that the 31-year-old was probably killed - putting
him at odds with four other experts, two Singaporean and two from
the US, who concluded suicide was most likely cause of death.</p>
            <p>In a statement, the US embassy said: "The inquiry into Dr Todd's
death was comprehensive, fair and transparent."</p>
            <p>His family "was given the opportunity to participate in the
hearing and was represented by experienced Singapore legal
counsel", the statement added.</p>
            <p>Mr Todd's parents withdrew their support for the Singapore probe
in May, saying they had no confidence in the investigation. They
were not present in court for the verdict.</p>
            <p>"It was apparent that the state was only interested in proving
suicide and that was why we left," Rick Todd, Shane Todd's father,
told AP news agency last week.</p>
            <p>"They never interviewed us and it became obvious from the court
that they never investigated the possibility of murder."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1369201883094"
                  href="/news/world-asia-22620604">Parents quit Singapore death
probe</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1368418074218"
                  href="/news/world-asia-22481559">Singapore opens US death
inquiry</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1362392387650"
                  href="/news/world-asia-21651616">Singapore seeks FBI help over
death</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">The inquiry into Dr Todd's death was
comprehensive, fair, and transparent”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">US embassy in Singapore</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
