<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23151452"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Egyptians are increasingly frustrated with President Mohammad Morsi, as the protests hollow out the foundations of their lives, says BBC Middle East editor Jeremy Bowen."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T16:26:45"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68511000/jpg/_68511292_68510392.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Egyptians frustrated amid power row"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23151452"/>
         <title>BBC News - Egyptians worry as old and new guard struggle for
power</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">17:26</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Egyptians worry as old and new guard
struggle for power</h1>
            <span class="byline byline-photo">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/48964000/jpg/_48964143_48964145.jpg"
                 alt="Jeremy Bowen"/>
               <span class="byline-name">By Jeremy
Bowen</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC Middle East editor,
Cairo</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68511000/jpg/_68511288_68510392.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Cairo graffiti comparing Mohammed Morsi and Hosni Mubarak (2 July 2013)"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Cairo is a huge,
teeming place, a human power station of energy, but it's also a
city of small neighbourhoods where everyone knows everyone
else.</p>
            <p>Mohammed Mahmoud Street is a long road that leads off Tahrir
Square, the centre of Egypt's protests. Ripples in national
politics splash down here as waves that the street's residents feel
are eroding the foundations of their lives. And they blame
President Mohammed Morsi of the Muslim Brotherhood.</p>
            <p>I asked four middle-aged men, two taxi drivers and two
accountants, sipping sweet tea and puffing tobacco through water
pipes in a scruffy pavement cafÃƒÂ©, whether
they would prefer to have a man like former President Hosni Mubarak
back in office.</p>
            <p>They all said yes, as if it was the most obvious thing in the
world. "It's because back then we were safe!" finished one of the
accountants, Said Ahmed, back home from his job in Saudi
Arabia.</p>
            <p>The epidemic of crime, especially street
robbery, is a big concern of many Egyptians.</p>
            <p>Old-style Middle Eastern police states were usually very safe,
as long as the security services were not after you. These days
Egyptians worry constantly about the security of their
families.</p>
            <p>The police have been mostly inactive since the revolution,
nursing their own grievances about being treated badly, and with a
legacy of conflict with the Muslim Brotherhood.</p>
            <p>Ali Fathalk, one of the taxi drivers, complained about the
current fuel shortage. It is partly caused by inefficiency, one of
Egypt's curses, and partly by the government's shortage of hard
currency to pay for exports. The value of the Egyptian pound has
plummeted.</p>
            <p>"I rent a taxi to work, then have to spend half the day queuing
to get petrol," Ali said. "I should be able to spend money on my
kids."</p>
            <p>I asked them where President Morsi had gone wrong. They all
scoffed.</p>
            <p>"Everywhere," said Yasser Abbas, the other taxi driver, adding:
"Morsi talks about his legitimate electoral victory, but he's done
illegal things too."</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68508000/jpg/_68508784_2dbc27fd-cd25-450e-8a34-eedad34a6a39.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Protester wearing chains and a mask of Mohammed Morsi (26/06/13)"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Critics say President Mohammed Morsi has
made Egypt a less safe place</span>
            </div>
            <p>He was referring to last year's constitutional declaration,
which put the president above the law. Later, after big protests,
he replaced it with another one, but for many Egyptians it showed a
dictatorial tendency they did not like.</p>
            <p>As they drank tea and smoked, the men echoed a common complaint
in Egypt - that the presidential election last year was
unsatisfactory because it came down to a choice between a veteran
of the Mubarak regime and Mr Morsi of the Brotherhood.</p>
            <p>They were convinced, without really having any proof, that there
were irregularities in the vote. The choice of candidates, by the
way, was not down to any manipulation but to the failure by secular
liberals and revolutionaries to organise themselves well enough to
get their candidate into the final round of the ballot.</p>
            <p>Since his victory, the four friends complained, President Morsi
has been governing for the good of the Muslim Brotherhood, not for
the good of the country.</p>
            <p>The Brotherhood was founded in 1928, though its roots go back to
religious revivalists in the 19th Century. It has spread across
Islamic countries, seeking the long-term goal of states shaped by
Sharia, or Islamic law.</p>
            <p>From the 1950s until the overthrow of President Mubarak, the
Brotherhood in Egypt was persecuted at times, tolerated at others,
but was always illegal.</p>
            <p>After Hosni Mubarak was ousted, the Brotherhood built itself a
splendid new headquarters in a suburb of Cairo. Its emblem, of a
Koran and swords, was fixed proudly above the door.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68509000/jpg/_68509335_172044246.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Burnt Muslim Brotherhood building"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Once a splendid symbol for the
Brotherhood's rise to power, its headquarters are just a burnt
shell after protesters stormed the building</span>
            </div>
            <p>The building was the symbol of the Muslim Brotherhood's rise
from being a banned organisation under the old regime to power in
the new Egypt.</p>
            <p>I visited it when it was new. Expensive cars lined the streets
outside, owned by some of the rich businessmen who are among the
Brotherhood's backers. Inside in the spacious foyer, old timers
from the movement received visitors and held court. Many of them
had spent years in prison.</p>
            <p>Now the headquarters building is a wrecked and burnt shell,
ransacked and torched by opponents of President Morsi.</p>
            <p>The Brotherhood, whatever the hopes of the opposition, will not
give up power easily. They argue they should not have to, because
they won a free election, the kind where you don't know the result
before you vote.</p>
            <p>Egypt has been through hard times, and it
might be that harder times are coming.</p>
            <p>The military's intervention is a play for high stakes. The
generals insist they are not planning a coup, but if they remove an
elected president, or take his power, their actions will match most
definitions of one.</p>
            <p>They risk on one side, a backlash by Egypt's jihadists, which
could be bloody. On their other flank are the Americans, who fund
the Egyptian army. The sight of armed forces funded by US taxpayers
removing an elected president will not go down well in
Washington.</p>
            <p>All of this matters across the region, not just in Egypt. What
is happening here will shape the new Middle East that is emerging
in the wake of the Arab uprisings.</p>
            <p>So far the Muslim Brotherhood, and political Islam, have looked
to be one of the big winners. Anything that damages, tarnishes or
even breaks the Brotherhood's power in Egypt will change the
struggle for power elsewhere in the Middle East.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12315833">Egypt in
crisis</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373156235629"
                     href="/news/magazine-23199377">Shifting sands</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373146727395"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23214054">What now for
Brotherhood?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373020716781"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23197801">Failed experiment</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373067054933"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23205101">Two years in Tahrir
Square</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68509000/jpg/_68509337_hi018070695.jpg"
              width="144"
              height="81"
              alt="Egyptian soldier"/>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">The generals insist they are not planning a
coup, but if they remove an elected president, or take his power,
their actions will match most definitions of one”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68509000/jpg/_68509871_172089497.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Egypt protesters (1 July 2013)"/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-middle-east-23096848">Egypt voices: Morsi
one year on</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-middle-east-23077898">Deeply polarised
nation</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
