<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23139980"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Fugitive US intelligence leaker Edward Snowden has sent asylum requests to 21 countries, Wikileaks says, but he has withdrawn an application to Russia."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T09:56:47"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68492000/jpg/_68492577_68343867.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Snowden 'broadens asylum requests'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23139980"/>
         <title>BBC News - Edward Snowden 'broadens asylum requests' -
Wikileaks</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">10:56</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Edward Snowden 'broadens asylum requests'
- Wikileaks</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68373000/jpg/_68373658_68343867.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Edward Snowden. File photo"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Edward Snowden is believed to be staying
at Moscow's Sheremetyevo airport</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Fugitive US
intelligence leaker Edward Snowden has sent asylum requests to 21
countries, according to a statement published by Wikileaks.</p>
            <p>
               <a href="http://wikileaks.org/Edward-Snowden-submits-asylum.html">They
include</a> China, France, Ireland and Venezuela. But eight
European countries said the requests were invalid.</p>
            <p>And Russia said Mr Snowden later withdrew the application to
Moscow as the Kremlin had set conditions.</p>
            <p>He accuses US President Barack Obama of putting pressure on the
countries to which he has applied.</p>
            <p>The former intelligence systems analyst, who is holed up at
Moscow airport, is wanted by the US on charges of leaking
secrets.</p>
            <p>US Secretary of State John Kerry raised
Mr Snowden's case in talks with his Russian counterpart Sergei
Lavrov on the sidelines of the Asean summit in Brunei.</p>
            <p>But Mr Kerry said the two did not discuss the matter
substantively.</p>
            <p>"I did raise the issue of Mr Snowden but that is not his
portfolio, nor is it mine, but it is being handled within the
justice department," he said, quoted by Reuters news agency.</p>
            <p>The Wikileaks press release said that most of the asylum
requests - including to Russia itself - were handed to the Russian
consulate at Sheremetyevo airport late on Sunday for delivery to
the relevant embassies in Moscow.</p>
            <p>The requests were submitted by Sarah Harrison, a British member
of the Wikileaks legal team acting as Mr Snowden's representative,
the statement added.</p>
            <p>But Kremlin spokesman Dmitry Peskov later said Mr Snowden
withdrew the application to Russia because Moscow had said he
should give up "anti-American activity".</p>
            <p>"After learning of Russia's position yesterday, voiced by
President Putin ... he abandoned his intention [of staying] and his
request to be able to stay in Russia," he said.</p>
            <p>Russian President Vladimir Putin had said that while Moscow
"never hands over anybody anywhere", Mr Snowden could only stay on
condition that he stopped damaging Russia's "American partners"
with his leaks.</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden has reportedly been in the transit area of
Sheremetyevo since arriving there from Hong Kong on 23 June.</p>
            <p>Mr Peskov confirmed he was still there and had not crossed into
Russian territory, adding that the former analyst had never been a
Russian agent and had never worked with its intelligence
services.</p>
            <p>Norway, Poland, Germany, Austria,
Finland, Ireland, Spain and Switzerland said asylum requests could
only be made on their soil.</p>
            <p>Venezuelan President Nicolas Maduro, who is on a visit to
Moscow, said Caracas had not yet received an asylum application
from Mr Snowden but that he had "done something very important for
humanity" and "deserved the world's protection".</p>
            <p>"The world's conscience should react, the world youth should
react, the decent people who want a peaceful world should react,
everyone should react and find solidarity with this young man who
has denounced and altered the world that they [the US] pretend to
control."</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden had previously submitted an application to Ecuador,
whose embassy in London is sheltering Wikileaks founder Julian
Assange, and to Iceland.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68487000/jpg/_68487391_68487390.jpg"
                 alt="Vladimir Putin"/>
               <p class="caption">Vladimir Putin: "He should cease his work aimed
at damaging our American partners"</p>
            </div>
            <p>Ecuador's President Rafael Correa told the Agence France-Presse
news agency on Monday that his country would process Mr Snowden's
asylum request if he managed to enter an Ecuadorean embassy.</p>
            <p>However, if he can complete his asylum request on Russian
territory , then "the situation can be processed and resolved
there," President Correa added.</p>
            <p>Details have also emerged of a letter from Mr Snowden to
President Correa, thanking Ecuador for guaranteeing "my rights
would be protected upon departing Hong Kong - I could never have
risked travel without that".</p>
            <p>Speaking in Tanzania on Monday, President Barack Obama said
Moscow and Washington had held "high level discussions" about Mr
Snowden, who he said had travelled to Moscow without valid
documents.</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden describes himself as "a stateless person", accusing
the US government of stopping him from exercising the "basic
right...to seek asylum".</p>
            <p>"The president ordered his vice president to pressure the
leaders of nations from which I have requested protection to deny
my asylum petitions," he is quoted by <a href="http://wikileaks.org/Statement-from-Edward-Snowden-in.html?snow">Wikileaks</a>
as saying.</p>
            <p>"This kind of deception from a world leader is not justice, and
neither is the extralegal penalty of exile. These are the old, bad
tools of political aggression. Their purpose is to frighten, not
me, but those who would come after me."</p>
            <p>The leaking of thousands of classified intelligence documents
has led to revelations that the US is systematically seizing vast
amounts of phone and web data.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>US spy leaks</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372684702774"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23123964">Revelations of US spy
scandal</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372869435767"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23165992">Where will Snowden end
up?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372702760008"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23133216">Is it OK to spy on your
allies?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372348565338"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-23077279">Wikileaks back in
spotlight</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/64130000/jpg/_64130802_64130801.jpg"
                    alt="image of Jonathan Marcus"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Jonathan Marcus</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
diplomatic correspondent</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>Vladimir Putin's warning to Mr Snowden that he should stop
"harming our American partners" is indicative of a significant
shifting of gear. Russia now has ownership of the Snowden affair.
What happens to Mr Snowden will depend upon Russia's calculations
and what serves Russia's interests.</p>
            <p>The authorities in Moscow could have moved Mr Snowden on
quickly, joining the diplomatic game of pass-the-parcel that began
in Hong Kong. But the longer the errant US intelligence analyst
stays in limbo at the Moscow airport, so the more Russia has become
a central actor in this drama.</p>
            <p>Russia must balance a range of factors in seeking to determine
Mr Snowden's fate - the risk of a serious rift with Washington and
Russia's own standing as an international actor that upholds the
legal order must be set against the strong vein of sympathy for Mr
Snowden amongst Russian public opinion.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Asylum requests to 21 countries</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Austria, Bolivia, Brazil, China, Cuba, Ecuador, Finland,
France, Germany, Iceland, India, Italy, Ireland, Netherlands,
Nicaragua, Norway, Poland, Russia (withdrawn), Spain, Switzerland,
Venezuela</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-us-canada-23123964">How the US spy scandal
unravelled</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-us-canada-23133216">US-EU bugging claims:
Is spying OK?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-us-canada-22837100">Profile: Edward
Snowden</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
