<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23178279"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The UK and green groups welcome a move to rescue the EU's carbon trading scheme, but urge deeper reforms."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T12:33:34"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68546000/jpg/_68546533_polishpowerafp.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Move to fix EU carbon market praised"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23178279"/>
         <title>BBC News - MEPs' move to fix EU carbon market
praised</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">13:33</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">MEPs' move to fix EU carbon market
praised</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68546000/jpg/_68546541_jaengergetty.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Germany's Jaenschwalde power station"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Germany's Jaenschwalde power station is among
Europe's biggest CO2 emitters</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The UK government
and green groups have welcomed a European Parliament move to rescue
the EU's carbon trading scheme, but say deeper reforms are
needed.</p>
            <p>MEPs backed a European Commission plan to freeze the auctioning
of some carbon dioxide (CO2) emission allowances.</p>
            <p>The idea is to reduce the current oversupply of allowances,
thereby pushing up the carbon price.</p>
            <p>Carbon trading gives heavy industry an incentive to cut CO2
emissions, which have been linked to global warming.</p>
            <p>The parliament voted on Wednesday to let the Commission delay
the auctioning of up to 900 million CO2 allowances.</p>
            <p>The plan still has to be agreed with EU governments to take
effect, and Poland - heavily dependent on carbon-rich coal - is
among several countries that oppose it.</p>
            <p>The EU is now in phase three of the Emissions Trading System
(ETS), a scheme launched in 2005 in a drive to tackle climate
change.</p>
            <p>By reducing the number of permits traded, the Commission hopes
to correct the oversupply which has pushed the carbon price below
four euros (Â£3.5; $5.2) per tonne - far
short of the original target of more than 20 euros.</p>
            <p>The UK Secretary of State for Energy and Climate Change, Ed
Davey, said: "This is a good decision by the European Parliament
and is an important step forward for climate change policy".</p>
            <p>But he also spoke of "an urgent need for structural reform" of
the ETS, "in order to promote growth in low-carbon industry in the
longer term". He said the UK and 11 other member states were
calling on the Commission to propose legislation by the end of this
year to reinvigorate the carbon market.</p>
            <p>The Commission says the carbon market now has a surplus of
nearly two billion CO2 allowances. Each allowance corresponds to
one tonne of CO2 emissions. Enterprises that adopt low-carbon
technology and emit less CO2 can sell their unused allowances.</p>
            <p>The Greens/European Free Alliance group in the parliament
welcomed the vote to delay, or "backload", the auctioning of CO2
allowances. But Greens MEP Bas Eickhout said it was "only a
stop-gap measure to buy more time for much-needed structural ETS
reform".</p>
            <p>The Greens want the Commission to permanently withdraw at least
1.4 billion allowances this year.</p>
            <p>The environmental campaign group Greenpeace said the current
plan "will not restore the credibility of the carbon market,
because as soon as the suspended allowances are allowed to re-enter
the system, the carbon market will be back to square one".
Greenpeace called for the Commission to remove 2.2 billion
allowances before 2020.</p>
            <p>Enterprises fuelled by coal generally need to buy more
allowances than those using gas, because their CO2 emissions are
higher.</p>
            <p>The ETS covers more than 12,000 power plants and manufacturing
installations in the EU, as well as airlines that use European
airports.</p>
            <p>The EU wants China and the US - the world's biggest CO2
polluters - to agree on more ambitious targets to limit climate
change.</p>
            <p>On current trends the world will miss the target of keeping the
rise in temperatures below 2C, which experts say increases the risk
of drought and rising sea levels.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1362743528021"
                  href="/news/world-europe-21712295">EU court rebuffs Poland over
CO2</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1331645657980"
                  href="/news/world-europe-17351137">EU plans CO2 cuts in
countryside</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1331509759672"
                  href="/news/business-17335616">Aviation plea on EU carbon price</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
