<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23096848"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A year after Mohammed Morsi was sworn into office as Egypt's first Islamist president, the country is deeply divided between his supporters and opponents. As both sides prepare for major protests, BBC Arabic's Marwa Nasser took the views on Mr Morsi of Egyptians in Cairo."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T10:58:20"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68430000/jpg/_68430359_mahasaid39housewife.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Egypt voices: Morsi one year on"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23096848"/>
         <title>BBC News - Egypt voices: Morsi one year on</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">11:58</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Egypt voices: Morsi one year on</h1>
            <p class="introduction">A year after Mohammed Morsi was sworn into
office as Egypt's first Islamist president, the country is deeply
divided between his supporters and opponents. As both sides prepare
for major protests, BBC Arabic's Marwa Nasser took the views on Mr
Morsi of Egyptians in Cairo.</p>
            <h2 class="section-header" id="heading-1">Engy Abdel Moneem, 45,
housewife</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68435000/jpg/_68435715_engyabdelmoneemhousewife45.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Engy Abdel Moneem, 45, housewife"/>
            </div>
            <p>Morsi doesn't need a second chance. Why would we give him a
chance when he himself said: "Once the people ask me to leave, I
will do so immediately?" Why didn't he keep his word? Is he just
saying things to us and then being a dictator?</p>
            <p>Everything in this country is getting worse. The presidency has
failed and protests are spreading everywhere. We're going
backwards. We still have unemployment, and factories are closing
down. Every day, we hear bad news about Sinai. The police are
getting worse.</p>
            <p>Nothing will stop me or anyone who loves their country from
protesting.</p>
            <h2 class="section-header" id="heading-2">Ahmed Hashem, 57,
electrician</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68431000/jpg/_68431029_ahmedhashem,57,electrician.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Ahmed Hashem, 57, electrician "/>
            </div>
            <p>Once Morsi was in power, protests flared up against him. How can
he work in that atmosphere? And to those who oppose him, I say:
"Why don't you show us what you can do?" The Muslim Brothers visit
poor areas and provide services. They sell food supplies at lower
prices, but they don't bribe people like some claim.</p>
            <p>Let the man do his job, then judge him. It's like tying
someone's hands and legs, and throwing him in the Nile, then asking
him to swim. The president is a man who fears God. All the
destruction is carried out by the opposition who keeps on
protesting. Would they have dared even walk around the presidential
palace during Mubarak's time, let alone throw Molotov cocktails at
it?</p>
            <p>Morsi has invited the opposition for talks many times and they
have refused. All the opposition has achieved is to divide people
in two groups and made people fight against each other. We should
let ballot boxes decide who's in power. I don't take part in any
protests and will not let any of my children go. Why would I go
somewhere where I might get hit by a bullet or a rock?</p>
            <h2 class="section-header" id="heading-3">Maha Said, 39,
housewife</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68431000/jpg/_68431033_mahasaid,39,housewife.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Maha Said, 39, housewife"/>
            </div>
            <p>This past year has been a year of horror and anxiety. I was
always concerned about the safety of my two children. Morsi has
accomplished nothing, and things are only going from bad to worse.
All the new jobs have been taken by the Muslim Brotherhood, and I
know some of the people who have personally. There are no jobs for
qualified young people.</p>
            <p>Only since the police went back to work have things got slightly
better, but before that we depended on ourselves when it came to
protecting our properties.</p>
            <p>These coming protests are at the right time. We have already
given him a whole year; we can't let the country collapse any
further.</p>
            <h2 class="section-header" id="heading-4">Waleed Ali, 39,
teacher</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68431000/jpg/_68431746_waleedali39,teacher.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Waleed Ali, 39, teacher"/>
            </div>
            <p>I voted for President Morsi, but I regret it. I hoped his
performance would be better than this. He doesn't take firm
decisions, and when he does, he doesn't keep them.</p>
            <p>I expected President Morsi to be much stronger, to preserve the
dignity of Egyptians abroad, but we are still being humiliated by
countries like Ethiopia. I don't see any improvement. I wish he'd
implement the Islamic project - as he promised - and Sharia law,
that's why we voted for him.</p>
            <p>We assumed that he was up to the job, but unfortunately he
isn't. I will not protest against him though. These protests are
not in the best interest of the country. Even if we want to judge
him, we need to give him a proper chance. Honestly, one year is not
enough to fix what 30 years of corruption have left behind. It's
very difficult.</p>
            <h2 class="section-header" id="heading-5">Ali Mohammed, 27,
unemployed</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68432000/jpg/_68432092_alimohammed,27,unemployed.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Ali Mohammed, 27, unemployed "/>
            </div>
            <p>Morsi is the elected president. Even though I'm against the
Brotherhood, I believe we should give him a chance for another
three years till he finishes his term. We don't have to vote for
him again afterwards. We can't just change the president every
year.</p>
            <p>What if he left? What if there was another president? The
Brotherhood would take to streets in their millions and protest and
it would never end. I can't say he's a failure; there are several
issues that still need to be worked on. But these can't just be
solved overnight. I don't defend him. I'm against him, I voted for
Shafiq in both rounds, but no president can change this country in
just four years.</p>
            <p>There are no jobs, but this has always been the case in Egypt. I
can't hold him accountable for that, there are other people working
under him who are responsible for finding more jobs.</p>
            <h2 class="section-header" id="heading-6">Amira Saleh, 41,
administrator</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68432000/jpg/_68432526_amirasaleh,41,adminstrator.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Amira Saleh, 41, administrator"/>
            </div>
            <p>Morsi's time is up. I will not wait for another three years. The
country is going down. The poor can't find food anymore. And people
are fighting everywhere. The lack of petrol and electricity are
making them lose their temper and they're fighting each other.</p>
            <p>The country is simmering. He's finished. Nothing has improved;
wherever you go in Cairo, you'll see piles of rubbish around each
corner. Nothing he promised has changed.</p>
            <h2 class="section-header" id="heading-7">Mohammed Ahmed, 28,
pharmacist</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68432000/jpg/_68432097_mohammedahmed,28,pharmacist.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Mohammed Ahmed, 28, pharmacist"/>
            </div>
            <p>We can't judge Morsi now. The country is full of problems and
the opposition is not giving him time to do anything. One year
ruling a country is not enough to judge him as a success or
failure. He must stay for his four years first.</p>
            <p>We can easily change him in four years. We will have at least
set the basis for democracy. But if we protest every year, then we
will never have a president for more than three months.</p>
            <p>If Morsi left only one year after being elected, the Islamists
would become the opposition to the coming president, and they're
fiercer and more organised. [In this case], we would have killed
democracy and let the streets be the judge.</p>
            <p>What has changed over the year are freedoms. Anyone can say
whatever they want without fear. I'm not intending to take part in
any protests whether pro or against. It's a waste of time.</p>
            <h2 class="section-header" id="heading-8">Abdel Zaher Haseeb, 52,
farmer</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68432000/jpg/_68432101_abdelzaherhaseeb,52,farmer.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Abdel Zaher Haseeb, 52, farmer"/>
            </div>
            <p>Before Morsi, we spent almost two years without a president and
things were so much better. Look around you now: nothing is moving.
Traffic and petrol problems have increased. Nothing has changed at
all, I will keep saying that even if they kill me for it.</p>
            <p>Have you heard of any prices that have decreased? I can't find
petrol to move my tractor around the land I farm. Salaries have
increased, but the price of food supplies has doubled. I don't get
a salary! But I'm still buying these supplies.</p>
            <p>There's nothing I can do. I'm helpless and the only thing I'm
asking for is to live with dignity. I voted for Morsi, I thought he
was a religious man, and knew God and knew about the poor people.
My family paid a fortune to educate me and I was able to secure a
degree in agriculture, but I have never been able to get a job in
the government.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
