<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23123817"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="At least 19 US firefighters are killed battling a wildfire in Arizona in the highest death toll for firefighters since 9/11."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T16:23:13"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68486000/jpg/_68486211_68486202.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="US wildfire kills 19 firefighters"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/US and Canada"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23123817"/>
         <title>BBC News - Arizona wildfire near Yarnell kills 19
firefighters</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">17:23</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Arizona wildfire near Yarnell kills 19
firefighters</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68471000/jpg/_68471336_fire3.jpg"
                 alt="Wildfires in central Arizona"/>
               <p class="caption">The dead firefighters were identified as members
of the Granite Mountain Hotshots crew</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">At least 19 US
firefighters have been killed battling a wildfire in central
Arizona, local officials say.</p>
            <p>They died while fighting the blaze threatening the town of
Yarnell, about 80 miles (130km) north-west of Phoenix.</p>
            <p>The fire was started by lightning on Friday and has spread
rapidly to 2,000 acres (800 ha) amid high heat, low humidity and
strong winds.</p>
            <p>Arizona and other parts of the western US - including California
- had near-record temperatures over the weekend.</p>
            <p>It is the highest death toll for firefighters in a single
incident since 9/11.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68486000/jpg/_68486207_68486202.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="The Granite Mountain Interagency Hotshot Crew is shown in this undated handout photo provided by the City of Prescott 1 July 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The dead firefighters were identified as
members of the Granite Mountain Hotshots crew, shown here in an
undated photograph</span>
            </div>
            <p>"We are heartbroken about what happened," US President Barack
Obama said in a press conference in Tanzania on Monday. Earlier he
called the deceased firefighters heroes.</p>
            <p>Arizona Senator John McCain said the families of the dead
firefighters were in the thoughts and prayers of all Americans.</p>
            <p>"This devastating loss is a reminder of the grave risks our
firefighters take every day on our behalf in Arizona and in
communities across this nation. Their sacrifice will never be
forgotten," he said in a <a href="http://www.mccain.senate.gov/public/index.cfm?FuseAction=PressOffice.PressReleases&amp;ContentRecord_id=98c547e5-07cf-11aa-50b5-dc4aa98cb697">
statement</a>.</p>
            <p>Arizona Governor Jan Brewer said it could
take "days or longer" to reveal how the deaths occurred.</p>
            <p>"This is as dark a day as I can remember," she said.</p>
            <p>The Prescott, Arizona, fire department has confirmed to the BBC
that 19 of its firefighters were killed in the blaze.</p>
            <p>The dead firefighters have been identified as members of an
elite unit called the Granite Mountain Hotshots.</p>
            <p>The crew had battled other wildfires in New Mexico and Arizona
in recent weeks, officials say.</p>
            <p>They were forced to deploy emergency tent-like structures meant
to shield them from flames after becoming trapped and "something
drastic" happened, said Prescott Fire Chief Dan Fraijo.</p>
            <p>"One of the last fail-safe methods a firefighter can do is
literally to dig as much as they can down and cover themselves with
a protective fire-resistant material, with the hope that the fire
will burn over the top of them and they can survive it," he
said.</p>
            <p>"Under certain conditions there's usually
only sometimes a 50% chance that they survive. It's an extreme
measure that's taken under the absolute worst conditions."</p>
            <p>Dwight Devlin from the Arizona Sheriff's Office told the BBC
that the firefighters were carrying fire blankets but they were
ineffective in this case.</p>
            <p>"Some were actually found with those blankets over them but
unfortunately it appears the flames and the heat were too much," he
said.</p>
            <p>Mr Devlin added that they were on their way on foot to an area
where they had been directed to clear brush to prevent the spread
of the fire.</p>
            <p>The tragedy is the worst in a wildfire since 1933, when at least
25 firemen died battling a fire in Griffith Park, Los Angeles.</p>
            <p>Some 250 firefighters are still battling the fast-moving
wildfire. In total, 18 specialist hotshot crews are being
deployed.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68476000/jpg/_68476479_68476478.jpg"
                 alt="Fire chief Dan Fraijo"/>
               <p class="caption">Fire chief Dan Fraijo: "They were the finest
most dedicated people"</p>
            </div>
            <p>The blaze has forced the evacuation of residents.</p>
            <p>An estimated 200 homes were destroyed in Yarnell, the Associated
Press reported, about half the properties in the town.</p>
            <p>In recent days, dozens of people across western US states have
been treated for exhaustion and dehydration, as the heatwave
continues.</p>
            <p>Temperatures in some areas were expected to reach 54C (130F),
close to the world's all-time high recorded 100 years ago in
California's Death Valley.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/66933000/gif/_66933045_line2.gif"
                 width="464"
                 height="1"
                 alt="line break "/>
            </div>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68481000/gif/_68481711_how_wildfires_spread_464_no_title.gif"
                 width="464"
                 height="262"
                 alt="How wildfires spread graphic"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>A fire needs fuel, oxygen and heat to burn. The fire
threatening the town of Yarnell was started by lightning and spread
rapidly in the very hot, dry conditions, fanned by strong
winds</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li>The fastest-moving and most dangerous part of the fire is known
as the "<strong>head</strong>". Areas ahead of the fire are warmed
as it approaches and flying embers blown by the wind spark
<strong>spot fires</strong>, which cause it to leap further
ahead</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li>Some vegetation or fuel will burn quicker than others and this
creates "<strong>fingers</strong>" of flame which, in turn, create
<strong>pockets</strong> of land surrounded by fire, making it
harder to tackle</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li>Fires travel faster uphill than downhill, as the heat and smoke
rise, heating areas higher up the hill and wind currents also tend
to blow uphill, pushing the flames further. Burning embers may roll
downhill, starting new fires</li>
            </ul>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/66933000/gif/_66933045_line2.gif"
                 width="464"
                 height="1"
                 alt="line break "/>
            </div>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68472000/jpg/_68472731_arizona_fire_624.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="400"
                 alt="Arizona fire map"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372684908227"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-23128457">Arizona wildfire: Battling the
blaze</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372661063162"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-23123961">In pictures: Arizona
wildfire</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story" rel="published-1372650852278" href="/news/23122710">Arizona mourns 19
dead firefighters <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/52272000/jpg/_52272274_pallabghosh2.jpg"
                    alt="image of Pallab Ghosh"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Pallab Ghosh</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Science correspondent, BBC News</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>Fires in the US have increased four-fold over the previous 15
years, according to a 2006 study published in Nature. More
alarmingly, the average size of fires increased six-fold.</p>
            <p>The reason is a deadly combination: a drier climate, the rapid
growth in people choosing to live in forested areas in the western
US, and less management of forests - partly because of cuts in
federal funding. All this coupled with the spread of mountain pine
beetle, which has killed millions of trees, is turning America's
forests into tinderboxes.</p>
            <p>Apart from the fires, there's now growing concern about
heatwaves' effect on health. At these temperatures it's not just
the elderly and ill that are at risk. Young healthy individuals are
also more likely to have heart and breathing problems - and
experience suggests that it's possible that hundreds may die if the
stifling conditions are sustained.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>US wildfire tragedies</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <strong>3 Oct 1933:</strong> At least 25 firemen killed at a
blaze in Griffith Park, Los Angeles</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>21 Aug 1937:</strong> Fifteen firefighters die in
Blackwater fire in Shoshone National Forest, Wyoming</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>5 Aug 1949:</strong> Twelve parachute firefighters and
a forest ranger killed by Mann Gulch fire near Helena, in the state
of Montana</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>9 July 1953:</strong> Rattlesnake fire in Mendocino
National Forest, southern California, kills 15 firefighters</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>6 July 1994:</strong> Fourteen firefighters killed in
lightning-induced Storm King Mountain blaze near Glenwood Springs,
Colorado</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <em>Source: US National Fire Protection Association</em>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
