<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23157801"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The Egyptian military has moved into key sites in Cairo as tens of thousands of demonstrators await a statement on the political crisis that has gripped the nation."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-03T18:20:44"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68535000/jpg/_68535396_68535387.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Army deployed amid Egypt tension"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23157801"/>
         <title>BBC News - Egypt army deployed amid Cairo tension</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">3 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">19:20</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Egypt army deployed amid Cairo
tension</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68532000/jpg/_68532550_68532549.jpg"
                 alt="Protesters in Tahrir Square"/>
               <p class="caption">The BBC's Ben Brown reports from Tahrir Square,
which he says is "incredibly noisy and absolutely packed"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The Egyptian
military has moved into key sites in Cairo hours after its
ultimatum passed for President Mohammed Morsi to resolve a
political crisis.</p>
            <p>Tens of thousands of pro- and anti-Morsi protesters have
gathered in areas of the capital, as Egyptians await a televised
statement.</p>
            <p>Opposition figure Mohammed ElBaradei and religious leaders will
make this statement, the state news agency said.</p>
            <p>Before the deadline passed, Mr Morsi repeated his refusal to
step down.</p>
            <p>His aides took to social media to describe the events as a
military coup but there was no confirmation of this.</p>
            <p>There are unconfirmed reports that Egyptian officials have
placed an international travel ban on Mr Morsi and other senior
members of the Muslim Brotherhood.</p>
            <p>The army is involved in a show of force, fanning out across
Cairo and taking control of the capital, BBC correspondent Quentin
Sommerville reports.</p>
            <p>He described seeing eight armoured
personnel carriers heading for Cairo University in Giza, where one
of the main pro-Morsi demonstrations was being held. At least 16
people were killed and about 200 wounded at the university when
gunmen opened fire on protesters on Tuesday night.</p>
            <p>Another pro-Morsi protest was being held in Nasr City, where New
York Times reporter Kareem Fahim tweeted that soldiers had fired
into the air to disperse demonstrators.</p>
            <p>Opponents of the president gathered in Tahrir Square in their
tens of thousands. When the army's 48-hour deadline passed, cheers
echoed across the square.</p>
            <p>Whether it is a military coup or not, on the streets of Cairo it
certainly looks like one, our correspondent says.</p>
            <p>Before the army's ultimatum to President Morsi expired at 16:30
(15:30 GMT), he posted a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=477521632340184&amp;set=a.390822984343383.93429.389032124522469&amp;type=1&amp;theater">
Facebook message</a> calling for a roadmap involving an interim
coalition government.</p>
            <p>His whereabouts were not immediately clear but BBC Arabic
confirmed that he was at the Cairo headquarters of the Republican
Guard, a military site where he has stayed since the start of the
protests.</p>
            <p>One of Mr Morsi's aides, Issam al-Haddad, wrote on his Facebook
page that he was "fully aware" his words might be the "last lines I
get to post on this page", adding that what was happening was a
"military coup".</p>
            <p>
               <strong>Defiant speech</strong>
            </p>
            <p>The army had earlier held meetings with political and religious
leaders to discuss the crisis.</p>
            <p>But the ruling Freedom and Justice party - the political arm of
Mr Morsi's Muslim Brotherhood - stayed away from the talks.</p>
            <p>Mr Morsi's opponents have accused him and the Muslim Brotherhood
of pushing an Islamist agenda onto Egypt, and say that he should
stand down.</p>
            <p>In a defiant televised speech on Tuesday evening, Mr Morsi said
he would give his life to defend constitutional legitimacy, and
blamed the unrest on corruption and remnants of the ousted regime
of Hosni Mubarak.</p>
            <p>Army chief Gen Abdel Fattah al-Sisi was reported to have met his
top commanders on Wednesday - and a source close to the military
told AFP news agency they had been discussing details of a
post-Morsi roadmap.</p>
            <p>Members of the Tamarod (Rebel) movement, which has mobilised
millions of demonstrators onto the streets to demand Mr Morsi's
resignation, were also part of the meeting. So too were leading
religious figures and Mr ElBaradei.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68510000/jpg/_68510029_68510028.jpg"
                 alt="Helicopters and flags in Cairo"/>
               <p class="caption">Egypt in 90 seconds: How did we get here?</p>
            </div>
            <p>The president was put under further pressure by the resignation
of six ministers from his government on Monday, including Foreign
Minister Kamel Amr.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>Elected president</strong>
            </p>
            <p>Mr Morsi became Egypt's first Islamist president on 30 June
2012, after winning an election considered free and fair following
the 2011 revolution that toppled Mubarak.</p>
            <p>But dissent has been growing, with protesters angry at the lack
of change in post-revolution Egypt and accusing the Brotherhood of
trying to protect its own interests.</p>
            <p>"This is a president threatening his own people. We don't
consider him the president of Egypt," said Mohammed Abdelaziz, a
leader of Tamarod.</p>
            <p>However, Mr Morsi and the Brotherhood still have significant
public support, and both sides have drawn huge numbers to rallies
in recent days.</p>
            <p>At least 39 people have now died since the protests began on
Sunday.</p>
            <p>The instability has also hit global oil prices, sending US light
crude above $100 a barrel for the first time since September last
year, amid concerns supply routes through the Suez Canal could be
affected.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68517000/jpg/_68517415_cairo_protests_2013_624_v5.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="400"
                 alt="Map"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12315833">Egypt in
crisis</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373156235629"
                     href="/news/magazine-23199377">Shifting sands</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373146727395"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23214054">What now for
Brotherhood?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373020716781"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23197801">Failed experiment</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373067054933"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23205101">Two years in Tahrir
Square</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Tamarod (Rebel)</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68477000/jpg/_68477293_68477292.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="A woman holds up a petition demanding President Mohammed Morsi's resignation (17 May 2013)"/>
            </div>
            <p>The Tamarod movement says more than 22 million people have
<a href="http://tamarod.com/index.php?page=english">signed a
petition</a> complaining that:</p>
            <ul>
               <li>Security has not been restored since the 2011 revolution that
toppled Hosni Mubarak</li>
               <li>The poor "have no place" in society</li>
               <li>The government has had to "beg" the International Monetary Fund
(IMF) for a $4.8bn (Â£3.17bn) loan to help
shore up the public finances</li>
               <li>There has been "no justice" for people killed by security
forces during the uprising and at anti-government protests since
then</li>
               <li>"No dignity is left" for Egyptians or their country</li>
               <li>The economy has "collapsed", with growth poor and inflation
high</li>
               <li>Egypt is "following in the footsteps" of the US</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-middle-east-23131953">Profile: Tamarod
protest movement</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
