<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23077299"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Is new Australian Prime Minister Kevin Rudd the saviour of his party or a dysfunctional leader, asks the BBC's Phil Mercer."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T07:57:26"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68405000/jpg/_68405357_018452709.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Kevin Rudd: Party saviour or 'recycled failure'?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23077299"/>
         <title>BBC News - Kevin Rudd: Party saviour or 'recycled
failure'?</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">08:57</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Kevin Rudd: Party saviour or 'recycled
failure'?</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Phil
Mercer</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News,
Sydney</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68405000/jpg/_68405199_018452709.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Kevin Rudd in parliament on 27 June 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Kevin Rudd: Party saviour or dysfunctional
leader?</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Is Kevin Rudd "a
psychopath with a giant ego" or a political messiah capable of
saving a divided and demoralised government from electoral
doom?</p>
            <p>Australia's 28th prime minister is a man of contradictions;
reportedly prone to furious tantrums and indecisiveness in private,
yet who is unremittingly casual and engaging in public.</p>
            <p>"You walk through a shopping centre with Kevin and it's a pretty
remarkable experience," enthused a Ruddite MP.</p>
            <p>He is the affable, bespectacled member for the inner Brisbane
seat of Griffith with "an angelic face", according to one voter,
and is arguably his country's most recognisable and popular
politician.</p>
            <p>But he is hated with an undiminished fury by a significant
portion of the governing Labor Party.</p>
            <p>His detractors, including the former Treasurer Wayne Swan, have
spent much of the past three years trying to sabotage Mr Rudd's
reputation since he was unexpectedly ousted as prime minister by
Julia Gillard in 2010.</p>
            <p>Last year, following a failed leadership coup, Mr Swan blasted
Kevin Rudd for his "dysfunctional decision-making and his deeply
demeaning attitude" towards his parliamentary colleagues.</p>
            <p>At the same time, the Labor MP Steve Gibbons gave Mr Rudd both
barrels on Twitter, decrying him as a "psychopath with a giant
ego".</p>
            <p>Another disgruntled Gillard cabinet loyalist, Tony Burke, was
also scathing of the new leader's record in the past. "The stories
that were around of the chaos, of the temperament, of the inability
to have decisions made, they are not stories," he said.</p>
            <p>But the kingmakers in Australian politics insist that those
demons have been largely purged and that Mr Rudd's political
rehabilitation is complete.</p>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68405000/jpg/_68405203_018452668.jpg"
                 width="224"
                 height="299"
                 alt="Julia Gillard in parliament on 27 June 2013"/>
               <span style="width:224px;">Labor MPs preferred Julia Gillard - but voters did
not warm to her</span>
            </div>
            <p>"He's reflected upon what's happened, he's learned lessons about
consultation, about listening, about learning lessons from the way
he would have done things differently from when he was in power the
first time," explained Bill Shorten, a Labor heavyweight.</p>
            <p>Kevin Rudd owes his remarkable return to power to the fear and
panic that have gripped Labor's ranks following a series of
disastrous opinion polls.</p>
            <p>Most MPs believe only the man who was once nicknamed "Dr Death"
for slashing public services in Queensland can save them from
annihilation at the ballot box.</p>
            <p>"Kevin Rudd is easily the best communicator, the best person to
connect with the Australian public that exists in politics today.
He is streets ahead of [opposition leader] Tony Abbott," said Labor
MP Richard Marles.</p>
            <p>But the task ahead seems immense or, if the polls are accurate,
impossible.</p>
            <p>Not only must the new prime minister try to heal a fractured
caucus but he must also convince voters that a divided government
deserves another chance at the next election.</p>
            <p>Denounced as dysfunctional by critics within his own party,
Kevin Rudd has been dismissed by Australia's conservative
opposition as a "recycled failure".</p>
            <p>With his mission for revenge completed, the man who spent his
childhood on a dairy farm on the Sunshine Coast north of Brisbane
has pleaded with his parliamentary adversaries to, well, be nice to
him.</p>
            <p>"As we all know political life is a very hard life. Occasionally
it can be kind, more often it is not. It has been that way since
time immemorial," Mr Rudd told MPs shortly after taking the oath of
office.</p>
            <p>"So let us try to be a little kinder and gentler with each other
in the further deliberations of this parliament."</p>
            <p>But the road to the next election due in September will be full
of unexpected twists and hair-raising turns, and stalked by
political highwaymen and women eager to ambush the Rudd
juggernaut.</p>
            <p>The big problem for Kevin Rudd is knowing where the real danger
lies; within the conservative opposition or inside his own
party.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story" rel="published-1277337809892" href="/news/10398741">Profile: Julia Gillard</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story" rel="published-1277370615278" href="/news/10400270">Profile: Kevin Rudd</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
