<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23094320"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Monsignor Nunzio Scarano is arrested over allegations of corruption and fraud in connection with an inquiry into the scandal-hit Vatican bank."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T12:04:31"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68432000/jpg/_68432131_li74xuac.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Cleric held in Vatican bank inquiry"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23094320"/>
         <title>BBC News - Monsignor Nunzio Scarano held in Vatican bank
inquiry</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">13:04</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Monsignor Nunzio Scarano held in Vatican
bank inquiry</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68445000/jpg/_68445242_68445160.jpg"
                 alt="Nunzio Scarano leaving building accompanied by policemen"/>
               <p class="caption">Footage shows Monsignor Scarano being escorted
to and from a police station, as the BBC's Alan Johnston reports
from</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A senior Italian
cleric has been arrested in connection with an inquiry into a
Vatican bank scandal over allegations of corruption and fraud.</p>
            <p>Monsignor Nunzio Scarano works in the Vatican's financial
administration. A secret service agent and a financial broker have
also been arrested.</p>
            <p>They are suspected of trying to move 20m euros ($26m;
Â£17m) illegally.</p>
            <p>Pope Francis ordered an unprecedented internal investigation
into the bank's affairs in the wake of recent scandals.</p>
            <p>Monsignor Scarano, 61, worked for years
as a senior accountant for a Vatican department known as Apsa (the
Administration of the Patrimony of the Apostolic See).</p>
            <p>He was suspended from that position "about a month ago, after
his superiors learnt about an investigation into his activities",
Vatican spokesman Federico Lombardi said.</p>
            <p>Monsignor Scarano has been under investigation by Italian police
for a series of suspicious transactions involving the recycling
through the Vatican bank of a series of cheques described as church
donations.</p>
            <p>Nunzio Scarano is a priest from Salerno in southern Italy, who
is called "monsignor" in recognition of his seniority at the
Vatican.</p>
            <p>He was arrested along with two other men suspected of plotting
to move 20m euros illegally from Switzerland to Italy. One,
Giovanni Maria Zito, is described as an Italian secret service
agent, and the other, Giovanni Carenzio, a financial broker.</p>
            <p>Earlier this month, the Pope named a trusted cleric to oversee
the management of the bank, which has been beset by allegations of
money laundering.</p>
            <p>Officially known as the Institute for the
Works of Religion (IOR), the bank is one of the world's most
secretive. It has 114 employees and 5.4bn euros of assets.</p>
            <p>Pope Francis has given the commission carte blanche, bypassing
normal secrecy rules, to try to get to the bottom of scandals which
have plagued the bank for decades.</p>
            <p>Traditionally, the Vatican Bank has refused to co-operate with
Italian authorities investigating financial crime on the grounds of
the sovereign independence of the Vatican city state, the BBC's
David Willey reports from Rome.</p>
            <p>But Pope Francis has shown that he is now determined to get to
the bottom of long-standing allegations of corruption and money
laundering involving the bank, our correspondent adds.</p>
            <p>The Institute for the Works of Religion was a major shareholder
in the Banco Ambrosiano, a big Italian bank which collapsed in 1982
with losses of more than $3bn.</p>
            <p>Its chairman, Roberto Calvi, was found hanging from Blackfriars
Bridge in London - in a murder disguised as a suicide. Mr Calvi had
close relations with the Vatican.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372245082802"
                  href="/news/world-europe-23063255">Pope sets up Vatican bank
inquiry</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1368719136803"
                  href="/news/world-europe-22551125">Pope Francis condemns 'money
cult'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1363204223008"
                  href="/news/world-europe-21777141">Profile: Pope Francis</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/66122000/jpg/_66122055_000086495.jpg"
                    alt="image of David Willey"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">David Willey</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
News, Rome</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>An allegedly corrupt Italian monsignor who until recently helped
administer the Vatican's financial assets ends up in handcuffs and
is hauled off to prison in Rome together with a financial broker
friend and an Italian secret service agent.</p>
            <p>Pope Francis's new attempt this week to impose transparency and
clarity on the Vatican's financial dealings could not be more
timely. A sweeping internal investigation into the running of the
Vatican's own bank was announced only two days ago. The result is
to be on the Pope's desk "promptly", and a cardinal on the
commission of inquiry has already admitted that major reforms are
necessary.</p>
            <p>Traditionally, great secrecy has been imposed by the Vatican on
the bank's functions. The Vatican has hitherto concealed its
activities behind a wall of confidentiality, justified by the
sovereign status of the papal enclave situated in the heart of
Rome.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Vatican Bank scandal</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <strong>September 2010:</strong> Italian police launch
investigation into money laundering at the bank</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>December 2010:</strong> Vatican sets up financial
authority to fight money laundering and make financial operations
more transparent</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>May 2012:</strong> Bank chief Ettore Gotti Tedeschi
dismissed for dereliction of duty</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>January 2013:</strong> Italian central bank suspends
all bank card payments in the Vatican, citing its failure to fully
implement anti-money laundering legislation</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>February 2013:</strong> German lawyer Ernst von
Freyberg appointed to head bank</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>June 2013:</strong> Pope Francis sets up a commission
to review the bank's activities</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
