<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23081103"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The Brazilian senate has approved a bill which will make corruption a &#34;heinous crime&#34; as mass protests for wide-ranging reforms continue."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T12:26:18"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68413000/jpg/_68413328_betterbrazil.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Brazil Senate passes corruption law"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Latin America"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23081103"/>
         <title>BBC News - Brazil Senate toughens punishments for
corruption</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">13:26</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Brazil Senate toughens punishments for
corruption</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68403000/jpg/_68403887_beloreu.jpg"
                 alt="Clashes at Belo Horizonte"/>
               <p class="caption">Julia Carneiro reports from Belo Horizonte as
police tackle protesters with tear gas</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Brazil's senate has
approved a bill which will toughen the punishment for corrupt
practices.</p>
            <p>Under the new law, corruption will be considered a "heinous
crime" and those found guilty will not be eligible for parole or
amnesty.</p>
            <p>The bill is the latest of a series passed as Brazil continues to
be rocked by mass rallies demanding reforms.</p>
            <p>It still needs to be approved by the chamber of deputies and
signed off by the president.</p>
            <p>The bill, which was first proposed in 2011, increases the
minimum prison sentence for corruption from two to four years.</p>
            <p>The maximum sentence stays the same at 12 years.</p>
            <p>It will apply to government officials who take advantage of
their job to demand favours and to those who embezzle public
funds.</p>
            <p>It will also apply to individuals or institutions who offer
bribes to officials.</p>
            <p>Brazil has seen a number of high-ranking officials convicted of
corruption over the past year.</p>
            <p>In the largest scandal, called Mensalao, more than two dozen
people were convicted for setting up a scheme that used public
funds to pay coalition parties for political support.</p>
            <p>Several were top politicians of the governing Workers Party
(PT).</p>
            <p>The vote comes a day after Congress rejected a constitutional
amendment which had been a key grievance of protesters.</p>
            <p>The protesters argued that the amendment would have made it more
difficult for federal prosecutors to investigate crimes, opening
the door to more corruption.</p>
            <p>Congress also voted to use all the royalties from newly
discovered oilfields for education and health.</p>
            <p>Some of the largest oil finds in recent years have been
discovered off the Brazilian coast, and the country is expected to
be able to produce tens of billions of barrels of crude oil over
the coming decades.</p>
            <p>In another attempt to pacify protesters, the government also
promised to speed up the pace of reform.</p>
            <p>It said it would simplify a referendum to establish a
constituent assembly - proposed on Monday by President Dilma
Rousseff - to allow for a vote as early as 7 September.</p>
            <p>Local governments have also passed reforms in an effort to quell
protests, with more than a dozen cities reversing public-transport
fare increases.</p>
            <p>Despite the reforms, about 50,000 protesters marched in the
streets of Belo Horizonte on Wednesday demanding more spending on
education and health, and a crackdown on corruption.</p>
            <p>They also complained about the high cost of the 2014 World Cup,
which Brazil will host.</p>
            <p>The protesters marched to the stadium where Brazil were playing
Uruguay in the semi-final of the Confederations Cup, a dress
rehearsal for the World Cup.</p>
            <p>About 20 people were detained when a small group tried to push
past police lines surrounding the venue.</p>
            <p>On Thursday, the city of Fortaleza will be hosting the second
semi-final between Spain and Italy.</p>
            <p>Protests have been planned for Thursday in more than a dozen
cities across Brazil, including in Fortaleza, Rio de Janeiro and
Sao Paulo.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>Brazil protests</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372142330896"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-23042841">Brazil leader plays hand over
protests</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371898134296"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-23013666">Scarred Brazil hopeful for
2014</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371694132110"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-22980894">Wrestling with unrest</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371753863911"
                     href="/news/world-europe-22995442">Containment or contagion?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
