<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-23095184"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The BBC's Sanjoy Majumder travels to the flood-hit Himalayan mountains in India's Uttarakhand state where bad weather and damaged roads are hampering rescue operations"/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T11:30:13"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68436000/jpg/_68436292_68433264.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="A journey through Uttarakhand's flooded landscape"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia/India"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-23095184"/>
         <title>BBC News - India floods: A journey through Uttarakhand's
flooded landscape</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">12:30</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">India floods: A journey through
Uttarakhand's flooded landscape</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68437000/jpg/_68437412_68437411.jpg"
                 alt="Empty town covered in mud following India's floods"/>
               <p class="caption">The BBC's Sanjoy Majumder visits a town left
encased in mud by the floods</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Devastating floods
in India's mountainous state of Uttarakhand damaged roads and
destroyed buildings frustrating the efforts of relief workers. The
BBC's Sanjoy Majumder took a journey into the mountains and found
ghost towns and abandoned homes.</p>
            <p>As we drive into the mountains it begins to rain, hard, just as
it has for much of the past week.</p>
            <p>We are on the main highway leading from Rishikesh, in the
foothills of the Himalayas, to Rudraprayag town and beyond to the
Hindu temple towns of Kedarnath and Badrinath.</p>
            <p>The Ganges river snakes alongside - its normally crystal blue
waters are completely muddy because of sediments from the floods
and landslides further up.</p>
            <p>Usually this highway is a busy one, filled with buses carrying
pilgrims either on their way to the Hindu shrines or back from
their spiritual journey.</p>
            <p>But for the most part now, there is hardly any traffic. It is
easy to see why.</p>
            <p>The road has been damaged in places and is so narrow in parts
that only one vehicle can pass at a time.</p>
            <p>At Devprayag, where the Alakananda and Bhagirathi rivers meet to
form the Ganges, part of the highway has been washed away. Workers
are busy trying to rebuild it.</p>
            <p>A few hours into our drive and the first real impact of the
floods becomes apparent.</p>
            <p>Just outside the town of Srinagar, we drive into a settlement
that is completely buried in the mud.</p>
            <p>The tops of a few houses are visible and a few cars stick out
from the sand that has been left behind after the flood waters
retreated.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68433000/jpg/_68433265_68433264.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Damaged houses above the flash flood-eroded Mandakini river in the town of Tilwara, around 30kms from Rudraprayag"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Many homes have been damaged by the
flood waters and landslides</span>
            </div>
            <p>It is eerily silent, like a ghost town.</p>
            <p>I finally meet a young man who is from a neighbouring
village.</p>
            <p>"There used to be 70 houses here," he tells me. "Most of them
were washed away."</p>
            <p>I walk into what used to be the local polytechnic. Its various
buildings - the library, the science block, the hostel - are all
covered with mud almost up to the roof.</p>
            <p>I peer into the window of what was clearly a classroom on the
second floor - it is now at the level of my knees and I can see the
ceiling fans inside. The rest of it is completely covered with
earth and muck.</p>
            <p>I find the college principal, Sanjeev Kumar, deep in
conversation with a few officials as they survey the damage.</p>
            <p>"It rained for 60 straight hours because of which the
Alakananda, which flows alongside, broke its banks and we were
flooded," he says.</p>
            <p>"Everything here was under 30 feet of water. The students rushed
out of their hostel, leaving everything behind. Now there's nothing
left. Their clothes, books, our equipment - all gone."</p>
            <p>We press on and join a convoy of trucks carrying relief material
heading up.</p>
            <p>Just outside Rudraprayag we come to a grinding halt. It is soon
obvious why.</p>
            <p>Ahead of us, a 50-metre section of the road is missing. It has
caved in because of a landslide. Some 200 vehicles are stranded at
both ends as bulldozers try and clear an alternate path.</p>
            <p>It is a frustrating wait especially for a group of volunteers
who have come from Delhi with several truckloads of critical
supplies.</p>
            <p>"We are carrying biscuits, water and medicines," one of the
volunteers - all dressed in bright red t-shirts - tells me.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68433000/jpg/_68433269_68433268.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Personnel from the Indian armed forces carry relief supplies from a helicopter for the stranded people at Guptkashi "/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Indian armed forces have carried out the
country's largest ever rescue operations</span>
            </div>
            <p>"We're headed for Badrinath, we've heard there are many people
there who need our help."</p>
            <p>They have already spent three hours waiting and it is not clear
how much longer it will take.</p>
            <p>Up ahead, the road to Badrinath is clear.</p>
            <p>But the highway to Kedarnath, the worst affected area, is
completely blocked. The only way to get there is to trek through
the thickly wooded mountains. Or from the air.</p>
            <p>Up above us, an Indian air force helicopter flies past in one of
several hundred missions in what has been the country's largest
ever rescue operation.</p>
            <p>Among those brought down is a group of Westerners who had come
here for a spiritual retreat on the banks of the Ganges.</p>
            <p>"We woke up to the news that the bridge leading to our ashram
over the river had been swept away," says Vishaal Kishore, who was
born in Essex, in the UK.</p>
            <p>"We realise now how incredibly lucky we are to have got
out."</p>
            <p>The local villagers were the first to come to their aid.</p>
            <p>"These people had lost everything, their homes, their
belongings," Mr Kishore says.</p>
            <p>"Yet they found time to cook food for us and cut a path through
the mountain to help us out."</p>
            <p>Most of those stranded in the mountains, mostly Hindu pilgrims
and tourists, have now been evacuated.</p>
            <p>But the focus is now shifting, as it must, to those left behind
- villages and local communities which have been completely
destroyed.</p>
            <p>It could take months before their homes and their lives are
rebuilt.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372325334484"
                  href="/news/world-asia-23078615">In pictures: Uttarakhand after
floods</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372073360755"
                  href="/news/world-asia-india-23026586">Frustrated efforts to rescue
flood victims</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371725316582"
                  href="/news/world-asia-india-22985093">Survivors' stories</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
