<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23095129"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A key al-Shabab leader in Somalia, Sheikh Hassan Dahir Aweys, has so far refused to surrender, elders from his clan tell the BBC."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T11:15:30"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68434000/jpg/_68434331_49176898.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Somali Islamist 'not surrendering'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Africa"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23095129"/>
         <title>BBC News - Somalia's al-Shabab leader Aweys 'not
surrendering'</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">12:15</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Somalia's al-Shabab leader Aweys 'not
surrendering'</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68432000/jpg/_68432910_49176898.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Hassan Dahir Aweys, file image"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Hassan Dahir Aweys is seen as the elder
statesman of Somali Islamists</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A key al-Shabab
leader in Somalia, Sheikh Hassan Dahir Aweys, has so far refused to
surrender, elders from his clan have told the BBC Somali
Service.</p>
            <p>The UN has reported that Mr Aweys has handed himself over to a
pro-government administration in central Somalia after falling out
with al-Shabab's leader.</p>
            <p>But Mr Aweys is in Galmudug region with his militia with the
consent of the local authorities, the elders say.</p>
            <p>They had flown there from the capital to see if he was willing
to make peace.</p>
            <p>Mr Aweys is seen as the elder statesman of Somali Islamists and
has been on a US list of people "linked to terrorism" since shortly
after the 9/11 attacks in 2001.</p>
            <p>Analysts say the administration in Adado - a town about 500km
(310 miles) north of the capital, Mogadishu - where Mr Aweys
arrived earlier in the week, does not want to provoke clashes.</p>
            <p>Mr Aweys left al-Shabab territory after factions within the
al-Qaeda linked group clashed last week - the first deadly
infighting since it launched an insurgency in 2006.</p>
            <p>Elders from Mr Aweys' Haber Gedir clan, which is powerful in the
Galmudug region, told the BBC they had been trying to mediate his
surrender after his arrival in Adado.</p>
            <p>They do not officially represent the UN-backed government of
President Hassan Sheikh Mohamud, though it seems likely he is fully
aware of the negotiations taking place, the BBC's international
development correspondent Mark Doyle says.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/67456000/gif/_67456379_som_controlled_areas_070513.gif"
                 width="304"
                 height="460"
                 alt="Map"/>
            </div>
            <p>The elders told the BBC Somali Service that negotiations with
the al-Shabab commander had so far failed.</p>
            <p>Mr Aweys denied that he had left al-Shabab and refused to go to
Mogadishu, join the government or enter mediation talks with the
government, they said.</p>
            <p>Analysts say if the split within al-Shabab is serious, Mr Aweys
may try to leave the country.</p>
            <p>If he stays in central Somalia he is at risk of capture from
Ethiopian troops, who back the Somali government, they say.</p>
            <p>Al-Shabab, which means "The Youth", is fighting to create an
Islamic state in Somalia - and despite being pushed out of key
cities in the past two years still remains in control of smaller
towns and large swathes of the countryside.</p>
            <p>It was formed in 2006 as a radical offshoot of the now-defunct
Union of Islamic Courts, which was led by Mr Aweys and for much of
that year controlled Mogadishu and many southern and central
areas.</p>
            <p>The exact cause of the al-Shabab split is not known, but there
has been a long-running internal power struggle between its leader
Ahmed Abdi Godane and those seen as more moderate who oppose links
with al-Qaeda, analysts say.</p>
            <p>There are conflicting reports about the fate of the
second-in-command - Ibrahim Afghan, the al-Shabab founder -
following last week's fighting. Initially, sources told the BBC he
had been captured and was in al-Shabab detention; subsequent
reports in local media say he has been executed.</p>
            <p>Some 18,000 African Union troops are in Somalia supporting the
government of President Mohamud who was elected by MPs last
September.</p>
            <p>His administration is the first one in more than two decades to
be recognised by the US and the International Monetary Fund
(IMF).</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>Somalia: Failed State</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1368265817426"
                     href="/news/world-africa-22492135">Lighting up Somalia</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1367881481721"
                     href="/news/world-africa-22429487">Struggle for unity</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1367922676211"
                     href="/news/world-africa-22434071">In pictures: Camp life</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1318862196109"
                     href="/news/world-africa-15336689">Q&amp;A: Who are al-Shabab?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
