<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23282168"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A woman described as a Saudi princess is arrested in California and accused of human trafficking after a Kenyan woman allegedly escaped from her home."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-12T02:21:02"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68687000/jpg/_68687411_68687395.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Saudi princess 'enslaved' Kenyan"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/US and Canada"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23282168"/>
         <title>BBC News - Saudi princess Meshael Alayban charged with
trafficking</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">12 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">03:21</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Saudi princess Meshael Alayban charged
with trafficking</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68687000/jpg/_68687405_68687404.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Saudi princess Meshael Alayban, right, listens to an interpreter during her scheduled appearance in court in Santa Ana, California 11 July 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Meshael Alayban did not enter a plea in
her first court appearance on Thursday</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A woman described as
a Saudi princess has been arrested in California and accused of
human trafficking.</p>
            <p>Meshael Alayban, 42, is accused of forcing a Kenyan woman to
work 16 hours a day while paying her far less than what she was
originally promised.</p>
            <p>Authorities say Ms Alayban took the woman's passport, precluding
her escape. Her lawyer called the case a dispute over work
hours.</p>
            <p>In November, California voters toughened human trafficking
penalties.</p>
            <p>If convicted, Ms Alayban faces a maximum sentence of 12 years in
prison, double the punishment prescribed before voters approved the
law known as Proposition 35.</p>
            <p>Prosecutors say she is one of six wives of Prince Abdulrahman
bin Nasser bin Abdulaziz al-Saud, a scion of the Saudi royal
family.</p>
            <p>The unnamed Kenyan woman had begun working for Ms Alayban last
year in Saudi Arabia under a two-year contract with an employment
agency.</p>
            <p>That contract guaranteed her $1,600
(Â£1,050) a month for eight-hour work days,
five days a week, California officials said. Instead she was paid
$220 a month and forced to work twice as long, according to
prosecutors.</p>
            <p>The 30-year-old Kenyan woman also alleges her passport was taken
from her when she arrived in Saudi Arabia. It was only returned to
her long enough for her to travel to the US with Ms Alayban.</p>
            <p>In California, she said she was forced to perform household
chores for at least eight people in four units at the same block of
flats where she was allegedly held captive. When she managed to
escape, she flagged down a bus driver and later went to police.</p>
            <p>Ms Alayban was arrested on Wednesday.</p>
            <p>"My client was a slave to this woman," said Steve Barick, a
lawyer for the accuser.</p>
            <p>"She wasn't able to freely move about. She had her ability to
move in and about the country taken away. She was intimidated. She
was promised one thing when she was in another country and when she
was brought here that was changed. She was overworked. She was
underpaid."</p>
            <p>Orange County District Attorney Tony Rackauckas described the
accuser's situation as "an example of forced labour."</p>
            <p>"It's been 150 years since the Emancipation Proclamation, so
slavery has been illegal in the United States and certainly in
California all this time," he said. "It's disappointing to see it
in use here."</p>
            <p>Ms Alayban did not enter a plea in her first court appearance on
Thursday. She was released on $5m bail shortly after the hearing
but was ordered to surrender her passport and to wear a GPS
tracking device.</p>
            <p>Prosecutors had asked a judge for bail to be set at $20m or
denied entirely, given Ms Alayban's wealth.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1340142214459"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-18514626">US reports reveals 'modern
slavery' toll</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
