<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23265423"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A Moscow court finds late Russian lawyer Sergei Magnitsky guilty of tax fraud in a case which has strained US-Russian ties."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-11T10:18:08"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68666000/jpg/_68666097_012385170-1.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Magnitsky found guilty of fraud"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23265423"/>
         <title>BBC News - Russia finds Magnitsky posthumously guilty of
fraud</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">11 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">11:18</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Russia finds Magnitsky posthumously guilty
of fraud</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68663000/jpg/_68663504_012385170-1.jpg"
                 alt="Sergei Magnitsky"/>
               <p class="caption">Oleg Boldyrev reports from Moscow: "Magnitsky
alleged that corrupt officials essentially stole some of the
companies... then used them to claim back millions in taxes"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A court in Moscow
has found late Russian lawyer Sergei Magnitsky guilty of tax
fraud.</p>
            <p>Magnitsky was arrested in 2008 after accusing officials of tax
fraud but was later himself accused of those crimes.</p>
            <p>His death in custody a year later led to a major diplomatic
dispute between Russia and the United States.</p>
            <p>William Browder, CEO of Hermitage Capital Management, which
Magnitsky represented, was found guilty in absentia and sentenced
to nine years.</p>
            <p>Browder, a US-born British citizen is in London, where the firm
is based.</p>
            <p>He has denied the charges and says the trial was politically
motivated. His defence team have said they will appeal against the
verdict.</p>
            <p>No sentence will be passed for Magnitsky, whose relatives regard
the case as illegal.</p>
            <p>A lawyer for the family told Russia's Rapsi news agency: "I did
not doubt that the decision would look like this."</p>
            <p>"I know that he committed no crimes."</p>
            <p>It is believed to be the first time in Soviet or Russian history
that a defendant was tried posthumously.</p>
            <p>Employed as an auditor for Hermitage,
Magnitsky uncovered what he described as a web of corruption
involving Russian tax officials, including the alleged theft of
more than $200m (Ã‚Â£125m).</p>
            <p>After reporting the allegations to the authorities, he was
himself detained on suspicion of helping Hermitage evade $17.4m in
taxes.</p>
            <p>He had pancreatitis and died in custody in 2009, but an
investigation by Russia's presidential council on human rights
concluded that he had been severely beaten and denied medical
treatment.</p>
            <p>Last December, a Russian court acquitted a prison doctor accused
of negligence over Mr Magnitsky's death. And in March this year the
investigation into his death was dropped altogether due to "lack of
evidence of a crime".</p>
            <p>Browder has described the charges filed against him as an
"absurdity" and revenge for his campaign to put pressure on Russia
over the Magnitsky case.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68662000/jpg/_68662740_41608244.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Hermitage Fund manager William Browder"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">William Browder has spearheaded efforts in the US to
put pressure on Russia over the Magnitsky case</span>
            </div>
            <p>Speaking to the BBC on Wednesday, he said the trial was "proof"
that President Vladimir Putin "will use the courts in order to
cover up his economic crimes".</p>
            <p>"This entire process has been done because Sergei Magnitsky
discovered a vast $230m fraud by the Russian state and blew the
whistle on the officials who orchestrated the crime, and for that
he was tortured and killed in police custody and then prosecuted
afterwards," he said.</p>
            <p>"Instead of Putin bringing justice he exonerated all the
officials involved and prosecuted the whistle blowers.</p>
            <p>He said he did not believe he would be arrested if
convicted.</p>
            <p>Interpol <a href="http://www.interpol.int/News-and-media/News-media-releases/2013/PR063"
               title="Interpol statement">has said</a> it considers the trial
politically motivated and Mr Browder said it was his expectation
"that no Western country will co-operate with the Russians".</p>
            <p>"We will carry on in our fight for justice for Sergei Magnitsky
as long as it takes," he said.</p>
            <p>The case became a symbol in the US of the fight against
corruption in Russia.</p>
            <p>Last year, Washington passed the Magnitsky Act, blacklisting
Russian officials accused of human rights violations, including
those linked to the case.</p>
            <p>In response, Russian President Vladimir Putin signed a law
barring Americans from adopting Russian orphans.</p>
            <p>The Russian foreign ministry also drew up its own blacklist of
US officials who are alleged to have committed human rights
violations.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1354813087205"
                  href="/news/world-europe-20626960">Q&amp;A: The Magnitsky
affair</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372175826094"
                  href="/news/world-europe-23048047">Call for Magnitsky 'smart
sanctions'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1354883604211"
                  href="/news/world-europe-20638613">Russia retaliates in US bill
row</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Instead of Putin bringing justice he
exonerated all the officials involved and prosecuted the whistle
blowers”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">William Browder</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
