<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23062291"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A political deal on the EU's hotly contested seven-year budget is struck as leaders of the 27 countries gather for a summit in Brussels."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T16:45:10"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68409000/jpg/_68409148_68409141.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="EU reaches deal on seven-year budget"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23062291"/>
         <title>BBC News - EU reaches political deal on seven-year
budget</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">17:45</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">EU reaches political deal on seven-year
budget</h1>
            <div class="has-icon-comment dna-comment-count-simple"> </div>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68409000/jpg/_68409187_018453738-1.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="301"
                 alt="European Parliament speaker Martin Schulz (left) talks to European Commission President Jose Manuel Barroso in Brussels, 27 June "/>
               <span style="width:464px;">European Parliament speaker Martin
Schulz (left) paid tribute to Mr Barroso (right)</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A political deal on
the EU's hotly contested seven-year budget has been struck,
European Commission President Jose Manuel Barroso has
announced.</p>
            <p>The deal on the 2014-2020 budget was reached between member
states and European Parliament leaders, he said.</p>
            <p>The 960bn-euro (Ã‚Â£822bn; $1.3tn) budget
cuts real spending for the first time.</p>
            <p>Speaking in Brussels as EU leaders gathered for a summit, Mr
Barroso said the deal would speed up spending on youth
employment.</p>
            <p>Nearly a quarter of people aged 18 to 25 in the EU have no job,
while in Greece and Spain it is more than half.</p>
            <p>EU leaders will consider mobilising 6bn
euros (Ã‚Â£5bn; $8bn) earlier than planned to
help youth training schemes.</p>
            <p>On the eve of the summit draft plans were also agreed on
<a href="/news/world-europe-23062284"
               title="EU to cut subsidies to big farms">agricultural reform</a> and how
to <a href="/news/business-23076541"
               title="EU in draft deal on bank bailouts">rescue troubled banks.</a>
            </p>
            <p>Amid widespread resistance to the ongoing austerity measures in
the eurozone, trade unions in Portugal began a 24-hour strike on
Thursday.</p>
            <p>Public transport crawled to a halt as a result of the action by
unions representing more than a million workers.</p>
            <p>The 2014-2020 budget was agreed at a summit in February but its
ratification had been blocked by the parliament.</p>
            <p>It appears that under the new deal, the figures agreed will
remain unchanged but, in a concession to the European Parliament,
unspent money will be transferred from one year to the next, rather
than returning to national budgets as at present.</p>
            <p>The speaker of the European Parliament, Martin Schulz, urged
MEPs to give it their backing.</p>
            <p>He told reporters the deal was "the minimum" that MEPs had
pushed for, but "from a psychological point of view it's
progress".</p>
            <p>If the 27 governments give unanimous approval, and a majority of
MEPs back the deal, the final text will be adopted in
September.</p>
            <p>European Council head Herman Van Rompuy said in <a href="http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_Data/docs/pressdata/en/ec/137616.pdf">
a press release</a> that youth employment schemes should be
accelerated and youth mobility increased.</p>
            <p>The Commission's <a href="http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_SPEECH-13-400_en.htm"
               title="Commissioner Andor on Youth Guarantee">Youth Guarantee plan</a>
would offer young people across Europe a quality apprenticeship or
job in the first four months after becoming unemployed or leaving
formal education.</p>
            <p>An unemployed Czech graduate, Dagmar Hvizdosova, told the BBC
"it's been one year since I got my bachelor degree in media studies
- IÃ‚Â´ve been trying to find a job in that
industry, however, I haven't been successful. I've therefore
decided to move abroad and go for a Master's degree...</p>
            <p>"Here in the Czech Republic there are so many people with
university degrees that it is impossible to find a job straight
after school. In addition, the bachelor degree is underrated - it
now has the same or possibly less value as secondary education
about 10 years ago."</p>
            <p>A source at the European Commission said an extra 10bn euros in
funding for the European Investment Bank (EIB) could be used to
encourage private banks to lend more to small and medium-sized
businesses (SMEs), which account for about 99% of businesses in the
EU.</p>
            <p>The draft summit conclusions, seen by the BBC, say the leaders
note "the importance of shifting taxation away from labour, as a
means of increasing employability and boosting job creation and
competitiveness".</p>
            <p>In a statement on arrival, UK Prime Minister David Cameron said
"what this [EU] council should be about is doing in Brussels what
we're doing in Britain, which is getting control of spending,
making sure we live within our means and then making ourselves more
competitive, getting rid of regulations, making it easier for
businesses to create jobs".</p>
            <p>Under the bank rescue deal, bank creditors and shareholders of
failed banks would take the first hits, followed by savers with
deposits of more than 100,000 euros.</p>
            <p>If that is not enough, government help would be called upon, and
taxpayers would be among the last to shoulder losses.</p>
            <p>Leaders are also expected to approve accession talks for Serbia,
as well as formalising Croatia's entry into the EU next week.</p>
            <p>Serbian Prime Minister Ivica Dacic said on the eve of the summit
that he hoped to see his country join within five years at
most.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372209027428"
                  href="/news/world-europe-23047678">Jobs crisis: Europe's great
migration</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1353579538537"
                  href="/news/world-europe-20442880">EU budget: Where the money
goes</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/49177000/jpg/_49177600_morris_bbc.jpg"
                    alt="image of Chris Morris"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Chris Morris</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
News, Brussels</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>The deal agreed by EU leaders in February did not have enough
support to be passed in the European Parliament. So something had
to give, because under the 2009 Lisbon Treaty, the parliament now
has the power to block the multi-annual budget if it wants.</p>
            <p>There are still MEPs who are disappointed but the new deal looks
set to be approved. The socialist group leader, Hannes Swoboda,
said the compromise was "not ideal, but there are decisive
improvements".</p>
            <p>The overall ceiling on spending will not change - and that means
leaders like UK Prime Minister David Cameron can continue to say
that they have secured a real-terms cut in the budget for the first
time. But the structure of the budget deal has become more
flexible, to reflect the fact that many MEPs want to ensure that as
much of the money as possible is actually spent.</p>
            <p>In the current seven-year budget, tens of billions of euros have
not been spent, and funds have been returned to national coffers.
If that does not happen over the next seven years - and money is
transferred from one area to another, or from one year to another,
as MEPs insist it should be - then it is possible in theory that
spending could rise.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Unemployment rates</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Greece - 27%</li>
               <li>Spain - 26.8%</li>
               <li>Portugal - 17.8%</li>
               <li>Cyprus - 15.6%</li>
               <li>Rep of Ireland - 13.5%</li>
               <li>Italy - 12%</li>
               <li>France - 11%</li>
               <li>EU average - 11%</li>
               <li>UK - 7.7%</li>
               <li>Germany - 5.4%</li>
            </ul>
            <p>Source: Eurostat, April 2013 (Figures for Greece &amp; UK are
for February 2013)</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
