<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23123963"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Brazil's victory at the Confederations Cup is overshadowed by the protests, which continue to shake the the country, says the BBC's Gary Duffy."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T08:26:30"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68472000/jpg/_68472985_hi018499823.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Protesters question Brazil leaders' credibility"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Latin America"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23123963"/>
         <title>BBC News - Protesters question Brazil leaders'
credibility</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">09:26</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Protesters question Brazil leaders'
credibility</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Gary Duffy</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC Brasil, Sao Paulo</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68472000/jpg/_68472977_hi018505226.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Protestors clash with riot squad officers on a street near Maracana stadium in Rio de Janeiro (30 June 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The actions of police, seen here
clashing with protesters near the Maracana stadium, are a subject
of widespread concern</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Brazil has emerged
from the Confederations Cup victorious on the pitch but shaken by
demonstrations and conflict on the streets.</p>
            <p>The tournament, which was meant be a dress rehearsal for the
World Cup, continued with South America's largest country making
headlines around the world for reasons it never expected.</p>
            <p>The cost of hosting the Confederations Cup, the 2014 World Cup
and the Olympics were key issues for many protesters, but the
demonstrations began for other reasons and there were other
concerns.</p>
            <p>Corruption, the state of Brazil's
education and health systems, police violence and crime, fares on
public transport, gay rights and constitutional change were all
raised on the streets.</p>
            <p>The scale of the protests has shaken Brazil's political elite,
which took days to work out how to respond and is still working on
its answers.</p>
            <p>Once again the actions of the police are a subject of widespread
concern.</p>
            <p>The newspaper Estado de Sao Paulo estimated that protests have
been taking place at least once an hour and affected as many as 353
Brazilian cities.</p>
            <p>Six people were reported to have died in incidents related to
protests and dozens were injured, while the image of tear gas
hanging in the air, and rubber bullets flying, filled national TV
bulletins.</p>
            <p>Even at the final in Rio's landmark Maracana stadium, where the
national team won a stunning victory over Spain, the gas from
nearby clashes managed to reach some watching in the stands.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68473000/jpg/_68473083_hi018505055.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Brazilian football team holds up trophy (30 June 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">President Rousseff was not there to
award the trophy</span>
            </div>
            <p>Fifa will certainly have some searching questions over security
for the Brazilian authorities in advance of next year's World
cup.</p>
            <p>That will be a worry for the government, but faced with an
election in 2014, President Dilma Rousseff has many pressing
concerns on her mind.</p>
            <p>In a personally humiliating moment,
having been booed at the opening ceremony of the tournament, she
decided not to attend Sunday's final.</p>
            <p>It was left to her Sports Minister, Aldo Rebelo, to hand over
the trophy instead.</p>
            <p>A poll published on Saturday suggested that 30% of Brazilians
currently consider Ms Rousseff's administration "good or
excellent", a fall from 57% just three weeks ago.</p>
            <p>The polling agency Datafolha described it as "the biggest drop
between one poll and another since 1990".</p>
            <p>Ms Rousseff's presidency has had record approval rates until
recently.</p>
            <p>She will draw some comfort from the fact that a majority of the
population still supports her government, with a total of 73%
rating it either average or excellent.</p>
            <p>But few politicians in Brazil are in doubt that their very
credibility has been called into question by the events of the last
few weeks.</p>
            <p>The government and the National Congress have been rushing to
approve or change measures to meet the protesters' demands.</p>
            <p>More money has been pledged to go towards transport while
foreign doctors are to be brought to Brazil to help tackle a
shortfall in the public health system.</p>
            <p>A controversial constitutional amendment which critics said
would weaken the power of federal prosecutors to investigate
corruption was defeated.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68473000/jpg/_68473085_hi018399109.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Bus near a vandalised bus stop in Rio de Janeiro (22 June 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The protests were sparked by an increase
in public transport fares</span>
            </div>
            <p>Several local authorities have reversed increases in fares on
public transport which was a key issue at the start of the
protests.</p>
            <p>President Rousseff has also proposed a plebiscite on political
reform but the measure needed to be refined within hours of being
announced, and remains at the centre of a heated debate.</p>
            <p>Brazilians did not take to the streets because of some
suppressed opposition to sporting tournaments they had cunningly
concealed from the rest of the world.</p>
            <p>Brazil's growing prominence in recent years has lifted millions
out of poverty and raised expectations that in many aspects of life
were not being met.</p>
            <p>Why is the public education for my child not adequate? Why is my
local hospital so poor, and why are my roads so bad, and my taxes
so high? Why is there so much crime in our cities?</p>
            <p>These are just some of the questions being raised, and a
high-profile sporting tournament provided the platform to raise
them on an international stage, energised by social media
campaigns.</p>
            <p>How these doubts are answered is now in the hands of Brazil's
political leaders and as they wrestle with that they are under
scrutiny from their own people as never before.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>Brazil protests</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372142330896"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-23042841">Brazil leader plays hand over
protests</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371898134296"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-23013666">Scarred Brazil hopeful for
2014</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371694132110"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-22980894">Wrestling with unrest</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371753863911"
                     href="/news/world-europe-22995442">Containment or contagion?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Protests have been taking place at least
once an hour and affected as many as 353 Brazilian
cities”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">A high-profile sporting tournament provided
the platform to raise them on an international stage, energised by
social media campaigns”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
