<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23235847"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A leaked Pakistan government report into the killing of Osama Bin Laden in 2011 accuses intelligence services of incompetence and negligence."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-08T23:18:38"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68620000/jpg/_68620616_52454297.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Pakistan 'incompetent' on Bin Laden"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23235847"/>
         <title>BBC News - Leaked Bin Laden report reveals Pakistan
failures</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">9 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:18</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Leaked Bin Laden report reveals Pakistan
failures</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68620000/jpg/_68620989_52454297.jpg"
                 alt="Purported Bin Laden video in 2007"/>
               <p class="caption">Some believed the failure to capture or kill Bin
Laden was the result of collusion by Pakistani officials</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Incompetence and
negligence allowed Osama Bin Laden to live in Pakistan undetected
for almost a decade, a leaked government report suggests.</p>
            <p>A version of the <a href="http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/spotlight/binladenfiles/2013/07/201378143927822246.html">
report leaked to al-Jazeera</a> says the killing of Bin Laden by US
forces was a "criminal act of murder" ordered by the US
president.</p>
            <p>It also reveals details of the al-Qaeda leader's whereabouts and
day-to-day life after fleeing Afghanistan in 2001.</p>
            <p>Bin Laden was killed by US forces in north-west Pakistan in May
2011.</p>
            <p>US suspicions about Bin Laden's location had previously been
dismissed by Pakistan. However, his discovery in a compound in
Abbottabad and subsequent killing in a US Navy Seal operation put a
strain on US-Pakistan relations.</p>
            <p>Shortly after the raid, the Pakistan parliament called for an
independent enquiry - the Abbottabad Commission - to establish
whether the failures of the government were due to incompetence or
colluding with al-Qaeda.</p>
            <p>It was also commissioned to investigate the Pakistani
intelligence services' failure to detect CIA activity on its soil
in the run-up to the raid "that culminated in the avoidable
humiliation of the people of Pakistan".</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68620000/jpg/_68620289_011885770.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Osama Bin Laden's compound in Abbottabad, north-west Pakistan"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">At least 25 people were living in the
Abbottabad compound</span>
            </div>
            <p>In its findings, the report described the lack of intelligence
as "government implosion syndrome".</p>
            <p>The leaked documents fiercely criticised the Pakistani
government and military, describing "culpable negligence and
incompetence at almost all levels of government".</p>
            <p>While the commission said it found nothing to support
allegations of complicity, it said it could not rule out "the
possibility of some degree of connivance inside or outside the
government".</p>
            <p>The report also voiced harsh criticism of the Navy Seal raid on
Abbottabad, describing it as an "American act of war" and
Pakistan's "greatest humiliation" since East Pakistan seceded in
1971.</p>
            <p>It quotes officials as saying that Pakistan air force jets were
scrambled to shoot down the US helicopters, but too late.</p>
            <p>The 336-page document was the result of interviews with more
than 200 witnesses, including senior civilian and military
officials, as well as with Bin Laden's three widows prior to their
deportation to Saudi Arabia.</p>
            <p>The report has been in the hands of the government for more than
six months, the BBC's Richard Galpin says, but it had been kept
under wraps.</p>
            <p>In the version leaked to al-Jazeera, the daily life of Bin Laden
after fleeing the US-led invasion of Afghanistan in 2001 is
documented.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68620000/jpg/_68620283_014656773.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Undated image of Osama Bin Laden watching TV in his Abbottabad compound "/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The report details the frugal lifestyle
of Bin Laden and his family, with "minimum security" at his
compound</span>
            </div>
            <p>He was reported to have arrived in Pakistan in the spring or
summer of 2002, staying in parts of South Waziristan, Bajaur,
Peshawar, Swat and Haripur before settling in Abbottabad in
2005.</p>
            <p>Referring to Bin Laden and his entourage, the report said: "They
kept a very low profile and lived extremely frugally. They never
exposed themselves to public view."</p>
            <p>Testimony from his widows said he wore a cowboy hat whilst
moving around the compound to avoid detection.</p>
            <p>However, over a period of six years the unusual nature of the
compound failed to the draw the attention of the intelligence
services, the report goes on.</p>
            <p>"How the entire neighbourhood, local officials, police and
security and intelligence officials all missed the size, the
strange shape, the barbed wire, the lack of cars and visitors etc
over a period of nearly six years beggars belief."</p>
            <p>Commenting on the leak, the head of the commission, Javed Iqbal,
told Pakistani Dunya TV that it was "based on assumptions" and did
not include even one out of more than 100 recommendations the
commission had made in its findings.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-13257972">Bin Laden
killed</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1304321155547"
                     href="/news/world-south-asia-13257330">How raid happened</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1304812369820"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-13325262">Revealing images</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1304797636730"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-13323849">What videos show</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1305232900135"
                     href="/news/world-south-asia-13384217">At al-Qaeda's helm?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
