<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-22963870"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Military helicopters and the army are leading rescue operations in India's flood-hit northern states, where 138 people are now known to have died."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T13:39:49"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68251000/jpg/_68251906_68251775.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Army leads north India flood rescue"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia/India"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-22963870"/>
         <title>BBC News - North India floods: Army leads rescue
operations</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">14:39</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">North India floods: Army leads rescue
operations</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68251000/jpg/_68251914_68251777.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Indian army officials help travellers and villagers up a steep slope after they were stranded by the rising floodwaters of the River Alaknanda near Govindghat, Chamoli District in the northern Indian state of Uttarakhand on June 18"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Thousands of pilgrims are stranded after
roads caved in</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Military helicopters
and the army are leading rescue operations in India's flood-hit
northern states, where 138 people are now known to have died.</p>
            <p>About 10,000 people have been rescued in worst-hit Uttarakhand
state over three days, PM Manmohan Singh said.</p>
            <p>Tens of thousands of pilgrims are still stranded in Uttarakhand,
where more than 100 people have been killed.</p>
            <p>Flood-related deaths have also been reported in Himachal Pradesh
and Uttar Pradesh states and neighbouring Nepal.</p>
            <p>At least 22 people have been killed and 18 are missing in
landslides and floods triggered by heavy rainfall in remote parts
of Nepal, home ministry spokesman Shankar Koirala told the AFP news
agency.</p>
            <p>He said that more than 100 homes - mostly in western Nepal - had
been damaged by the floods and the government had agreed to step up
relief efforts at an emergency meeting.</p>
            <p>The monsoon season generally lasts from
June to September, bringing rain which is critical to the farming
output of both countries, but this year the rain in the north of
India and parts of Nepal has been heavier than usual.</p>
            <p>On Wednesday afternoon, Prime Minister Manmohan Singh and
Congress party chief Sonia Gandhi flew over Uttarakhand to assess
the damage caused by the floods.</p>
            <p>Mr Singh later described the situation there as "distressing"
and announced a 10bn rupee ($170m; Â£127m)
aid package for the state.</p>
            <p>"The maximum devastation has been in [the temple town of]
Kedarnath and its vicinity," he said. "The priority is to rescue
the stranded and provide urgently needed succour to those most
needing it."</p>
            <p>Mr Singh said in Uttarakhand, 102 people had died, but he feared
that "the loss of lives could eventually be much higher".</p>
            <p>Meanwhile, more than 5,500 soldiers and hundreds of paramilitary
and disaster management officials are working to rescue and provide
emergency supplies to thousands of tourists and pilgrims stranded
in towns and temples.</p>
            <p>Military officials said five airbases were being used to help
speed up rescue operations.</p>
            <p>The situation in Uttarakhand was "really very bad", top disaster
management official Piyush Rautela was quoted as telling news
agency AFP.</p>
            <p>The floods have swept away buildings and triggered landslides in
some places, blocking roads. More than 20 bridges have
collapsed.</p>
            <p>Portions of a Hindu temple in Kedarnath were washed away and the
shrine was "submerged in mud and slush", Uttarakhand disaster
relief minister Jaspal Arya said.</p>
            <p>India's Home Minister Sushil Kumar Shinde said more than 62,000
pilgrims were stranded at various places.</p>
            <p>Most of the pilgrims - bound for local Himalayan shrines - are
stranded in Rudraprayag, Chamoli and Uttarkashi districts after
roads caved in and bridges collapsed.</p>
            <p>Some of the pilgrims who are stranded in a guest house in
Joshimath town spoke to the BBC Hindi's Shalini Joshi about their
ordeal.</p>
            <p>"We were stuck in the car for 14 hours, we spent the entire
night there. The mountains were collapsing above us, while a river
in spate was raging below us," Delhi resident Asha Mahajan
said.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68251000/jpg/_68251764_68251758.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="A view of the Hindu holy town of Kedarnath from a helicopter after a flood, in the northern Indian state of Uttarakhand, India, Tuesday, June 18, 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The temple town of Kedarnath is among
the worst affected, officials say</span>
            </div>
            <p>"There was a huge traffic jam, we could neither go forward, nor
move back. Anything could have happened. It was raining heavily and
we were afraid that there might be a landslide. Thank God we are
all right," she added.</p>
            <p>"This is the first time we've come to the mountains. But we're
now stuck in Joshimath. We are so close to the holy shrine of
Badrinath, but we've been told not to go there. It makes me really
said, but what can we do? If I survive, I'll come back here," said
Dineshbhai Kishanbhai Patel who is visiting from the western state
of Gujarat.</p>
            <p>"It's been a harrowing trip for us," said Trilochan Singh from
Mumbai city. "We hear the roads are all broken, cars and shops have
been swept away. It is frightening. We are very lucky to be
alive."</p>
            <p>Local officials told the BBC that the number of dead was
expected to rise as rescue workers had still not reached many
affected areas.</p>
            <p>In Himachal Pradesh, where at least 10 people have been killed
in landslides, Chief Minister Virbhadra Singh was himself stranded
in Kinnaur district for nearly 60 hours.</p>
            <p>He was evacuated on Tuesday by a helicopter hired by his
Congress party, reports said.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371533349514"
                  href="/news/world-asia-india-22947552">In pictures: India
floods</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371463831411"
                  href="/news/world-asia-india-22936533">India floods: At least 19 dead
<span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370306586773"
                  href="/news/world-asia-india-22750169">Why is India obsessed with
monsoon rains?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>AT THE SCENE</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">Shalini Joshi</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Dehradun</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>The scale of devastation in Uttarakhand is staggering. As
rescuers establish contact with more of the affected villages and
settlements, they say many have been flattened to the ground.</p>
            <p>On Wednesday, Chief Minister Vijay Bahuguna flew over Kedarnath,
Guptkashi, Govindghat and Joshimath areas to assess the damage.</p>
            <p>Most of the temple town of Kedarnath - apart from the main Shiva
temple - is buried under mud and debris. There are scenes of
devastation everywhere. Officials said it would take at least three
to four years to get the town back on its feet.</p>
            <p>Many of the villages remain cut off with emergency workers
unable to reach marooned villages. There are are reported to be
groups of people stranded in remote areas without any supplies.
Most roads are still closed and many bridges, homes, schools and
hotels have been damaged, hampering the relief operation.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
