<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-22964089"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="High levels of a toxic radioactive isotope, strontium-90, have been found in groundwater at Japan's Fukushima nuclear plant, its operator says."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T09:32:04"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68251000/jpg/_68251953_68007671.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Toxic substance in Fukushima water"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-22964089"/>
         <title>BBC News - Fukushima nuclear plant: Toxic isotope found in
groundwater</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">10:32</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Fukushima nuclear plant: Toxic isotope
found in groundwater</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68007000/jpg/_68007670_017771308-1.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="File photo: IAEA inspectors at the Fukushima Dai-ichi nuclear power plant, 17 April 2013 "/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Radioactive water was found to be
leaking from a storage tank at the plant last month</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">High levels of a
toxic radioactive isotope have been found in groundwater at Japan's
Fukushima nuclear plant, its operator says.</p>
            <p>Tokyo Electric Power Company (Tepco) said tests showed
Strontium-90 was present at 30 times the legal rate.</p>
            <p>The radioactive isotope tritium has also been detected at
elevated levels.</p>
            <p>The plant, crippled by the 2011 earthquake and tsunami, has
recently seen a series of water leaks and power failures.</p>
            <p>The tsunami knocked out cooling systems to the reactors, which
melted down.</p>
            <p>Water is now being pumped in to the reactors to cool them but
this has left Tepco with the problem of how to safely store the
contaminated water.</p>
            <p>There have been several reports of leaks from storage tanks or
pipes.</p>
            <p>Strontium-90 is formed as a by-product of
nuclear fission. Tests showed that levels of strontium in
groundwater at the Fukushima plant had increased 100-fold since the
end of last year, Toshihiko Fukuda, a Tepco official, told
media.</p>
            <p>Mr Fukuda said Tepco believed the elevated levels originated
from a leak of contaminated water in April 2011 from one of the
reactors.</p>
            <p>"As it's near where the leak from reactor number two happened
and taking into account the situation at the time, we believe that
water left over from that time is the highest possibility," he
said.</p>
            <p>Tritium, used in glow-in-the-dark watches, was found at eight
times the allowable level.</p>
            <p>Mr Fukuda said that samples from the sea showed no rise in
either substance and the company believed the groundwater was being
contained by concrete foundations.</p>
            <p>"When we look at the impact that is having on the ocean, the
levels seem to be within past trends and so we don't believe it's
having an effect."</p>
            <p>But the discovery is another setback for Tepco's plan to pump
groundwater from the plant into the sea, correspondents say.</p>
            <p>Nuclear chemist Michiaki Furukawa told Reuters news agency that
Tepco should not release contaminated water into the ocean.</p>
            <p>"They have to keep it somewhere so that it can't escape outside
the plant," he said. "Tepco needs to carry out more regular testing
in specific areas and disclose everything they find."</p>
            <p>The Fukushima power plant has faced a series of problems this
year. Early this month, radioactive water was found leaking from a
storage tank.</p>
            <p>The plant also suffered three power failures in five weeks
earlier this year. A leak of radioactive water from one of the
plant's underground storage pools was also detected in April.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370498435874"
                  href="/news/world-asia-22793353">Water leak at Fukushima nuclear
plant</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1366627160915"
                  href="/news/world-asia-22246464">IAEA urges Fukushima
improvements</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1365506122001"
                  href="/news/world-asia-22079370">Fukushima radioactive water
'leak'</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <div class="correspondent-byline">
               <a href="/news/correspondents/mattmcgrath/">
                  <span class="byline-picture">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/64427000/jpg/_64427842_mcgrath144x104white.jpg"
                       alt="image of Matt McGrath"/>
                  </span>
               </a>
               <span class="byline-heading">Analysis</span>
               <a href="/news/correspondents/mattmcgrath/">
                  <span class="byline-name">Matt
McGrath</span>
               </a>
               <span class="byline-title">Environment
correspondent, BBC News</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>Detecting increasing levels of the highly radioactive substance
Strontium-90 indicates that Tepco is still struggling to contain
the Fukushima reactors.</p>
            <p>Water continues to be a massive problem as the company is
running out of storage space for the large amounts of the liquid
they use every day as to cool the plant.</p>
            <p>On top of that around 400 tonnes of groundwater flow into the
reactor buildings every day. They have even dug up 12 relief wells
near the site in an effort to halt the ingress.</p>
            <p>As to the high levels of Strontium-90 detected, it has a half
life of 29 years. This means that in humans it can continue to
irradiate them for many years. It can be ingested from food or
water and tends to concentrate in the bones and is believed to
cause cancer there.</p>
            <p>In animal studies, exposure to Strontium-90 also caused harmful
reproductive effects. These effects happened when animals were
exposed to doses more than a million times higher than typical
exposure levels for humans.</p>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/correspondents/mattmcgrath/">Read more from
Matt</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
