<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-22814837"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Calcutta loves football, and it adores its foreign players, writes BBC Hindi's Zubair Ahmed."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T00:30:53"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68128000/jpg/_68128124_match_afp.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Why foreign footballers are big in Calcutta"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia/India"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-22814837"/>
         <title>BBC News - Why foreign footballers are big in
Calcutta</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:30</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Why foreign footballers are big in
Calcutta</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Zubair
Ahmed</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC Hindi,
Calcutta</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68126000/jpg/_68126774_match_afp.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="300"
                 alt="A foreign footballer who plays for India's East Bengal Club"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Calcutta's top football leagues have
about 40 foreign players</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Edeh Chidi may not
be known in his native Nigeria, but in the eastern Indian city of
Calcutta, he is a hero.</p>
            <p>Calcutta loves football, and it adores its foreign players.</p>
            <p>Recently Chidi, who plays for East Bengal, tasted fans'
adulation after scoring a brace against arch rivals Mohun
Bagan.</p>
            <p>"The feeling's incredible. You receive a lot of gifts, chanting
of names and autograph requests," says the Lagos-born striker.</p>
            <p>But what brought him to Calcutta from football-rich Nigeria?</p>
            <p>"I knew nothing about Calcutta football. I came here when I was
15 straight from the Pepsi Academy in Nigeria."</p>
            <p>Chidi, 25, has never played professional football in Nigeria.
"You play wherever you can. My agent approached me just when I
graduated from the academy and I came here."</p>
            <p>India, ranked 150 in the world by football's governing body
Fifa, is not exactly the first choice for Nigerian players. But
Calcutta fans love them for their skills and their physical
dominance on the pitch.</p>
            <p>For Chidi, adjusting to life in the city was difficult initially
"with people, food and language being different", but now he feels
"completely at home".</p>
            <p>Nigerians dominate the 19-club Calcutta premier league, which
began in 1898 and is the oldest in Asia.</p>
            <p>Ranti Martins of Prayag United and Odafa Okolie of Mohun Bagan
have been the two top scorers this year.</p>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68125000/jpg/_68125401_barisi2.jpg"
                 width="224"
                 height="299"
                 alt="Andrew Barisi "/>
               <span style="width:224px;">Australian Andrew Barisi plays for Calcutta's East
Bengal team</span>
            </div>
            <p>There are about 40 foreign players in the top league, many of
whom have come from South Sudan, Australia, Brazil, Portugal and
Japan.</p>
            <p>Foreign players are also to be found in the seven-tier league's
lower divisions.</p>
            <p>Australian Andrew Barisi - Chidi's team-mate - came to Calcutta
in January after playing in Indonesia for two years. Like many
other foreign players, he knew nothing about the 115-year-old
history of Calcutta football.</p>
            <p>So why did he choose Calcutta?</p>
            <p>"You can say football might be better in Indonesia in terms of
quality but everything off the field is shocking over there.
There's so much politics. So the plan was to move forward, and with
Indian football there's a lot to move forward to," he says.</p>
            <p>"As a foreigner I thought it would be a lot harder here than all
the places I have been to, such as Germany, Indonesia and Croatia.
But from the first week everyone's been amazing to me," he
adds.</p>
            <p>For years, Calcutta was the place to earn fame and fortune for
those foreign players who failed to break into their national teams
or those who came here very young.</p>
            <p>Brazilian Jose Ramirez Barreto was barely out of his teens when
he was cajoled into joining Mohun Bagan in 1999. "I learned Mohun
Bagan needed a forward and a Calcutta player from my country
recommended me to them," he says. "Over the years, I have realised
how big the club is and how old the city football culture is."</p>
            <p>He left the club briefly but the fans' adoration and "love for
Calcutta" was a big pull that brought him back to the city. Talking
about his status in the club history, he says modestly: "They loved
me and I loved them. It was an exchange."</p>
            <p>Barreto says foreign players come to Calcutta because it is a
football hub, and the fans have a great passion for the game.</p>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68125000/jpg/_68125403_nassiri2.jpg"
                 width="224"
                 height="299"
                 alt="Jamshed Nasiri "/>
               <span style="width:224px;">Iranian Jamshed Nasiri is among the legends still
revered in the city</span>
            </div>
            <p>But in recent years, clubs from Goa, Mumbai and Pune have caught
up with Calcutta and today these clubs have players and coaches
from Australia, Japan, Gabon, Lebanon and Sudan, as well as Nigeria
and Brazil.</p>
            <p>Barreto believes that football has become a level playing field.
"In the past, Calcutta could buy the best home-grown talent from
across the country and buy odd foreign players. Now, all clubs are
buying good domestic and foreign players."</p>
            <p>This broke Calcutta football's dominance in terms of winning
trophies and tournaments. Since its inception in 2007, the 15-team
I-League - the Indian equivalent of the English Premier League -
has never been won by a Calcutta club.</p>
            <p>There are currently five teams from Calcutta, competing with
sides from all over India, as well as in their local league.</p>
            <p>The I-League teams together have more than 40 foreigners; but
teams from Goa - with players and coaches from Brazil, Portugal,
Morocco and Nigeria - have dominated, winning the league every
year.</p>
            <p>The All India Football Federation allows a club to register up
to four foreign players (including one Asian) and today, a foreign
player can command up to $400,000
(Â£255,000) - a sum affordable for most
football clubs.</p>
            <p>Clubs from Calcutta may have lost their supremacy in Indian
football. But the city's passion for football and love for players,
especially foreigners, remains undiminished.</p>
            <p>Iranians Majid Baskar and Jamshed Nasiri and Nigerian Chima
Okerie are some of the legends still revered in the city. Swapan
Ball, who has been the East Bengal manager since 1998, calls Baskar
"the best ever foreign import in India".</p>
            <p>Baskar went back to Iran, but Nasiri made the city home. He and
Okerie, who divides his time between England and Calcutta, married
locally and have developed deep roots here.</p>
            <p>Nasiri's love for Calcutta is well-known in the city: "This is
my home now. People here are cultured. They love sport and have
great sportsmanship spirit."</p>
            <p>But has the Calcutta fan's love for football helped improve the
quality of the game in India? Football writer with the Hindustan
Times newspaper Dhiman Sarkar does not think so.</p>
            <p>"The standard has stayed pretty much the same. Yes, in the 1970s
we had more football heroes, but then we didn't get to see Arsenal
play Liverpool [on television]. The only benchmark that I see is
how we did internationally then, and how we do it now, and I think
the answer is pretty much the same. We are as good - or bad - now
as we were then."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1361190970164"
                  href="/news/business-21496112">Football
India's 'fastest growing sport' <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1334098813228"
                  href="/news/business-17614190">Football looks for Indian
toehold</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
