<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23159159"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The remains believed to be of three of Nelson Mandela's children are exhumed from his grandson's homestead hours after a South African court ruling."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-03T20:21:28"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68534000/jpg/_68534227_68533993.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Remains of 'Mandela children' exhumed"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Africa"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23159159"/>
         <title>BBC News - Remains exhumed from Nelson Mandela grandson's
homestead</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">3 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">21:21</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Remains exhumed from Nelson Mandela
grandson's homestead</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68537000/jpg/_68537843_68537842.jpg"
                 alt="A convoy of police and funeral vehicles approaches the homestead of Mandla Mandela"/>
               <p class="caption">Police approach Mandla Mandela's homestead</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The remains believed
to be of three of Nelson Mandela's children have been exhumed from
a property belonging to his grandson, Mandla Mandela.</p>
            <p>They have been taken from Mvezo in South Africa's Eastern Cape
Province to a funeral parlour in nearby Mthatha, Lt Col Mzukisi
Fatyela told the BBC.</p>
            <p>It comes hours after a court ruled the remains should be removed
for reburial in a nearby family graveyard.</p>
            <p>Mandla moved the remains in 2011, allegedly without the family's
consent.</p>
            <p>Lt Col Fatyela said forensic investigations would be carried out
on the exhumed remains in Mthatha.</p>
            <p>Nelson Mandela remains critically ill in hospital suffering from
a recurring lung infection.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68544000/jpg/_68544270_68544269.jpg"
                 alt="ANC Gauteng Womens League"/>
               <p class="caption">The ANC Gauteng Women's League sing outside Mr
Mandela's hospital</p>
            </div>
            <p>Court papers filed last week reveal that Mr Mandela has been on
a life support machine, South Africa's Mail and Guardian newspaper
reports.</p>
            <p>"Nelson Mandela's health is perilous. [An] affidavit will be
provided from physicians that he is assisted in breathing by a life
support machine," the paper <a href="http://mg.co.za/article/2013-07-03-nelson-mandelas-health-is-perilous-says-makaziwe-mandela">
quotes the documents filed by Mr Mandela's family last Thursday</a>
as saying.</p>
            <p>President Jacob Zuma said on Monday that Mr Mandela's condition
remained critical but had stabilised, and he urged South Africans
to plan for his 95th birthday on 18 July.</p>
            <p>The former president has said he wants to
be buried in the family graveyard in the village of Qunu, where he
spent several years as a child and mostly lived after he
retired.</p>
            <p>A court last Friday granted 16 members of the Mandela family an
order for the remains to be exhumed and moved from Mandla Mandela's
homestead in Mvezo, the former president's birthplace, to nearby
Qunu, 22km (14 miles) away.</p>
            <p>But Mandla Mandela, who was appointed as chief of Mvezo by his
grandfather, went to court to challenge it.</p>
            <p>On Wednesday, the Mthatha High Court confirmed its initial
decision and said the exhumations should take place - despite an
appeal lodged by Mandla Mandela, which reports said the High Court
refused to hear.</p>
            <p>Police and a bailiff arrived at his property on Wednesday
afternoon accompanied by Mr Mandela's daughter Makiziwe, the BBC's
Gringo Wotshela in Mvezo reports, breaking down the gates with an
axe.</p>
            <p>The remains are those of Makgatho
Mandela, Mandla's father who died from Aids-related diseases in
2005, and Makgatho's siblings, Thembekile, who was killed in a car
accident in 1969, and Makaziwe, Nelson Mandela's first daughter,
who died when she was nine months old.</p>
            <p>The BBC's Pumza Fihlani in Johannesburg says Mandla Mandela's
plans to open a heritage centre dedicated to his grandfather in
Mvezo, in the former site of the graves, have left a bitter taste
among many within the family.</p>
            <p>Some family members have also laid a criminal complaint against
him for illegal grave tampering.</p>
            <p>The police told the BBC on Tuesday they would investigate such
allegations and a public prosecutor would then decide whether to
press charges.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68525000/jpg/_68525988_sa_624_v4.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="474"
                 alt="Map"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372691524885"
                  href="/news/world-africa-23070676">Mandela feud over family
graves</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1279528055276"
                  href="/news/world-africa-10632753">Profile: Mandla Zwelivelile
Mandela</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372934834492"
                  href="/news/world-africa-23178568">Mandela: Well-wishers visit hospital
<span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/48738000/jpg/_48738869_004475160-1.jpg"
                    alt="image of Mike Wooldridge"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Mike Wooldridge</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
News, Mthatha</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>Behind the drama in the High Court in Mthatha over the moving of
the remains of three of Nelson Mandela's late children from Qunu to
Mvezo and now back again lies a struggle for authority within the
divided Mandela family - amid the increasing frailty of the family
patriarch.</p>
            <p>With the court ruling going against Nelson Mandela's grandson
Mandla - heir apparent, he is often called - the question is
whether his influence and authority have been undermined.</p>
            <p>It has been suggested by some traditional elders here that the
feuding has disturbed the spirit of the ailing former president
when it should be at peace.</p>
            <p>One thing is sure. There is a stark contrast between what US
President Barack Obama called "the current outpouring of love for
Nelson Mandela" as he lies in his hospital bed, and the sorry saga
played out before the cameras in court here.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Nelson Mandela's children</h2>
            <p>
               <strong>With Evelyn Mase:</strong>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>Thembekile born 1945, died 1969</li>
               <li>Makaziwe born 1947, died aged nine months</li>
               <li>Makgatho born 1950, died 2005</li>
               <li>Makaziwe, born 1954</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <strong>With Winnie Madikizela-Mandela:</strong>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>Zenani born 1959</li>
               <li>Zindziswa born 1960</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
