<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23264940"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Boston Marathon bomb suspect Dzhokhar Tsarnaev pleads not guilty to all charges, in his first appearance in a court, as blast victims look on."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-10T21:31:56"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68662000/jpg/_68662219_68662576.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Boston bomb accused denies charges"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/US and Canada"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23264940"/>
         <title>BBC News - Boston bomb accused Dzhokhar Tsarnaev denies
charges</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">10 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">22:31</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Boston bomb accused Dzhokhar Tsarnaev
denies charges</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68662000/jpg/_68662575_1541d220-e729-4b77-b0bf-7a41b3954d2b.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="A court sketch of Dzhokhar Tsarnaev (10 July 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Tsarnaev appeared in court with his face
swollen and his arm in a cast, perhaps from injuries suffered
during his capture by police in April</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Boston Marathon bomb
suspect Dzhokhar Tsarnaev has pleaded not guilty to all charges in
his first court appearance, as blast victims looked on.</p>
            <p>Mr Tsarnaev, 19, faces 30 counts of using a weapon of mass
destruction in the two 15 April blasts that killed three, including
an eight-year-old boy.</p>
            <p>He appeared in shackles and an orange prison suit, and replied
"not guilty" as the charges were read to the court.</p>
            <p>Prosecutors could press for the death penalty for 17 counts.</p>
            <p>The suspect has also been charged over the death of a fourth
person, a university police officer, who was allegedly shot dead by
Mr Tsarnaev and his brother Tamerlan in the days after the
attack.</p>
            <p>He is also charged in a carjacking incident and with downloading
internet material from Islamist radicals some time before the
blasts.</p>
            <p>People appeared outside the federal courthouse in Boston as
early as 07:30 EST (12:30 BST) to claim a seat inside the court and
two overflow rooms for a hearing that lasted just seven
minutes.</p>
            <p>Mr Tsarnaev arrived at court with his face swollen and his arm
in a cast.</p>
            <p>Two of the suspect's sisters watched the proceedings. One sobbed
during the hearing while the other held a baby.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68656000/jpg/_68656706_68656705.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Police and reporters outside the federal courthouse in Boston, Massachusetts 10 July 2013"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">People arrived at the courthouse early
to secure a seat inside</span>
            </div>
            <p>Before he was led out of the courtroom, the suspect seemed to
smile and to gesture a kiss to his family members in the room.</p>
            <p>Among the crowd was a young friend of Mr Tsarnaev, Hank Alvarez,
19. He said: "Just knowing him, it's hard for me to face the fact
that he did it."</p>
            <p>Mr Tsarnaev, a US citizen, was not in court last month during an
indictment hearing, when a federal grand jury agreed that he should
be tried on 30 charges.</p>
            <p>His first court appearance took place at his hospital bedside,
where he was recovering from injuries suffered in a shootout with
police during the manhunt. He was later transferred to a prison
hospital near Boston.</p>
            <p>Mr Tsarnaev's older brother Tamerlan, 26, was killed days after
the attack during a massive police operation. He is also suspected
of carrying out the attacks.</p>
            <p>Authorities say the accused ran over his older brother as he
fled the shootout in a hijacked car.</p>
            <p>Dzhokhar Tsarnaev was found the next day, 19 April, hiding in a
boat in a residential garden in Watertown, Massachusetts.</p>
            <p>According to the indictment, he wrote about his motivations for
the bombing on the inside walls and beams of the boat.</p>
            <p>Authorities say he scrawled: "The US Government is killing our
innocent civilians" and "I can't stand to see such evil go
unpunished."</p>
            <p>The brothers are from a family of ethnic Chechen Muslims from
Russia and had been living in the US for about a decade.</p>
            <p>More than 260 people were injured when two pressure cooker bombs
packed with nails, ball bearings and other shrapnel were detonated
at the finish line of the Boston Marathon.</p>
            <p>The bombing was the worst mass-casualty attack on US soil since
11 September 2001.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="/news/world-us-canada-22166073">Boston Bombs</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1367515828236"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-22377255">Key players</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1366661722826"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-22255403">Lone wolf</a>
                  </li>
                  <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1366881125240"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-22290459">Amputee: I'll dance again
<span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                     </a>
                  </li>
                  <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1366644236981"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-22227698">Boston Muslims on suspects
<span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                     </a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
