<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23231993"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The BBC's Steve Rosenberg assesses whether Georgia's efforts to tackle corruption have been effective."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-10T00:54:32"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68629000/jpg/_68629446_police-station-624.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Can glass walls tackle corruption?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23231993"/>
         <title>BBC News - Georgia: Are glass-walled police stations enough
to tackle corruption?</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">10 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:54</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Georgia: Are glass-walled police stations
enough to tackle corruption?</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Steve
Rosenberg</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News,
Tbilisi</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68625000/jpg/_68625111_police-station-624.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Georgian police station"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A decade ago,
Georgia had a terrible reputation for corruption. Political changes
brought about substantial reform - including much-vaunted
glass-walled police stations - but have the issues really been
dealt with?</p>
            <p>In recent years, the ancient city of Tbilisi has acquired
something of a modern sparkle, with glass palaces popping up across
Georgia's capital. At first glance, they look like car
showrooms.</p>
            <p>On closer inspection, they're police stations - see-through to
make the officers inside more accountable to the public.</p>
            <p>Glass police precincts symbolise the new transparency which
Georgia has been promoting since the 2003 "Rose Revolution". For a
country which was being described a decade ago as one of the most
corrupt nations in the world, cleaning up its act has been a
challenge.</p>
            <p>"There was a sense of pride here about
corruption," says Mark Mullen of Transparency International
Georgia.</p>
            <p>"There are a lot of words in Georgian for admirable sneakiness -
like "magarichi", which means "gift among men''. This was a small
country among big empires which had skimmed a bit from the caravan
and had done well by saluting the powers that be - while taking
care of family and friends."</p>
            <p>But corruption was strangling post-Soviet Georgia.</p>
            <p>All commercial transactions were under the table. If you wanted
a construction permit or to register a company, you had to give a
bribe. If you wanted to get into a good university and guarantee
good grades, greasing someone's palm was the way to do it. Some
people even paid bribes just to get their lights switched on at
home, because of power shortages - certain jobs could only be
secured by a backhander.</p>
            <p>Georgians used to pay massive bribes to get a job in the traffic
police. Once in, new officers would start taking bribes themselves
to recoup their losses. The result was a system rotten from top to
bottom.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>Mission impossible</strong>
            </p>
            <p>In 2003 things began to change.</p>
            <p>Incensed by rampant corruption and a
rigged parliamentary election, people power swept away the old
guard. Mikheil Saakashvili became the new president and promised
Georgians something they'd never had before - transparency.</p>
            <p>Cue the glass police stations. And a revamped police force.</p>
            <p>Captain Nino Gvinianidze takes me out in her US-style patrol
car. When she pulls over vehicles, she greets drivers with a salute
and a smile. The Patrol Police replaced Georgia's notoriously
corrupt traffic police force, which was scrapped with the loss of
16,000 jobs. The new recruits were better paid and monitored
closely to make sure they didn't take bribes.</p>
            <p>"In the past," Captain Nino recalls, "many people tried to give
police officers money. But nowadays everyone knows officers don't
take money."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68626000/jpg/_68626074_publicservice_hall464.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Public hall"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Georgia's public halls enable people to obtain
documents such as passports without having to pay
bribes</span>
            </div>
            <p>It's not just the police that became more transparent.</p>
            <p>The Georgian government opened giant public service palaces, to
enable Georgians to obtain documents without having to pay bribes.
Transactions that were once under the table, like getting a
passport, are now out in the open.</p>
            <p>"I remember when I was 16 years-old and I was asked to bring a
bribe for my first passport," Public Service Hall manager Givi
Chanukvadze tells me. "Right now people are coming here, just
taking a photo and that's it. They don't need any other
documents."</p>
            <p>By cleaning up its act in the police and public services,
Georgia seemed to have fulfilled a mission impossible. From being
right down near the bottom of the global league table on
transparency, it rose to a ranking higher even than some EU
states.</p>
            <p>But some Georgians complain that their shiny new system of
transparency had strict limits.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>'People screaming'</strong>
            </p>
            <p>In a small office in Tbilisi I meet Mamia Sanadiradze, the
former owner of one of Georgia's largest telecom companies. Mr
Sanadiradze maintains that the same government which claimed to be
fighting corruption was putting pressure on his business. His
problems began, he says, when the interior ministry asked him to
facilitate secret surveillance of internet users.</p>
            <p>"I refused," Mr Sanadiradze says, "They
told me other telecom operators are wiser than me and that I might
have problems in the future."</p>
            <p>Mr Sanadiradze claims that, soon after, some of his company's
cables were cut. Then, he received a $7.45m
(Ã‚Â£5 million) fine from the tax office which
he couldn't afford.</p>
            <p>"I had no choice. I had to transfer the company under the
control of governmentally well-connected business groups. The
government were acting like a criminal gang. They were using state
institutions - ministry of interior, chief prosecutor's office, tax
police - to push rich individuals in Georgia to give up their
properties."</p>
            <p>Givi Maisuradze did go to jail. His sister, who lives abroad,
had bought a section of an old gas pipeline in Georgia that was
being auctioned off. Two years ago Mr Maisuradze was arrested and
told his sister's pipeline must be given back to the state as a
gift.</p>
            <p>"I spent four months in prison," he tells me. "Every evening I
could hear people screaming, it sounded as if they were being
tortured. I was a hostage. My sister said: You're a hostage because
of ME. So she signed the papers and handed the pipeline over. Two
days later I was freed."</p>
            <p>
               <strong>'Elite corruption'</strong>
            </p>
            <p>Last October, President Saakashvili's party, the UNM, was voted
out of office after nearly a decade running Georgia. Mr Saakashvili
remained president, but there was a new government. It was headed
by his rival, the billionaire Bidzina Ivanishvili. He believes the
anti-corruption government which preceded him was no beacon of
transparency.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68626000/jpg/_68626078_ivanishivililisteningsmiling.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Bidzina Ivanishvili"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Prime Minister Ivanishvili believes the previous
government failed to tackle top-level corruption</span>
            </div>
            <p>"When it comes to fighting corruption on the low and medium
levels, our predecessors were successful," Mr Ivanishvili explains
to me. "But what happened was that the money which had previously
been divided up among the lower levels was being shared by a small
group of people higher up. This was elite corruption."</p>
            <p>Mikhail Saakashvili denies the accusations.</p>
            <p>"You can say that the judiciary was not totally independent. I
would agree with that," President Saakashvili tells me. "You can
say that prosecutors were somehow overstretching their limit. I
would agree with that. But nobody was taking bribes. Nobody was
stealing money. And the only reason they were sometimes
overstretching their limits was just to try not to allow corruption
back into our country."</p>
            <p>But the president has been accused recently of spending public
money on private whims. The procedural committee of the Georgian
parliament has published what it says are expense records showing
how President Saakashvili spent thousands of dollars from his
security budget on luxury hotel rooms, paintings and beauty
treatments in New York - including Botox injections. It's the Botox
claims that appear to cause President Saakashvili particular
offence.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68625000/jpg/_68625038_saakashvili-look-at-me464.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="President Saakashvili"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">President Saakashvili is incensed at
allegations that he spent part of his security budget on Botox
injections</span>
            </div>
            <p>"Look at me. Look at me! Can you see anything?" the president
asks me, pointing to his face. "Look at the prime minister and his
friend Vladimir Putin and you will see the difference. The point
is, is that all they could claim and find? Where are all these
'millions' and 'billions' 'misspent' or stolen'? Nowhere. Because
this country was clean."</p>
            <p>If that is the case, why are a string of President Saakashvili's
former ministers and party officials now under investigation? Is
this about fighting corruption at the very top, as the new
government claims. Or is about settling scores?</p>
            <p>"Is it politically motivated? Yes, it's politically motivated,"
believes Mark Mullen of Transparency International. "Is it a
reasonable exercise in the rule of law? Yes it is, because there
were so many laws broken. The thing to watch is the trend line -
will this continue? Is this going to be a way of making sure there
is no opposition?"</p>
            <p>Georgia has achieved so much, so fast. Never in its history has
corruption been so difficult here to conceal.</p>
            <p>But Georgia's story shows that shiny palaces themselves are no
guarantee of total transparency or rule of law. As long as
politicians on all sides - in their glasshouses - are still
throwing stones.</p>
            <p>
               <em>There will be a series of special reports and articles this
week as the BBC examines why bribes and backhanders are part of the
system in so much of the world, looks at countries which have tried
to roll back the tide - and explains how corruption works.</em>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373346038206"
                  href="/news/business-23231318">Map: Which country pays the most
bribes?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373346016603"
                  href="/news/business-23227382">Corruption getting worse, says
poll</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373281760309"
                  href="/news/business-23199258">Bribery is
'exactly the same' world over <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Some people even paid bribes just to get
their lights switched on at home”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Nowadays everyone knows officers don't take
money”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Captain Nino Gvinianidze</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Georgia Patrol Police</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Georgia at a glance</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68480000/gif/_68480371_georgia.gif"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Map of Georgia"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>Situated at strategically important crossroads where Europe
meets Asia</li>
               <li>Annexed by Russia in the 19th Century</li>
               <li>Gained independence from the Soviet Union in 1991</li>
               <li>Opposition allegations of irregularities in parliamentary
elections triggers 'Rose Revolution'</li>
               <li>President Mikheil Saakashvili loses control of parliament in
2012</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-17301647">Georgia
profile</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
