<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23140785"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A deadly wildfire in the US state of Arizona remains uncontained, as the 19 elite firefighters killed by the blaze are identified."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T02:42:20"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68493000/jpg/_68493352_68486202.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Lethal Arizona wildfire rages on"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/US and Canada"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23140785"/>
         <title>BBC News - Arizona blaze rages on as 19 dead firefighters
are named</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">03:42</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Arizona blaze rages on as 19 dead
firefighters are named</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68486000/jpg/_68486207_68486202.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="The Granite Mountain Interagency Hotshot Crew is shown in this undated handout photo provided by the City of Prescott 1 July 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The dead firefighters were identified as
members of the Granite Mountain Hotshots crew, shown here in an
undated photo</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A deadly wildfire
raging in Arizona remains uncontained, as the 19 elite firefighters
killed by the blaze were identified and mourned.</p>
            <p>The bodies of the men, aged 21-43, received an honour guard on
Monday as they were brought to Phoenix for post-mortem
examinations.</p>
            <p>President Barack Obama, on a visit to Africa, called the Arizona
governor to offer condolences.</p>
            <p>It is the highest death toll for a fire crew in a single
incident since 9/11.</p>
            <p>The firefighters, who died on Sunday, were part of a unit called
the Granite Mountain Hotshots, and had battled other wildfires in
New Mexico and Arizona in recent weeks, officials say.</p>
            <p>Fourteen of the deceased crewmen were in their 20s and many were
described as family men.</p>
            <p>One victim, 25-year-old Billy Warneke, had been expecting his
first child with his wife, his grandmother told the Associated
Press news agency.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68471000/jpg/_68471336_fire3.jpg"
                 alt="Wildfires in central Arizona"/>
               <p class="caption">Scores of homes have been destroyed and hundreds
of residents evacuated</p>
            </div>
            <p>Chris MacKenzie, 30, and Kevin Woyjeck, 21, had followed in
their fathers' footsteps to become firefighters.</p>
            <p>"They were dedicated, hard-working people," Prescott Fire Chief
Dan Fraijo said of his team members.</p>
            <p>"I never heard them complain. They always seemed to be playing
pranks on each other and a few on me. And I had a great deal of
respect for them."</p>
            <p>The firefighters reportedly covered themselves in foil-lined,
heat-resistant tarpaulins in a last-gasp effort to save themselves
- but to no avail.</p>
            <p>Only one member of the hotshots team survived - he was
reportedly moving the unit's truck at the time of the tragedy,
which unfolded 80 miles (130km) north-west of Phoenix.</p>
            <p>On Monday a line of white vans carried the bodies of the
deceased firefighters to Phoenix, the largest city in the state,
for post-mortem examinations.</p>
            <p>The procession received an honour guard of police officers and
firefighters, passing under an arch of flags hanging from the
ladders of two trucks parked on either side of the road.</p>
            <p>Arizona Governor Jan Brewer has ordered flags in the state to be
flown at half-mast, saying it was "as dark a day as I can
remember".</p>
            <p>"I know that it is unbearable for many of you, but it also is
unbearable for me," she said, addressing residents and reporters in
the town of Prescott, which has a population of about 40,000.</p>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68493000/jpg/_68493402_68493401.jpg"
                 width="226"
                 height="282"
                 alt="Procession carries the bodies of 19 firefighters to Phoenix, Arizona 1 July 2013"/>
               <span style="width:226px;">The bodies were brought to Phoenix on
Monday for post-mortem examinations</span>
            </div>
            <p>"I know the pain that everyone is trying to overcome and deal
with today."</p>
            <p>President Obama, who was visiting Tanzania on Monday, offered
federal support to battle the blaze.</p>
            <p>He said the incident would prompt a reassessment of how to
handle large, destructive wildfires.</p>
            <p>But as the town mourned, the wildfire continued to burn out of
control.</p>
            <p>About 200 additional firefighters have been brought to tackle
the blaze, bringing the total force to about 400. They included
other hotshot teams sent from around the US.</p>
            <p>The fire was believed to have been sparked by lightning on
Friday near the small mountain town of Yarnell.</p>
            <p>The uncontained conflagration was said to have scorched some
8,400 acres (3,400 hectares) of land.</p>
            <p>Scores of homes have been destroyed and two towns evacuated.</p>
            <p>In recent days, dozens of people across western US states have
been treated for exhaustion and dehydration, amid a heatwave.</p>
            <p>Temperatures in some areas were expected to reach 54C (130F),
close to the world's all-time high recorded 100 years ago in
California's Death Valley.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/66933000/gif/_66933045_line2.gif"
                 width="464"
                 height="1"
                 alt="line break "/>
            </div>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68481000/gif/_68481711_how_wildfires_spread_464_no_title.gif"
                 width="464"
                 height="262"
                 alt="How wildfires spread graphic"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>A fire needs fuel, oxygen and heat to burn. The fire
threatening the town of Yarnell was started by lightning and spread
rapidly in the very hot, dry conditions, fanned by strong
winds</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li>The fastest-moving and most dangerous part of the fire is known
as the "<strong>head</strong>". Areas ahead of the fire are warmed
as it approaches and flying embers blown by the wind spark
<strong>spot fires</strong>, which cause it to leap further
ahead</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li>Some vegetation or fuel will burn quicker than others and this
creates "<strong>fingers</strong>" of flame which, in turn, create
<strong>pockets</strong> of land surrounded by fire, making it
harder to tackle</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li>Fires travel faster uphill than downhill, as the heat and smoke
rise, heating areas higher up the hill and wind currents also tend
to blow uphill, pushing the flames further. Burning embers may roll
downhill, starting new fires</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story" rel="published-1372706394216" href="/news/23137482">Life as a 'hotshot' firefighter</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372684908227"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-23128457">How to fight a wildfire</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372661063162"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-23123961">In pictures: Arizona
wildfire</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
