<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-22961519"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Mali's government signs a peace deal with Tuareg rebels to end conflict in the north in the run-up to elections next month."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-18T20:47:59"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68247000/jpg/_68247747_67992068.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Mali signs peace deal with Tuareg"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Africa"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-22961519"/>
         <title>BBC News - Mali and Tuareg rebels sign peace deal</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">18 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">21:47</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Mali and Tuareg rebels sign peace
deal</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68248000/jpg/_68248842_68248841.jpg"
                 alt="Francois Hollande"/>
               <p class="caption">President Francois Hollande said the deal would
allow elections to be held</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Mali's government
has signed a peace deal with Tuareg rebels to help pave the way for
elections next month.</p>
            <p>The accord calls for an immediate ceasefire and for government
troops to return to the rebel-held northern town of Kidal,
officials said.</p>
            <p>The rebels captured Kidal after a French-led offensive forced
militant Islamists out of the town in February.</p>
            <p>The Tuaregs have been fighting for autonomy in the north since
Mali gained independence from France in 1960.</p>
            <p>They say they are marginalised by the government in the capital,
Bamako.</p>
            <p>French President Francois Hollande, announcing the deal after
the G8 summit in Northern Ireland, said the agreement paved the way
for a presidential election across Mali, including in Kidal.</p>
            <p>The main rebel group which signed the accord, National Movement
for the Liberation of Azawad (MNLA), had formed an alliance with
al-Qaeda-linked militants to seize the north in 2012.</p>
            <p>But the alliance quickly crumbled, and
the Islamists took control of the MNLA's strongholds.</p>
            <p>Government and MNLA negotiators reached the deal after nearly
two weeks of talks brokered by Burkina Faso's President Blaise
Compaore in the Burkina capital, Ouagadougou.</p>
            <p>The army had threatened to seize Kidal if no agreement was
reached.</p>
            <p>Malian government representative Tiebile Drame said the two
sides had overcome their greatest differences.</p>
            <p>"I think we can say that the biggest task is finished. We have
agreed on the essentials," AP news agency quoted him as saying.</p>
            <p>"There is an international consensus as well as a Malian
consensus on the fundamental questions, which include the integrity
of our territory, national unity, and the secular and republican
nature of our state.''</p>
            <p>MNLA spokesman Moussa Ag Attaher confirmed a deal had been
reached.</p>
            <p>"The MNLA and the High Council for the Azawad [the rebel name
for northern Mali] have given everything for peace and so we accept
this accord,'' AP quoted him as saying.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/67900000/gif/_67900880_mali_gao_march_2012.cmp.gif"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="map"/>
            </div>
            <p>The MNLA has watered down its demand for independence, saying it
will settle, as a first step, for autonomy for the desert region
where they live.</p>
            <p>The UN is due to deploy a 12,600-strong peacekeeping force
before planned elections on 28 July, which will incorporate
thousands of West African troops already in the country in support
of the French intervention.</p>
            <p>The elections will be the first in Mali since the military
staged a coup in 2012, accusing the government of failing to end
the conflict in the north.</p>
            <p>However, the Islamists and Tuareg rebels took advantage of the
ensuing chaos in Bamako to capture more territory.</p>
            <p>France intervened in January after the Islamists advanced
southwards, raising fears that they intended to seize the
capital.</p>
            <p>It plans to gradually hand over to the Malian army and a UN
peacekeeping force before presidential and parliamentary elections
are held.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>Mali conflict</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1365415530790"
                     href="/news/world-africa-22061222">Fear in Timbuktu</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1367538786552"
                     href="/news/world-africa-22391857">Turning soldiers into
fighters</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1364217958570"
                     href="/news/world-africa-21919769">On the frontline</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1360880915766"
                     href="/news/world-africa-21467982">Amputation horror</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">Thomas Fessy</span>
               <span class="byline-title">West Africa correspondent, BBC
News</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>The UN, the European Union and France have all been swift in
praising this deal, signed after many more days than planned. The
EU even described it as "historic". But is it really?</p>
            <p>This is not an overall peace deal putting an end to a rebellion
that started a year-and-a-half ago. This is an agreement that is
meant to allow a presidential election to go ahead next month
everywhere in Mali, including Kidal, which is still controlled by
Tuareg fighters.</p>
            <p>But then, what happens after the election? Tuareg rebels insist
this deal will allow them to keep their weapons while they are
being garrisoned. Disarmament will only be discussed after a new
president is elected, allowing much broader peace talks to take
place to address the rebels' grievances.</p>
            <p>Tuareg rebels have agreed to be committed to peace; they aren't
laying down their weapons yet.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
