<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23181352"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Nelson Mandela's grandson Mandla accuses his relatives of seeking to control the ex-president's legacy, as three of his children are reburied."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T17:02:56"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68551000/jpg/_68551002_68548428.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Nelson Mandela family feud deepens"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Africa"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23181352"/>
         <title>BBC News - Nelson Mandela family feud deepens as Mandla hits
back</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">18:02</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Nelson Mandela family feud deepens as
Mandla hits back</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68553000/jpg/_68553047_68553046.jpg"
                 alt="South African newspapers"/>
               <p class="caption">The case has shocked South Africa, as Gabriel
Gatehouse reports</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Nelson Mandela's
grandson Mandla has accused his relatives of being vengeful and
seeking to control the former South African president's legacy.</p>
            <p>His comments came as the bodies of three of Mr Mandela's
children were being reburied at the anti-apartheid icon's home
village of Qunu.</p>
            <p>On Wednesday police exhumed the bodies from Mandla's homestead,
after court action by his relatives.</p>
            <p>Mr Mandela, 94, remains "critical but stable" in hospital, a new
update says.</p>
            <p>President Jacob Zuma issued a statement
after visiting the hero of the fight against white minority rule in
a Pretoria hospital.</p>
            <p>"Madiba [Mr Mandela's clan name] is receiving the best medical
care from a multi-disciplinary team of health professionals who are
at his bedside around the clock," he said, again urging South
Africans to celebrate his birthday later this month.</p>
            <p>Correspondents say there has been a long-running battle over Mr
Mandela's legacy, but it has intensified as his health has
deteriorated.</p>
            <p>Court papers filed last week revealed that he has been on life
support. He was admitted on 8 June with a recurring lung
infection.</p>
            <p>His wife Graca Machel on Thursday said Mr Mandela was sometimes
"uncomfortable, but he has never been in pain".</p>
            <p>The dispute between Mandla and his relatives is linked to where
Mr Mandela will be buried.</p>
            <p>A group of the Mandela family, including his daughter Makaziwe
and Mrs Machel, last week went to court, accusing Mandla of
unlawfully relocating the graves of the three children to his
village of Mvezo.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68553000/jpg/_68553873_68553872.jpg"
                 alt="Mandla Mandela"/>
               <p class="caption">Mandla Mandela: "It seems like anyone and
everyone can come and say 'I am a Mandela'"</p>
            </div>
            <p>Mandla had relocated the graves to ensure that his grandfather
would be buried in Mvezo, Makaziwe said in an affidavit, South
Africa's Mail &amp; Guardian newspaper reports.</p>
            <p>This was in defiance of the wishes of Mr Mandela, who wants to
be buried in the nearby village of Qunu, where he grew up, she is
quoted as saying.</p>
            <p>The court ruled that the bodies should be re-interned in the
family graveyard in Qunu.</p>
            <p>A hearse and a large contingent of police arrived with the
bodies for the reburial after forensic tests confirmed that they
were Mr Mandela's children.</p>
            <p>Some relatives had gathered for the reburial of the three
children - Mr Mandela's eldest son Madiba Thembekile who died in a
car accident in 1969, Mandla's father Makgatho, who died of an
Aids-related illness in 2005; and the ex-president's first
daughter, also called Makaziwe, who died as an infant in 1948.</p>
            <p>The bodies were taken from Qunu to Mvezo
in 2011 by Mandla, who became chief of the village with Mr
Mandela's backing in 2007.</p>
            <p>In his first comments since losing the case, Mandla said he had
brought the remains to Mvezo "temporarily", until Mr Mandela's
wishes were known.</p>
            <p>"In the past few days I have been the target of attacks from all
sorts of individuals wanting a few minutes of fame and media
attention at my expense," he said, AFP news agency reports.</p>
            <p>"At the moment it seems that anyone and everyone can come and
say 'I am a Mandela' and demand to be part of decision-making in
this family. Individuals decided to jump on the Mandela wagon."</p>
            <p>Makaziwe was trying to "sow divisions and destruction" in the
family, Mandla said.</p>
            <p>The court case was linked to a battle for control of Mr
Mandela's financial assets, he said.</p>
            <p>His family rivals were motivated by revenge as he had refused to
support their legal case to oust three of Mr Mandela's aides from
companies the ex-president had set up, Mandla added.</p>
            <p>Makaziwe and another daughter of Mr Mandela, Zenani launched
their case in April alleging that Mr Mandela's aides, including
respected human rights lawyer George Bizos, had no right to be on
the boards of two companies worth about $1.7m
(Â£1.1m).</p>
            <p>Mr Bizos said they would defend the action.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68525000/jpg/_68525988_sa_624_v4.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="474"
                 alt="Map"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372691524885"
                  href="/news/world-africa-23070676">Behind the Mandela family
feud</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1279528055276"
                  href="/news/world-africa-10632753">Profile: Mandla Zwelivelile
Mandela</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372845254177"
                  href="/news/world-africa-23153579">Zoomable image: Messages for
Mandela</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/48738000/jpg/_48738869_004475160-1.jpg"
                    alt="image of Mike Wooldridge"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Mike Wooldridge</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
News, Mvezo</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>Tragic drama is nothing new in the Mandela family but the
bitterness in the views expressed by Nelson Mandela's grandson,
Mandla, is the strongest public evidence of deep division and
mistrust for some while.</p>
            <p>And the significance is that it comes at this time when Nelson
Mandela is in hospital in a critical condition.</p>
            <p>In the aftermath of the remains of three of the former
president's children being exhumed on a court order from the graves
at his homestead where he had them buried, Mandla Mandela has
accused family members behind the legal action of wanting to take
revenge against him.</p>
            <p>But he also clearly wanted to counter the impression that his
own status and authority within the Mandela family has been
undermined by his defeat in court.</p>
            <p>His message was that he had been groomed for leadership and
service by Nelson Mandela and he would not be bowed by any
campaigns against him.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Nelson Mandela's children</h2>
            <p>
               <strong>With Evelyn Mase:</strong>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>Thembekile born 1945, died 1969</li>
               <li>Makaziwe born 1947, died aged nine months</li>
               <li>Makgatho born 1950, died 2005</li>
               <li>Makaziwe, born 1954</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <strong>With Winnie Madikizela-Mandela:</strong>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>Zenani born 1959</li>
               <li>Zindziswa born 1960</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
