<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23138680"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The director and deputy director of the Vatican bank resign following the arrest of a senior Italian cleric over corruption and fraud allegations."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T19:43:37"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68491000/jpg/_68491156_018469124-1.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Vatican bank chief and deputy resign"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23138680"/>
         <title>BBC News - Vatican bank director and deputy resign amid
scandal</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">20:43</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Vatican bank director and deputy resign
amid scandal</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68491000/jpg/_68491070_018469124-1.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Headquarters of Vatican Bank (file pic)"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The Vatican bank has been plagued by financial
scandals for decades</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The director and
deputy director of the Vatican bank have resigned following the
arrest of a senior Italian cleric over corruption and fraud
allegations.</p>
            <p>Paolo Cipriani and Massimo Tulli offered to step down on Monday
"in the best interest of the institute and the Holy See'', the
Vatican says.</p>
            <p>It comes three days after the arrest of Monsignor Nunzio
Scarano.</p>
            <p>The 61-year-old and two others are suspected of trying to move
20m euros ($26m; Â£17m) illegally.</p>
            <p>Monsignor Scarano, a priest from southern Italy, worked for
years as a senior accountant for a Vatican department known as Apsa
(the Administration of the Patrimony of the Apostolic See).</p>
            <p>He has been under investigation by Italian police for a series
of suspicious transactions involving the recycling through the
Vatican bank of a series of cheques described as church
donations.</p>
            <p>The two other men arrested on 28 June have been named as
Giovanni Maria Zito, who is described as an Italian secret service
agent, and Giovanni Carenzio, a financial broker.</p>
            <p>Ernst von Freyberg, the current president of the bank, would
serve as its interim director, taking over from Mr Cipriani, a
Vatican statement said.</p>
            <p>A new position of chief risk officer would also be created to
improve compliance with financial regulations.</p>
            <p>Last week, Pope Francis set up a commission of inquiry to look
into the bank, which has been beset by allegations of money
laundering for decades. He had already named a trusted cleric to
oversee the way the institution had been managed.</p>
            <p>Officially known as the Institute for the Works of Religion
(IOR), the bank is one of the world's most secretive. It has 114
employees and 5.4bn euros of assets.</p>
            <p>The scandal is an embarrassment to the Vatican with Pope Francis
campaigning for the Catholic Church to be closer to the people of
the developing world.</p>
            <p>Some churchmen are even questioning whether the Vatican needs
its own bank, BBC Rome correspondent David Willey reports.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372407943641"
                  href="/news/world-europe-23094320">Cleric held in Vatican bank
inquiry</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372245082802"
                  href="/news/world-europe-23063255">Pope sets up Vatican bank
inquiry</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
