<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23215319"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="At least four people die and at least 30 are hurt when a bomb explodes in a busy food street in the eastern Pakistan city of Lahore, officials say."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-07T09:19:02"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68590000/jpg/_68590054_68589800.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Bomb blast in Lahore kills four"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23215319"/>
         <title>BBC News - Pakistan bomb kills four in Lahore restaurant
district</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">7 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">10:19</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Pakistan bomb kills four in Lahore
restaurant district</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68589000/jpg/_68589799_018574904-2.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Chairs and tables are strewn across a street in Lahore following a bomb which killed at least three people"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The street was reportedly crowded with
diners at the time</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">At least four people were killed and dozens
injured when a bomb went off in a busy food street in Pakistan's
eastern city of Lahore, officials say.</p>
            <p>Local media said the explosion happened as people sat eating at
restaurants in the Anarkali area on Saturday night.</p>
            <p>At least 30 people were believed to have been wounded, with some
in a critical condition. Children were reportedly among the
casualties.</p>
            <p>There was no immediate claim of responsibility.</p>
            <p>The attack was the first of its kind for three years in Lahore,
the capital of Pakistan's Punjab province and home city of newly
elected Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif.</p>
            <p>However, there has been a series of attacks around the country
since Mr Sharif was sworn in last month - blamed on Islamist groups
including the Pakistan Taliban - which have left more than 150
people dead.</p>
            <p>The bomb was placed in an outdoor eating area in the old part of
Lahore and detonated at a particularly busy part of the
evening.</p>
            <p>Pictures taken shortly after the explosion show broken chairs
and tables lying on the ground.</p>
            <p>Eyewitnesses reported seeing windowpanes smashed and furniture
from the food stalls destroyed.</p>
            <p>"The blast site is just few metres away and the blast was so
loud that I was stunned for a while," shopkeeper Naseed Ahmed told
Reuters.</p>
            <p>"There was chaos everywhere."</p>
            <p>Local resident Mohammad Anwer said more should be done to
protect people.</p>
            <p>"This happened on the weekend when there is huge crowd gathered
here," he told Reuters news agency.</p>
            <p>"The government should do something about these kinds of
incidents. People feel very insecure."</p>
            <p>Police official Zulfiqar Hameed said the bomb was connected to a
deep freezer in one of the restaurants, according to the news
agency.</p>
            <p>Mr Sharif has called on the leaders of all major political
parties to meet on Friday to discuss initial ideas for a new
security strategy to tackle the growing threat posed by
militants.</p>
            <p>But the BBC's Richard Galpin in the capital Islamabad says it
could be months before any plan comes into effect.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
