<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23086184"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The pain of shattering Australia's glass ceiling: What Julia Gillard might be remembered for after three years as prime minister."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T16:49:16"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68422000/jpg/_68422162_68422155.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Gillard: Why was she ousted?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23086184"/>
         <title>BBC News - What Julia Gillard did for Australia and
sexism</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">17:49</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">What Julia Gillard did for Australia and
sexism</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Madeleine
Morris</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News,
Melbourne</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68419000/jpg/_68419227_624_gillard_getty.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Julia Gillard"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">In the end, Julia
Gillard is likely to be remembered more for the manner of her
coming, the manner of her going and her gender, than for what she
achieved during her three years as Australia's prime minister.</p>
            <p>That will be a shame for a leader who guided 532 pieces of
legislation through a hung parliament, including some major social
and environmental reforms.</p>
            <p>But for better or for worse, it will be an accurate reflection
of how her premiership was perceived in Australia at the time.</p>
            <p>Julia Gillard was then-Prime Minister Kevin Rudd's deputy when,
to stem the wound of Labor's plummeting popularity, she deposed him
in a surprise coup in June 2010.</p>
            <p>The irony that he too had been given the boot, before being
allowed to serve out his term as Australia's elected leader, has
not been lost on the many Gillard detractors.</p>
            <p>Despite Australia's long history of <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-21863630"
               title="Australia's coup culture">political coups</a>, that event set the
idea that Julia, as she is frequently referred to in Australia, had
knifed a mate.</p>
            <p>There are many narratives about what finally led to her
downfall.</p>
            <p>All have elements of truth and which one you believe most
depends on which tribe you belong to.</p>
            <p>To many women, it was the undeniable misogyny and sexist
scrutiny she endured throughout her leadership that brought her
down.</p>
            <p>"Deliberately barren", "bitch" and "witch" were all phrases
thrown around, sometimes by opposition MPs.</p>
            <p>One of Australia's most listened-to radio commentators
suggested, weeks after her beloved father passed away, that he had
"died of shame".</p>
            <p>Another radio "shock-jock" asked her if her partner was gay.</p>
            <p>He lost his job. The first commentator is still on air.</p>
            <p>A Liberal party supporter penned a mock menu for a fundraiser
which promised to serve up "Julia Gillard Kentucky Fried Quail
-Small Breasts, Huge Thighs and a Big Red Box".</p>
            <p>Even feminist Germaine Greer once said the PM's "arse was
fat".</p>
            <p>Many Australians rightly say that no male politician has ever
been subjected to such continued, personal attacks.</p>
            <p>But that is not the whole story.</p>
            <p>Even her supporters agree that her government was gifted at
shooting itself in the foot.</p>
            <p>The opposition's strategy of hammering home Labor's U-turns was
made easy by two big policy flips: the carbon tax and the promise
of a budget surplus.</p>
            <p>It imposed the first when it said it would not and did not
manage the second when it repeatedly said it would.</p>
            <p>Tony Abbott: 2, Julia Gillard: 0.</p>
            <p>Labor under Gillard was also perplexingly bad at letting the
electorate know about its achievements - a revolutionary national
insurance system for the disabled, a much-needed plan to save a key
Australian river system, tax reform, education reform.</p>
            <p>They all seem to have been somehow overshadowed and not just by
powerful negative messaging from the opposition.</p>
            <p>On the day she was delivering an historic apology to victims of
forced adoptions, she was subjected to a phantom leadership
challenge by her own party.</p>
            <p>Instead of a powerful message of a government righting wrongs,
the electorate got a vision of a party in disarray and this was the
image it carried home.</p>
            <p>Australia is nearly unique in Western democracies for the way it
has survived the global financial crisis. Unemployment is low, debt
to GDP ratio is comparatively low and its citizens enjoy a
remarkable standard of living.</p>
            <p>But this is not the message that Australians have absorbed.</p>
            <p>Instead it is one of a country on the verge of a crash, with
unacceptably high debt and precarious finances.</p>
            <p>This is partially down to a media that seems to be particularly
adept at looking for the gloom, but must also be down to a
government that never found a way to explain to Australians how
well they have endured the crisis.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68392000/jpg/_68392664_68392663.jpg"
                 alt="Julia Gillard"/>
               <p class="caption">Julia Gillard thanked Australians for their
support</p>
            </div>
            <p>Julia Gillard herself was not the best communicator. Even her
friends acknowledge she needed to show more of the passion and
warmth that was there but was so often kept in reserve.</p>
            <p>But really what did for Julia was Kevin Rudd himself - the man
she had toppled, who never let go of his dream of getting back into
the top job.</p>
            <p>Once he challenged and failed. Another time his supporters
called for him to challenge and he did not.</p>
            <p>The third time he rose again, after spending months courting the
media in carefully scripted moments that were officially about
campaigning for Labor, but were really about reminding voters he
was still there, waiting in the wings, should they want him.</p>
            <p>Polls show Labor is likely to do much better in the coming
election under Kevin Rudd than Julia Gillard and the caucus finally
decided to risk seeming like a fickle rabble rather than face a
thrashing under a maligned leader.</p>
            <p>Hillary Clinton famously said, when she lost out on the US
Democratic party's presidential nomination, that she had not
shattered her country's "highest and hardest" glass ceiling, but
there were now 18 million cracks in it.</p>
            <p>The lesson we might take from Julia Gillard's career is that
shattering Australia's glass ceiling resulted in walking on a lot
of broken shards.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370491948597"
                  href="/news/world-asia-22793352">Australia's election: 100 days to
go</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story" rel="published-1277337809892" href="/news/10398741">Profile: Julia Gillard</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story" rel="published-1277370615278" href="/news/10400270">Profile: Kevin Rudd</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
