<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-22965842"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="At least 15 people, including four foreigners, are killed in an assault by militant Islamists on a UN office in the Somali capital, Mogadishu."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T15:53:55"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68260000/jpg/_68260355_68257837.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Deadly attack on Somalia UN office"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Africa"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-22965842"/>
         <title>BBC News - Somalia UN office attack by al-Shabab 'kills
15'</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">16:53</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Somalia UN office attack by al-Shabab
'kills 15'</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68267000/jpg/_68267372_68267371.jpg"
                 alt="Security agents stand near the scene of a suicide bomb attack outside the United Nations compound in Somalia&#34;s capital Mogadishu"/>
               <p class="caption">Footage shows the aftermath of the attack on the
UN office in Mogadishu</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">At least 15 people,
including four foreigners, have been killed in an assault by
militant Islamists on a UN office in the Somali capital, Mogadishu,
a government minister says.</p>
            <p>The gun-battle inside the office lasted for more than an hour,
witnesses said.</p>
            <p>A cameraman outside the UN Development Programme office told the
BBC a suicide bomber blew up a car at its entrance and he saw four
gunmen enter.</p>
            <p>The al-Qaeda-linked group al-Shabab said it was behind the
attack.</p>
            <p>Officials say pro-government forces have
now secured the compound.</p>
            <p>The UN has only recently expanded its operations in Mogadishu
after years when its Somalia mission was based in neighbouring
Kenya because of security fears.</p>
            <p>This is the first time the UN offices have been attacked since
it relaunched its mission in Somalia.</p>
            <p>The UN Development Programme office is next to the heavily
fortified airport in southern Mogadishu.</p>
            <p>"A suicide bomber blew himself up at the gate of the UNDP and
then several armed fighters went in and opened fire," a senior
police official told the Reuters news agency.</p>
            <p>Interior Minister Abdikarim Hussein Guled said at least 15
people had been killed - four foreign security workers, four local
guards and seven militants.</p>
            <p>Two of the dead worked for South African state weapons firm
Denel, the company says.</p>
            <p>The UK Foreign and Commonwealth Office says it is looking into
reports that three British nationals are among the dead.</p>
            <p>The al-Shabab Twitter feed says it killed 16 UN workers,
including three Britons, two Kenyans and a South African during the
attack.</p>
            <p>A police official told AFP that three civilians also died after
being caught in crossfire.</p>
            <p>The cameraman, who asked not to be named for security reasons,
told the BBC Somali Service that he had personally helped three
people to a military ambulance.</p>
            <p>Local residents have fled and some buildings were seriously
damaged after the vehicle exploded, he said.</p>
            <div id="slideshow_container" class="storybody-halfwide-include">
               <div id="ss_slides">
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68260000/jpg/_68260802_68260801.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Government soldiers arrive to secure the United Nations compound following a suicide bomb attack in the capital Mogadishu, 19 June 2013"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">The security forces arrived at the scene
soon after the explosion. The UNDP compound is next to the airport
where the AU forces have a base.</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68260000/jpg/_68260363_68260362.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Somali government soldiers arrive to secure the United Nations compound following a suicide bomb attack in the capital Mogadishu, 19 June 2013"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">A vehicle was blown up in front of the
blue gates of the UNDP's office...</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68260000/jpg/_68260737_68260736.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Somali government soldiers pictured after a suicide bomb attack inside the United Nations compound in the Somali capital Mogadishu 19 June 2013"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">Most residents fled the area as gunfire
could be heard from inside the compound...</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68260000/jpg/_68260741_68260740.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Somali government soldiers evacuate an injured man after a suicide bomb attack inside the United Nations compound in the Somali capital Mogadishu, 19 June 2013"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">Several people outside were injured in
the suicide explosion. Exact details of casualties are not known;
al-Shabab said it had killed some foreigners...</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption full-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68260000/jpg/_68260804_68260803.jpg"
                       width="624"
                       height="351"
                       alt="Somali government soldiers gather in front of the UN compound - 19 June 2013"/>
                     <span style="width:624px;">The fighting inside the UNDP complex
went on for well over an hour.</span>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="ss_controls">
                  <a href="#prev" class="ss_prev ss_button ss_button_disabled">
                     <span>previous
slide</span>
                  </a>
                  <a href="#next" class="ss_next ss_button ss_button_disabled">
                     <span>next
slide</span>
                  </a>
               </div>
            </div>
            <p>As the cameraman was talking to the BBC
at about 09:30 GMT, gunshots could be heard in the background.</p>
            <p>He said a number of security experts had
joined the African Union (Amisom) and Somali soldiers in tackling
the militants.</p>
            <p>Just after 10:15 GMT al-Shabab said on its Twitter feed: "We've
just contacted the Mujahideen inside the #UNDP and they are still
fighting some western mercenaries inside the compound."</p>
            <p>Later it said it had killed some foreigners in the raid.</p>
            <p>"The situation is under control now... Somali soldiers along
with African Union forces stormed the compound and killed the
attackers," Somali police official Abdulahi Osman told the AFP news
agency.</p>
            <p>Amisom described the attacked as "cowardly" and Somali Prime
Minister Abdi Farah Shirdon Saaid praised the speed of the security
forces' response.</p>
            <p>"Somali and Amisom security forces responded immediately to the
situation after the initial explosion and have brought the
situation under control. Sadly we must wait to hear the full
details and confirmation of any casualties," he said in a
statement.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/67456000/gif/_67456379_som_controlled_areas_070513.gif"
                 width="304"
                 height="460"
                 alt="Map"/>
            </div>
            <p>"All our thoughts and prayers are with our UN colleagues today.
But al-Shabab will not derail the peace process. They will not stop
our recovery. Violence will not win."</p>
            <p>Earlier a UN official told the Associated Press news agency that
during the sustained firing all staff were "moved to the bunkers
where it's safe".</p>
            <p>Andrew, an aid agency worker staying at a nearby hotel,
witnessed some of the fighting.</p>
            <p>"When I heard the explosions I went up onto the roof of the
Jazeera Hotel," he told the BBC.</p>
            <p>"There were six mini-explosions. We saw UN troops on the roof of
their compound shooting down at the attackers. An RPG-7 hit the
hotel, it hit the side wall on the fifth floor."</p>
            <p>Al-Shabab, which had been in control of parts of Mogadishu for
more than two years, withdrew in August 2011 under pressure from
pro-government forces, but continues to launch occasional suicide
attacks in the city.</p>
            <p>It has also been pushed out of other cities, but still remains
in control of smaller towns and large swathes of the countryside in
central and southern Somalia.</p>
            <p>The improving security situation has prompted the return of
Somalis from the diaspora and allowed UN agencies and foreign
embassies to return to the country.</p>
            <p>Some 18,000 AU troops are in the country supporting the
government of President Hassan Sheikh Mohamud who was elected by
MPs last September.</p>
            <p>His administration is the first one in more than two decades to
be recognised by the US and the International Monetary Fund
(IMF).</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>Somalia: Failed State</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1368265817426"
                     href="/news/world-africa-22492135">Lighting up Somalia</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1367881481721"
                     href="/news/world-africa-22429487">Struggle for unity</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1367922676211"
                     href="/news/world-africa-22434071">In pictures: Camp life</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1318862196109"
                     href="/news/world-africa-15336689">Q&amp;A: Who are al-Shabab?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/67615000/jpg/_67615363_006685253-1.jpg"
                    alt="image of Mark Doyle"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Mark
Doyle</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC International
Development Correspondent</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>The UN compound in Mogadishu is just a few hundred metres from
the airport where thousands of African Union troops are based.</p>
            <p>It is in the heart of one of the most sensitive and
theoretically well-guarded areas of the city.</p>
            <p>But following the audacious attack the gateway into the compound
is now a wreck of twisted metal and rubble.</p>
            <p>For more than a year now the Somali government - and its Western
and African backers - have been lauding improved security in
Somalia.</p>
            <p>At a diplomatic conference in London in February, hosted by the
British Prime Minister David Cameron, there was optimistic talk
about the new government which was for the first time elected by a
parliament.</p>
            <p>It is true that the militant Islamist al-Shabab group has been
forced, by African Union troops, to leave most of their military
positions in the city.</p>
            <p>But this attack shows that opponents of the government still
have the capacity to hit a high-profile target which should be one
of the best protected locations in the country.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Al-Shabab At A Glance</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Name means "The Youth" in Arabic</li>
               <li>Formed as a radical offshoot of the Union of Islamic Courts,
which controlled Mogadishu, in 2006</li>
               <li>Previously ran much of southern Somalia</li>
               <li>Lost some popular support by banning Western aid agencies
during 2011 famine</li>
               <li>Affiliated to al-Qaeda</li>
               <li>Estimated to have 7,000 to 9,000 fighters</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-africa-15336689">Q&amp;A: Who are
al-Shabab?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
