<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23103853"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Georgia's Orthodox Church wields influence and power behind the scenes and on the streets, writes Paul Rimple."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T08:02:53"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68470000/jpg/_68470746_patriarch.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Georgia's mighty Orthodox Church"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23103853"/>
         <title>BBC News - Georgia's mighty Orthodox Church</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">09:02</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Georgia's mighty Orthodox Church</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68442000/jpg/_68442926_patriarch.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Patriarch Ilia II, the head of Georgia's Orthodox church"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Patriarch Ilia II has presided over a
dramatic increase in the size, influence and prestige of Georgia's
Orthodox church</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">When several dozen Georgian Orthodox
priests led tens of thousands of people on a violent attack against
a small group of gay rights activists in Tbilisi earlier this year,
much of the rest of the country was horrified, writes journalist
Paul Rimple, who has been based in the country for 10 years.</p>
            <p>Georgians pride themselves on their reputation for being
hospitable and tolerant, and most consider themselves
Christian.</p>
            <p>While the notion of homosexuality is not
widely understood or accepted in this deeply traditional Caucasus
nation, most Georgians were appalled by the scenes that unfolded in
Tbilisi on 17 May.</p>
            <p>And yet, what happened clearly illustrates the importance of the
Church in Georgia.</p>
            <p>Georgia was an early adopter of Christianity making it a state
religion in 337AD. Georgians maintained their faith over the
centuries despite the waves of invading hordes, including the
armies of Ghengis Khan and Tamerlane.</p>
            <p>Although the Soviets permitted religion
to be practised, its reach was severely limited. In 1917, there
were 2,455 working churches in Georgia, but by the mid-1980s there
were only 80, along with a few monasteries and a seminary.</p>
            <p>"During communism, the church was outdated, something for old
ladies," says political analyst Ghia Nodia.</p>
            <p>That attitude quickly changed after independence in 1991, when
the elected president, Zviad Gamsakhurdia, espoused a philosophy of
ethnic nationalism, which the Church embraced.</p>
            <p>"During the (Gamsakhurdia) national movement, the concept that
real Georgians are Orthodox Christians spread really fast," Mr
Nodia says.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68446000/jpg/_68446075_cathedral.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="405"
                 alt="Tbilisi's Sameba cathedral was built at considerable expense after Georgia gained independence in 1991"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Tbilisi's Sameba cathedral was built at
considerable expense after Georgia gained independence in
1991</span>
            </div>
            <p>Over 80% of Georgia's 4.5 million people say they belong to the
Georgian Orthodox Church, however, experts claim only about 15% -
25% actively participate in rituals.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, the Orthodox Church remains the most trusted
institution in Georgia. In a February survey carried out by the
Caucasus Resource Research Center (CRRC), 95% of respondents had a
favourable opinion of its work.</p>
            <p>Beka Mindiashvili, a former theologian who is now head of the
Tolerance Center at the public defender's office, attributes such
high confidence in the Church to the 80-year-old Patriarch, Ilia
II.</p>
            <p>"He possesses all the right attributes. He is charismatic, he
speaks slowly and each word is regarded saintly, holy," Mr
Mindiashvili says.</p>
            <p>"He is a person for everybody. To a simple person, he speaks
simply; to a politician, he speaks politically; to an intellectual,
he speaks of Umberto Eco and of classical music. And he acquired
absolute power in the Church all by himself."</p>
            <p>There were only about 50 priests when Ilia II became patriarch
in 1977. Today there are approximately 1,700.</p>
            <p>His first major test in power was in 1997, when a number of
anti-ecumenical abbots threatened to break communion with him for
being too liberal. He avoided a schism by breaking off ecumenical
activities and pursuing what philosopher Zaza Piralishvili calls an
"imitation of medieval rhetoric".</p>
            <p>Examples of the Church's
ultra-conservative interventions included warnings that yoga was
full of false "charms" that lured people away from God as well as a
recent mass mobilisation against ID cards after some Georgian
Orthodox leaders claimed the cards bore the mark of the
anti-Christ.</p>
            <p>The Church is recognised for maintaining a neutral political
stance and Ilia II is renowned for playing a significant role as
mediator in political confrontations, which in Georgia can easily
turn violent.</p>
            <p>Professor Iago Kachkachishvili, head of the sociology department
at Tbilisi State University, says the Church's political neutrality
is a myth.</p>
            <p>"The Church's influence comes from public opinion," he says. "It
uses the trust of the people as a source of strength. And every
government and politician uses the Georgian Orthodox Church as a
source of legitimacy."</p>
            <p>While the constitution stipulates a separation between church
and state, a 2002 concordat defined this relationship by granting
the Church official recognition in Georgia and a special
consultative role in the government, particularly in education.</p>
            <p>In 2009, Mikheil Saakashvili's government awarded the Church a
$15m (Ã‚Â£10m) grant - three times the amount
of the previous year - and presented luxury sports utility vehicles
to each of the 10 archbishops.</p>
            <p>Despite the lavish gifts, many conservative elements within the
Church, who are pro-Russian, openly voiced their displeasure with
the president. They saw his pro-Western orientation as a threat to
Georgian traditions and the Church's influence on the people.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68446000/jpg/_68446072_antigaysmall.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Orthodox priests were at the fore front of the protest over the gay rights march in Tbilisi"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Orthodox priests were at the forefront
of the protest over the gay rights march in Tbilisi</span>
            </div>
            <p>The clash of ideologies came to head in July 2011, when
parliament passed a law allowing religious minority groups in
Georgia to be registered as legal entities in public law giving
them legal protection previously only enjoyed by the Orthodox
Church.</p>
            <p>The move was applauded in the West, but the Georgian Orthodox
Church saw this as an infringement on its special status.</p>
            <p>Although Ilia II requested the clergy to maintain neutrality in
the 2012 parliamentary elections, many priests broke ranks and
openly supported the coalition of billionaire Bidzina Ivanishvili,
who had provided the funds to build Tbilisi's Sameba Cathedral, the
largest church in Georgia.</p>
            <p>But on 13 May, Bidzina Ivanishvili who by now was prime
minister, took an independent stance and became the first Georgian
politician to declare openly that sexual minorities were equal
citizens of this country.</p>
            <p>Three days later, Ilia II called on the authorities to ban the
17 May demonstration. This marked the first open confrontation
between church and state and culminated in expletive-shouting
priests chasing gay activists down the main streets of the
capital.</p>
            <p>Protesters broke through barricades and police were forced to
bus the small number of activists out of the area for their
protection.</p>
            <p>The day after the attacks, Tbilisi artist Magda Guruli joined
some 100 people who rallied in the city centre to call for
justice.</p>
            <p>She believes the response to the protest was a manifestation of
the patriarch's power over the state.</p>
            <p>"I'm here to say give me back my religion," she said. "Orthodoxy
is part of our culture, but who are these people who try to
influence society and try to influence their thoughts and try to
cultivate blind faith?"</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68238000/jpg/_68238727_georgiadirect304x80.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="80"
                 alt="Georgia Direct graphic"/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-europe-23010526">Georgia wants to make up
with Russia</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p01bzbcy" title="Fast Track">The Georgian hills are alive with music</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p01c1f92" title="Fast Track">Redefining Georgia</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-radio-and-tv-22953687">Working Lives
Georgia</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-22841606">More
from Georgia Direct</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">During communism, the church was outdated,
something for old ladies”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Ghia Nodia</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Georgian political analyst</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68446000/jpg/_68446077_iliaii.jpg"
              width="144"
              height="192"
              alt="Patriarch Ilia II, the head of Georgia's Orthodox church"/>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">He is charismatic, he speaks slowly and each
word is regarded saintly, holy.”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Beka Mindiashvili</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Theologian</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
