<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-china-23081653"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content=" More than two million Tibetans have been moved into so-called &#34;socialist villages&#34; by China over the last seven years, Human Rights Watch says."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T13:58:19"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68414000/jpg/_68414724_tibet_houses_getty.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="China 'moves two million Tibetans'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia/China"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-china-23081653"/>
         <title>BBC News - China resettles two million Tibetans, says Human
Rights Watch</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">14:58</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">China resettles two million Tibetans, says
Human Rights Watch</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Celia
Hatton</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC Beijing
correspondent</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68414000/jpg/_68414511_tibet_houses_getty.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Tibet houses - rows of homes for herders as part of a resettlement programme - March 2012"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Human Rights Watch says that Communist
officials are stationed in villages</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">More than two
million Tibetans have been resettled by the Chinese government over
the last seven years, a <a href="http://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/reports/tibet0613webwcover_0.pdf">
new report</a> by Human Rights Watch says.</p>
            <p>Many, including hundreds of thousands of nomads, were forced
into so-called "socialist villages", the group says.</p>
            <p>The aim is to exert tighter political control over ethnic
Tibetans, says HRW.</p>
            <p>China denies forced evictions. This comes amid reports that
restrictions on the worship of the Dalai Lama have been eased in
some areas.</p>
            <p>But the BBC was unable to confirm claims that Buddhists in
China's Tibetan areas were able to openly worship their exiled
spiritual leader and that some temples were displaying portraits of
him.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68414000/jpg/_68414323_chinese_village_464.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="507"
                 alt="Chinese village before/after"/>
            </div>
            <p>Images from Google Earth published by Human Rights Watch appear
to show the mass destruction of existing housing and the
construction of villages with uniform rows of new buildings.</p>
            <p>"The government has started to despatch new teams of Communist
Party officials to each single village of the Tibet Autonomous
Region," explained Nicholas Bequelin, Asia Researcher with Human
Rights Watch.</p>
            <p>"The new personnel stationed in these villages have been
instructed to eat, live and work with the villagers and that
includes monitoring their political opinions and identifying whose
loyalty to the Party or the government is questionable."</p>
            <p>The Chinese government has consistently
maintained that it is pouring billions of dollars into Tibet in
order to bolster its economy and improve the Tibetans' way of
life.</p>
            <p>However, tensions remain. In the past four years, at least 117
Tibetans have set themselves on fire to protest at Chinese
government rule, resulting in 90 deaths.</p>
            <p>Many Tibetans resent the influx of Han Chinese into Tibet and
the Communist Party's restrictions on their religious freedoms.</p>
            <p>In response, the Chinese government has tightened surveillance
over the entire Tibetan plateau. In cities, the authorities appear
to be keeping tabs on potential troublemakers by dividing each
neighbourhood along a grid system.</p>
            <p>The new security system is designed to closely monitor the
situation at street-level to prevent a repeat of mass protests that
centred in Lhasa, the capital of Tibet, in March 2008.</p>
            <p>In addition, the report says, about 300,000 nomadic herders have
been relocated and settled since the early 2000s and the
authorities have reportedly announced their intention to turn an
additional 113,000 into sedentary dwellers by the end of 2013.</p>
            <p>In a separate development, some Buddhists in China's Tibetan
areas are now able to openly worship their exiled spiritual leader,
the Dalai Lama, according to Radio Free Asia. In an experimental
change in policy, some temples can openly display portraits of the
Dalai Lama and no one is allowed to criticise him.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68414000/jpg/_68414256_68414255.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Tibetan spiritual leader the Dalai Lama prays during a talk to young Tibetans at the Tibetan Children&#34;s Village School in Dharmsala, India, Thursday, June 27, 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Unconfirmed reports suggest the
Communist Party has relaxed its attitudes towards the Dalai
Lama</span>
            </div>
            <p>Tibetan Buddhists are allowed to worship their leader in his
role as a religious figure and not a political one, according to
sources quoted by RFA.</p>
            <p>If this policy change is true, it could represent a significant
relaxation of the Communist Party's attitudes towards the Dalai
Lama.</p>
            <p>For years, senior Communist officials have infuriated Tibetan
Buddhists by referring to the Dalai Lama by a series of derogatory
names. Zhang Qingli, the Communist Party chief in charge of Tibet
until 2011, famously referred to the Buddhist cleric as "a wolf in
monk's robes".</p>
            <p>Still, it is far from clear whether an experimental policy is
under way. And some analysts say that, if true, it may simply be
because the authorities had failed to stamp out worship of the
Dalai Lama and use of his image in monasteries.</p>
            <p>The BBC contacted the Communist Party's State Administration for
Religious Affairs, headquartered in Beijing, for confirmation of
this change in policy.</p>
            <p>The administration did not respond to the
BBC's repeated requests for comment. China's state-run media are
also silent on a possible change of policy towards the Dalai
Lama.</p>
            <p>One source at a Buddhist temple in Qinghai province said that he
had heard about the change in policy but could not speak about it
on the telephone. The source refused to give his name.</p>
            <p>A spokesperson for the Central Tibetan Administration, the
Tibetan government in exile based in Dharamshala, India, said he
had heard reports of the experimental policy, but had not been able
to verify its existence.</p>
            <p>"Such reports, if true, are localised reports," notes Tashi
Phuntsok, secretary for the department for information and
international relations for Tibet's government-in-exile. "It is
possible some areas have adopted a softer policy to prevent further
self-immolations."</p>
            <p>"I've seen similar news online," one monk in Sichuan's Ganzi
Prefecture told the BBC by phone. "I don't know if it is true or
not. But it's certainly not happening here."</p>
            <p>Another monk in Sichuan's Aba Prefecture, where many of the
self-immolations have taken place, admitted: "I have not heard of
this news. But we cannot hang the Dalai Lama's portrait inside the
monastery or worship him openly.</p>
            <p>"We can only do it in secret. Not in our monastery, not in the
monastery around here either, not that I know."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1353717249918"
                  href="/news/world-asia-china-20457627">Will China's new leaders change
Tibet policy?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1352724490195"
                  href="/news/world-asia-china-20293887">China warns Dalai Lama on
Tibet</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1348741094039"
                  href="/news/world-asia-china-19739803">Dalai Lama hopes for China
change</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">We cannot hang the Dalai Lama's portrait
inside the monastery or worship him openly. We can only do it in
secret”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Monk in Sichuan's Aba prefecture</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>The Tibet Divide</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>China says Tibet has always been part of its territory</li>
               <li>Tibet had long periods of autonomy</li>
               <li>China launched a military assault in 1950</li>
               <li>Opposition to Chinese rule led to a bloody uprising in
1959</li>
               <li>Tibet's spiritual leader, the Dalai Lama, fled to India</li>
               <li>Dalai Lama now advocates a "middle way" with Beijing, seeking
autonomy but not independence</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-asia-pacific-16747814">The Tibet issue:
Two views</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-asia-china-16761606">Inside Tibet</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
