<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23178275"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Portugal's prime minister fights to patch up his fragile coalition, as markets spooked by the latest eurozone crisis watch nervously."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T19:54:48"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68541000/jpg/_68541309_portdemonewafp.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Portugal battles to defuse crisis"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23178275"/>
         <title>BBC News - Portugal battles to ease crisis and market
pressure</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">20:54</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Portugal battles to ease crisis and market
pressure</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68541000/jpg/_68541301_portpmcoelhoafp.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Portugal PM Pedro Passos Coelho"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Portugal's prime minister has faced a
wave of street protests over austerity</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Portugal's prime
minister has been meeting his former foreign minister, who resigned
this week, trying to persuade him to rescue their coalition.</p>
            <p>Talks have been called "constructive" - bringing calm to markets
that had feared a possible government collapse.</p>
            <p>PM Pedro Passos Coelho is keen to defuse the political crisis
and avoid the turmoil of an early election.</p>
            <p>President Anibal Cavaco Silva is due to begin talks with the
parties on Monday.</p>
            <p>The ruling coalition is under intense pressure to stick to the
tough austerity targets dictated by Portugal's bailout.</p>
            <p>Yields on 10-year Portuguese bonds fell to 7.26% early on
Thursday. A sharp spike - topping 8% on Wednesday - had revived
market jitters about instability in the eurozone.</p>
            <p>Portugal has doggedly stuck to its austerity programme, despite
its severe recession.</p>
            <p>That has angered trade unions and left-wing parties but brought
praise from Portugal's international partners.</p>
            <p>"I think Portugal has achieved very remarkable results -
certainly, it's been a painful route - and the results that have
been achieved have been quite significant, remarkable, if not
outstanding," European Central Bank president Mario Draghi said on
Thursday.</p>
            <p>Mr Cavaco Silva is known to be keen to avoid calling early
elections, the BBC's Alison Roberts reports from Lisbon.</p>
            <p>He is clearly putting pressure on the coalition to patch things
up, given the adverse reaction to the crisis in the markets, our
correspondent says.</p>
            <p>Left-wing opposition parties are demanding early elections, and
opinion polls suggest the ruling conservatives would do badly. The
Communist Party held a big anti-government rally in central Lisbon
on Wednesday.</p>
            <p>The crisis began on Monday with the resignation of Finance
Minister Vitor Gaspar, who for two years had overseen the unpopular
austerity policies.</p>
            <p>The prime minister's choice to replace him, the former Treasury
Secretary Maria Luis Albuquerque, is seen as just as wedded to
austerity, says our Lisbon correspondent.</p>
            <p>It was that fact that the foreign minister and junior coalition
leader, Paulo Portas, cited in tendering his resignation on
Tuesday.</p>
            <p>The European Commission President, Jose Manuel Barroso, said he
was following the situation "with concern".</p>
            <p>Portugal received a bailout worth more than 78bn euros ($102bn;
Â£67bn) in May 2011, on the condition it
implemented austerity measures.</p>
            <p>Demonstrators have taken to the streets in recent days to
protest against planned austerity reforms.</p>
            <p>Portugal has been in recession for two years and the economy is
expected to contract by 2.3% this year.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372852236043"
                  href="/news/world-europe-23162786">Eurozone crisis: Why Portugal
matters</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372792312133"
                  href="/news/world-europe-23154232">Resignations rock Portugal
politics</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372794198263"
                  href="/news/world-europe-23155475">Portuguese PM vows to fight
on</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
