<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-22977607"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The BBC's Daniel Sandford travels with Marina Khodorkovskaya to the prison where her son Mikhail - once Russia's richest man - is being held on what he says are politically-motivated charges."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T01:04:20"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68267000/jpg/_68267319_012125645-1.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Khodorkovsky's mother: 'Contempt' for Kremlin"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-22977607"/>
         <title>BBC News - Khodorkovsky's mother: 'Contempt' for
Kremlin</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:04</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Khodorkovsky's mother: 'Contempt' for
Kremlin</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Daniel
Sandford</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News,
Moscow-Segezha</span>
            </span>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68487000/jpg/_68487516_68487515.jpg"
                 alt="Marina Khodorkovskaya"/>
               <p class="caption">Marina Khodorkovskaya: "I want to hope, but I
don't believe in it"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Moscow's
Leningradsky Vokzal is the best known railway station in
Russia.</p>
            <p>It is the terminus where the heroine of Leo Tolstoy's 19th
Century novel Anna Karenina watches a man being cut in two by a
train - a warning of the tragedy to come.</p>
            <p>Today the station is still a busy place, with long-distance
trains setting off for St Petersburg and the Arctic.</p>
            <p>This month, on a Tuesday night, well after midnight, an elderly
woman made her way through the crowds and bustle to board the
"Arktika" express to Murmansk. It was the start of a long journey
in a two-bed sleeper compartment.</p>
            <p>Marina Khodorkovskaya was not heading for Murmansk. She was
planning to alight a few stops earlier at Segezha - a scruffy town
close to the Arctic Circle, known for its pulp and paper factory
and for the gulag of the Stalin era.</p>
            <p>These days there is still a prison in Segezha - Penal Colony No
7.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/53410000/jpg/_53410387_012125645-1.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Mikhail Khodorkovsky (right). File photo"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Mikhail Khodorkovsky urged Russians to "tell the
truth and speak out"</span>
            </div>
            <p>That is where Mrs Khodorkovskaya was heading to visit her son
Mikhail Khodorkovsky, once Russia's richest man, and now seen by
many as its longest serving political prisoner.</p>
            <p>She makes the journey every three months, and this month she
agreed that we could travel with her.</p>
            <p>She told me she had lost count of the number of times over the
last 10 years that she had made the journey either to Segezha or to
Eastern Siberia where her son use to be held.</p>
            <p>"I used to collect tickets," she recalled. "But then I threw
them all away."</p>
            <p>When she described the visiting room, it
sounded more suited to violent criminals than those convicted of
economic crimes.</p>
            <p>"It is a long room divided into two with prisoners on one side
and relatives on the other," she explained. "Then there are
partitions - each with a little desk and a phone set on either of
the thick glass. If somebody talks loudly next to you, you can
hardly hear anything."</p>
            <p>The journey to Segezha takes 20 hours in each direction. The
three-monthly visits last four hours.</p>
            <p>Mikhail Khodorkovsky is also allowed a 15-minute weekly phone
call from a booth outside.</p>
            <p>"It's very cold there in winter," Mrs Khodorkovskaya said. "Once
we thought he was ill, because he was speaking very strangely. But
it turned out that his lips were frozen, and he couldn't speak with
his normal voice."</p>
            <p>Khodorkovsky was a billionaire who made his money in the 1990s
by building Russia's biggest oil company Yukos.</p>
            <p>When Vladimir Putin became president he told the oligarchs to
stay out of politics, but in 2003 Khodorkovsky started challenging
that, pushing back against the increasing authoritarianism and -
according to some ministers of the time - buying influence in the
Duma.</p>
            <p>Eventually he was arrested and put on trial for tax evasion and
fraud.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68268000/jpg/_68268360_outsideprison2.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Prison where Mikhail Khodorkovsky is held"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The prison's watchtowers are strangely reminiscent
of a World War II movie</span>
            </div>
            <p>There is little doubt that some of his business practices in the
1990s had been questionable.</p>
            <p>The pro-Putin Duma deputy Vyacheslav Nikonov told me: "I don't
consider Khodorkovsky to be a political prisoner. He got what he
deserved according to the Russian criminal code. There is no-one
saying that he paid his due share of taxes."</p>
            <p>But no other oligarch was put on trial, and when Khodorkovsky's
eight year sentence was drawing to a close he was put on trial
again and given a further six years in prison.</p>
            <p>The US and EU called it "selective justice." The Russian
opposition insists he is a "political prisoner", and it is hard to
argue with that.</p>
            <p>As the seemingly endless birch forests and lakes of northern
Russia trundled past the window of the "Arktika" express, I asked
Mrs Khodorkovskaya if she still got angry.</p>
            <p>"You know, it's not anger", she replied.</p>
            <p>"It's contempt - contempt towards people who are ready to
destroy the lives of people, and their wives and children, just for
money. Lives destroyed, and why? Only because of money."</p>
            <p>We were not able to go in with Mrs Khodorkovsky to visit her
son.</p>
            <p>The colony's governor told me to my face that if the BBC team
came within 50m of the prison we would be arrested.</p>
            <p>But what we saw from the road is a dilapidated compound
surrounded by rusting barbed-wire fences and guard dogs.</p>
            <p>Giant spotlights can be seen on top of some of the buildings,
and all around the perimeter stand wooden watchtowers strangely
reminiscent of a World War II movie. It is not a high-tech prison,
but it is strangely intimidating.</p>
            <p>Khodorkovsky's incarceration has become relevant this year,
partly because it is his 10th year in prison, but also because
there has been an acceleration recently of what seem to be
"political trials."</p>
            <p>Amnesty International has declared two imprisoned women from the
punk protest group Pussy Riot to be "prisoners of conscience".</p>
            <p>A group of street protesters who demonstrated on the day before
President Putin's inauguration have been in jail for almost a year,
and are still awaiting trial.</p>
            <p>The most charismatic leader to emerge from the new opposition,
Alexei Navalny, is on trial for embezzlement - in what he claims is
a political prosecution. The maximum prison sentence he faces is 10
years.</p>
            <p>Ahead of her visit Marina Khodorkovskaya agreed to ask her son a
question on our behalf. What were his thoughts about those standing
trial today?</p>
            <p>Through his mother, Khodorkovsky sent his reply.</p>
            <p>"Because our courts are unfair, it is hard to stay strong. But
people need to be honest, tell the truth and speak out. They should
not be afraid."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1293442483864"
                  href="/news/world-europe-12082222">Profile: Mikhail
Khodorkovsky</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1330926749932"
                  href="/news/world-europe-17254826">Khodorkovsky case to be
reviewed</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1297705796570"
                  href="/news/world-europe-12454974">Khodorkovsky judge 'under
orders'</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Khodorkovsky got what he deserved according
to the Russian criminal code”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Vyacheslav Nikonov</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Duma deputy</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
