<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23156808"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="At least 17 people have been killed in a suspected US drone strike in north-west Pakistan, officials say, in the deadliest such attack this year."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-03T10:13:56"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68517000/jpg/_68517492_68516430.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Pakistan drone strike 'kills 17'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23156808"/>
         <title>BBC News - Suspected US drone 'kills 17' in north-west
Pakistan</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">3 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">11:13</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Suspected US drone 'kills 17' in
north-west Pakistan</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/60071000/gif/_60071910__52903566__49021847_pak_s_304x171-1-1.gif"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Map"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">At least 17 people
have been killed in a suspected US drone strike on a compound in
north-west Pakistan, Pakistani officials say.</p>
            <p>At least two missiles were fired at a house in North Waziristan
tribal region early on Wednesday, the deadliest drone attack in
Pakistan this year.</p>
            <p>It is the third such attack since new PM Nawaz Sharif won
elections in May. He has demanded an end to such attacks.</p>
            <p>A government statement said the strike violated Pakistan's
sovereignty.</p>
            <p>"Pakistan has repeatedly emphasised the importance of bringing
an immediate end to drone strikes," a foreign ministry spokesman
said.</p>
            <p>"They are counter-productive, entail loss of innocent civilian
lives and have human rights and humanitarian implications."</p>
            <p>In a separate development, at least six security personnel are
reported to have been killed and at least six more injured in an
early morning attack by militants at a checkpoint near
Peshawar.</p>
            <p>At least two more are reported to be missing, possibly kidnapped
by the attackers.</p>
            <p>Reports citing local officials said most of those killed in the
drone strike were thought to be from the militant Haqqani
group.</p>
            <p>Officials say four missiles were fired by
a US drone, targeting two houses and two vehicles, near Miranshah,
the main town in North Waziristan. A number of other people were
also injured.</p>
            <p>The Haqqani network has been described by US military commanders
as one of the most resilient militant groups operating in
Afghanistan.</p>
            <p>The troubled border region is a known stronghold for al-Qaeda
and Taliban militants.</p>
            <p>Seven people were killed in a similar strike on 8 June, also in
North Waziristan, just three days after the new prime minister was
sworn in.</p>
            <p>After that incident the Pakistani government summoned a senior
US diplomat in protest, condemning what it called a "violation of
Pakistan's sovereignty and territorial integrity".</p>
            <p>At least two key leaders of the Pakistani Taliban have been
killed in earlier US drone strikes this year. Mullah Nazir was
killed in January and Waliur Rehman was killed in May, shortly
after Mr Sharif swept to election victory.</p>
            <p>The BBC's Richard Galpin in Islamabad says that the latest air
strike by US forces will further heighten tensions between
Washington and the new Pakistani government.</p>
            <p>Mr Sharif has called for a joint strategy to stop US drone
strikes. The issue is hugely controversial in Pakistan, where parts
of the government and military have often been accused of
criticising the use of drones in public, but co-operating in
private.</p>
            <p>Drone strikes are a source of severe tension between the US and
Pakistan.</p>
            <p>It is estimated that between 2004 and 2013, CIA drone attacks in
Pakistan killed up to 3,460 people.</p>
            <p>About 890 of them were civilians and the vast majority of
strikes were carried out by the Obama administration, research by
the Bureau of Investigative Journalism said.</p>
            <p>Earlier this year, Mr Obama called the strikes part of a
legitimate campaign against terrorism, but he also pledged more
programme transparency and stricter targeting rules.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370027934147"
                  href="/news/world-asia-22737481">Sharif condemns US drone
strike</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1360350380996"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-21389200">The cost of Obama's secret drone
war</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1333572865624"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-17618273">Close-up look at US drone
<span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Drones in Pakistan</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68516000/jpg/_68516429_hi018103537-1.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Pakistani tribal villagers in Islamabad hold a rally to condemn US drone attacks on their villages in border areas along the Afghan border (December 2010)"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>Recent US report highlighted "terror" felt by civilians in
north-west Pakistan, where drones target areas such North and South
Waziristan</li>
               <li>Hundreds of low-level militant commanders and substantial
minority of civilians killed</li>
               <li>Exact figures difficult to compile because independent media
and researchers denied access to area by authorities</li>
               <li>Bureau of Investigative Journalism estimates up to 3,460 people
killed in drone strikes, of which about 890 were civilians</li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://livingunderdrones.org/">Living Under Drones
report</a> says top commanders account for estimated 2% of
victims</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
