<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23157256"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Nato's new supreme allied commander in Europe, General Philip Breedlove, discusses Nato's future after it pulls out of Afghanistan."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-03T08:56:41"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68518000/jpg/_68518941_natosoldiersgetty.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Where does Nato go post-Afghanistan?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23157256"/>
         <title>BBC News - Nato commander Philip Breedlove on post-Afghan
future</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">3 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">09:56</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Nato commander Philip Breedlove on
post-Afghan future</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Jonathan
Marcus</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC diplomatic
correspondent</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68518000/jpg/_68518253_breedlove.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="General Breedlove"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Gen Breedlove is in charge of the Nato mission to
provide Afghan troops with support after 2014</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">As Nato's
decade-long mission in Afghanistan begins to wind down, one of the
alliance's senior military leaders discusses what the future
holds.</p>
            <p>The next 18 months will be a period of significant change for
Nato. The alliance's combat troops and their equipment will be
gradually withdrawn from Afghanistan by the end of 2014. But after
that the Afghans will not be entirely on their own.</p>
            <p>A new Nato mission - dubbed "Resolute Support" - will begin to
provide the Afghan armed forces with critical advice and
support.</p>
            <p>The man who has to watch over this crucial and potentially
difficult period of transition is the alliance's new supreme allied
commander in Europe (Saceur), General Philip Breedlove.</p>
            <p>His job is to not only to keep an eye on the transition process
but to begin to think about a Nato beyond the Afghan War.</p>
            <p>What sorts of missions should it be training for? What
challenges lie ahead?</p>
            <p>I met Gen Breedlove, just a few weeks into his new job, at the
Nato headquarters at Northwood just outside London.</p>
            <p>So how was the transition in Afghanistan going?</p>
            <p>Afghan forces, he insisted, were stepping up to the mark.</p>
            <p>"They are standing, fighting not wilting," he told me. "They are
fighting well and recovering from those engagements."</p>
            <p>There were still, as he put it, "some areas where we need to
work on their abilities to sustain themselves in the fight - we
have until the end of 2014 to do that".</p>
            <p>I pushed him, though, on the increasing Afghan Army
casualties.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68518000/jpg/_68518935_natosoldiersgetty.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Nato soldiers in Afghanistan on 18 June 2013"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Nato's combat troops are scheduled to leave
Afghanistan by the end of 2014</span>
            </div>
            <p>Wasn't this a problem for morale, especially problems with
casualty evacuation, or casevac as it's known.</p>
            <p>Again his recipe was that more work was required, though he
acknowledged that the Afghans' own capabilities in this area would
not be at the level that used to be provided by Nato helicopters
and medical teams.</p>
            <p>Gen Breedlove is also beginning to think about Nato's role after
2014.</p>
            <p>Talks had begun with Afghan leaders, he told me, but "right now
it is primarily about focussing on our own internal planning,
shaping the force, understanding the mission and reaching consensus
on that mission".</p>
            <p>Surely, I asked, once the combat phase for Nato is over there is
a strong danger that alliance nations will lose interest in
Afghanistan, especially if there is still a significant risk of
casualties to trainers and other support troops.</p>
            <p>The general insisted this was not going to happen.</p>
            <p>"We have communicated directly - both the Nato secretary general
and myself to President Karzai - we will be there, we are not
abandoning the Afghan people and this mission - Resolute Support -
will go forward and it will go forward well," he said.</p>
            <p>Of course there are many other problems on Saceur's radar, not
least the potential spill-over of the Syrian crisis into alliance
territory in Turkey.</p>
            <p>"What is happening in Turkey right now is a great demonstration
of what Nato is all about. Nato has come to the aid of an ally," he
told me.</p>
            <p>Six batteries of Patriot missiles from three countries - the US,
Germany and the Netherlands - are operational there on the
ground.</p>
            <p>What about a potential Nato-led "no fly" operation, I asked. How
quickly could it be up and running?</p>
            <p>Gen Breedlove would not be drawn.</p>
            <p>"Right now there is no intention for Nato
to be involved inside Syria in a kinetic way," he said. "I can only
opine that if there were to be a Syria operation it would be a
non-Nato mission."</p>
            <p>"The focus now," he insisted, "is on defence of Turkey."</p>
            <p>But with combat operations in Afghanistan - at least for Nato -
drawing down, Gen Breedlove is also inevitably thinking about the
alliance's wider military role post-Afghanistan.</p>
            <p>I put it to him that almost ever since the end of the Cold War
there has been some kind of military mission - starting in the
Balkans - that gave Nato a sense of military purpose.</p>
            <p>"Clearly we will see a change in our mission in Afghanistan," he
cautioned, but "the mission is not over".</p>
            <p>But he is thinking a great deal about going forward, he told
me.</p>
            <p>"Right now we have a Nato that is at the pinnacle of its ability
to operate together - our tactics, techniques and procedures are
better than they have ever been. We work cohesively now in a team
way that was never known in Nato."</p>
            <p>How do we not lose that?</p>
            <p>"It will be a central focus of mine to capture this excellence
and to maintain it," he explained.</p>
            <p>"We are going from deployed to ready and that will be my
focus."</p>
            <p>But, I asked, is that habit of joint action - however successful
- sufficient to sustain the alliance in the years ahead?</p>
            <p>There are clearly differing views as to the degree of success
that Nato has had in Afghanistan. It has certainly been an
unpopular war in many alliance countries.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68518000/jpg/_68518949_afghannationalarmyap.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Afghan national army troops in June 2013"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Afghan troops will take the lead for security
throughout the country</span>
            </div>
            <p>Gen Breedlove not surprisingly preferred to stress the
positives.</p>
            <p>He accepted that for the future there were differing views as to
the direction that Nato should go, a tension between some countries
who stress the alliance's role well beyond its own boundaries, and
others who want it to return to its core mission - the so-called
Article V task - of the direct defence of Nato territory.</p>
            <p>"I think the beauty of Nato all along," Gen Breedlove said, "has
been the flavour of 28 nations - the richness of Nato is this
discussion that countries bring to the table."</p>
            <p>But he accepted that after years of counter-insurgency warfare,
Nato forces would need to refresh some of their skills in the sort
of high-end combat with heavier forces that is key to the
Alliance's defensive mission.</p>
            <p>But equally Gen Breedlove stressed that Nato would have to
remain ready to carry out a wide variety of missions.</p>
            <p>New threats were emerging, and he pointed to North Africa and
the rise of al-Qaeda there as one troubling development that Nato
was watching closely.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1284981539718"
                  href="/news/world-south-asia-11371138">Q&amp;A: Foreign forces in
Afghanistan</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371535894004"
                  href="/news/world-asia-22942013">Nato hands over security to
Afghans</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1364503922155"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-21971786">Nato supreme commander
nominated</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Right now we have a Nato that is at the
pinnacle of its ability to operate together - our tactics,
techniques and procedures are better than they have ever been, we
work cohesively now in a team way that was never known in
Nato”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Gen Phillip Breedlove</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Nato supreme allied commander in
Europe</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
