<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23267440"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="US allies Mexico, Brazil, Colombia and Chile join the chorus of disapproval over allegations that the US is conducting widespread espionage."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-11T09:15:14"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="US allies demand answers over spying"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Latin America"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23267440"/>
         <title>BBC News - US allies Mexico, Chile and Brazil seek spying
answers</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">11 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">10:15</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">US allies Mexico, Chile and Brazil seek
spying answers</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68666000/jpg/_68666227_68666224.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="A woman burns US flags during a protest in support of Bolivian President Evo Morales in front of the US embassy in Mexico City, on 4 July"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Protests have spread from the streets to
the parliaments of Latin America</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">US allies Mexico,
Brazil, Colombia and Chile have joined other Latin American nations
in demanding answers from Washington over spying allegations.</p>
            <p>Brazilian media reported earlier this week that the US had
seized web traffic and phone calls across the region.</p>
            <p>Spying targets included oil and energy firms, Venezuela's
military purchases and information on Mexico's drug wars.</p>
            <p>The reports, based on leaks by fugitive Edward Snowden, said the
US ran a "data-collection base" in Brasilia.</p>
            <p>The O Globo newspaper said the US facility in the Brazilian
capital was part of a network of 16 such bases maintained by the
National Security Agency (NSA) around the world to intercept
transmissions from foreign satellites.</p>
            <p>The paper said it had evidence that the base was in operation
until at least 2002, but it was unclear whether it still
existed.</p>
            <p>Brazil apparently remains the main target of US snooping in
Latin America, with major firms and foreign visitors routinely
targeted.</p>
            <p>The surveillance was allegedly conducted through partnerships
between Brazilian telecoms firms and US agencies, although the
reports did not name any companies.</p>
            <p>On Monday Brazilian President Dilma Rousseff urged the US to
explain, and has ordered an investigation into the claims.</p>
            <p>She said if true they would represent
"violations of sovereignty and human rights".</p>
            <p>During angry exchanges in parliament on Wednesday, senators
suggested Brazil should give Mr Snowden asylum, while others said
Brazil should cancel lucrative defence contracts with the US.</p>
            <p>The allegations on O Globo detailed claims of US spying across
Latin America, sparking an angry reaction from traditional American
foes in the region like Venezuela and Ecuador.</p>
            <p>But analysts say the US will be much more concerned with the
irritation the revelations have caused in Brazil, Colombia, Mexico
and Chile.</p>
            <p>Mexican President Enrique Pena Nieto said the foreign ministry
had asked "quite clearly" for an explanation about the spying
allegations.</p>
            <p>"And we want to know if this is the case, and if it is so, it
would obviously be totally unacceptable," he said.</p>
            <p>Officials in Chile and Colombia made similar statements earlier
in the week.</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden is still believed to be staying in the transit area
of Moscow's Sheremetyevo airport, where he fled after being named
as the source of a series of leaks about the US spying
programme.</p>
            <p>He has asked for asylum in several countries, with Bolivia,
Nicaragua and Venezuela indicating they would offer him refuge.</p>
            <p>According to various reports, Venezuela appears his most likely
destination, although it is unclear how he can get there without
being intercepted by the US or its allies.</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden's leaks have led to revelations that the US is
systematically seizing vast amounts of phone and web data across
the world, under an NSA programme known as Prism.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>US spy leaks</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372684702774"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23123964">Revelations of US spy
scandal</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372869435767"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23165992">Where will Snowden end
up?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372702760008"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23133216">Is it OK to spy on your
allies?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372348565338"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-23077279">Wikileaks back in
spotlight</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Snowden leaks timeline</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <strong>5 June</strong>: First leak published in the Guardian
saying the National Security Agency (NSA) is <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-22793851">collecting the
telephone records</a> of millions of people in the US</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>6 June</strong>: Details of the <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-22811580">US Prism internet
surveillance programme</a> published by the Guardian and Washington
Post</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>9 June</strong>: Guardian <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-22836378">identifies
Edward Snowden</a> as the source of the leaks, at his own request,
and says he has been in Hong Kong since 20 May</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>14 June</strong>: US <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23012317">files criminal
charges</a> against Mr Snowden</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>23 June:</strong> Mr Snowden leaves Hong Kong for
Moscow, Ecuador confirms he has applied for political asylum</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>2 July:</strong> Bolivian leader Evo Morales' plane is
diverted to Vienna and apparently searched for Mr Snowden</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>6 July:</strong> Bolivia, Venezuela and Nicaragua say
they would offer Mr Snowden asylum</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-us-canada-22837100">Who is Edward
Snowden?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-us-canada-23165992">Where will Snowden end
up?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
