<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23283684"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Fugitive US intelligence leaker Edward Snowden has requested a meeting with human rights groups at Moscow airport, Russian officials say."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-12T08:42:55"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68689000/jpg/_68689308_snowdenreuters.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Snowden 'asks to meet activists'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23283684"/>
         <title>BBC News - Edward Snowden 'requests human rights groups
meeting'</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">12 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">09:42</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Edward Snowden 'requests human rights
groups meeting'</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68557000/jpg/_68557197_68557196.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Edward Snowden"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Edward Snowden is believed to be currently staying
at a Moscow airport</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Fugitive US
intelligence leaker Edward Snowden has requested a meeting with
human rights groups in Moscow, Russian officials say.</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden wants to meet them later on Friday at Sheremetyevo
airport, where he is thought to be staying.</p>
            <p>The former CIA contractor is wanted by the US on charges of
leaking secrets about US surveillance schemes.</p>
            <p>He has sent requests for political asylum to at least 21
countries, most of which have turned down his request.</p>
            <p>However, Bolivia, Nicaragua and Venezuela have indicated they
could take him in.</p>
            <p>But even if a country accepted the American's application,
getting there could prove difficult.</p>
            <p>Last week, several European countries refused to allow the jet
of Bolivian president Evo Morales to cross their airspace on its
way back from Moscow - apparently because of suspicions that Edward
Snowden was on board.</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden planned to make a statement on Friday, Russia's
Interfax news agency quoted an unnamed airport source as
saying.</p>
            <p>The American is believed to have been stuck in transit since
arriving in Moscow from Hong Kong on 23 June, even though no
pictures of his stay there have emerged.</p>
            <p>He has emailed meeting requests to leading human rights
organisations, including Amnesty International and Human Rights
Watch.</p>
            <p>An airport spokeswoman confirmed the
meeting would take place in the transit area. It is scheduled for
17:00 local time (13:00 GMT), the BBC's Steven Rosenberg, in
Moscow, reports.</p>
            <p>Sergei Nikitin, the head of Amnesty International's Russia
office, confirmed he had received an invitation and planned to
attend the gathering.</p>
            <p>Prominent Moscow lawyer Genrikh Padva is also reported to have
been invited.</p>
            <p>Human Rights Watch representative Tanya Lokshina <a href="https://www.facebook.com/tanya.lokshina">posted the text of Mr
Snowden's alleged email</a> on her Facebook page.</p>
            <p>In the message, the 30-year-old fugitive complained that the US
government was waging an "unlawful campaign" to prevent him from
securing asylum.</p>
            <p>"This dangerous escalation represents a threat not just to the
dignity of Latin America or my own personal security, but to the
basic right shared by every living person to live free from
persecution," the message read.</p>
            <p>The email said the fugitive wanted to discuss the "next steps
forward" in his situation.</p>
            <p>It also instructed those attending to bring a copy of the invite
and identification papers, as "security will likely be tight at
this meeting".</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden cannot leave the transit zone without asylum
documents, a valid passport or a Russian visa, none of which he
reportedly has.</p>
            <p>Washington seeks to prosecute Mr Snowden over the leaking of
thousands of classified US intelligence documents.</p>
            <p>The leaking of classified intelligence documents has led to
revelations that the US is systematically seizing vast amounts of
phone and web data.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68687000/jpg/_68687178_68687103.jpg"
                 alt="William Burns"/>
               <p class="caption">US officials said China's failure to hand over
Mr Snowden had undermined trust between both nations</p>
            </div>
            <p>The documents have revealed that both the UK and French
intelligence agencies allegedly run similarly vast data collection
operations, and the US has been eavesdropping on official EU
communications.</p>
            <p>The case has strained relations between the US and China.</p>
            <p>President Barack Obama said on Thursday he was "disappointed"
that China had chosen not to hand over Mr Snowden to the US
authorities when he was in Hong Kong in June.</p>
            <p>A US government official said the decision had undermined calls
for co-operation between the two countries</p>
            <p>But China said Hong Kong - which allowed Mr Snowden to leave for
Russia - had acted in accordance with the territory's law.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>US spy leaks</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372684702774"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23123964">Revelations of US spy
scandal</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372869435767"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23165992">Where will Snowden end
up?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372702760008"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23133216">Is it OK to spy on your
allies?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372348565338"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-23077279">Wikileaks back in
spotlight</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Snowden leaks timeline</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <strong>5 June</strong>: First leak published in the Guardian
saying the National Security Agency (NSA) is <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-22793851">collecting the
telephone records</a> of millions of people in the US</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>6 June</strong>: Details of the <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-22811580">US Prism internet
surveillance programme</a> published by the Guardian and Washington
Post</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>9 June</strong>: Guardian <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-22836378">identifies
Edward Snowden</a> as the source of the leaks, at his own request,
and says he has been in Hong Kong since 20 May</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>14 June</strong>: US <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23012317">files criminal
charges</a> against Mr Snowden</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>23 June:</strong> Mr Snowden leaves Hong Kong for
Moscow, Ecuador confirms he has applied for political asylum</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>2 July:</strong> Bolivian leader Evo Morales' plane is
diverted to Vienna and apparently searched for Mr Snowden</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>6 July:</strong> Bolivia, Venezuela and Nicaragua say
they would offer Mr Snowden asylum</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-us-canada-22837100">Who is Edward
Snowden?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-us-canada-23165992">Where will Snowden end
up?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
