<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23072361"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="As the BBC's Damien McGuiness departs Georgia after two years, he reflects on some surprising things he learned."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T01:28:21"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68540000/jpg/_68540465_georgian_road_signs.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="10 things you might not know about Georgia"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23072361"/>
         <title>BBC News - 10 things you might not know about
Georgia</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:28</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">10 things you might not know about
Georgia</h1>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68525000/jpg/_68525837_compo2.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="composite image of photographs from Georgia "/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">For much of the last two decades since
independence the former Soviet republic of Georgia has often hit
the headlines for all the wrong reasons. War, instability,
corruption and Stalin. But, as Damien McGuinness reports, there is
more to Georgia than that.</p>
            <p>Here are 10 other memorable things about the country.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68528000/jpg/_68528234_georgian_road_signs.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Georgian road sign "/>
            </div>
            <p>Spoken Georgian is like no other language you are likely to
hear. It belongs to its own ancient linguistic group unlike any
other language spoken outside the region. It includes rare sounds
that many visitors may never have heard before. Some consonants,
for example, are pronounced from the back of the throat with a
sudden guttural puff of air. Georgian has its own 33-letter
alphabet thought to be based on the sort of Aramaic spoken in the
time of Jesus. To the untutored eye, the letters look very much
alike. A squiggle too far and your "k" can easily turn into a "v"
or a "p". But even without understanding it, Georgian writing is
beautiful, a myriad of theatrical swirls and flourishes. Very
fitting to a country of dramatic personalities.</p>
            <p>At least, not by Georgians. They call
their country Sakartvelo. The origins of the country's name in
English are obscure. One theory points to the Middle Ages when
Christian crusaders swept through the region on their way to the
Holy Land. At that time, it was part of the Persian Empire and the
people here were known as "Gurj". They were also devotees of St
George. Theory has it that the crusaders made the connection and
named the country Georgia. These days, there's no mistaking the
link to St George. A golden statue of the saint slaying a dragon
dominates Tbilisi's central square. He is also Georgia's patron
saint and the national flag featuring his red cross on a white
background is everywhere.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68499000/jpg/_68499771_jm_tb_bbc.011.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Flea market in Tbilisi selling pictures of Joseph Stalin "/>
            </div>
            <p>Go to any flea market in Georgia and you're likely to stumble
across a moustachioed face looking out at you amid the bric-a-brac.
Sixty years after his death there's still a market for portraits of
Joseph Stalin, the Georgian-born ruler of the former Soviet Union.
As Georgia's most famous son, attitudes here towards "Uncle Joe"
are complicated. After independence, many Stalin statues were torn
down but now some are returning to town squares. Some older
Georgians revere him as a strong leader, who defeated Hitler, and
are proud that tiny Georgia produced someone who had such an impact
on world history. But more often he's viewed as a tyrant
responsible for brutal purges of his own people.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68499000/jpg/_68499773_skiing.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Skier on a ski lift in Georgia's Caucasus mountains"/>
            </div>
            <p>What's the highest mountain range in Europe? The Alps? Wrong. It
is the Caucasus Mountains marking the border between Georgia and
Russia. While the highest peak is in Russia, Georgia lays claim to
the second highest, Shkara, which at 5,193m (17,040 ft) beats Mont
Blanc by nearly 400m (1,312 ft). These dramatic mountains, with
their terrifying hairpin roads and hidden villages cut off at
winter, are the stuff of legend. In Greek mythology they were one
of the pillars holding up the world. And it was here that Zeus tied
up Prometheus, to have his liver eaten by eagles. Today they are
increasingly becoming a <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p01536wm">destination for
climbers, walkers or skiers looking for adventure</a>.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68499000/jpg/_68499775_154525551.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Georgia's new parliament building "/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Not to everyone's taste</span>
            </div>
            <p>There is a startling amount of space-age architecture in
Georgia. The new parliament building is a huge glass and concrete
bubble, looking like a giant frog's eye. A slew of new police
stations have been built that are all glass and see through,
symbolic of Georgia's aspirations for democratic transparency.
Meanwhile, many of the country's roads and infrastructure remains
in bad shape. President Mikheil Saakashvili's preference for flashy
prestige projects to impress foreign investors and politicians, has
not gone unnoticed. Also, while glass government buildings may work
well in temperate Northern Europe, buildings constructed like
greenhouses are less suited to Georgia's scorching summers.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68407000/jpg/_68407012_anti-gayafp.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Two men in Georgia holding an anti-gay banner"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">A small gay rights march in May sparked a furious
response from some Georgians</span>
            </div>
            <p>There is a lot of body contact between men in Georgia. Men
stroll down the main avenue arm-in-arm, or lounge on street
corners, limbs entwined. A casual observer might be forgiven for
thinking that this was a sign of tolerance towards homosexuality.
They'd probably be wrong. According to surveys Georgia is one of
the world's most homophobic countries - attitudes which came to the
surface in May during a violent anti-gay demonstration in Tbilisi.
Tens of thousands of people were angry because a group of gay
rights activists had wanted to gather for 30 minutes against
homophobic violence. The anti-gay protesters shouted slogans
through megaphones, and called for "gays to go back to Europe".
Many other Georgians, though, were shocked by the display of
intolerance, describing it as "a sad day for Georgia."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68407000/jpg/_68407010_toastwithhilaryafp.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="President Mikhail Saakashvili toasting US Secretary of State Hilary Clinton"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">How it is done. President Mikhail
Saakashvili toasting US Secretary of State Hillary
Clinton</span>
            </div>
            <p>A guest is a gift from God, goes the saying in Georgia. So
foreign visitors are plied with food and drink - an enjoyable
experience, if not always good for the waistline. But "a toast!" is
the phrase dreaded by any visitor with a busy work day ahead. Out
comes a bottle of Chacha, the lethal Georgian schnapps, or a large
plastic bottle of homemade wine. Both must be downed in large
shots. Excuses that you have to drive back six hours along twisting
mountain roads won't be accepted. Instead, you'll be offered a bed
for the night, and be propelled into a full-scale traditional
feast.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68407000/jpg/_68407014_churchafp.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="A religious procession celebrating the Orthodox Christmas in Tbilisi."/>
               <span style="width:464px;">A religious procession celebrating the
Orthodox Christmas in Tbilisi.</span>
            </div>
            <p>While many European nations have seen religious adherence fall
in recent decades, the Orthodox Church in Georgia is booming.
Attendance, adherence and respect for the Church are all growing.
Over 80% of Georgians say they belong to the Church while its head,
Patriarch Ilia II, is the most respected public figure by far, with
popularity ratings over 90%. Dating back to the 4th Century, the
Church helped the country keep its ancient musical traditions
during the Soviet era and has been central to Georgians' sense of
themselves since independence.</p>
            <p>After centuries of domination by foreign powers, Georgians are
sceptical of government. So family and friends are crucial for
getting anything done. "I have a cousin who can sort it," is what I
was frequently told when I had a problem. One such cousin helped us
buy a second-hand car, another got us accommodation at an army base
when heavy snow trapped us in the mountains. With social welfare
often patchy, it's the family on which Georgians rely in times of
crisis.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68534000/gif/_68534418_georgia_europe_624.gif"
                 width="624"
                 height="265"
                 alt="Map showing location of Georgia in relation to Europe"/>
            </div>
            <p>The leafy boulevards of the Georgian capital Tbilisi look like
Paris, and the English-speaking young hipsters wouldn't look out of
place in Berlin. But take a look at a map and you'll find the
former Soviet republic 1,000km (600 miles) east of the Bosphorus,
marooned in Asia. One definition of Europe marks the Caucasus
Mountains as its border, putting Georgia firmly in Asia. Other
definitions place the whole Caucasus region, including Georgia, in
Europe which is where most Georgians feel it belongs. Head into the
countryside however, where farmers scratch out a subsistence
living, and it's a different story. If this is Europe, it can
sometimes feel more like 19th-Century Sicily than the modern-day
EU.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68238000/jpg/_68238727_georgiadirect304x80.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="80"
                 alt="Georgia Direct graphic"/>
            </div>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-europe-23010526">Georgia wants to make up
with Russia</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p01bzbcy" title="Fast Track">The Georgian hills are alive with music</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p01c1f92" title="Fast Track">Redefining Georgia</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-radio-and-tv-22953687">Working Lives
Georgia</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-22841606">More
from Georgia Direct</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
