<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23096831"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The family of a Qatari doctor say he has been beaten and held in solitary confinement in the UAE, after being arrested there four months ago."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T13:08:08"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68435000/jpg/_68435710_qataridoc.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Qatari doctor 'beaten' in UAE jail"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23096831"/>
         <title>BBC News - Qatari doctor held and 'beaten' in unknown UAE
jail</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">14:08</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Qatari doctor held and 'beaten' in unknown
UAE jail</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Bill Law</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Gulf analyst</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68433000/jpg/_68433593_qataridoc.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Dr Mahmoud al-Jaidah"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Dr Mahmoud al-Jaidah is being held in an unknown
location, his family say</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The family of a
Qatari doctor say he has been beaten and held in solitary
confinement in the UAE, after being arrested there four months
ago.</p>
            <p>Dr Mahmoud al-Jaidah was detained at Dubai Airport on 26
February.</p>
            <p>International human rights groups have consistently criticised
the UAE for detaining critics of the government.</p>
            <p>The UAE government has said that all prisoners are treated
according to the law and that any allegations of mistreatment are
investigated.</p>
            <p>Dr Jaidah has not been charged with any offence.</p>
            <p>His case bears a striking resemblance to that of Salah Yafai who
was arrested at Dubai airport on 26 April 2013.</p>
            <p>The Bahraini citizen was held for almost seven weeks in an
unknown location without charge.</p>
            <p>Mr Yafai was released on 15 June after the Bahrain government
intervened on his behalf.</p>
            <p>Mr Yafai, a fitness trainer and educator, is a member of the
Bahrain al-Islah society, a conservative religious organisation
with links to the Muslim Brotherhood.</p>
            <p>Last year 94 people, most of them members of the al-Islah
society in the UAE, were arrested and are on trial charged with
plotting to overthrow the government.</p>
            <p>The detainees include two prominent human rights lawyers, as
well as judges, teachers, and student leaders.</p>
            <p>If convicted, the activists, including 13 women, each face up to
15 years in jail, with no right of appeal.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>Lost weight</strong>
            </p>
            <p>A family member said that he thought authorities in the UAE were
trying to link Dr Jaidah to the 94 and to the Muslim
Brotherhood.</p>
            <p>"He is not a member of the brotherhood, a supporter maybe but
not a member".</p>
            <p>The relative said that Dr Jaidah was deprived of sleep for three
days: "They beat him and made him say things he didn't do".</p>
            <p>He added that the family did not know where Dr Jaidah was being
held.</p>
            <p>Qatar has long supported the Muslim Brotherhood, while the UAE
view the brotherhood as a serious threat.</p>
            <p>Both countries are members of the Gulf Cooperation Council
(GCC).</p>
            <p>Dr Jaidah's family told the BBC that the Qatari government had
facilitated three visits, the most recent on 23 June.</p>
            <p>On each occasion, according to the relative, the doctor was
driven blindfolded to a government building in Abu Dhabi from
wherever he was being held.</p>
            <p>The family member said that Dr Jaidah told them that he was not
being beaten any longer but that he was still in solitary
confinement and had lost nearly two stone (10 kgs) whilst in
detention.</p>
            <p>A lawyer hired by the family had met with his client only once
for 10 minutes and in the presence of an official.</p>
            <p>The family member said "our government has told us they are
trying but are getting no response. They need to try more".</p>
            <p>No-one from the Qatari government was available for comment.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371218065516"
                  href="/news/world-middle-east-22896454">Bahraini 'disappears in UAE
jail'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372343228728"
                  href="/news/world-middle-east-23084903">New allegations of UAE
torture</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1354802782971"
                  href="/news/world-middle-east-20587246">Gulf states attempt to stem tide
of online criticism</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
