<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-22893341"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The issue of homosexuality is widely taboo in the Middle East, including Yemen where the penalty for being gay can be severe. Despite such suppression, one young Yemeni man has declared his homosexuality very publicly in a blog."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T03:11:48"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68232000/jpg/_68232148_yemen2.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Alaa Jarban: One of Yemen's first openly gay men"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-22893341"/>
         <title>BBC News - Alaa Jarban: One of Yemen's first openly gay
men</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">04:11</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Alaa Jarban: One of Yemen's first openly
gay men</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68156000/jpg/_68156335_yemen1.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="405"
                 alt="Alaa Jarban"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Alaa Jarban's "I'm Queer" post has provoked a
backlash</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The issue of
homosexuality is widely taboo in the Middle East, including Yemen
where the penalty for being gay can be severe. Despite such
suppression, one young Yemeni man has declared his homosexuality
very publicly in a blog. He spoke to a BBC Arabic reporter about
the reaction he received and his fears for his safety.</p>
            <p>In the early days of Yemen's revolutionary uprising a
21-year-old student preparing to sit his finals at Sana'a
university emerged as one of the key figures in the country's youth
movement.</p>
            <p>Alaa Jarban organised and led protests throughout the revolution
in 2011, calling for the ousting of then-Yemeni President Ali
Abdallah Saleh.</p>
            <p>Last week, inspired by the hope the revolution created, Alaa
became one of the first people to come out publicly as gay while
still living in Yemen.</p>
            <p>Those following him on social networking sites found out about
his sexual orientation through a link to his blog where he
announced: "I'm Queer."</p>
            <p>In his post, Mr Jarban revealed intimate thoughts and reflected
on a perplexed and isolated period of adolescence growing up as a
gay boy in a conservative society.</p>
            <p>News of his statement spread quickly through Yemen's activist
community, and has already provoked a strong backlash.</p>
            <p>In a country where homosexual activity is illegal, many in
Yemen's revolutionary circles still do not equate freedom with
sexual liberation.</p>
            <p>Asked why he came out so openly when the repercussions could be
so severe, Mr Jarban replied: "It's very difficult to live a life
that is not you every single day.</p>
            <p>"I took part in the revolution to change our reality; it is not
a revolution if we don't revolutionise every aspect of our
community and ourselves."</p>
            <p>The rights activist was speaking from Canada where he was
attending a conference. Since coming out, he has continued his life
with little interruption, trying to ignore the hate mail he now
receives.</p>
            <p>Since his revelation, Mr Jarban has been
attacked by those he previously thought of as friends and
revolutionary comrades.</p>
            <p>One message on his blog read: "You make me sick. I can't believe
I shook hands with you one day. Can't believe we were in the same
square and revolution together.</p>
            <p>"It's because of faggot people like you that our revolution
didn't succeed... people like you deserve to DIE. I spit on you,
you dog."</p>
            <p>Mr Jarban knew his statement would not be received well, and yet
he is still sad and hurt at losing many close friends as a
consequence of coming out.</p>
            <p>"But I will never regret doing it," he said.</p>
            <p>Alongside the hateful messages, he also found support from a
small community of more accepting people.</p>
            <p>Finding positive support shared on a public platform, regardless
of how small, shows a distinct shift in attitudes towards
homosexuality among some in Yemen.</p>
            <p>"Tolerating homosexuality is associated with modernity," said
Brian Whitaker, author of Gay and Lesbian life in the Middle
East.</p>
            <p>But while for some that is a good thing, for others it
reinforces the idea that Yemenis need to preserve their traditions
in order to fight off this creeping so-called "Western
modernity".</p>
            <p>The prospect of accepting homosexual people seems distant in a
country that does not acknowledge their existence.</p>
            <p>"I asked friends where is the gay community, and people said
there are no gays in Yemen," wrote a girl who was afraid to share
her real identity on Alaa's blog, which has become a platform for
contributors from the LGBT [lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender]
community.</p>
            <p>"What, I don't exist?"</p>
            <p>
               <strong>'I feel lost'</strong>
            </p>
            <p>"When the protests reached Yemen, I decided to take part in the
hope of finding a new side to my country, a side I could finally
relate to," said Mr Jarban.</p>
            <p>But that hope began to wane as he watched the limited impact the
revolution had on traditional Yemeni life and attitudes - despite
the ousting of a president who had ruled for 32 years.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68232000/jpg/_68232146_kamalal-solaylee-creditpeterbregg.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Kamal al-Solaylee"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Kamal al-Solaylee says his decision to come out as a
gay Yemeni encouraged others</span>
            </div>
            <p>Kamal al-Solaylee - author of Intolerable: A Memoir of Extremes,
a book about the trials he faced coming out as member of the Yemeni
diaspora - described Mr Jarban's decision as brave, especially for
a man so young.</p>
            <p>"But he understood the consequences when he made that decision,"
said the Canadian of Yemeni origin.</p>
            <p>Acutely aware of those consequences, Mr Solaylee is nearly 50
and lives in Canada.</p>
            <p>After his book was published, gay Yemeni men sought him out,
eager to share experiences and embrace their sexual identity in an
accepting Yemeni community.</p>
            <p>Mr Solaylee was deluged with emails and letters. "I became the
godfather of gay Yemeni men," he joked.</p>
            <p>He feels protective of Mr Jarban and wants to help him, but
there is little he can do if the 23-year-old decides to stay in
Yemen.</p>
            <p>"He can't possibly go back to Yemen," said Mr Solaylee, who is
both concerned about the younger man's safety and a possible
crackdown on Yemen's LGBT community.</p>
            <p>For his part, Mr Jarban feels torn by having to make a
decision.</p>
            <p>"I feel lost," he said. "People tell me to stay in Canada where
I would be safer."</p>
            <p>Yemen's transitional government has much to deal with other than
the security of minority communities.</p>
            <p>The overstretched administration is tackling mounting security
threats from al-Qaeda, recurring clashes with Houthi rebels in the
north, a moribund economy and is in the midst of a thorny so-called
National Dialogue.</p>
            <p>"Diplomatic pressure might be exerted on the government not to
prosecute Alaa if the situation gets complicated," said Brian
Whitaker. "But it [the Yemeni government] can do very little to
protect Alaa."</p>
            <p>The Yemeni government did not respond to BBC requests for a
comment.</p>
            <p>In Canada he is safe, but Mr Jarban knows that sooner or later
he will have to face the repercussions of his decision.</p>
            <p>But that has not deterred him from being vocal about LGBT issues
at home.</p>
            <p>"The situation has to change," he said.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12813859">Yemen
unrest</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1363608487786"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-21831081">In pictures: Long road to
dialogue</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1360049148296"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-21325844">A rare 'success' at
risk</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1347302365090"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-19551599">Serious blow</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1329825474487"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-17112797">Multiple challenges</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">I will never regret doing it”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Alaa Jarban</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
