<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23162786"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Portugal's political crisis is a reminder that bailout countries are struggling to meet tough targets, Gavin Hewitt reports."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-03T11:50:36"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68525000/jpg/_68525469_img_2327.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Eurozone crisis: Why Portugal matters"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23162786"/>
         <title>BBC News - Eurozone crisis: Why Portugal matters</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">3 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">12:50</span>
            </span>
            <div class="correspondent-byline">
               <div class="correspondent-byline-inner">
                  <a href="/news/correspondents/gavinhewitt">
                     <span class="correspondent-portrait">
                        <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/58405000/jpg/_58405505_7206dcc3-8739-47e9-870c-ae02affa38e1.jpg"
                          alt="Gavin Hewitt, Europe editor"
                          width="144"
                          height="104"/>
                     </span>
                     <span class="byline-lead-in">Article written
by</span>
                     <span class="name">Gavin Hewitt</span>
                  </a>
                  <span class="bbc-role">Europe editor</span>
                  <ul class="social-links">
                     <li>
                        <a rel="me" href="/news/correspondents/gavinhewitt">More from
Gavin</a>
                     </li>
                     <li>Follow <a rel="me" href="http://twitter.com/BBCGavinHewitt">Gavin on Twitter</a>
                     </li>
                  </ul>
               </div>
            </div>
            <h1 class="story-header">Eurozone crisis: Why Portugal matters</h1>
            <div class="has-icon-comment dna-comment-count-simple"> </div>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68522000/jpg/_68522584_portap.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Anti-government protest in Lisbon, 2 Jul 13"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Lisbon: Tough austerity measures have fuelled
anti-government protests</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The political crisis in Portugal sends a
signal that the eurozone crisis is not over. The interest rate on
Portugal's ten-year bonds edged above 8% today, a reminder of
conditions when the crisis was at its most intense.</p>
            <p>The government in Lisbon has been zealous in following the
Brussels/Berlin script by cutting spending and implementing
reforms. Portugal has applied some of the fiercest tax rises and
budget cuts. In Brussels it was feted as an example of a country
doing everything asked of it</p>
            <p>It appears, however, that the austerity drive has reached its
limits. Even within the government <a href="/news/world-europe-23154232"
               title="Resignations rock Portugal politics">ministers are having
doubts.</a> The recession has shown no sign of ending. Unemployment
is at 17.6%. There are 932,000 people without jobs. Thousands of
graduates are leaving the country. Last week Portugal endured
another general strike.</p>
            <p>Portugal has already been granted more time to reach the target
for cutting its deficit. Even so the IMF has said its debt levels
remain "very fragile". The level of concern could be judged by
statements from the European Commission today. It called on
Portugal to clarify its situation "as soon as possible". The
President of the Commission, Jose Manuel Barroso, warned that the
"financial credibility built up by Portugal could be jeopardised by
the current political instability. If this happens it would be
especially damaging for the Portuguese people..."</p>
            <p>The head of the Eurogroup (the eurozone finance ministers),
Jeroen Dijsselbloem, said "the situation is worrying. So I'm
calling on Portugal to take responsibility."</p>
            <p>Germany weighed in, saying it was "confident" Portugal would
stick to the reforms. Politicians in Portugal are under enormous
pressure to stick with the programme.</p>
            <p>So what is to be done? Portugal will struggle to find political
consensus behind continuing with the reforms and cuts. The
government might try and persuade Brussels to ease again the terms
of its 78bn-euro (Ã‚Â£66bn; $101bn) bailout,
which was agreed in 2011. That will not be easy.</p>
            <p>The prime minister has already warned the Portuguese people to
prepare for new sacrifices, to avoid a second bailout. The German
Chancellor Angela Merkel, facing an election, may be very reluctant
to contemplate a second bailout. It would raise, once again, doubts
about the whole strategy.</p>
            <p>What this latest crisis underlines is just how difficult it will
be for countries like Portugal to exit their bailout programme and
regain access to the markets.</p>
            <p>It is not, however, just Portugal which remains in crisis.
Greece is once again in trouble. The ruling coalition is fragile
and the country has only a few days to demonstrate how it can meet
the terms of its EU/IMF bailout. The privatisation programme, which
was central to it raising funds, is faltering. New problems are
emerging in the accounts of the state-run health insurer. The IMF
is signalling its alarm. Greece will have to show how it can meet
its targets or the IMF may withdraw from the rescue programme.
That, in itself, would deepen the crisis.</p>
            <p>There are some hopeful signs. Activity in the manufacturing and
service sector in much of the eurozone seems to be improving, but
very slowly and, all the time, the patience of voters in many of
these countries is being tested.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372842466224"
                  href="/news/business-23160037">Crisis hits Portugal borrowing
costs</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1305132071108"
                  href="/news/business-13359367">Eurozone in crisis: Unemployment</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
