<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23208617"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="North and South Korean officials agree in principle to reopen the Kaesong industrial complex after marathon talks at the truce village of Panmunjom."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-07T06:35:46"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68590000/jpg/_68590212_hi018567591.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Koreas reach deal on Kaesong zone"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23208617"/>
         <title>BBC News - Kaesong talks: North and South Korea reach
agreement</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">7 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">07:35</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Kaesong talks: North and South Korea reach
agreement</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68590000/jpg/_68590205_hi018567591.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Park Chol-Su and Su Ho (6 July 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">North Korea's chief delegate Park Chol-Su (L) and
his South Korean counterpart, Su Ho reached an agreement after at
least 15 hours of talks</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Officials from North
and South Korea have agreed in principle to reopen the Kaesong
industrial complex.</p>
            <p>The deal, which includes facilities inspections, was reached
after marathon talks held at the truce village of Panmunjom in the
demilitarised zone.</p>
            <p>Work at the factory park was halted in April amid high regional
tensions.</p>
            <p>Correspondents say the closure of Kaesong, seen as a symbol of
inter-Korean ties, showed how serious this year's political
tensions were.</p>
            <p>The industrial complex is a major source of income for the
North.</p>
            <p>Attempts to hold high-level talks last month failed on
procedural grounds.</p>
            <p>The meeting on the North Korea side of Panmunjom started on
Saturday and lasted at least 15 hours.</p>
            <p>Officials will meet at Kaesong on Wednesday to "restart
operations, prevent an operation suspension in the future and
normalise the zone as soon as both sides are ready to do so", South
Korea's chief delegate Suh Ho told reporters after the talks.</p>
            <p>"We got an impression that the North was very willing to resolve
the Kaesong issue and is making great efforts as well," Suh Ho
said.</p>
            <p>As part of the deal, both sides agreed to allow South Korean
company managers to inspect their factories, as well as retrieve
finished goods and raw materials.</p>
            <p>Prior to operations being suspended, there were around 120 South
Korean businesses in the factory park. The firms have been unable
to reach their goods for three months.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68584000/jpg/_68584531_68584530.jpg"
                 alt="Kaesong talks"/>
               <p class="caption">There are hopes that the talks will renew
diplomatic efforts between the two Koreas</p>
            </div>
            <p>Some have since threatened to abandon the zone entirely and
relocate their equipment.</p>
            <p>Seoul suggested the working-level talks on Thursday, a day after
Pyongyang said Seoul businessmen could visit the closed complex to
inspect and maintain equipment.</p>
            <p>Late on Thursday, North Korea accepted the offer, the South
said.</p>
            <p>Pyongyang withdrew its 53,000 workers from the complex in April,
apparently angered by tightened UN sanctions in the wake of its
nuclear test in February, and annual South Korea-US military
drills.</p>
            <p>North Korea also prevented South Korean workers from entering
the joint commercial zone.</p>
            <p>The last South Korean workers left the zone on 3 May.</p>
            <p>The talks were very limited but could pave the wave for
discussion of bigger issues such as North Korea's nuclear
programme, says the BBC's Seoul correspondent Lucy Williamson.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="/news/world-asia-pacific-11421928">Korea
crisis</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371436696165"
                     href="/news/world-asia-22902119">What does Pyongyang want?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1367365842342"
                     href="/news/world-asia-22350948">Why US talks are unlikely</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1365489685975"
                     href="/news/world-asia-china-22062589">What is China's role?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1367787887827"
                     href="/news/business-22393749">Kaesong: focus of frustration</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
