<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23249012"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The senior pilot in the cockpit of Asiana flight 214 realised the plane was flying too low when it was 500ft (152m) over the water, an official says."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-10T00:10:41"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68642000/jpg/_68642162_68635636.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Pilot 'knew' crash plane was too low"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/US and Canada"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23249012"/>
         <title>BBC News - Asiana 214 pilot realised plane flying too
low</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">10 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:10</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Asiana 214 pilot realised plane flying too
low</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68635000/jpg/_68635639_68635636.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt=" Investigator in Charge Bill English, foreground, and NTSB Chairwoman Deborah Hersman discuss the progress of the investigation into the crash of Asiana Airlines Flight 214 in San Francisco 9 July 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Investigators are sifting through the
wreckage to determine the factors that helped so many passengers
escape serious injury</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The senior pilot in
the cockpit of Asiana flight 214 realised the plane was too low
when it was flying at only 500ft (152m), an official has said.</p>
            <p>The Boeing 777 crash-landed at the San Francisco airport on
Saturday, killing two passengers and injuring 180.</p>
            <p>The pilot at the South Korean plane's controls was about
half-way through his Boeing 777 training, an official said.</p>
            <p>Investigators have indicated the plane was flying too slowly
when it struck a sea wall before crashing on the runway.</p>
            <p>In a press briefing on Tuesday, National Transportation Safety
Board Chairman Deborah Hersman cautioned against speculating about
the cause of the crash.</p>
            <p>Ms Hersman also revealed that the South Korean airliner's pilots
were not tested for drugs or alcohol after the crash, because they
do not fall under US regulations.</p>
            <p>And she said two flight attendants who had been sitting at the
back of the plane were ejected when the plane crashed and thrown
onto the tarmac. They survived but were seriously injured.</p>
            <p>The two passengers who died have been identified as Chinese
teenagers Ye Mengyuan and Wang Linjia. Police are investigating
whether one of them survived the crash only to be run over by an
emergency vehicle deploying to the crash site.</p>
            <p>An account has emerged in recent days of Asiana 214's final
moments.</p>
            <p>As the flight bound from Incheon in South Korea approached San
Francisco after its 11-hour journey across the Pacific Ocean, three
out of four pilots aboard were in the cockpit.</p>
            <p>Lee Kang-kuk, who was still completing his initial training on
the Boeing 777 and had never before flown one into San Francisco,
was at the controls, Ms Hersman said on Tuesday.</p>
            <p>Beside him and in command of the aeroplane was an instructor
pilot, flying in that capacity for the first time, Ms Hersman
said.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68642000/jpg/_68642853_plane2.jpg"
                 alt="Debbie Hersman"/>
               <p class="caption">Hersman: "Two flight attendants in the rear of
the aircraft were ejected"</p>
            </div>
            <p>In the jump seat behind the two pilots was a relief first
officer who had flown to San Francisco five or six times as a
monitoring pilot. A fourth crewman, serving as relief captain, was
in the cabin as the plane landed, and was still being interviewed
by investigators on Tuesday.</p>
            <p>As the plane approached on a clear day, the pilot in control of
the plane was cleared to land. About 34 seconds prior to impact,
the plane was flying at 500ft and at about 134 knots (154mph;
248km/h), when the instructor pilot realised it was flying too
low.</p>
            <p>He told the pilot to pull back on the stick, and seconds later
he realised that the automated throttle controls, which had been
engaged, were not maintaining the correct speed of 137 knots. About
eight seconds before impact, the pilot in control pushed the
throttles forward to speed up.</p>
            <p>Less than two seconds before the crash, the pilot tried to abort
the landing, but it was too late. The plane came in much too
shallow. The main landing gear struck a sea wall well short of the
end of the runway, then the tail struck and was ripped off the rear
of the aircraft.</p>
            <p>The aeroplane then rotated left and went into 360-degree spin
before coming to rest to the left of the runway.</p>
            <p>The first officer was hospitalised with a cracked rib, and
neither of the two pilots were seriously injured.</p>
            <p>At least 30 surviving passengers remain in San Francisco
hospitals, many with serious spinal injuries.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68643000/jpg/_68643120_b51d898e-323f-4c37-b3d8-52700837b55a.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Yoon Young-doo (9 July 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Asiana President Yoon Young-doo departed
Korea on Tuesday for San Francisco</span>
            </div>
            <p>The two teenagers who died had been sitting in the rear of the
plane, where many of the most seriously injured passengers were
seated, but their bodies were found on the tarmac.</p>
            <p>Ms Hersman has said airport surveillance video did not
conclusively show whether an emergency vehicle had run over one of
the students, and a county coroner has said he would need at least
two weeks to rule on the death.</p>
            <p>Large teams of investigators have begun sifting through the
wreckage.</p>
            <p>Asiana Airlines President Yoon Young-doo arrived in San
Francisco on Tuesday to visit victims in hospital and apologise for
the crash. He was mobbed by dozens of reporters at the San
Francisco airport.</p>
            <p>Mr Yoon spoke briefly in Korean and was then escorted back into
the terminal by police. He is also scheduled to meet with NTSB
investigators and tour the accident site.</p>
            <p>South Korean President Park Geun-hye has sent a condolence
letter to China President Xi Jinping and the families of the two
deceased young women, calling the crash "regrettable".</p>
            <p>The Boeing 777 has a good safety record, and this is thought to
be the first crash involving fatalities.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68593000/jpg/_68593615_plane_crash_624.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="980"
                 alt="Graphic"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373235088611"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-23222048">Crash plane 'tried to abort
landing'</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373282769643"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-23227673">Survivor: 'I thought I was dying'
<span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373145766744"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-23214501">Crash plane 'has good reputation'
<span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
