<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23077537"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="One year after sectarian violence broke out in Burma, the country's unwanted Rohingya community remain marginalised and unwanted, the BBC's Jonathan Head reports."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T02:15:12"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68412000/jpg/_68412616_rohingyawhiteidcardsahnaukpyin-6248.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Burma's unwanted people"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23077537"/>
         <title>BBC News - The unending plight of Burma's unwanted
Rohingyas</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">03:15</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">The unending plight of Burma's unwanted
Rohingyas</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Jonathan
Head</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News,
Rakhine</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68408000/jpg/_68408380_rohingyamosqueahnaukpyin-6294.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Rohingya children gather outside a mosque at Ah Nauk Pyin"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Rohingya hamlet Ah Nauk Pyin is
surrounded by a ring of Buddhist villages</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">It has been a year
since sectarian fighting broke out in Burma's westernmost state,
forcing 140,000 people from their homes and casting a dark shadow
over the promising start made by the new reformist government.</p>
            <p>Ugly anti-Muslim sentiment that was evident in those first
clashes between Buddhists and the Rohingya minority in Rakhine
state last June and October has now spread, setting off assaults on
Muslim communities in several parts of the country.</p>
            <p>Nearly all of those displaced in Rakhine state were Rohingyas,
and their plight has drawn in substantial international assistance,
channelled through major NGOs and UN agencies.</p>
            <p>The Burmese government has become conscious of the negative
publicity created by the long-standing discrimination against
Rohingyas. It has authorised one official inquiry into the
violence, and is co-operating with the international relief
effort.</p>
            <p>But, as I discovered on a recent visit to Rakhine state, not
much has changed for the Rohingyas.</p>
            <p>In fact, their already tenuous status in Burma, also known as
Myanmar, appears to be weakening.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68407000/jpg/_68407202_myanmararmyatrohingyacamp-5809.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Burmese soldiers at a Rohingya camp"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Inmates in Rakhine's Rohingya camps are barred from
travelling freely</span>
            </div>
            <p>A combination of intense hostility from the Rakhine Buddhist
majority, and an official policy of segregation which imposes
restrictions on the Rohingyas alone, has forced them to the margins
of this already poor region, unwanted and unrecognised.</p>
            <p>My visit coincided with that of the UK
International Development Minister Alan Duncan, who had come to see
how British aid to Rakhine state totalling
Ã‚Â£6.4 million was being spent, and to assess
the prospects for reconciliation between the two estranged
communities.</p>
            <p>It was a typically rushed affair, with little time in each of
the camps he visited.</p>
            <p>He was accompanied at all times by the jovial figure of Burma's
Deputy Minister for Borders, Major-General Zaw Win, in full
military uniform, and by squads of police and soldiers.</p>
            <p>Nonetheless, the Rohingyas he met were unabashed in venting
their frustration over their situation.</p>
            <p>"We just want to go home," one woman shouted. "I want
citizenship, and I want my old life back."</p>
            <p>Her camp was just a few kilometres from the state capital
Sittwe, but the inmates are not allowed to go there, either for
supplies or to seek work.</p>
            <p>Military checkpoints all around Sittwe block the Rohingyas from
travelling, although the Buddhists are usually free to go where
they want.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68472000/jpg/_68472512_rohingyacampmyebonrakhine-5742.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="A Rohingya camp in Myebon, Rakhine"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Conditions in Rohingya camps can deteriorate quickly
in the rain</span>
            </div>
            <p>Some improvements have been made to the camps, but they are
limited.</p>
            <p>Enough food is supplied, and the government has made a start
building elevated long-houses to protect the Rohingyas from the
rain.</p>
            <p>But these primitive barracks are a far cry from the neat, solid
rows of individual houses already constructed for the small number
of displaced Buddhists, who have been living in settlements far
better made and situated than those housing the Rohingyas.</p>
            <p>Their camps quickly become muddy quagmires every time it rains,
which it does every day now.</p>
            <p>And the ban on travel means Rohingyas cannot go to hospital for
treatment, even to have babies.</p>
            <p>Burmese officials justify these restrictions on grounds of
security. But the way they are applied to just one group has
uncomfortable echoes of apartheid in South Africa, or segregation
in the southern USA.</p>
            <p>One constant obsession is the high birth-rate.</p>
            <p>Buddhists all over Burma believe Muslims are on track to become
the majority because of the number of wives and children they have,
even though official statistics put the Muslim population at around
4%.</p>
            <p>But one exasperated international NGO worker pointed out to me
that the attacks on Rohingyas and their subsequent isolation had
disrupted a once-successful family planning programme.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68407000/jpg/_68407206_residentsaungmingalalastmuslimsinsittwe-5830.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Residents at Aung Mingala, Sittwe"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Foreigners are rarely allowed in Aung
Mingala, the last Muslim town in Sittwe</span>
            </div>
            <p>The hostility felt by the local Buddhists to the Rohingyas is a
real problem for the local and central government.</p>
            <p>As I was told by a spokesman for the
Rakhine Nationalities Development Party, now one of the largest in
parliament and often accused of stirring up anti-Muslim feeling,
even if the government wants Rohingyas to move back to their former
homes in Sittwe, the people won't allow it.</p>
            <p>In a grand old gym in the town I watched young men training
hard.</p>
            <p>Some have aspirations to represent their country when it hosts
the South East Asian Games later this year, another milestone on
Burma's journey away from its former isolation.</p>
            <p>But they were unyielding in their attitude to the Rohingyas.</p>
            <p>"It's not possible to live with them, and we don't want to",
Kyaw Lyaw Win, a Taekwondo instructor told me.</p>
            <p>"They invaded our country. It's not just me saying this. Ask any
Rakhine Buddhist - they will say the same thing."</p>
            <p>There is only one Muslim neighbourhood left in Sittwe, called
Aung Mingala, sealed off by checkpoints. Travelling with the
British minister, we were the first foreigners allowed in for
several weeks.</p>
            <p>I bumped into Aziz, a bright young man who helped me when I was
there last November. Now he is trapped in what has become a
Rohingya ghetto.</p>
            <p>He told me a small delegation was allowed out twice a week, to
visit Muslim districts outside the town.</p>
            <p>Another man who helped me before is Aung Win, one of the most
outspoken and respected Rohingya leaders. I had to negotiate with a
police checkpoint to meet him in the Muslim neighbourhood of Bumay,
where he escaped after being arrested in February for trying to
meet the visiting UN Human Rights Rapporteur.</p>
            <p>But this means he is now separated from his wife, children and
95-year-old father, who are still at his home in Aung Mingala.</p>
            <p>He has repeatedly asked for permission to see them, and
repeatedly been turned down.</p>
            <p>The situation of those Rohingyas who were not driven from their
villages during the violence is little better.</p>
            <p>I travelled two hours north by boat to see the little hamlet of
Ah Nauk Pyin, a Rohingya community entirely ringed by Buddhist
villages.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68407000/jpg/_68407198_rohingyawhiteidcardsahnaukpyin-6248.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="A Rohingya in Ah Nauk Pyin holds up his white ID card"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">In Ah Nauk Pyin, Rohingyas are given ID
cards, but no citizenship</span>
            </div>
            <p>Paths into Ah Nauk Pyin were guarded by Burmese soldiers -
something the Muslims said they were grateful for.</p>
            <p>But they can't leave. Even if they were allowed to, they fear
attacks by their Buddhist neighbours, and in any case all their
boats, along with their livestock, were taken during the
unrest.</p>
            <p>They told me the village dated back 200 years - we are not
illegal Bengali immigrants, they said.</p>
            <p>Yet none of them had citizenship. They pulled out the white ID
cards they are issued.</p>
            <p>"This is very important for us", said Ali Jofar, a young man who
has been designated the village medical expert, although he is not
a doctor. "If we try to travel outside our village with these
cards, we get arrested."</p>
            <p>So no one there can reach hospital either.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68408000/jpg/_68408384_moryanahnaukpyin-6167.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Moryan at her in-laws' home at Ah Nauk Pyin"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Moryan says she has no husband, no money, and no one
to care for her</span>
            </div>
            <p>18-year-old Moryan sat, pale, shaking and weeping, in her
in-laws' straw house. Her house was burned down, and her husband
one of 170 men from the village still imprisoned after the
conflict.</p>
            <p>She has been seriously ill since she gave birth to her son six
months ago. She cannot walk, nor can she breastfeed her baby.</p>
            <p>The remaining men in Ah Nauk Pyin walk to the little blue
mosque, washing in the village pond before going in to pray.</p>
            <p>They've been given simple tractors by an NGO, so, after a year,
they can start farming again.</p>
            <p>But where would they sell their produce, in a country so hostile
it has sealed them off from the outside world?</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-pacific-11669604">Burma's
Transition</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1339433065276"
                     href="/news/world-asia-18395788">Q&amp;A: Communal violence</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1366641358409"
                     href="/news/world-asia-22254493">EU lifts sanctions against
Burma</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1365068511125"
                     href="/news/world-asia-22023830">What's behind violence?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1363053076244"
                     href="/news/world-asia-21738734">Will opposition adapt?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">I want citizenship, and I want my old life
back”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Rohingya camp inmate</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">It's not possible to live with them, and we
don't want to”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Kyaw Lyaw Win</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Taekwondo instructor</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
