<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-china-23222240"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="A Chinese court gives former Railways Minister Liu Zhijun a suspended death sentence for bribery and abuse of power, state media report."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-08T08:45:40"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68599000/jpg/_68599945_68072459.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="China ex-railway minister convicted"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia/China"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-china-23222240"/>
         <title>BBC News - China ex-rail minister given suspended death
sentence</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">8 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">09:45</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">China ex-rail minister given suspended
death sentence</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68603000/jpg/_68603166_68601726.jpg"
                 alt="Liu Zhijun is escorted into court"/>
               <p class="caption">The BBC's Martin Patience: "If there is any
surprise, it is that it has taken this long to get to trial"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">A Chinese court has
given former Railways Minister Liu Zhijun a suspended death
sentence for corruption and abuse of power, state media report.</p>
            <p>Liu was accused of accepting bribes totalling more than 64m yuan
($10m; Ã‚Â£6m) over 25 years.</p>
            <p>Prosecutors said he awarded government rail contracts in return
for bribes.</p>
            <p>Liu is the most high-profile official to be tried and found
guilty of corruption since Xi Jinping became China's leader earlier
this year.</p>
            <p>Mr Xi has called for a crackdown on corruption, vowing to tackle
it from the powerful "tigers" at the top to the "flies" at the
bottom of the Communist Party.</p>
            <p>China's railways ministry, once a powerful department, was
disbanded in March.</p>
            <p>It had been criticised for a series of safety scandals, and
faced allegations of fraud which were uncovered by government
audits.</p>
            <p>Liu was convicted by a court in the capital Beijing on Monday,
state-run Xinhua news agency said.</p>
            <p>He was sentenced to death with a two-year reprieve, deprived of
his political rights for life and jailed for 10 years, Xinhua said,
quoting the court verdict. His personal property will also be
confiscated.</p>
            <p>Despite his sentence, he is not expected to face the death
penalty - suspended death sentences are normally commuted to life
imprisonment in China.</p>
            <p>Liu was suspended from the Communist Party last May, following
allegations that he embezzled funds and received bribes when
handing out contracts for China's high-speed rail project.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/59166000/jpg/_59166878_014076640-1.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="File photo: Beijing train"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">China's high-speed railway network has
expanded rapidly in recent years</span>
            </div>
            <p>During the trial, prosecutors argued that he had helped 11
people win contracts and promotions in return for bribes.</p>
            <p>The indictment reportedly said that Liu's "malpractice" led to
"huge losses of public assets and damage to the interests of the
state and people".</p>
            <p>Liu began his tenure as railways minister in 2003 and led a
multi-billion dollar investment programme expanding the rail
network.</p>
            <p>China's high-speed railway network, said to be the largest in
the world, has been plagued with safety scandals involving a series
of accidents.</p>
            <p>A deadly crash in Wenzhou city in July 2011 killed 40 people and
caused a national outcry.</p>
            <p>At least two government audits - one released in 2010 and
another in 2013 - showed evidence of fraud and irregular accounting
in the handling of government funds.</p>
            <p>In March, China dissolved the railways ministry in a raft of
measures aimed at boosting government efficiency and tackling
corruption, placing its functions under the transport ministry.</p>
            <p>Liu is the most high-profile official to
be tried and found guilty of corruption since Xi Jinping became
China's president in March.</p>
            <p>But a host of other relatively senior officials, both at a
central and provincial level, have also found themselves under
investigation.</p>
            <p>In May, China announced that it was investigating Liu Tienan,
formerly the top official at the body responsible for planning
China's economy, for "serious disciplinary violations".</p>
            <p>Allegations against Mr Liu first surfaced in December, after an
investigative journalist alleged that he made questionable
financial deals, fabricated his academic record and threatened to
kill a former mistress.</p>
            <p>Last month, Lei Zhengfu, a former official at the centre of a
sex tape extortion scandal, was jailed for accepting bribes.</p>
            <p>And earlier this month, state media announced that a high-level
provincial official in Inner Mongolia was also under investigation
for "serious disciplinary violations" - which is often code for
corruption.</p>
            <p>News of the former rail minister's verdict generated extensive
discussion on China's microblogs, with many users scathing about
what they saw as a relatively light sentence.</p>
            <p>"How long do you think it'll be before he's out again?" user
Clockwork Monkey wrote on Sina Weibo, a Twitter-like website in
China.</p>
            <p>"Liu Zhijun wasn't sentenced to death, because if he was, a
whole batch [of officials] would have to die," user 2011 Varyag
wrote. "Chinese law is a freak!"</p>
            <p>Many users on Sina Weibo mocked a Xinhua report that described
Liu's sentence as "a demonstration that everyone is equal before
the law" and that "both the 'tigers' and 'flies' are being
tackled".</p>
            <p>"The 'tigers' can't be killed, and the 'flies' can't be
eliminated," user Hu Shengjie Scarf wrote.</p>
            <p>"If Liu Zhijun was a regular railway employee, rather than the
former railways minister, would his life really have been spared?"
user Concerned about the World's Wellbeing wrote.</p>
            <p>However, there were a few voices in support of Liu's
verdict.</p>
            <p>A user going by the name of The Unsilent Majority wrote: "A
suspended death sentence is still considered a light sentence? What
on earth has Liu Zhijun done that deserves a certain death penalty?
... Our bosses today are not so weak or silly as to let public
opinion pressurise the judicial system."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373273659560"
                  href="/news/world-asia-23223195">China
ex-rail minister sentenced <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370842854935"
                  href="/news/world-asia-china-22837597">China tries ex-railways
minister</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1365574112325"
                  href="/news/world-asia-china-22089011">Former Chinese minister is
charged</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">The 'tigers' can't be killed, and the
'flies' can't be eliminated”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Sina Weibo user</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
