<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23264789"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Luxembourg will hold new elections after Prime Minister Jean-Claude Juncker announced he would resign following a secret service scandal."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-10T22:01:43"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68661000/jpg/_68661962_68661904.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Juncker to resign over spy scandal"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23264789"/>
         <title>BBC News - Luxembourg PM Juncker to resign over spy
scandal</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">10 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">23:01</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Luxembourg PM Juncker to resign over spy
scandal</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68661000/jpg/_68661970_018609121-2.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Luxembourg outgoing Prime Minister Jean-Claude Juncker outside parliament on 10 July 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Jean-Claude Juncker has been prime
minister of Luxembourg since 1995</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Luxembourg will hold
new elections after Prime Minister Jean-Claude Juncker announced he
would resign following a secret service scandal.</p>
            <p>Mr Juncker, Europe's longest-serving head of government, told
parliament he would step down on Thursday.</p>
            <p>The move came as his junior coalition partner called for the
dissolution of parliament and early elections.</p>
            <p>It follows claims he failed to stop illegal security agency
activity such as phone-taps and corruption.</p>
            <p>Mr Juncker has been prime minister since 1995 and was head of
the Eurogroup of eurozone finance ministers between 2005 and
January 2013.</p>
            <p>"I will convene the government tomorrow morning at 10:00 (08:00
GMT) and will go to the Palace to suggest snap elections to the
Grand Duke," he said on Wednesday.</p>
            <p>Luxembourg's parliament had reviewed a
report alleging a series of cases of misconduct by the country's
SREL security agency, which the prime minister oversees.</p>
            <p>It included claims of illegal bugging of politicians, the
purchase of cars for private use and payments in exchange for
access to local officials.</p>
            <p>Mr Juncker has denied any wrongdoing but has faced criticism
that he focused too much on his eurozone duties.</p>
            <p>"The intelligence service was not my top priority," he told
parliament in a two-hour speech.</p>
            <p>"Moreover, I hope Luxembourg will never have a prime minister
who sees SREL as [his or her] priority."</p>
            <p>But there were demands for action from Mr Juncker's coalition
partner, the Socialists (LSAP).</p>
            <p>"We invite the prime minister to take full political
responsibility in this context and ask the government to intervene
with the head of state to clear the path for new elections," LSAP
President Alex Bodry said.</p>
            <p>The report was commissioned after a Luxembourg weekly newspaper
published a secretly-taped conversation from 2008 between Mr
Juncker and the head of SREL at the time, Marco Mille.</p>
            <p>Mr Mille revealed that his staff had secretly recorded a
conversation involving Luxembourg's Grand Duke and that the
sovereign was in regular contact with Britain's MI6.</p>
            <p>It was not immediately clear whether the outgoing prime minister
and head of Luxembourg's centre-right Christian Social Party (CSV)
was planning to fight the next election, which must be held within
three months.</p>
            <p>As head of state, only the Grand Duke can officially dissolve
parliament.</p>
            <p>The current government would then remain until elections take
place, but it would be unable to pass any new laws.</p>
            <p>However, with parliament due to go on its summer break, it would
be unlikely that the government would face any important
decision-making for some months.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1365588970398"
                  href="/news/business-22089639">Luxembourg to relax bank secrecy</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1333012437844"
                  href="/news/world-europe-17548470">Luxembourg country profile</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1354598905604"
                  href="/news/business-20590171">Eurogroup's Juncker to step down</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Jean-Claude Juncker</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Born in 1954 in Redange-sur-Attert, Luxembourg</li>
               <li>Trained as a lawyer</li>
               <li>Elected to parliament in June 1984 for centre-right Christian
Social Party (CSV)</li>
               <li>Seen as resolutely pro-European Union</li>
               <li>Signed Maastricht Treaty in 1992</li>
               <li>Former governor of World Bank and International Monetary
Fund</li>
               <li>Elected prime minister of Luxembourg in 1995</li>
               <li>Head of Eurogroup of eurozone finance ministers, from 2005
until January 2013</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
