<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23246295"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Sex attacks in Cairo's Tahrir Square have become a grim feature of the site synonymous with protests, but could the current political change make a difference to the treatment of women, asks the BBC Claire Read."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-12T00:12:54"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68671000/jpg/_68671012_68671010.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Will Egypt's post-Morsi era be safer for women?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23246295"/>
         <title>BBC News - Will Egypt's post-Morsi era be safer for
women?</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">12 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:12</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Will Egypt's post-Morsi era be safer for
women?</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Claire
Read</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC Arabic,
Cairo</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68633000/jpg/_68633756_68633755.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Male volunteers separate women from men in Tahrir Square on 5 July 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Volunteers have formed lines to help
protect women during the protests</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Sex attacks in
Cairo's Tahrir Square have become a grim feature of the site
synonymous with protests, but could the political changes make a
difference to the treatment of women?</p>
            <p>A roped off section of staircase creates a safe passage for
women as they exit the metro in Cairo's Tahrir Square during
protests.</p>
            <p>But it is not manned by transport security, or the police. It is
male volunteers, who cordon off a pathway so that women can get
into the square without being pressed upon by the men already
outside.</p>
            <p>These volunteers are protecting women against minor incidents of
sexual harassment: touching and groping. But brutal attacks
continue to take place.</p>
            <p>Hassan Nassar, a 22-year-old youth activist, spent much of last
week's protests working to protect women in Tahrir Square. He spent
some time bringing women out of the metro, and other times
patrolling the area.</p>
            <p>Women who have been victims of assault,
and witnesses too, report a similar sequence of events. They say a
group of men isolates the woman, then other men on the outside tell
onlookers they are trying to help someone in distress.</p>
            <p>"We go into the middle of crowds to get the girls out and take
them to a car to get away," Mr Nassar says. "I do it because this
doesn't belong in our society. You can imagine it's your sister or
your mum and you have to help."</p>
            <p>Sexual assaults during protests in Tahrir Square, in particular
since the mass protests against a power-grabbing constitutional
declaration in November 2012, have become so frequent that activist
groups have formed to take action against them.</p>
            <p>One of the groups is Operation Anti-Sexual Harassment and
Assault.</p>
            <p>Their volunteers alone helped more than 150 women following
<a href="http://www.hrw.org/news/2013/07/03/egypt-epidemic-sexual-violence"
               title="Human Rights Watch report">incidents of physical sexual
harassment</a>, including three rapes, between 30 June and 3 July
2013.</p>
            <p>Maryam Kirollos, a member of Operation Anti-Sexual Harassment
and Assault, blamed the Morsi government's inaction for the
continual occurrence of these attacks. She told the BBC that people
who went to Tahrir Square and did nothing to help were also at
fault.</p>
            <p>Hanya Moheeb, a freelance journalist, was one of 19 women
sexually attacked by mobs in Tahrir Square on 25 January 2013, the
second anniversary of the revolution that toppled former President
Hosni Mubarak.</p>
            <p>She believes the issue of violence against women became worse
under the rule of the Muslim Brotherhood, to which the ousted
President Mohammed Morsi belongs, because they view women as "tools
of sex".</p>
            <p>"This became the official stance of institutions," she says.</p>
            <p>But following the military's announcement
to remove President Morsi from office, she is feeling optimistic.
"If things go fine for the opposition, I think it will be a big
step for support of women's rights."</p>
            <p>The Muslim Brotherhood, however, says the issue of violence
against women is not of its doing.</p>
            <p>"This culture does not respect women," says Hamza Zoba, a
spokesperson for the Muslim Brotherhood's Freedom and Justice
Party.</p>
            <p>"Islamic culture respects women. This issue is not related to
the government but to culture. It's up to society. NGOs should be
protecting women."</p>
            <p>And it is not only the group's members who believe that. Some of
their opponents do too.</p>
            <p>"Harassment has nothing to do with the Brotherhood because it's
always been around. It's a problem with society and a lack of
security," Hassan Nassar says.</p>
            <p>But throughout the last 12 months of President Morsi's rule, the
Brotherhood has come under fire for its women's rights policy.</p>
            <p>The group condemned a UN declaration
calling for an end to violence against women, saying the
declaration would lead to the "complete disintegration of
society".</p>
            <p>And women's rights groups reject the now suspended constitution,
drawn up by a committee with a large Brotherhood contingent, saying
it does not guarantee equality. Women are only mentioned in the
context of the family.</p>
            <p>Omneya Talaat, a writer and women's rights activist, said she
was shocked by the constitution that was finalised in December
2012.</p>
            <p>"We would have been doomed," she says. "The Brotherhood wanted
to go back 100 years in women's rights, it was a catastrophe."</p>
            <p>But now any future for the Muslim Brotherhood's rule is looking
increasingly precarious, she is more hopeful.</p>
            <p>"I can't say I'm optimistic or pessimistic, but I'm very sure
that respect for women's rights will happen," she says. "[Without
the Brotherhood] the law will be on women's side."</p>
            <p>But there are other factors at play. Sexual assaults are not a
new phenomenon in Egypt and sexual harassment is commonplace.</p>
            <p>"Almost every woman in Egypt has experienced it, no matter their
age," says Lamia, 24, who lives in a village east of Cairo.</p>
            <p>Lamia believes politics won't change
that.</p>
            <p>"Our leaders are focused on political issues," she says. "To
develop we need education and we have to be good people."</p>
            <p>Egypt is a strongly patriarchal society and many also attribute
the lack of action on violence against women to this.</p>
            <p>Marina Alfred Mishreki, 22, used to work night shifts in a call
centre.</p>
            <p>"I used to come back at 5am and the neighbours asked a lot of
questions," she says. "They might have thought I was a prostitute.
There were sometimes men who accused me of that." She now has to be
home by 10pm to keep her father happy.</p>
            <p>"My parents are less strict with my brother because he's a boy,
even though he's younger than me," she says. "To some extent it's
that my father is concerned for me, but it's more about showing his
authority."</p>
            <p>There are taboos for women talking about sexual assaults. Many
men blame women themselves, due to the clothes they wear or the
fact they are in a certain place at a certain time. Women might
also be accused of lying.</p>
            <p>In the 18-month period under the Supreme Council of the Armed
Forces, between the election of Mohamed Morsi as president and the
ousting of former President Hosni Mubarak, the authorities carried
out so-called virginity tests ostensibly to prevent women lying
about being raped.</p>
            <p>At least six women taking part in a sit-in in Tahrir Square in
March 2011 were subject to these tests. The military confirmed to
researchers from Human Rights Watch that all female detainees
underwent these tests so they could not accuse guards of rape in
prison.</p>
            <p>One of those women, Samira Ibrahim, filed a case against the
military and the court ruled to make virginity tests illegal. But
the army doctor accused of carrying out the "examinations" was
acquitted in a military trial.</p>
            <p>The history of attacks on women at protests goes back to 2005,
when women at an anti-government demonstration were groped and
assaulted. But it is widely acknowledged that celebrations of
public holidays are a time for women to be wary of attacks.</p>
            <p>During Eid festivities each year, women in downtown Cairo are
targeted by groups of young men, and it is also common following
football matches.</p>
            <p>But the opening up of society since the toppling of Mubarak has
allowed the creation of dozens of anti-harassment groups.</p>
            <p>"After the revolution, these groups flourished. Before that we
were just individuals who wanted to do something, but now we're
organised," says Hassan Nassar.</p>
            <p>He believes the only way to stamp it out is a dedicated security
presence at large gatherings along with social awareness
campaigns.</p>
            <p>But until then, he is ready to help in Tahrir Square.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12315833">Egypt in
crisis</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373367962889"
                     href="/news/world-23242777">The struggle to save Egypt's
revolution</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373378586180"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23244940">Is Egypt heading for holy
war?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373156235629"
                     href="/news/magazine-23199377">Shifting sands</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373316808755"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23236012">Coup or no coup?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68665000/jpg/_68665041_hassan-nassar.jpg"
              width="144"
              height="81"
              alt="Hassan Nassar"/>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Harassment has nothing to do with the
Brotherhood because it's always been around”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Hassan Nassar</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Youth activist</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">The Brotherhood wanted to go back 100 years
in women's rights, it was a catastrophe”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Omneya Talaat</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Women's rights activist</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>UN Women report 2013</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68675000/gif/_68675751_report_304.gif"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="UN women report"/>
            </div>
            <p>
               <a href="http://www.unwomen.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Sexual-Harassment-Study-Egypt-Final-EN.pdf">
                  <span class="pdf-icon">PDF download</span> A survey of experiences
of sexual assault and harrassment in Egypt<sub>[738k]</sub>
               </a>
            </p>
            <p>Most computers will open PDF documents automatically, but you
may need Adobe Reader</p>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://get.adobe.com/reader/">Download the reader
here</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68634000/jpg/_68634483_marinaalfredmishreki.jpg"
              width="144"
              height="81"
              alt="Marina Alfred Mishreki"/>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">My parents are less strict with my brother
because he's a boy”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Marina Alfred Mishreki</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
