<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-23065247"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The head of a once powerful royal family in India's Manipur state is on hunger strike, aides say, in protest against moves to evict him from his palace."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T09:39:47"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68404000/jpg/_68404908_new_img_2464.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Manipur king fasts over palace plans"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia/India"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-23065247"/>
         <title>BBC News - Manipur king fasts against palace eviction
move</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">10:39</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Manipur king fasts against palace eviction
move</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Subir
Bhaumik</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Calcutta</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68404000/jpg/_68404859_new_img_2436.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Sana Konung palace in Imphal "/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Manipur's royal family faces eviction
from the Sana Konung palace</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The titular king of India's north-eastern
state of Manipur is on hunger strike, aides say, in protest against
the state government's decision to evict him from his ancestral
palace.</p>
            <p>Aides to Leishemba Sanajaoba say the decision was taken without
his consent.</p>
            <p>They say it is in violation of a 2006 agreement between the once
powerful royal family and the state government.</p>
            <p>The authorities say they want to take over the palace and
surrounding land to develop it as a heritage site.</p>
            <p>King Sanajaoba began his fast on Monday, two days after the
Manipur cabinet decided to take over the Sana Konung palace in the
state capital, Imphal.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68406000/jpg/_68406990_91a635e4-107a-42e3-a67e-93f2a4feab63.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Map"/>
            </div>
            <p>"The king feels betrayed because the government is violating a
2006 memorandum between the two that clearly said no decision would
be taken about the palace without his consent," said his adviser
Puyam Tomcha.</p>
            <p>State officials say they want to renovate the palace and turn it
into a tourist attraction.</p>
            <p>"The government will arrange for alternative accommodation for
King Sanajaoba," a spokesman said.</p>
            <p>"We are taking over the palace to turn it around and preserve
royal artefacts in it so that the future generations will know
about the glorious past of Manipur."</p>
            <p>Another big palace in Imphal - the Kangla palace - is being
turned into a museum.</p>
            <p>The government argues that much of the land around Sana Konung
palace has lost its traditional character because it was sold by
former King Okendra and used for the construction of high-rise
buildings.</p>
            <p>"This is why we have appealed to the residents to let the
government take over the land around the palace so that we can
relive the olden times," the official said.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68404000/jpg/_68404857_new_img_2464.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Titular king of Manipur Leishemba Sanajaoba"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">King Sanajaoba feels let down, aides
say</span>
            </div>
            <p>The Manipur royal family occupied the Kangla palace after the
1891 Anglo-Manipur War and built the Sana Konung for the royals to
live in.</p>
            <p>Later, it became a military headquarters, housing the
paramilitary Assam Rifles after the state joined the Indian
federation.</p>
            <p>However, the royals, who now have little real power or
influence, continue to live in Sana Konung.</p>
            <p>In the neighbouring state of Tripura, the royal family has been
living in a part of the Ujjyanta palace in the state capital,
Agartala, ever since the government acquired most of the building
to house the state legislative assembly.</p>
            <p>Both Tripura and Manipur became parts of India on 15 October
1949.</p>
            <p>But while Tripura's royals have been influential in state
politics and are financially much better off, their counterparts in
Manipur have struggled to make ends meet.</p>
            <p>In recent years they have often been forced to sell land to meet
their expenses.</p>
            <p>While friends, family and attendants have joined King
Sanajaoba's protest over the move, many others in Manipur say the
government should have taken the royal family into its confidence
before announcing the renovation project.</p>
            <p>Manipur has been in the news for another highly publicised
hunger strike. For 13 years, Irom Sharmila has refused to eat in
protest at the special powers which she, like many Manipuris, feel
have been grossly abused by Indian security forces during
counter-insurgency operations in the state. She is force-fed
through her nose.</p>
            <p>Although King Sanajaoba's fast may not continue for that long,
it has created ripples in the state where many feel his forefathers
were forced to join India.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
