<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-china-23123833"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Tens of thousands of people march in Hong Kong to demand China honour promises to hold fully democratic elections in 2017."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T11:56:24"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68475000/jpg/_68475368_68475361.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Hong Kong marchers demand democracy"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia/China"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-china-23123833"/>
         <title>BBC News - Hong Kong marchers demand China uphold democracy
pledge</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">12:56</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Hong Kong marchers demand China uphold
democracy pledge</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68488000/jpg/_68488100_china.jpg"
                 alt="Anti-government protesters in the streets of Hong Kong"/>
               <p class="caption">BBC's Juliana Liu: "Protesters... do not trust
Mr Leung and they believe he is Beijing's man"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Tens of thousands of
people have marched in Hong Kong to demand China honour promises to
hold fully democratic elections in 2017.</p>
            <p>Crowds braved pouring rain for the annual pro-democracy rally,
on the 16th anniversary of the former British colony's handover to
China.</p>
            <p>Marchers called for universal suffrage and criticised the
leadership of the current chief executive, CY Leung.</p>
            <p>Hong Kong's top official is currently chosen by a group of 1,200
electors.</p>
            <p>Earlier Mr Leung said that the Hong Kong government was
committed to introducing full democracy by 2017.</p>
            <p>Speaking at a ceremony on Monday, he
described "implementation of universal suffrage for the chief
executive election in 2017" as a "major task" for the Hong Kong
government.</p>
            <p>"We hope that people holding different views can set aside their
differences and seek consensus as far as possible in an
accommodating, pragmatic and peaceful manner," he added.</p>
            <p>He said consultations on deciding the scope of the elections
would begin "at an appropriate time".</p>
            <p>However, pro-democracy activists say progress on reform has been
slow and fear interference in the nomination process from
Beijing.</p>
            <p>The BBC's Juliana Liu in Hong Kong says they want a commitment
that the nomination process will be fair, and that candidates not
perceived as loyal to the Chinese government will stand a
chance.</p>
            <p>"The right to elect a chief executive is a basic political
right, which we have been denied for many years," said
pro-democracy lawmaker Albert Ho. "We can't afford to wait any
longer."</p>
            <p>Hong Kong currently has a complex voting
system with only some seats in the Legislative Council chosen by
the public. Mr Leung was elected last year by a small group of
electors largely loyal to Beijing, our correspondent reports.</p>
            <p>Organisers said they expected up to 400,000 people to take part
in the march.</p>
            <p>Protesters gathered in Victoria Park on Hong Kong Island, before
starting the march to Central, Hong Kong's main financial
district.</p>
            <p>Two hours after the rally had started, there were still new
protesters entering the park to join the march, Hong Kong media
reported.</p>
            <p>Participants could be heard shouting "CY Leung step down" and
"protect Hong Kong".</p>
            <p>One protester, James Lam, said: "I am here to fight for
democracy and freedom. If Hong Kong people did not come out to
fight for our freedom, we would lose it in the future."</p>
            <p>Some also held up posters calling for the release of Nobel Peace
Laureate Liu Xiaobo, who is in jail in mainland China on subversion
charges.</p>
            <p>In an indication of the level of anti-China sentiment among some
protesters, a number of participants held up Hong Kong's colonial
flag, which was used prior to 1997, when the city was a British
colony.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68473000/jpg/_68473990_018506360.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="The Hong Kong (L) and Chinese flags (R) are released during a flag-raising ceremony at Golden Bauhinia Square in Hong Kong on 1 July 2013 to celebrate the 16th anniversary of the handover"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">An early-morning flag raising ceremony
kicked off the handover commemorations</span>
            </div>
            <p>In addition to demanding universal suffrage, protesters are also
rallying against high property prices and income inequality.</p>
            <p>The march took place on the anniversary of Hong Kong's handover
to China in 1997.</p>
            <p>A pro-government rally and a pop concert were also being held on
1 July, which is a public holiday in Hong Kong. Some retailers also
offered major city-wide discounts on Monday.</p>
            <p>Critics have described these as attempts to draw people away
from the pro-democracy march.</p>
            <p>The demonstration has become an annual event since 2003, when
500,000 protesters turned out in opposition to a proposed national
security bill and the economic downturn.</p>
            <p>The protest contributed to then chief executive Tung Chee-hwa
resigning the following year.</p>
            <p>Hong Kong is governed under the principle of "one country, two
systems", under which China has agreed to give the region a high
degree of autonomy and to preserve its economic and social systems
for 50 years from the date of the British handover.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372649826050"
                  href="/news/business-23122788">Shops try
to woo marchers <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1346461898710"
                  href="/news/world-asia-china-19407425">Hong Kong debates 'national
education'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1329306574142"
                  href="/news/world-asia-pacific-16517764">Hong Kong profile</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/52344000/jpg/_52344242_julianaliuphoto.jpg"
                    alt="image of Juliana Liu"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Juliana Liu</span>
               <span class="byline-title">Hong
Kong correspondent, BBC News</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>People of all ages and from all walks of life took part in the
peaceful annual protest. They scoffed at a promise made by Chief
Executive CY Leung that his position would be popularly elected by
2017.</p>
            <p>They believe the Chinese government will manipulate the
nomination process through its proxies to ensure someone acceptable
to Beijing is elected.</p>
            <p>Mr Leung took office exactly one year ago, after he was chosen
by an elite committee composed of members largely loyal to the
Chinese government. The demonstrators believe he has no authority
to make promises. In fact, the rally leaders singled out Mr Leung
for criticism and ridicule. For hours, they shouted for the chief
executive to step down.</p>
            <p>Dozens of protesters, mostly young men, even flew the old
blue-and-red colonial flag, saying they supported Hong Kong
independence. Their views, while extreme, demonstrate the depth of
anger against Chinese rule.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">I am here to fight for democracy and
freedom”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">James Lam</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Pro-democracy protester</span>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-asia-pacific-16517764" class="quote-link">Hong Kong profile</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/july/1/newsid_2656000/2656973.stm"
                  class="quote-link">1997: Hong Kong handover</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/6223506.stm" class="quote-link">Hong Kong's activists</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
