<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23146744"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="After a purge in Somalia's militant group al-Shabab, which saw veteran Islamist Sheikh Hassan Dahir Aweys surrender, the BBC's Farouk Chothia considers the fighters' future."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T01:32:06"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68513000/jpg/_68513020_aw.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Will Somali Islamist purge strengthen al-Shabab?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Africa"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23146744"/>
         <title>BBC News - Will Somali Islamist purge strengthen
al-Shabab?</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:32</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Will Somali Islamist purge strengthen
al-Shabab?</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Farouk
Chothia</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC Africa
analyst</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68512000/jpg/_68512944_aw.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Sheikh Hassan Dahir Aweys speaks in Mogadishu (24 June 2009)"/>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The surrender of
Somalia's veteran militant Islamist, Sheikh Hassan Dahir Aweys,
signals that his faction has lost the battle for control of the
al-Shabab group to hardliners determined to step up their military
campaign to establish an Islamic state in the East African
country.</p>
            <p>The 78 year old - whose trademark is a goatish beard, coloured
with red henna - was forced to give himself up to government forces
last weekend, fuelling speculation that his life was under threat
from the young Islamists who once revered him as their elder
statesman, but have now rallied behind his bitter rival,
Afghan-trained Ahmed Abdi Godane.</p>
            <p>Somali analyst Hassan Abukar, <a href="http://africanarguments.org/2013/07/02/somalia-the-godane-coup-and-the-unraveling-of-al-shabaab-%e2%80%93-by-hassan-m-abukar/"
               title="blog">writing in the African Arguments blog of the UK-based
Royal African Society</a>, said Mr Aweys' surrender came after Mr
Godane's fighters had staged a "coup" in al-Shabab, killing the
group's co-founder Ibrahim al-Afghani, who also fought in
Afghanistan and was a close ally of late al-Qaeda leader Osama bin
Laden.</p>
            <p>Al-Shabab's former spokesman Mukhtar
Robow has also been forced to flee, reportedly to the southern Bay
and Bakol region where his Rahanweyn clan is based.</p>
            <p>"In a single stroke, Godane, the emir of al-Shabab who goes by
the nom de guerre of 'Abu Zubeir', managed to re-align the radical
group's leadership dynamics and further consolidated his power by
getting rid of his major detractors," Mr Abukar said.</p>
            <p>For Kenya-based Somali analyst Rashid Abdi, Mr Godane's victory
suggests that al-Shabab will intensify its military campaign to
establish an Islamic state in Somalia.</p>
            <p>"It will want to show that it remains a cohesive force, and my
fear is that there will be an escalation of conflict, with more
bombings. It is still a potent military force," he told the
BBC.</p>
            <p>Al-Shabab has carried out a spate of
hit-and-run attacks and bombings, especially in the capital,
Mogadishu, after the African Union force launched an offensive in
2011 to help the government recapture territory.</p>
            <p>In the most recent attack on 19 June, at least 15 people,
including four foreigners, were killed in an assault on a heavily
guarded UN office in Mogadishu.</p>
            <p>"The group has been successful in attacking soft targets, such
as the UN compound, perhaps to distract its fighters from
debilitating fragmentation among its leaders," said Mr Abukar.</p>
            <p>"It is unlikely that this terror group will vanish from the
political scene in Somalia in the near future. Godane and his
followers will continue to exploit the government's inability to
exert its control outside Mogadishu."</p>
            <p>Former BBC Somali Service editor Yusuf Garaad Omar says Mr
Aweys' surrender is a political coup for the government, and its
regional and Western allies.</p>
            <p>"Al-Shabab is highly secretive, and he is intelligence material
for the government. They will expect him to download information
about its leadership structure, training and funding sources. In
that sense, his surrender is a blow to al-Shabab," he told the
BBC.</p>
            <p>A security officer in the regime of
autocratic ruler Siad Barre who was overthrown in 1991, Mr Aweys
had a reputation of being a Somali and Islamic nationalist, in
contrast to Mr Godane's image as a global jihadist who led
al-Shabab into an alliance with al-Qaeda last year.</p>
            <p>"Aweys is the father of the jihadist ideology in Somalia, and
supported suicide bombings. But he was a bit averse to foreign
influence, and more perceptive to public opinion because his goal
was to achieve power," Mr Abdi told the BBC.</p>
            <p>However, Mr Garaad argues that Mr Aweys was forced to join
al-Shabab about three years ago as it had the upper hand over his
Hizbul Islam militia.</p>
            <p>"Aweys relied more on local resources and was conquered by
al-Shabab, which had foreign links in terms of training and
know-how," he says.</p>
            <p>His feud with Mr Godane - who refused to anoint him as
"spiritual leader" - boiled over last year when Mr Aweys used a
Friday religious sermon to accuse al-Shabab's top brass, <a href="http://africanarguments.org/2012/04/04/somalia-sheikh-hassan-dahir-aweys-and-the-politics-of-the-al-shabaab-split-by-abdi-aynte/"
               title="blog">as Somali journalist Abdi Aynte wrote at the time</a>,
of "monopolising jihad, globalising the Somali conflict,
assassinating innocent Somalis and, more damningly, acting in a
manner unbecoming of upright jihadists".</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/67456000/gif/_67456379_som_controlled_areas_070513.gif"
                 width="304"
                 height="460"
                 alt="Map"/>
            </div>
            <p>Mr Aynte said Mr Aweys - who had been designated a terrorist by
the US and UN in 2001 - preferred a "primarily nationalist
ideology" in Somalia.</p>
            <p>"For more than three decades, Aweys defined Somalia's narrative
of political Islam, earning him both friends and foes within the
Islamic movements... He argued that Islam is the only answer for
Somalia and can be the only uniting factor against tribalism and
factionalism," he said.</p>
            <p>As for the younger generation led by Mr Godane, they are simply
"caught up in the cult of martyrdom" fuelled by al-Qaeda, says Mr
Abdi.</p>
            <p>"They don't care about public opinion. They want to establish an
Islamic state through military conquest, and they love martyrdom
more than power," he told the BBC.</p>
            <p>However, it is far from clear that Mr Godane has the backing of
al-Qaeda.</p>
            <p>"Two months ago, Ibrahim al-Afghani wrote an open letter to
Ayman al-Zawahiri, the leader of al-Qaeda, in which he criticised
Godane for targeting foreign jihadists, imprisoning them in secret
detention centres in the areas the terror group controls, and even
killing them," Mr Abukar says.</p>
            <p>The foreign jihadists who joined al-Shabab - including <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-13068133"
               title="BBC article">US citizen Omar Hammami known as "al-Amriki"</a>, who
reportedly survived an assassination attempt by Godane loyalists -
have become increasingly disillusioned with it, he says.</p>
            <p>"Moreover, the influx of foreign
jihadists into Somalia has, for all practical purposes, decreased
and further eroded the place of that country in the annals of
global jihad."</p>
            <p>For Mr Aynte the in-fighting suggests that al-Shabab is on the
path of "self-immolation".</p>
            <p>"In the final analysis, the split within al-Shabab is yet
another chapter in Somalia's extraordinarily complex political
system, where alliances shift constantly. The break-up presents
another dilemma for the international community, as it attempts to
help Somalia resuscitate itself from 20 years of state collapse,"
he added.</p>
            <p>The fate of Mr Aweys is unclear. He could be charged with war
crimes or he could end up joining a peace process, focusing on
winning over youth from al-Shabab.</p>
            <p>But the more likely scenario is that he will negotiate his
retirement, Mr Abdi told the BBC.</p>
            <p>"He is still seen as a father figure by certain Somalis, and the
government may decide to let him fade away. He is old now, and
probably thinking of his retirement, but there are many Somalis who
won't forgive him for what he did to their country."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>Somalia: Failed State</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1368265817426"
                     href="/news/world-africa-22492135">Lighting up Somalia</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1367881481721"
                     href="/news/world-africa-22429487">Struggle for unity</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1367922676211"
                     href="/news/world-africa-22434071">In pictures: Camp life</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1318862196109"
                     href="/news/world-africa-15336689">Q&amp;A: Who are al-Shabab?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Al-Shabab is highly secretive, and Aweys is
intelligence material for the government”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Yusuf Garaad</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Ex-BBC Somali Service editor</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Al-Shabab At A Glance</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68535000/jpg/_68535417_shababafp.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Al-Shabab fighters (file photo)"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>"The Youth" in Arabic</li>
               <li>Formed as a radical offshoot of the Union of Islamic Courts,
which controlled Mogadishu, in 2006</li>
               <li>Previously ran much of southern Somalia</li>
               <li>Lost some popular support by banning Western aid agencies
during 2011 famine</li>
               <li>Estimated to have 7,000 to 9,000 fighters</li>
               <li>Led by Ahmed Abdi Godane, who trained in Afghanistan</li>
               <li>Ibrahim al-Afghani, an explosives expert who also fought in
Afghanistan, was a co-founder</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">They love martyrdom more than
power”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Rashid Abdi</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Somali analyst</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Life and times of Hassan Dahir Aweys</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Served in the regime of ex-ruler Siad Barre</li>
               <li>Formed Somalia's first Islamist militia, Ittahad al-Islamiyyah,
in 1990s</li>
               <li>On a US terror list since 2001</li>
               <li>Briefly captured the capital, Mogadishu, in 2006 under banner
of Union of Islamic Courts</li>
               <li>Merged his Hizbul Islam militia with al-Shabab in 2010</li>
               <li>Surrendered to government forces in July 2013</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
