<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23073984"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Egyptian President Mohammed Morsi says continuing unrest threatens to &#34;paralyse the country&#34;, as he prepares to mark one year in office."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T01:00:19"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68402000/jpg/_68402153_hi018448883.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Morsi warns of risks from unrest"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23073984"/>
         <title>BBC News - Egypt's President Morsi warns unrest risks
paralysis</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:00</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Egypt's President Morsi warns unrest risks
paralysis</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68403000/jpg/_68403992_morsi.jpg"
                 alt="Egyptian President Mohammed Morsi"/>
               <p class="caption">President Mohammed Morsi: ''I did my best''</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Egyptian President
Mohammed Morsi has warned that continuing unrest is "threatening to
paralyse the country".</p>
            <p>In a speech marking his first year in office, Mr Morsi
acknowledged making some "mistakes" and offered opponents a say in
amending the new constitution.</p>
            <p>But the president also threatened those he saw as conspiring
against him and trying to "sabotage" democracy.</p>
            <p>Troops have been deployed in cities across the country ahead of
planned weekend protests demanding his removal.</p>
            <p>Ahead of Mr Morsi's speech, deadly clashes broke out in the
northern city of Mansoura.</p>
            <p>Two people were killed and 170 injured in fighting between
supporters and opponents of the government, a health ministry
spokesman said.</p>
            <p>Mr Morsi, who hails from the Muslim Brotherhood, became Egypt's
first Islamist president on 30 June 2012, after winning an election
considered free and fair. His first year in office has been marred
by constant political unrest and a sinking economy.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68402000/jpg/_68402160_hi018448406.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Anti-government protesters in Cairo (26 June 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Anti-government protesters gathered
across Cairo ahead of the president's national address</span>
            </div>
            <p>In his two-hour televised address on Wednesday evening, Mr Morsi
defended his performance, admitting errors and promising immediate
and radical reforms to address them.</p>
            <p>"I was right in some cases, and wrong in other cases," he said.
"I have discovered after a year in charge that for the revolution
to achieve its goals, it needs radical measures."</p>
            <p>He apologised for the fuel shortages that have caused long lines
at petrol stations and angered many Egyptians, and also for failing
to involve the nation's youth enough.</p>
            <p>But despite Mr Morsi's initial conciliatory tone, the speech
swiftly moved into a condemnation of those he blamed for Egypt's
problems, the BBC's Aleem Maqbool in Cairo reports.</p>
            <p>"I took responsibility for a country mired in corruption and was
faced with a war to make me fail," he said, naming several
officials he believed wanted to "turn the clock back" to the
Mubarak era, including politicians, judges and a journalists.</p>
            <p>"Political polarisation and conflict has
reached a stage that threatens our nascent democratic experience
and threatens to put the whole nation in a state of paralysis and
chaos," he warned. "The enemies of Egypt have not spared effort in
trying to sabotage the democratic experience."</p>
            <p>Mr Morsi called on opposition figures to "enter elections if you
want to change the government" and criticised them for refusing to
take part in a national dialogue.</p>
            <p>The president said he would invite party leaders to meet on
Thursday to choose a chairman for a committee that will prepare
amendments to the constitution, approved in a referendum last year
amid protests by secularists, liberals, women and minorities. He
also said he was forming a committee of leading public figures to
promote national reconciliation.</p>
            <p>"I say to the opposition, the road to change is clear," he
added. "Our hands are extended."</p>
            <p>Anti-government supporters had gathered in the capital's Tahrir
Square and outside the defence ministry ahead of Mr Morsi's
speech.</p>
            <p>The head of the army earlier warned it would not allow Egypt to
slip into "uncontrollable conflict".</p>
            <p>Soldiers have been stationed in areas of the capital, Cairo,
where pro-Morsi demonstrators are expected to gather following
Friday prayers.</p>
            <p>Armoured trucks are lining the streets near Rabaa al-Adawiya
Mosque in the city's east, which has become a gathering point for
Islamist protesters.</p>
            <p>Troops have also been deployed to protect the presidential
palace - the scene of previous clashes - and other public buildings
in Cairo.</p>
            <p>Tensions in Cairo have been rising ahead of the demonstrations
planned for the weekend, with counter-demonstrations by Islamists
in support of Mr Morsi planned for the coming days.</p>
            <p>There have also been acute shortages of fuel in the city,
leading to huge traffic jams as well as long and sometimes
bad-tempered queues at petrol stations, adding to the febrile
atmosphere.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68401000/jpg/_68401803_12.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Egypt's armed forces prepare for large-scale protests near the Presidential Palace 26 June 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Soldiers have been deployed across Cairo
and other cities around the country ahead of the
protests</span>
            </div>
            <p>Some Cairenes have begun stockpiling food in anticipation of
street clashes between the two opposing political camps, with
staples including canned goods, grains and frozen vegetables much
sought after.</p>
            <p>Gen Abdul Fattah al-Sisi said the army was obliged to stop Egypt
plunging into a "dark tunnel", in remarks which were seen as one of
the strongest interventions since the army handed over power to
President Morsi last year.</p>
            <p>Anti-Morsi activists say they have gathered 13 million
signatures on a petition calling for the Islamist leader to step
down. They want early presidential elections to be called to
replace him.</p>
            <p>His supporters say any move to unseat him now would be
undemocratic.</p>
            <p>Many analysts say the instability and a continuing threat of
violence have frightened away foreign investors and tourists.</p>
            <p>There is increasing unemployment, particularly among the young,
and the country's foreign currency reserves are falling.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12315833">Egypt in
crisis</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373156235629"
                     href="/news/magazine-23199377">Shifting sands</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373146727395"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23214054">What now for
Brotherhood?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373020716781"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23197801">Failed experiment</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373067054933"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23205101">Two years in Tahrir
Square</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Mohammed Morsi's year in review</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <strong>June 2012 -</strong> Narrowly wins presidential
election. Orders parliament to meet in defiance of a military
decree dissolving it</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>July 2012 -</strong> Submits to a Supreme Court ruling
that the parliamentary elections were invalid</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>August 2012 -</strong> Dismisses Defence Minister
Hussein Tantawi and Chief of Staff Sami Annan and strips military
of say in legislation and drafting the new constitution</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>November 2012</strong> - Rescinds a decree stripping
the judiciary of the right to challenge his decisions, after
popular protests</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>December 2012 -</strong> Public vote approves draft
constitution boosting the role of Islam and restricting freedom of
speech and assembly</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>March 2013 -</strong> Court halts his plans to bring
parliamentary elections forward to April, citing failure to refer
the electoral law to the Constitutional Court</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>June 2013</strong> - Puts Islamist in charge of 13 of
Egypt's 27 governorships - controversially he appoints a member of
the former armed group Gamaa Islamiya to be governor of Luxor</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-middle-east-23077898">Polarisation marks
Morsi's first year</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
