<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23066168"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Nearly one in five Portuguese may be unemployed but there are still seasonal jobs for the taking on the Algarve, Mira Galanova reports."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T00:25:12"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68392000/jpg/_68392811_bar8.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Portugal's seasonal jobs paradox"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23066168"/>
         <title>BBC News - Portugal's seasonal jobs paradox</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:25</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Portugal's seasonal jobs paradox</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Mira
Galanova</span>
               <span class="byline-title">The
Algarve</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68392000/jpg/_68392818_bar8.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="301"
                 alt="Cafes on the Algarve, Portugal"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The Algarve draws tourists from across
Europe</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Bar terraces are
filling up with red-skinned holidaymakers ready for a drink after a
day on a beach. Daylight is giving way to neon signs. Laughter
mingles with summer hits. Cocktail bars in Portugal's tourist
hotspot, the Algarve, are just warming up for a busy night. But
their managers are struggling to find staff - in a country where
unemployment has just hit a record high of 18%.</p>
            <p>"Almost everybody is looking for people to work," a young
manager of the Piccadilly bar, Joao Carvalho says. On a window, a
notice in Portuguese and English indicates he is looking for
waiters and bartenders.</p>
            <p>In the Algarve, where unemployment is higher than elsewhere in
Portugal, bars, together with restaurants and hotels, provide one
out of every six jobs.</p>
            <p>But long working hours, often from six in the evening to four in
the morning, six days a week, put job-seekers off bar jobs.</p>
            <p>"They want to work in hotels, have two days off, good salaries,"
says a tired-looking Rui Carvalho, the manager of the Second bar.
For weeks, he has been trying to make up for missing staff.</p>
            <p>What about those who fail to get hotel jobs? "Some people prefer
to live on benefits rather than working," says Jorge Sa of the JC
bar.</p>
            <p>After all the austerity measures in crisis-hit Portugal,
unemployment benefits are still quite generous.</p>
            <p>At 65% of the pre-unemployment wage,
jobseekers get between 419 and 1,048 euros (approx
Ã‚Â£355-Ã‚Â£888; $549;
$1,374) a month for the first half-year and 10% less
afterwards.</p>
            <p>People in their 20s and 30s - the age typical of bar staff - can
receive the benefits for some 12 months, if they have worked for
just a couple of years.</p>
            <p>They form a significant part of the Algarve's unemployed. One in
four of the 25- to 34-year olds was without a job in March,
according to Portugal's statistics institute.</p>
            <p>Not all of them are on benefits. "Young people live too long in
their parents' homes and have no need to get a job," says Lourenco
Vicente of the Meet bar.</p>
            <p>Similar claims come from others, not only bar managers. So are
the Portuguese in the Algarve really happier jobless than working?
Experts say it is not that simple.</p>
            <p>"The situation in Portugal is too tough to believe that people
have free choice between work and unemployment," says Portuguese
economist Jose Reis.</p>
            <p>On a hot June morning, the door at one of the Algarve's job
centres is very much open for business. Many of those coming in
"are willing to accept jobs they wouldn't have a few years ago",
says Carlos Baia, the regional director of Portugal's employment
agency.</p>
            <p>However, jobseekers who have a choice are
cautious about the job they take. "They don't want work for just
six months," says Rui Carvalho.</p>
            <p>Tourist season in the Algarve ends in October. Few bars stay
open and keep their staff all year round. Many are left to survive
the winter without a job and with no right to any financial help
from the state.</p>
            <p>Only the jobless who have worked for at least 12 months during
the last two years qualify for unemployment benefits, leaving out
all those who worked their first season.</p>
            <p>The prospect of long months without a job greatly reduces the
appeal of otherwise good salaries that bars offer. This has shrunk
even more after a recent rise in income tax.</p>
            <p>"I'm earning 100 euros less than last year," says Daniel Napier,
a daytime waiter.</p>
            <p>He is planning to get a job in the UK during the winter. "Then
I'll come back and work another season here," he says. "In Portugal
it is like this."</p>
            <p>To encourage employers to keep their employees on over the
winter, the government has offered to pay half of the wages.
"During the low season we give training to the workers so that they
improve their skills and do their job better the next summer," says
Mr Baia of the employment agency.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68392000/jpg/_68392996_beach8.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="301"
                 alt="Holidaymakers on a beach in the Algarve"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Tourism only creates seasonal work</span>
            </div>
            <p>The programme under which this is happening was launched too
late to make any significant impact last year.</p>
            <p>Whether it will interest small bar owners is uncertain. "Bosses
don't want to keep the staff," says Mr Vicente. "Nobody wants to
promise anything, because you don't know what will happen next
year."</p>
            <p>Managers are impatiently waiting for the end of the school year,
when students from other parts of Portugal and abroad come to work
during the summer.</p>
            <p>"Last year I had staff from Denmark, Holland, two years ago from
Norway," says Mr Vicente.</p>
            <p>Bar jobs, shunned by Portuguese, are attracting jobseekers from
neighbouring Spain, where unemployment is at 27%.</p>
            <p>But managers' new darlings are immigrants from eastern Europe.
Ukrainians, Romanians and Moldovans form a big chunk of the
Algarve's foreign community.</p>
            <p>They do not shy away from any kind of employment. "Maybe they
don't like it, but they can do the job," Mr Vicente says. "They
have come here to work, not to have fun."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-18094883">Eurozone
crisis</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1365204978521"
                     href="/news/magazine-22042727">Bank staff fear for jobs and
savings</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1365030846536"
                     href="/news/business-22002153">Is Cyprus's euro membership
viable?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1364205392214"
                     href="/news/business-21922110">Q&amp;A: Cyprus deal</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1363964556893"
                     href="/news/world-21899515">German gamble</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68392000/jpg/_68392990_lourencovicente.jpg"
              width="144"
              height="121"
              alt="Lourenco Vicente"/>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Young people live too long in their parents'
homes and have no need to get a job”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Lourenco Vicente</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Meet bar</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68392000/jpg/_68392994_danielnapier.jpg"
              width="144"
              height="121"
              alt="Daniel Napier"/>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">I'm earning 100 euros less than last
year”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Daniel Napier</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Waiter</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
