<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-22964785"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Brazil is to send a national security force to five major cities to help restore order after massive protests, the justice ministry says."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T13:51:39"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68263000/jpg/_68263279_burningrtr.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Brazil sends force to quell unrest"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Latin America"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-22964785"/>
         <title>BBC News - Brazil sends national force to control protest
trouble</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">14:51</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Brazil sends national force to control
protest trouble</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68252000/jpg/_68252714_riotpoliceafp.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Rio police in Sao Paulo on 18 June 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Riot police tried to quell violent outbreaks at
protests in the city of Sao Paulo on Tuesday</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Brazil's government
says it will deploy a national security force to five major cities
after a wave of protests which has seen almost a quarter of a
million people demand better public services.</p>
            <p>The national force will be sent to Rio de Janeiro, Belo
Horizonte, Salvador, Fortaleza and the capital, Brasilia.</p>
            <p>All of the cities are hosting games in Fifa's Confederations
Cup.</p>
            <p>The announcement comes after riot police and protesters clashed
in fresh protests on Tuesday in Sao Paulo.</p>
            <p>Brazil's ministry of justice said that Recife was the only
Confederations Cup host city not to request the support of the
National Public Security Force (FNSP).</p>
            <p>A source in the ministry said it would be up to local
governments to decide how long the FNSP would stay.</p>
            <p>Shops and banks in Brazil's largest city,
Sao Paulo, were vandalised on Tuesday by groups of masked
activists, who fought other demonstrators trying to stop the
violence.</p>
            <p>The protest was the latest in a wave of demonstrations engulfing
at least a dozen cities.</p>
            <p>Brazilian President Dilma Rousseff said she was proud that so
many people were fighting for a better country.</p>
            <p>Vice-President Michel Temer cut short a visit to Israel and the
Palestinian territories on Wednesday to return to Brazil.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68268000/gif/_68268218_busburnrhs_624afp(2).gif"
                 width="624"
                 height="442"
                 alt="protesters graphic"/>
            </div>
            <p>"This morning, after being in contact with his staff and with
Brazil, the Vice-President decided to cancel his entire programme
and return tonight," his spokesperson told Efe news agency.</p>
            <p>The protests were sparked by anger at a rise in public transport
fare prices in Sao Paulo on 2 June but have since mushroomed into
much broader discontent with high levels of corruption, the poor
state of the health and education services and the high cost of
living.</p>
            <p>They are the largest since 1992, when people took to the streets
to demand the impeachment of then-President Fernando Collor de
Mello.</p>
            <p>Scuffles broke out between police and protesters outside the
office of Sao Paulo Mayor Fernando Haddad on Tuesday after a march
attended by more than 50,000 people had wound its way through the
city centre.</p>
            <p>Police officers sought refuge inside the building as protesters
threw stones, and students tried to break down the door to Mr
Haddad's office.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68252000/jpg/_68252337_68252336.jpg"
                 alt="Students try to break down a door of the City Hall building in Sao Paulo, Brazil on June 18, 2013,"/>
               <p class="caption">Footage shows Sao Paulo police taking shelter in
the mayor's office after being attacked by protesters</p>
            </div>
            <p>Brazilian TV showed images of a small group of people involved
in looting at nearby offices and shops.</p>
            <p>Mr Haddad has indicated he is open to the idea of reversing the
price increase in transport costs if that is possible, says the
BBC's Gary Duffy in Sao Paulo.</p>
            <p>The mayors of Cuiaba, Recife, Joao Pessoa and other cities have
already announced a reduction in bus fares in response to Monday's
protests, which saw more than 200,000 people take to the streets in
more than a dozen cities.</p>
            <p>The dilemma for the country's political leadership is how to
answer so many different concerns among a vast group of people with
momentum and social media on their side, our correspondent
reports.</p>
            <p>Demonstrations also took place in the states of Rio de Janeiro
and Minas Gerais.</p>
            <p>The protests come as Brazil is hosting the Confederations Cup, a
curtain-raiser event for next year's football World Cup.</p>
            <p>Many of the demonstrators have complained of the huge sums spent
on construction for the World Cup and the 2016 Olympics, which will
be hosted by Rio de Janeiro.</p>
            <p>On Wednesday, two Confederations Cup matches are due to take
place in north-eastern Brazil, between Brazil and Mexico in
Fortaleza, and Italy and Japan in Recife.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68257000/gif/_68257523_brazil_protests_464.gif"
                 width="464"
                 height="525"
                 alt="Map"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>Brazil protests</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372142330896"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-23042841">Brazil leader plays hand over
protests</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371898134296"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-23013666">Scarred Brazil hopeful for
2014</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371694132110"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-22980894">Wrestling with unrest</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1371753863911"
                     href="/news/world-europe-22995442">Containment or contagion?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Brazil's National Public Security Force</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Created in 2004</li>
               <li>Made up of members of various Brazilian public safety
forces</li>
               <li>Led by the police commissioner of Brazil's Federal Police</li>
               <li>Deployed in cases of "social unrest and exceptional situations
in Brazilian states when public order is challenged"</li>
            </ul>
            <p>Source: Brazilian Government website</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
