<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-23123799"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Nearly 3,000 people are still missing in India's flood-hit Uttarakhand, its chief minister says, and the number of dead may never be known."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-02T01:08:31"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68472000/jpg/_68472059_68471453.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="India floods: The search for missing victims"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia/India"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-23123799"/>
         <title>BBC News - India floods: The search for missing
victims</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">2 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:08</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">India floods: The search for missing
victims</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68471000/jpg/_68471455_68471453.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="300"
                 alt="Relatives of missing people, affected by the flash floods and landslides, display their photographs outside the Indian Air Force base in Dehradun, in the Himalayan state of Uttarakhand June 26, 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Officials say some 3,000 people are
missing</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">As India begins to
wind down the rescue operations in flood-hit Uttarakhand state, the
focus now shifts to families searching for the missing, reports the
BBC Hindi's Vineet Khare from Rishikesh.</p>
            <p>"Please help me find my brother. He is everything to me," a
teary-eyed Indu Sindhwani implores me.</p>
            <p>We are standing outside a crowded bus station in the holy city
of Rishikesh in the northern Indian state of Uttarakhand, which has
been ravaged by floods and landslides in the last fortnight.</p>
            <p>Deepak Sindhwani, who had gone for a pilgrimage to the temple
town of Kedarnath, is among some 3,000 people who, officials say,
are still missing after the disaster.</p>
            <p>More than 800 people are reported to have been killed so far,
but the exact number of deaths, say officials, may never be
known.</p>
            <p>Mr Sindhwani spoke to his sister last on 16 June and said he was
trapped in Kedarnath after a bridge collapsed. After that, his
phone went dead.</p>
            <p>Since then, Ms Sindhwani has been unsuccessfully running from
pillar to post to get information about her brother's
whereabouts.</p>
            <p>Nilesh Ninav, 39, has been camping in Rishikesh for the past
fortnight to look for his parents, Dattatreya Ganapat and Lata.</p>
            <p>They spoke for the last time on 15 June when his parents rang up
to say that they were caught in a traffic jam.</p>
            <p>"I have been running around trying to speak to officials, but I
am not getting any answers," he said.</p>
            <p>Officials admit they have no easy answers to help the distraught
relatives of the missing, whose faces are plastered on the walls of
railway and bus stations and on billboards and vehicles in
Rishikesh.</p>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68477000/jpg/_68477605_20130701_084950.jpg"
                 width="224"
                 height="299"
                 alt="Mitesh Goradia with pictures of his mother and cousin"/>
               <span style="width:224px;">Mitesh Goradia has been searching for
his mother and cousin</span>
            </div>
            <p>Swollen rivers have swept away entire villages, where there were
many travellers in what is the peak tourist and pilgrimage
season.</p>
            <p>Several bodies, which were found in a highly decomposed state,
have been cremated in the affected areas. Many bodies may have been
washed away or remain buried under debris.</p>
            <p>"The families want to know the real picture. But considering the
scale of the disaster and with so little information available, we
cannot give them a definite answer," says Piyoosh Rautela, a senior
disaster management official.</p>
            <p>A helpline set up for the relatives of the missing has received
more than 25,000 calls so far. Officials say the number of calls
has reduced, possibly as many people have given up on finding their
relatives.</p>
            <p>But people like Mitesh Goradia from Gujarat are not giving up
yet.</p>
            <p>Mr Goradia and his brothers flew to the state capital, Dehradun,
looking for their mother Pushaben, cousin Jayprakash and his wife
Varsha, who had gone on a pilgrimage and not returned.</p>
            <p>They have sought help from the police, the army, politicians and
officials. They have recorded video interviews on their mobile
phones with returning pilgrims who they think may have met their
mother and cousin.</p>
            <p>"We have proof they were alive till 23 June. We do not know what
happened after that - whether they were killed during the rescue or
are still in the villages looking for help," he said.</p>
            <p>"We will wait until the last person is rescued. After the rescue
mission is called off we will go up the hills ourselves and try to
find whether my mother is with the locals."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372650312074"
                  href="/news/world-asia-india-23123795">'Thousands missing' in India
floods</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372325334484"
                  href="/news/world-asia-23078615">In pictures: Uttarakhand after
floods</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372073360755"
                  href="/news/world-asia-india-23026586">Frustrated efforts to rescue
flood victims</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
