<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23088201"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Chilean police arrest 122 people, many of them teenagers, after raiding schools occupied by students in Santiago, amid protests against education reforms."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T21:16:15"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68420000/jpg/_68420667_171559469.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Chile students held in school raids"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Latin America"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23088201"/>
         <title>BBC News - Chilean students arrested in school raids after
protests</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">22:16</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Chilean students arrested in school raids
after protests</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68421000/jpg/_68421192_68421190.jpg"
                 alt="A student is hit by a jet of water sprayed by riot police in Santiago"/>
               <p class="caption">The clashes were among the worst in Santiago
since protests began in 2011</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Chilean police have
arrested 122 people, many of them teenagers, after raiding
secondary schools that had been taken over by their students.</p>
            <p>The schools are due to be used as polling stations on Sunday
when Chileans choose candidates for the presidential election in
November.</p>
            <p>The occupation was part of a two-year campaign calling for
education reforms.</p>
            <p>Police clashed with students in the capital Santiago on
Wednesday night after a national protest on Wednesday.</p>
            <p>The violence was among the worst seen in Chile since the
demonstrations began in 2011, the BBC's Gideon Long reports from
Santiago.</p>
            <p>The country's powerful student movement has staged major
demonstrations over the past two years demanding free and improved
education.</p>
            <p>Sporadic school and university takeovers have been part of the
campaign.</p>
            <p>On Thursday, police launched pre-dawn raids on more than 20
schools across Santiago, where students had barricaded themselves
in with tables and chairs. Local media broadcast footage of
officers bursting into the buildings.</p>
            <p>Interior Minister Andres Chadwick later said security forces had
"restored order", adding that most of the evictions had been
peaceful.</p>
            <p>"As dialogue didn't yield expected results, and given that we
are 72 hours away from the start of the primaries, as the
government we had the obligation to avoid any disturbances," he
said.</p>
            <p>The raids came after a day and night of violence in
Santiago.</p>
            <p>More than 100 people were arrested and 10 police officers were
injured after the city-wide demonstration, which drew tens of
thousands of students, teachers and unionists.</p>
            <p>Violence erupted when masked youths began to throw stones and
Molotov cocktails at security forces who responded with tear gas
and water cannon.</p>
            <p>Although Chile's education system is regarded by many as one of
the best in Latin America, students argue it is deeply unfair.</p>
            <p>They say middle-class students have access to some of the best
schooling in the region, while the poor have to be content with
under-funded state schools. The country has no free
universities.</p>
            <p>The campaign for educational reform is the biggest protest
movement Chile has seen since the return to democracy in 1990.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1368043021543"
                  href="/news/world-latin-america-22459229">Chile students resume
protests</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1369185905971"
                  href="/news/world-latin-america-22565124">Unmasking Chile's hooded
protesters</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1345725499022"
                  href="/news/world-latin-america-19357497">Chile country profile</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
