<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23091302"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The US Senate passes a broad immigration reform bill that includes a path to citizenship for an estimated 11 million undocumented immigrants."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T21:39:15"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68426000/jpg/_68426128_68424915.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="US Senate passes immigration reform"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/US and Canada"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23091302"/>
         <title>BBC News - US Senate passes far-reaching immigration reform
bill</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">22:39</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">US Senate passes far-reaching immigration
reform bill</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68425000/jpg/_68425066_68425060.jpg"
                 alt="Joe Biden presided over the vote"/>
               <p class="caption">Before reading the final tally, Vice-President
Biden warned the chamber not to cheer - or boo - the result</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The US Senate has
passed a broad immigration reform bill that includes a path to
citizenship for an estimated 11 million undocumented
immigrants.</p>
            <p>The 68-32 vote comes after months of debate and a recent deal to
boost border security spending significantly.</p>
            <p>But the legislation faces a tough road in the more conservative
House.</p>
            <p>House Speaker John Boehner has said he will not advance
legislation that lacks support of most of his fellow Republicans,
who remain resistant.</p>
            <p>After the bill's passage on Thursday, President Barack Obama
said the vote brought the US "a critical step closer to fixing our
broken immigration system once and for all".</p>
            <p>"Today, the Senate did its job," Mr Obama said in a statement.
"It's now up to the House to do the same."</p>
            <p>Mr Obama has made immigration a top priority for his second
term, asking Congress to deliver a bill for him to sign by
autumn.</p>
            <p>As the vote was held on Thursday
afternoon, Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid, a Democrat, made the
rare request of asking all 99 of his colleagues to be present and
to vote from their desks.</p>
            <p>"This is not a vote where people should be straggling in," Mr
Reid said.</p>
            <p>After the vote, members of the bipartisan group that negotiated
the original bill, known as the Gang of Eight, thanked the broad
coalition that had backed immigration reform efforts.</p>
            <p>One member of the group, Democratic Senator Dick Durbin, said
the voices of young undocumented immigrants "had made a
difference".</p>
            <p>Republican Senator Lindsey Graham said the bill's border
security measures had "exceeded every expectation I had", and said
the bill had "practically militarised the border".</p>
            <p>Forward movement on the bill comes shortly after two Republican
senators this week brokered a compromise to increase border
security spending by $38bn (Â£24bn). That
amendment to the bill added an additional 20,000 border security
agents, new fencing, electronic surveillance, and unmanned drones
and passed on Wednesday.</p>
            <p>Earlier, the non-partisan Congressional
Budget Office estimated the legislation, without the increased
border funds, would reduce the US budget deficit by $175bn
(Â£114bn) over 10 years and boost economic
growth.</p>
            <p>And analysts say many Republicans acknowledge that support for
immigration reform will be critical for their future election
prospects as Hispanics become an increasingly important voter
bloc.</p>
            <p>On Thursday, Mr Boehner, the Republican House speaker, said the
House would not take up the Senate bill directly.</p>
            <p>"We're going to do our own bill... that reflects the will of our
majority and the will of the American people," he said.</p>
            <p>Mr Boehner's comments cast doubt on the chances legislation will
quickly reach Mr Obama's desk, and could portend failure for
immigration reform entirely, analysts say.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68424000/jpg/_68424910_68049142.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Immigrants await their turn for green card and citizenship interviews at the US Citizenship and Immigration Services (USCIS) office in Queens, New York City 30 May 2013"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Beginning with a provisional status, the
citizenship programme would take 13 years to complete</span>
            </div>
            <p>Separate bills designed by House Republicans include stricter
border and interior security measures, employment checks and most
significantly, no path to citizenship for undocumented
immigrants.</p>
            <p>Some Republicans believe a path to citizenship rewards those who
broke the law by immigrating to the country illegally.</p>
            <p>Senator Chuck Grassley, who voted against the Senate bill, said
he was counting on the House to pass legislation that is "much more
tough".</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370949211631"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-22848900">America's immigration
conundrum</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371988448143"
                  href="/news/business-23006909">US
immigration reforms prove divisive <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1365558673792"
                  href="/news/magazine-22084414">Lives of
Latinos in US beyond stereotypes <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <div class="correspondent-byline">
               <a href="/news/correspondents/jonnydymond/">
                  <span class="byline-picture">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/63719000/jpg/_63719744_dymond_112x81.jpg"
                       alt="image of Jonny Dymond"/>
                  </span>
               </a>
               <span class="byline-heading">Analysis</span>
               <a href="/news/correspondents/jonnydymond/">
                  <span class="byline-name">Jonny
Dymond</span>
               </a>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News,
Washington</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>Today's triumph may yet be the high tidemark of the immigration
reform effort. Some think reform is already dead in the water, but
there is a more nuanced view.</p>
            <p>A Democratic congressman recently told me that John Boehner, the
Republican speaker of House, wants this to happen. It has
significant support from the business community, and evangelical
Christian churches have vigorously backed it. And most Republicans
know that immigration reform is a necessary if not sufficient
condition of Hispanic support in the future. But amongst some
Republican activists there is disquiet about backing a bill that
"rewards" lawbreaking with (eventual) citizenship.</p>
            <p>"It's a good day," the vice-president said as he left the
Senate. Supporters should savour the moment, because this may yet
be as good as it gets.</p>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/correspondents/jonnydymond/">Read more from
Jonny</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>What's in the Senate immigration bill?</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Path to citizenship for immigrants who arrived illegally before
31 December 2011</li>
               <li>Billions in funding for border security, including 20,000 new
Border Patrol agents, 700 miles of fencing, unmanned drones and
electronic surveillance</li>
               <li>Requirement that border security and fencing goals be met
before undocumented immigrants can become permanent residents</li>
               <li>A start-up visa for foreign entrepreneurs; new visa programmes
for low-skilled workers and the agricultural sector</li>
               <li>All employers must use E-Verify, a programme to verify
electronically each employee's legal status within four years</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/z?c113:S.744:">Full Bill
Text</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
