<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-22962873"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Speaking at Berlin's Brandenburg Gate, President Barack Obama calls for reductions to be made in US and Russian nuclear stockpiles."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-19T20:26:22"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68265000/jpg/_68265209_68265206.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Obama calls for nuclear arsenal cuts"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-22962873"/>
         <title>BBC News - Obama in Berlin calls for US-Russia nuclear
weapons cuts</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">19 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">21:26</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Obama in Berlin calls for US-Russia
nuclear weapons cuts</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68266000/jpg/_68266828_68266827.jpg"
                 alt="President Obama"/>
               <p class="caption">President Obama: "I intend to move beyond Cold
War nuclear postures"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">US President Barack
Obama has called for greater efforts to be made to reduce US and
Russian nuclear arsenals.</p>
            <p>Speaking at the Brandenburg Gate during a visit to the German
capital, Berlin, he said he was confident the US could maintain its
security while reducing its nuclear capacity by a third.</p>
            <p>He also called for reductions in the number of tactical warheads
in Europe.</p>
            <p>However Russia's Deputy Prime Minister Dmitry Rogozin said
Moscow "cannot take these assurances seriously".</p>
            <p>The US and Russian signed a joint agreement in 2010 to mutually
reduce their stockpiles of nuclear weapons to a maximum of 1,550
warheads and no more than 700 deployed launchers.</p>
            <p>Mr Obama said the US was "on track" to
cutting its warheads to pre-Cold War levels, but "we have more work
to do".</p>
            <p>He said he had determined that the US could ensure its own and
its allies security and maintain a credible deterrent "while
reducing our deployed strategic nuclear weapons by up to one
third".</p>
            <p>"I intend to seek negotiated cuts with Russia to move beyond
Cold War nuclear postures," he said.</p>
            <p>"We may no longer live in fear of global annihilation but so
long as nuclear weapons exist, we are not truly safe."</p>
            <p>Mr Obama added that the US would also work alongside Nato allies
to seek "bold reductions" in the use of tactical weapons in Europe,
and would also seek to forge a new international framework for the
use of peaceful nuclear power.</p>
            <p>He also said the US rejected the nuclearisation of countries
like North Korea and Iran.</p>
            <p>But Mr Rogozin, a former Russian ambassador to Nato, said Moscow
"cannot take these assurances seriously" while the US is taking
steps to build up its missile defence systems.</p>
            <p>"The offence arms race leads to a defence arms race and vice
versa," he said in comments quoted in Russia's state-owned
Itar-Tass</p>
            <p>Shortly before Mr Obama spoke, Russian President Vladimir Putin
was quoted as saying that Moscow "cannot allow the balance of the
system of strategic deterrence to be disturbed or the effectiveness
of our nuclear force to be decreased".</p>
            <p>A senior foreign policy adviser to Mr Putin said other
nuclear-armed countries would have also have to reduce their
stockpiles for such a plan to work.</p>
            <p>"The situation now is not like in the
1960s and 1970s when only the United States and the Soviet Union
held talks on reducing nuclear arms," Yury Ushakov told a briefing
in Moscow.</p>
            <p>"Now we need to look more broadly... and increase the circle of
participants in possible contacts on this matter."</p>
            <p>Mr Obama's visit to Berlin is his first as American
president.</p>
            <p>His address to students and government officials at the
Brandenburg Gate, which once divided East and West Germany, comes
almost 50 years after President John F Kennedy's celebrated "Ich
bin ein Berliner" speech.</p>
            <p>Mr Obama said that for the US, moving beyond the Cold War
"mindset of perpetual war" also meant redoubling efforts to close
the US prison camp at Guantanamo, tightly controlling the use of
new technology like drones and "balancing the pursuit of security
with the protection of privacy".</p>
            <p>In her morning meetings with Mr Obama, Mrs Merkel had criticised
Prism, the recently exposed US phone and internet surveillance
programmes, saying: "We do see the need for gathering information,
but there is a need for due diligence and proportionality."</p>
            <p>The chancellor grew up in Communist East Germany, where police
surveillance was widespread.</p>
            <p>She acknowledged that the internet "enables enemies of a free
liberal order to use and abuse and bring threats to all of us", but
"an equitable balance must be struck".</p>
            <p>Mr Obama said the monitoring applied within narrow limits to do
with national security. It had detected 50 potential threats and
saved many lives, he emphasised.</p>
            <p>"This is not a situation where we simply go into the internet
and begin searching any way we want," he told a news conference in
Berlin.</p>
            <p>Mr Obama's visit comes after G8 leaders backed calls for holding
Syrian peace talks in Geneva "as soon as possible".</p>
            <p>Speaking earlier, Mr Obama said the US was confident that the
Syrian government had used chemical weapons during the 26-month-old
conflict, but refused to spell out what aid might go the
rebels.</p>
            <p>"I cannot and will not comment on specifics on our programmes
related to the Syrian opposition," he said, stressing his support
for a political transition.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371587595666"
                  href="/news/world-middle-east-22961216">Did G8 summit deliver on
Syria?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371565487332"
                  href="/news/world-europe-22957599">As it happened: G8 summit</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1371569693593"
                  href="/news/world-middle-east-22958520">Cameron outlines Syria plan
<span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/64130000/jpg/_64130802_64130801.jpg"
                    alt="image of Jonathan Marcus"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Jonathan Marcus</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
diplomatic correspondent</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>President Barack Obama is seeking to revive the process of
nuclear disarmament which figured prominently during his first
term, but which has largely disappeared from the agenda since
then.</p>
            <p>Reducing the stockpiles of strategic or long-range nuclear
weapons further is one thing - though without a resolution of
US-Russian differences over missile defence it may be difficult to
make headway.</p>
            <p>Are the Russians willing to play ball - perhaps by accepting
parallel reciprocal cuts thus avoiding some of the lengthy
timetable of a detailed new treaty?</p>
            <p>If not, is Mr Obama ready to push forward with cuts anyway ?</p>
            <p>Bringing shorter-range - so-called tactical nuclear weapons -
into the picture could also be problematic.</p>
            <p>Russia has an overwhelming preponderance of these weapons in
Europe and has often seen them as tied to imbalances in
conventional weaponry.</p>
            <p>Opening up that whole can of worms could be difficult.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>New Start treaty</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68262000/gif/_68262620_nuclear_weapons_304.gif"
                 width="304"
                 height="655"
                 alt="Graph"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>US and Russia allowed 1,550 nuclear warheads each, maximum</li>
               <li>No more than 700 launchers each (including submarines and heavy
bombers)</li>
               <li>Each side able to make on-site inspections to verify how many
warheads a missile is carrying</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-europe-12066494">Q&amp;A: New
Start</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
