<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23176047"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Nearly 600 firefighters are continuing to win their battle against a devastating blaze in central Arizona that killed 19 of their colleagues."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-04T22:31:23"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68559000/jpg/_68559674_hi018544947.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Half of Arizona fire 'under control'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/US and Canada"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23176047"/>
         <title>BBC News - Deadly Arizona fire nearly half-contained, say
officials</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">4 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">23:31</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Deadly Arizona fire nearly half-contained,
say officials</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68559000/jpg/_68559639_hi018553576.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Firefighters at a makeshift memorial in Prescott, Arizona (4 July 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Firefighters paid their respects at a
makeshift memorial in Prescott, the hometown of the squad who died
in the wildfire</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Nearly 600
firefighters are continuing to tame a blaze in central Arizona that
killed 19 of their colleagues.</p>
            <p>The fire, which has so far razed 13 sq miles (33 sq km), was at
least <a href="http://www.inciweb.org/incident/3461/">45%
contained</a>, authorities said..</p>
            <p>Officials added they could not rule out the possibility some
residents who refused to evacuate had also perished in the
blaze.</p>
            <p>The deadliest US wildfire in 80 years, it was ignited by
lightning in forest around the town of Yarnell.</p>
            <p>At least 129 homes have been destroyed by the blaze, which was
fuelled by 40mph winds and dry conditions.</p>
            <p>Officials on Thursday said gusts and
thunderstorms also remained a threat.</p>
            <p>Authorities said they hoped to allow Yarnell residents to return
to their homes this weekend, the AP news agency reports.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile, an initial autopsy report on the firefighters found
the men had died from accidental "fire-related injuries", including
burns and inhalation problems.</p>
            <p>In the town of Prescott, the nearby hometown of the fallen
squad, families of the dead men and their colleagues from across
the state are expected to attend an Independence Day fireworks
display.</p>
            <p>Fire officials say they will take precautions to ensure the
pyrotechnics do not spark another blaze in the tinderbox
conditions.</p>
            <p>Arizona Governor Jan Brewer has ordered state flags to be flown
at half-mast for 19 days to honour each firefighter lost.</p>
            <p>Only one member of the unit survived, a lookout on higher ground
who was about a mile away from the others.</p>
            <p>Hundreds of residents were evacuated, but some refused to leave.
Authorities fear finding more bodies during the clearing-up
operation.</p>
            <p>"This fire moved approximately four miles in 20 minutes,"
Yavapai County Sheriff Chief Deputy John Russell told Reuters news
agency.</p>
            <p>"We had already started evacuating everyone... and we
experienced people who were not going to leave."</p>
            <p>Investigators are trying to determine how the members of the
elite Granite Mountain Hotshots became trapped by the flames.</p>
            <p>The inquiry team, which includes forest managers and safety
experts, is expected to release a preliminary report within
days.</p>
            <p>Sunday's tragedy marked the greatest loss of life from a US
wildland blaze since at least 25 men died in 1933 battling the
Griffith Park fire in Los Angeles.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68481000/gif/_68481711_how_wildfires_spread_464_no_title.gif"
                 width="464"
                 height="262"
                 alt="How wildfires spread graphic"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>A fire needs fuel, oxygen and heat to burn. The fire
threatening the town of Yarnell was started by lightning and spread
rapidly in the very hot, dry conditions, fanned by strong
winds</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li>The fastest-moving and most dangerous part of the fire is known
as the "<strong>head</strong>". Areas ahead of the fire are warmed
as it approaches and flying embers blown by the wind spark
<strong>spot fires</strong>, which cause it to leap further
ahead</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li>Some vegetation or fuel will burn quicker than others and this
creates "<strong>fingers</strong>" of flame which, in turn, create
<strong>pockets</strong> of land surrounded by fire, making it
harder to tackle</li>
            </ul>
            <ul>
               <li>Fires travel faster uphill than downhill, as the heat and smoke
rise, heating areas higher up the hill and wind currents also tend
to blow uphill, pushing the flames further. Burning embers may roll
downhill, starting new fires</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story" rel="published-1372706394216" href="/news/23137482">Life as a 'hotshot' firefighter</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372684908227"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-23128457">How to battle the blaze</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372661063162"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-23123961">In pictures: Arizona
wildfire</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">This fire moved approximately four miles in
20 minutes”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">John Russell</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Sheriff Chief Deputy</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
