<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23232189"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The Syrian opposition figure tasked with forming an interim government to administer rebel-held areas resigns, citing an inability to do so."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-08T16:34:35"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68616000/jpg/_68616078_68612781.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Syria opposition figure Hitto quits"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23232189"/>
         <title>BBC News - Syria opposition government head Ghassan Hitto
resigns</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">8 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">17:34</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Syria opposition government head Ghassan
Hitto resigns</h1>
            <div class="caption">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68612000/jpg/_68612786_68612785.jpg"
                 width="224"
                 height="299"
                 alt="Ghassan Hitto (file)"/>
               <span style="width:224px;">Ghassan Hitto was mistrusted by many within the
National Coalition</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The Syrian
opposition figure tasked with forming an interim government to
administer rebel-held areas has resigned, citing an inability to do
so.</p>
            <p>In a statement, Ghassan Hitto said he would "continue working
for the interests of the revolution".</p>
            <p>His decision follows a leadership overhaul by the National
Coalition.</p>
            <p>Ahmed Jarba was named leader of the main opposition alliance on
Saturday as Saudi-backed candidates defeated those allied with
Qatar in several elections.</p>
            <p>On Monday, Mr Jarba warned that there was a "real humanitarian
disaster" in the central city of Homs and said he was prepared to
offer President Bashar al-Assad a truce during the Islamic holy
month of Ramadan to stop the fighting there.</p>
            <p>As government forces continued an offensive on opposition-held
districts of Homs, state media said the army had killed
"terrorists" in several areas, including Bab Houd in the Old City
and several outlying towns.</p>
            <p>The Syrian Observatory for Human Rights reported that Bab Houd
and al-Safsafa had been hit by heavy artillery and tank fire on
Monday.</p>
            <p>The UK-based activist group said troops had also captured about
a fifth of the besieged northern district of Khalidiya. A
government official had earlier claimed that the entire district
was under army control.</p>
            <p>A car bomb also exploded in the predominantly Alawite and
Christian area of Akrama, killing at least four people, officials
and activists said.</p>
            <p>The violence in Homs and elsewhere in
Syria has left civilians in rebel-held areas in dire need of
humanitarian assistance, opposition and humanitarian activists
say.</p>
            <p>In March, Mr Hitto was tasked by the National Coalition for
Syrian Revolutionary and Opposition Forces with forming an interim
government to administer so-called "liberated" zones, co-ordinating
the provision basic services and supplies.</p>
            <p>However, Mr Hitto was mistrusted by many members of the
opposition alliance, who saw him as too close to the Muslim
Brotherhood and Qatar, and he has been effectively side-lined
since.</p>
            <p>The National Coalition's former president, Moaz al-Khatib,
believed the creation of an interim government was premature and
announced his resignation five days after Mr Hitto's
appointment.</p>
            <p>On Monday, Mr Hitto said he was standing down as prime minister
after being unable to form an administration.</p>
            <p>"I emphasise I will continue working for the interests of the
revolution and towards achieving its objectives," he added.</p>
            <p>Mr Jarba, an influential tribal figure with close links to Saudi
Arabia, meanwhile said he expected advanced weapons supplied by
Saudi Arabia to reach rebel fighters "soon" and that they would
change the military balance in Syria.</p>
            <p>He also said the National Coalition would not attend peace talks
in Geneva planned by the US and Russia unless its military position
improved.</p>
            <p>"If we are going to go to Geneva, we have to be strong on the
ground, unlike the situation now, which is weak," he told the
Reuters news agency.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68616000/jpg/_68616146_4ca4c74d-3cb4-4c17-8dcf-7a99f4e7fee3.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="300"
                 alt="Photograph published by activists purportedly showing buildings damaged by conflict in Homs (3 July 2013)"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The violence in Homs has left civilians
in dire need of humanitarian assistance</span>
            </div>
            <p>In a separate development on Monday, Syria's ruling Baath Party
announced that it had elected a new regional command, replacing its
ageing leadership, including Vice-President Farouq al-Sharaa.</p>
            <p>State TV said the 16 members of the top decision-making body
were chosen during a meeting of the party's central committee.</p>
            <p>"The Baath Party must develop to strengthen a culture of
dialogue... and deepen interaction with citizens to overcome the
negative effect of the crisis," President Assad was quoted as
saying.</p>
            <p>Among the new members of the regional command are parliamentary
speaker Jihad al-Laham and Prime Minister Wael al-Halqi.</p>
            <p>During nearly five decades in power in Syria, the Baath Party
has evolved from an Arab nationalist movement into a vast
organisation that has infiltrated every aspect of public life.</p>
            <p>Although a large number of low-ranking officials have publicly
left the party since the start of the uprising in March 2011, its
main leadership bodies have remained steadfastly loyal to Mr
Assad.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-17258397">Syria
conflict</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373015828941"
                     href="/news/magazine-23190533">Face-to-face with 'heart-eating
cannibal'</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372738930238"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23139784">Harsh justice</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372123956146"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23026868">Fragmented future?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1370996099643"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-22847540">Behind the battle lines</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">If we are going to go to Geneva we have to
be strong on the ground, unlike the situation now, which is
weak”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Ahmed Jarba</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">President, National Coalition for Syrian
Revolutionary and Opposition Forces</span>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-middle-east-23229258" class="quote-link">Profile: Ahmad Jarba</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
