<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23092817"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="There have been deadly clashes in Egypt as both supporters and opponents of President Mohammed Morsi stage mass demonstrations."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T22:59:06"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68445000/jpg/_68445719_68442533.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Violence erupts at Egypt protests"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23092817"/>
         <title>BBC News - Clashes break out at protests in northern
Egypt</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">23:59</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Clashes break out at protests in northern
Egypt</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68448000/jpg/_68448819_68448818.jpg"
                 alt="Opponents of Egyptian President Mohamed Morsi burn the content of a Freedom and Justice Party office in the coastal city of Alexandria on June 28, 2013"/>
               <p class="caption">Footage from Alexandria shows protesters setting
fire to the headquarters of the Muslim Brotherhood</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">There have been
deadly clashes in Egypt as both supporters and opponents of
President Mohammed Morsi staged mass demonstrations across the
country.</p>
            <p>Tension has risen ahead of a protest planned by the opposition
on Sunday, calling on Mr Morsi to step down.</p>
            <p>In Cairo, thousands of Morsi supporters rallied outside the main
mosque.</p>
            <p>At least two people, one said by state TV to be a US journalist,
were killed in the city of Alexandria as protesters stormed a
Muslim Brotherhood office.</p>
            <p>There are conflicting reports about how the young American, who
was reported to be taking photos of clashes, died on Friday.</p>
            <p>Egyptian officials say he was stabbed in the chest, but other
reports say he was hit by gun pellets.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68444000/jpg/_68444568_68444566.jpg"
                 alt="Anti-Mursi protesters carry a banner saying &#34;leave&#34;"/>
               <p class="caption">The BBC's Aleem Maqbool in Cairo says all of
Egypt is tense</p>
            </div>
            <p>The US state department said it was investigating the reports of
his death.</p>
            <p>Washington also warned American nationals against all but
essential travel to Egypt, and said non-emergency diplomatic staff
could leave the country.</p>
            <p>The other fatality on Friday was an Egyptian man who was shot
dead, according to medical sources.</p>
            <p>Dozens more people were injured as
anti-Morsi protesters and Islamists clashed in the northern city,
Egypt's second-largest.</p>
            <p>The office of the Muslim Brotherhood, which backs Mr Morsi, was
set on fire, and the authorities are reported to have called in
riot police and army helicopters to try to quell the violence.</p>
            <p>There are also reports of an explosion in Port Said, also in the
north, with a local security chief saying one person was killed and
five injured.</p>
            <p>At least seven people are now believed to have died in northern
Egypt in violence linked to the political situation in recent
days.</p>
            <p>Security is tight in many areas with troops deployed in Cairo
and elsewhere.</p>
            <p>Egypt's leading Muslim authority, the Al-Azhar institute, has
issued a statement warning against escalating violence.</p>
            <p>"We must be alert lest we slide into a civil war that does not
differentiate between supporters and opponents," it said.</p>
            <p>Mr Morsi's supporters are holding "open-ended" rallies before
what the opposition bills as big protests on Sunday calling for him
to resign. Sunday is the first anniversary of the president's
inauguration.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68444000/jpg/_68444898_68444897.jpg"
                 alt="Amr Moussa"/>
               <p class="caption">Leading opposition figure Amr Moussa: "He
(Morsi) should take the voice of the people seriously"</p>
            </div>
            <p>Thousands of supporters of the Muslim Brotherhood and its
Islamist allies massed outside Nasr City's Rabaa al-Adawiya mosque
on Friday.</p>
            <p>They stressed what they see as Mr Morsi's "legitimacy",
rejecting the opposition's demand for him to resign.</p>
            <p>Morsi opponents gathered in Tahrir Square and anti-Morsi
protesters began a sit-in outside the building.</p>
            <p>The main opposition coalition on Thursday rejected President
Morsi's offer of dialogue.</p>
            <p>In a statement, the National Salvation Front said it "remained
determined to call for an early presidential election".</p>
            <p>"We are confident the Egyptian people will come out in their
millions to hold peaceful demonstrations on all of Egypt's squares
and streets to realise their aspirations and to put the 25 January
revolution back on track," it added.</p>
            <p>The opposition was referring to the
popular uprising in January 2011 which ousted President Hosni
Mubarak.</p>
            <p>Mr Morsi said divisions threatened to "paralyse" Egypt, in a
speech on Wednesday to mark a year in office.</p>
            <p>Mr Morsi, who hails from the Muslim Brotherhood, became Egypt's
first Islamist president on 30 June 2012, after winning an election
considered free and fair.</p>
            <p>His first year as president has been marred by constant
political unrest and a sinking economy.</p>
            <p>In his speech, President Morsi defended his performance,
admitting errors and promising immediate and radical reforms to
address them.</p>
            <p>"I was right in some cases, and wrong in other cases," he said.
"I have discovered after a year in charge that for the revolution
to achieve its goals, it needs radical measures."</p>
            <p>He apologised for the fuel shortages that have caused long lines
at petrol stations and angered many Egyptians, and also for failing
to involve the nation's youth enough.</p>
            <p>But despite Mr Morsi's initial conciliatory tone, the speech
swiftly moved into a condemnation of those he blamed for Egypt's
problems, the BBC's Aleem Maqbool in Cairo reports.</p>
            <p>"I took responsibility for a country mired in corruption and was
faced with a war to make me fail," he said, naming several
officials he believed wanted to "turn the clock back" to the
Mubarak era, including politicians, judges and journalists.</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68431000/jpg/_68431457_cairo_protests624.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="400"
                 alt="Map"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12315833">Egypt in
crisis</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373156235629"
                     href="/news/magazine-23199377">Shifting sands</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373146727395"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23214054">What now for
Brotherhood?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373020716781"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23197801">Failed experiment</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373067054933"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23205101">Two years in Tahrir
Square</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68439000/jpg/_68439183_mahasaid39housewife.jpg"
              width="144"
              height="81"
              alt="Maha Said, 39, housewife"/>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">This past year has been a year of horror and
anxiety... Morsi has accomplished nothing, and things are only
going from bad to worse”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Maha Said</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Housewife</span>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-middle-east-23096848" class="quote-link">Egypt voices: Morsi one year on</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Mohammed Morsi's first year</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <strong>June 2012 -</strong> Narrowly wins presidential
election. Orders parliament to meet in defiance of a military
decree dissolving it</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>July 2012 -</strong> Submits to a Supreme Court ruling
that the parliamentary elections were invalid</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>August 2012 -</strong> Dismisses Defence Minister
Hussein Tantawi and Chief of Staff Sami Annan and strips military
of say in legislation and drafting the new constitution</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>November 2012</strong> - Rescinds a decree stripping
the judiciary of the right to challenge his decisions, after
popular protests</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>December 2012 -</strong> Public vote approves draft
constitution boosting the role of Islam and restricting freedom of
speech and assembly</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>March 2013 -</strong> Court halts his plans to bring
parliamentary elections forward to April, citing failure to refer
the electoral law to the Constitutional Court</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>June 2013</strong> - Puts Islamists in charge of 13 of
Egypt's 27 governorships - controversially he appoints a member of
the former armed group Gamaa Islamiya to be governor of Luxor</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-middle-east-23077898">Polarisation marks
Morsi's first year</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-middle-east-23096848">Egyptian views of
Morsi one year on</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-middle-east-23105004">Families torn by
political divide</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
