<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23222172"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Brazil request clarifications from the US government over allegations that its intelligence agencies spied on Brazilian citizens and companies."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-08T01:37:14"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68599000/jpg/_68599716_68599632.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Brazil challenges US on 'espionage'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Latin America"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23222172"/>
         <title>BBC News - Brazil asks US to explain internet
surveillance</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">8 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:37</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Brazil asks US to explain internet
surveillance</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68599000/jpg/_68599772_68599707.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Brazilian on the phone in Rio favela"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Millions of Brazilians could have had their phone
calls and emails monitored</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Brazil has requested
clarifications from the US government about reports that its
intelligence agencies monitored millions of emails and phone calls
from Brazilian citizens.</p>
            <p>The allegations were published on Saturday by O Globo
newspaper.</p>
            <p>They were based on documents disclosed by fugitive American
intelligence analyst Edward Snowden.</p>
            <p>Brazil received the reports "with deep concern," Foreign
Minister Antonio Patriota in a statement.</p>
            <p>President Dilma Rousseff called several cabinet ministers to a
meeting on Sunday to discuss the issue, following the publication
of the newspaper articles on Saturday.</p>
            <p>Mr Patriota was taking part in an international literature
meeting in the city of Paraty, near Rio de Janeiro, but called the
media in the afternoon to read a statement.</p>
            <p>"The Brazilian government has asked for clarifications through
the US embassy in Brasilia and the Brazilian embassy in
Washington," he said.</p>
            <p>Mr Patriota said it was going to request that the United Nations
work on regulation "to impede abuses and protect the privacy" of
internet users.</p>
            <p>Communications Minister Paulo Bernardo said the Federal Police
and the Brazilian Telecommunications Agency (Anatel) would carry
out an investigation to find out whether internet providers based
in Brazil had been involved in the alleged surveillance scheme.</p>
            <p>"If that has happened, these companies broke Brazilian law and
acted against our Constitution, which safeguards the right to
privacy," said Mr Bernardo.</p>
            <p>"But the surveillance was probably done through undersea cables
and satellites. Most of the cables for international communications
go through the US," he added.</p>
            <p>According to O Globo newspaper, Brazil had one of the highest
numbers of electronic messages and phone calls monitored by the US,
even though the country has good relations with the US.</p>
            <p>"It is not known the number of people and companies spied on in
Brazil, but there is evidence that there was a large volume of data
collected on a regular basis," says the report.</p>
            <p>"Brazil appears on the charts of the American agency (National
Security Agency, or NSA) as a prime target for the espionage of
phone calls and other data, alongside nations like China, Russia,
Iran and Pakistan," says O Globo.</p>
            <p>The allegations come at a difficult time for relations between
the United States and Latin American countries.</p>
            <p>On Tuesday, a Bolivian government plane was denied access to the
airspace of France, Italy, Spain and Portugal.</p>
            <p>President Evo Morales, who was returning from an official visit
to Moscow, was forced to wait for 13 hours in Vienna before being
allowed to return to La Paz.</p>
            <p>France apologised for the incident, blaming it on "conflicting
information" that Edward Snowden was on board.</p>
            <p>The American whistleblower is believed to be holed up at an
airport in Moscow since fleeing from Hong Kong.</p>
            <p>Mr Morales and other Latin American leaders reacted angrily,
denouncing a "neo-colonialist" approach from the US and some of its
European allies.</p>
            <p>Bolivia, Venezuela and Nicaragua have since stated that they are
willing to give Mr Snowden asylum.</p>
            <p>A statement by Brazil's President Rousseff said: "The
embarrassment to President Morales hits not only Bolivia, but all
of Latin America."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372888922080"
                  href="/news/world-latin-america-23174874">France apology in Bolivia jet
row</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1373060619904"
                  href="/news/world-europe-23201774">Snowden receives asylum
offers</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372702760008"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-23133216">US-EU bugging claims: Is spying
OK?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
