<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23201774"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The presidents of Nicaragua, Venezuela and Bolivia indicate their countries could offer political asylum to US fugitive Edward Snowden."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-06T15:38:48"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68581000/jpg/_68581094_snowdenreuters.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Snowden receives asylum offers"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23201774"/>
         <title>BBC News - Bolivia, Venezuela and Nicaragua offer Snowden
asylum</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">6 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">16:38</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Bolivia, Venezuela and Nicaragua offer
Snowden asylum</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68581000/jpg/_68581975_68581973.jpg"
                 alt="Edward Snowdon"/>
               <p class="caption">The presidents of Venezuela and Nicaragua
explain their offers</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The presidents of
Nicaragua, Venezuela and Bolivia have indicated their countries
could offer political asylum to US fugitive Edward Snowden.</p>
            <p>Venezuela's Nicolas Maduro said it would give asylum to the
intelligence leaker, who is believed to be holed up in a transit
area of Moscow airport.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile Nicaraguan President Daniel Ortega said his country
would do so "if circumstances permit".</p>
            <p>Bolivia's Evo Morales said Mr Snowden could get asylum there if
he sought it.</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden has sent requests for political asylum to at least 21
countries, most of which have turned down his request. Earlier,
Wikileaks said he had applied to six additional countries on
Friday.</p>
            <p>The whistleblowing website said it would not name the countries
"due to attempted US interference".</p>
            <p>But even if a country accepted the American's application,
getting there could prove difficult, the BBC's Steven Rosenberg, in
Moscow, reports.</p>
            <p>European airspace could be closed to any aircraft suspected of
carrying the fugitive, our correspondent says.</p>
            <p>Earlier this week, several European countries reportedly refused
to allow the Bolivian president's jet to cross their airspace on
its way back from Moscow - apparently because of suspicions that
Edward Snowden was on board.</p>
            <p>Mr Morales described Mr Snowden's actions as "a fair way of
protesting" and described him as "persecuted by his fellow
countrymen".</p>
            <p>"We are not scared [of reprisals]," he added.</p>
            <p>President Maduro made his announcement in a speech on
Venezuela's Independence Day.</p>
            <p>"As head of state and government of the Bolivarian Republic of
Venezuela I have decided to offer humanitarian asylum to the young
US citizen Edward Snowden so he can come to the fatherland of
Bolivar and Chavez to live away from the imperial North American
persecution," President Maduro said.</p>
            <p>The US wants to prosecute Mr Snowden over the leaking of
thousands of classified intelligence documents.</p>
            <p>Earlier Mr Ortega said Nicaragua had received an application at
its embassy in Moscow.</p>
            <p>"We are open, respectful of the right to asylum, and it is clear
that if circumstances permit it, we would receive Snowden with
pleasure and give him asylum here in Nicaragua," AFP news agency
quoted the Nicaraguan president as saying.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68581000/jpg/_68581102_afportega.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Daniel Ortega, file photo 14 June 2013"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">President Ortega said the asylum application was
received in Moscow</span>
            </div>
            <p>Daniel Ortega was a fierce opponent of the US during his first
period as Nicaragua's president in the 1980s, after the left-wing
Sandinista movement came to power.</p>
            <p>Bolivia, which had also suggested it could offer Mr Snowden
asylum, saw its presidential plane barred from European airspace on
Tuesday.</p>
            <p>There was speculation the 30-year-old was on the plane carrying
President Evo Morales back from Russia to La Paz earlier this
week.</p>
            <p>"Edward Snowden has applied to another six countries for
asylum," tweeted Wikileaks, which has been helping the former CIA
contractor.</p>
            <p>"They will not be named at this time due to attempted US
interference."</p>
            <p>The US has been blamed for being behind the decision by France,
Portugal, Italy and Spain to close its airspace to Bolivia's
president, whose plane was grounded in Austria for 13 hours as a
result.</p>
            <p>Earlier on Friday, Spain's Foreign Minister Jose Manuel
Garcia-Margallo admitted he and other European officials had been
told that Mr Snowden was on board - but refused to say who gave out
the information.</p>
            <p>He denied Spain had closed its airspace to the presidential
plane, explaining that the delay in Austria meant the flight permit
had expired and needed to be renewed.</p>
            <p>His comment is the first official recognition by the European
states that the incident with Mr Morales' plane was connected with
the Snowden affair.</p>
            <p>It has been widely condemned by President Morales and several
other South American nations, who were critical of the US.</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden arrived in the Moscow airport from Hong Kong last
month.</p>
            <p>He revealed himself to be responsible for the leaking of
classified US intelligence documents that revealed a vast
surveillance programme of phone and web data.</p>
            <p>The documents have also led to allegations that both the UK and
French intelligence agencies run similarly vast data collection
operations, and the US has been eavesdropping on official EU
communications.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>US spy leaks</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372684702774"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23123964">Revelations of US spy
scandal</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372869435767"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23165992">Where will Snowden end
up?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372702760008"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23133216">Is it OK to spy on your
allies?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372348565338"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-23077279">Wikileaks back in
spotlight</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
