<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23078655"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="US President Barack Obama calls on African governments to give gay people equal rights by decriminalising homosexual acts, as he starts a three-nation African tour."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T17:37:41"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68417000/jpg/_68417059_68410459.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Obama in Africa gay rights appeal"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Africa"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23078655"/>
         <title>BBC News - Obama urges gay rights in Africa during trip to
Senegal</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">18:37</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Obama urges gay rights in Africa during
trip to Senegal</h1>
            <div class="has-icon-comment dna-comment-count-simple"> </div>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68408000/jpg/_68408992_68408991.jpg"
                 alt="The Obamas with President Sall and wife"/>
               <p class="caption">The BBC's Thomas Fessy says the visit recognises
Senegal's move towards a stronger democracy</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">US President Barack
Obama has called on African governments to give gay people equal
rights by decriminalising homosexual acts.</p>
            <p>Mr Obama made the comments in Senegal after meeting President
Macky Sall on the first leg of his African tour.</p>
            <p>Mr Sall said Senegal was a "very tolerant" country but it was
"not ready to decriminalise homosexuality".</p>
            <p>Homosexual acts are still a crime in 38 African countries, where
most people hold conservative religious views.</p>
            <p>In 2011, the US and UK hinted that they could withdraw aid from
countries which did not respect gay rights.</p>
            <p>Mr Obama said at a news conference that the issue did not come
up in his discussions with Mr Sall.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, he believed that while different customs and
religions should be respected, the law should treat everybody
equally, he said.</p>
            <p>Mr Obama welcomed the US Supreme Court's
decision on Wednesday to strike down a law that denied the
recognition of same-sex marriages.</p>
            <p>The ruling was a "victory for American democracy and a proud day
for equal rights", he said</p>
            <p>Mr Sall said Senegal was still not ready to change its laws, but
that "does not mean we are homophobic''.</p>
            <p>This is Mr Obama's third visit to Africa since he became
president in 2008.</p>
            <p>He is also due to travel to South Africa and Tanzania.</p>
            <p>Africa had made "amazing" strides in achieving democracy, Mr
Obama said.</p>
            <p>Senegal, a mainly Muslim country which has never experienced a
coup, was one of America's "strongest partners" on the continent,
he added.</p>
            <p>"It's moving in the right direction with reforms to deepen
democratic institutions, and as more Africans across this continent
stand up and demand governments that are accountable and serve the
people, I believe Senegal can be a great example," Mr Obama
said.</p>
            <p>Mr Obama, along with his wife Michelle
and children, was due to travel by ferry to Senegal's Goree Island,
a memorial to Africans who were caught up in the Atlantic slave
trade.</p>
            <p>"A visit like this by an American president, any American
president, is powerful," said White House spokesman Jay Carney
ahead of the trip.</p>
            <p>"I think that will be the case when President Obama visits and
I'm sure particularly so, given that he is African American."</p>
            <p>On Sunday, Mr Obama is expected to visit Robben Island, where
South Africa's first black president Nelson Mandela was jailed for
18 of the 27 years he spent in prison, on the second leg of his
African tour.</p>
            <p>However, it is unclear whether the visit will take place because
of Mr Mandela's deteriorating health, correspondents say.</p>
            <p>Mr Obama is due to end his African tour with a visit to
Tanzania, where he will pay his respects at a memorial outside the
US embassy in the main city, Dar es Salaam, in honour of 11 people
killed in a bombing by al-Qaeda in 1998.</p>
            <p>He has excluded from his itinerary Kenya, where his father was
born, and Nigeria, Africa's biggest oil producer which has been hit
by an Islamist insurgency.</p>
            <p>US officials reportedly said the indictment of Kenyan President
Uhuru Kenyatta at the International Criminal Court on charges of
fuelling violence after the 2007 election, which he denies, made it
politically impossible for Mr Obama to visit the country.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68418000/gif/_68418319_gay_africa464x495.gif"
                 width="464"
                 height="495"
                 alt="map showing gay rights in africa"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372268790992"
                  href="/news/world-africa-23070006">Obama in Africa: Too little too
late?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372118514554"
                  href="/news/world-africa-23033423">'Homophobia' in Africa
condemned</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370939859841"
                  href="/news/world-radio-and-tv-22853746">Obama 'is our son' <span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/64630000/jpg/_64630262_elvis3intake_016687083_thomasfessy-bamakonov2012.jpg"
                    alt="image of Thomas Fessy"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Thomas Fessy</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
News, Dakar</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>While President Barack Obama's comments on gay rights may grab
the headlines in the Western media, his Senegalese counterpart's
response - "Senegal is not yet ready to decriminalise
homosexuality" - may just be what many Senegalese wanted to
hear.</p>
            <p>As laws legalising gay marriage were being contested in the US
and France recently, rumours spread in the West African country
that President Macky Sall wanted to do the same. They sparked
heated discussion in the local media which forced Mr Sall's
administration to clarify its position that it would not legalise
same-sex unions.</p>
            <p>Many Senegalese are of the opinion that if Mr Obama came to
"change" their mentality, he has had a wasted journey. Although
Senegal is not one of Africa's aggressively homophobic nations,
there have been cases of violent attacks against gay men and
lesbians.</p>
            <p>The fact that Mr Obama chose to visit Senegal will be what most
Senegalese are likely to focus on - and the hope that this will
attract more development money and investors.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Goree: Slave island</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68410000/jpg/_68410457_68409831.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="The House of Slave on Goree Island"/>
            </div>
            <ul>
               <li>16-19th Century: Slaves shipped from Goree</li>
               <li>1776: Slave House built</li>
               <li>1978: Designated World Heritage Site</li>
               <li>Notable visitors: Pope John Paul II, Nelson Mandela, Bill
Clinton, George W Bush</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-africa-23078662">Goree: Senegal's slave
island</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
