<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-22943878"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Spanish police are advancing crime detection with their savvy use of Twitter, the BBC's Aida Prados reports."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-26T23:39:19"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68366000/jpg/_68366821_68366819.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Cracking crime with Twitter in Spain"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-22943878"/>
         <title>BBC News - Cracking crime with Twitter in Spain</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:39</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Cracking crime with Twitter in Spain</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Aida
Prados</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC Mundo</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68363000/jpg/_68363492_police.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="301"
                 alt="Spanish police celebrate their 500,000th follower on Twitter"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Spanish police celebrate their 500,000th
follower on Twitter with a cake</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">With Twitter
reaching ever further into all aspects of life, police forces are
investigating how they can use it to help fight crime. Spain is at
the forefront of this revolution.</p>
            <p>Officials are now frequently posting attention-grabbing messages
to alert citizens to serious crimes and also to track down
suspects.</p>
            <p>The information gathered helped them carry out at least 300
arrests on drug charges last year.</p>
            <p>The Spanish-language account <a href="https://twitter.com/policia">@policia</a> has the second-biggest
following for a police force in the world, after the <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=FBI&amp;src=typd">FBI</a>.</p>
            <p>It does not just help gather clues to crimes - it also helps
spread information.</p>
            <p>"Drugs = poo, even a child can understand that," goes one tweet.
"Get hooked and you are on a downer for life. Try to deal and
you'll regret it forever."</p>
            <p>So popular have the messages proved, that they can easily gather
5,000 retweets.</p>
            <p>Officials cannot believe their own popularity.</p>
            <p>"It has been incredible for us but credit goes to the people who
generously give us their trust and support," says Carlos Fernandez
Guerra, from the digital strategy team of the Spanish National
Police.</p>
            <p>With the use of the information gathered on Twitter, in the past
year the Spanish police have been able to warn people against new
viruses and online fraud, continue the hunt for some of the
most-wanted fugitives and arrest people accused of spreading child
pornography on the internet.</p>
            <p>Input from Spanish users of Twitter is proving a vital part of
the strategy.</p>
            <p>In the battle against drug-trafficking, Spanish police have made
what they call "tweet raids" - attempts to use Twitter to solicit
potential leads from tweeters.</p>
            <p>The Spanish police first launch an online campaign to spread the
word on Twitter, and provide internet users with a specific email
account that guarantees confidentiality to facilitate online
collaboration.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68363000/jpg/_68363954_policewomen.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="231"
                 alt="Spanish police monitor their twitter account "/>
               <span style="width:304px;">The force plans "tweet patrols"</span>
            </div>
            <p>According to official figures, tweet raids led to the arrest of
300 individuals in Spain last year.</p>
            <p>"We received about 11,500 emails containing valuable information
thanks to one of our tweet raids," says Mr Fernandez Guerra.</p>
            <p>"Such information was filtered by the drugs department and was
later conveyed to the respective local police forces, which
incorporated the data into their own investigations."</p>
            <p>One of the biggest coups for the Spanish police was a tweet raid
last year that led to the seizure of 277kg (610lb) of cocaine,
hidden in cowhide which arrived in Spain from the Dominican
Republic.</p>
            <p>The Spanish police received the tip-off by email and this
allowed them to identify and capture a drug-trafficking ring
distributing cocaine in Spain.</p>
            <p>According to Spanish police, they are just trying to use the
online tools available to become what they call "police 3.0", and a
model for other police forces worldwide.</p>
            <p>This month, @policia reached half a million followers on
Twitter.</p>
            <p>Spanish Prime Minister Mariano Rajoy, Twitter and the FBI were
among those who sent messages to congratulate the institution.</p>
            <p>"@policia congrats on your half million followers," the FBI
wrote. "The greatest weapon against crime is the co-operation of
the citizens we serve."</p>
            <p>One notable recent success was an arrest in a high-profile rape
case, relating to an attack on a 15-year-old girl at a party in a
park in Seville.</p>
            <p>Several people who were in the vicinity took photographs of the
young woman and her aggressor which later circulated across the
social networks.</p>
            <p>After locating the author of an image posted on Twitter, who had
apparently witnessed the episode, police made contact with him and
obtained enough information to be able to arrest the main
suspect.</p>
            <p>Spain's success with Twitter is already resonating in other
countries.</p>
            <p>In police forces in Colombia, Ecuador and Chile, there is also a
growing use of information from social networks to track down
criminal activities.</p>
            <p>"We are constantly sharing information with these three
countries in order to improve our investigations with the use of
social networks," says Mr Fernandez Guerra.</p>
            <p>The next step for Spanish police will be the creation of "tweet
patrols".</p>
            <p>The aim is to live-tweet from a police patrol during a night
shift to allow users to experience live policing.</p>
            <p>As Mr Fernandez Guerra says, it is all crucial to keep the
people on board.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1336064361084"
                  href="/news/world-europe-17941641">Spain country profile</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
