<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23067765"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Clashes between the Lebanese army and forces loyal to radical Sunni preacher Sheikh Ahmad al-Assir demonstrate how the war in Syria could re-ignite sectarian conflict in Lebanon, writes the BBC's Kevin Connolly."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T07:08:34"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68405000/jpg/_68405505_68405503.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Syria war exerts growing strain on Lebanon tinderbox"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23067765"/>
         <title>BBC News - Syria war exerts growing strain on Lebanon
tinderbox</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">08:08</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Syria war exerts growing strain on Lebanon
tinderbox</h1>
            <span class="byline byline-photo">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68415000/jpg/_68415025_018289700.jpg"
                 alt="Kevin Connolly"/>
               <span class="byline-name">By Kevin
Connolly</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News,
Tripoli</span>
            </span>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68400000/jpg/_68400712_68400710.jpg"
                 alt=" Ahmad al-Assir"/>
               <p class="caption">Men like Sunni preacher Ahmad al-Assir and his
rival Shia counterparts hold the key to what happens next in
Lebanon</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">In the northern
Lebanese port city of Tripoli, armoured personnel carriers from the
national army thunder through the chaotic traffic that chokes the
city centre.</p>
            <p>In the jittery days that have followed the violent clashes
between Lebanon's army and fighters loyal to the radical Sunni
preacher Sheikh Ahmad al-Assir, the army has two urgent tasks.</p>
            <p>The first is to find Mr Assir, who managed to melt away as
soldiers stormed the apartment block he had turned into a fortress
in the heart of a residential district in the southern city of
Sidon.</p>
            <p>The second - and more important - task is to reassure an
increasingly anxious Lebanese public that it has the capacity to
restore calm and maintain order.</p>
            <p>It is no surprise that Mr Assir has been the catalyst that has
set off the chain of military and political reactions which has
left the Lebanese army facing perhaps its most testing week since
neighbouring Syria erupted into civil war.</p>
            <p>You can trace the sheikh's rapid evolution from fiery, if rather
eccentric, radical Sunni preacher to militia leader in fragments of
video widely shown on TV here.</p>
            <p>In older footage, there are amusing stunts in which the smiling
sheikh takes busloads of his followers onto a ski slope. The
cultural message was heavy-handed but harmless, even charming:
Islamists like to play in the snow with their children just like
everyone else.</p>
            <p>But more recent pictures show a much
darker figure emerging as the darker clouds that hang over Syria
threaten to blow across the border.</p>
            <p>We see him long-bearded in a black boiler suit with a
Kalashnikov slung across his chest.</p>
            <p>It was the civil war in Syria that transformed the sheikh,
according to his friends and supporters, just as it threatens to
transform everything else here.</p>
            <p>As a Sunni radical he has always been a fierce critic of the
Shia militant movement Hezbollah. But as Hezbollah began sending
fighters in larger and larger numbers to Syria to fight for the
government side, Mr Assir decided that fiery denunciation was no
longer enough.</p>
            <p>He began encouraging his own Sunni followers to travel to Syria
to fight for the rebels.</p>
            <p>With Mr Assir on the run, I went to the port of Tripoli to talk
to another influential Sunni cleric who has issued a similar call
to arms.</p>
            <p>Sheikh Salem Rafii has also told the young Sunni men of Lebanon
to go and fight in Syria - but says men like him and Mr Assir are
merely responding to Hezbollah's decision to go and fight there
first.</p>
            <p>"There's no doubt that Hezbollah has been interfering in Syria,"
he told me.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68392000/jpg/_68392491_68392490.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Lebanese soldiers stand by as black smoke rises from a mosque in Sidon where Sunni cleric Sheik Ahmad al-Assir preaches"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The army faced strong resistance from
Sheikh Assir's followers during clashes in Sidon</span>
            </div>
            <p>"That's a factor that can ignite a crisis in Lebanon. If war
happens here it will be because of Hezbollah.</p>
            <p>"They're stoking the fires in Syria and naturally that will be
felt here," Mr Rafii says.</p>
            <p>It seems impossible that large numbers of young men can continue
crossing from Lebanon into Syria to fight on either side of that
bitter and protracted civil war without eventually bringing the
violence back across the border.</p>
            <p>That is why this week's clashes in Sidon matter - because they
provide a dangerous template that could easily be repeated
elsewhere in Lebanon on a larger scale.</p>
            <p>It started with clashes between rival Shia and Sunni groups,
which Lebanese soldiers moved in to quell.</p>
            <p>The more serious violence erupted after one of Mr Assir's men
was caught at a military checkpoint with unauthorised weapons in
his car.</p>
            <p>The precise sequence of events that followed the discovery is a
subject of fierce dispute, but the bottom line is not: there was
heavy fighting between the army and Mr Assir's followers, which
left 17 soldiers dead.</p>
            <p>When the army finally overran Mr Assir's compound it found heavy
weapons and military-style uniforms.</p>
            <p>And it was not just the scale of the violence that worried
ordinary Lebanese - it was the way in which its roots could be seen
so clearly in Syria and in how quickly it had sucked in the forces
of the state here.</p>
            <p>Lebanon is home to a patchwork of ethnic and religious
communities very much like Syria's, and they have been held -
almost miraculously - in a kind of delicate equilibrium since the
country's own civil war ended more than 20 years ago.</p>
            <p>Events in Syria are putting that delicate equilibrium under
strain; the longer the war there continues the greater that strain
will become.</p>
            <p>No-one knows where Mr Assir has gone - he is in hiding and may
even be in Syria - but men like him and his counterparts in the
rival Shia community hold the key to what happens next in Lebanon
and how deeply this country will be affected by Syria's war.</p>
            <p>After the events of the last week here it is harder than ever to
be optimistic.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-17258397">Syria
conflict</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373015828941"
                     href="/news/magazine-23190533">Face-to-face with 'heart-eating
cannibal'</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372738930238"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23139784">Harsh justice</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372123956146"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23026868">Fragmented future?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1370996099643"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-22847540">Behind the battle lines</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">If war happens here it will be because of
Hezbollah. They're stoking the fires in Syria and naturally that
will be felt here”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Sheikh Salem Rafii</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Sunni cleric</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
