<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23076517"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Kevin Rudd is sworn in as Australian prime minister, taking over from Julia Gillard a day after he ousted her as Labor Party leader,"/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T07:50:23"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68403000/jpg/_68403909_018443232.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Rudd sworn in as new Australian PM"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-23076517"/>
         <title>BBC News - Kevin Rudd sworn in as new Australian prime
minister</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">27 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">08:50</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Kevin Rudd sworn in as new Australian
prime minister</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68403000/jpg/_68403268_rudd1.jpg"
                 alt="Kevin Rudd is sworn in as the new Australian prime minister"/>
               <p class="caption">Kevin Rudd was sworn in, promising to do his
''absolute best''</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Kevin Rudd has been
sworn in as prime minister of Australia, a day after he ousted
Julia Gillard as leader of the Labor Party.</p>
            <p>Mr Rudd took the oath at Government House in front of
Governor-General Quentin Bryce.</p>
            <p>He then addressed parliament briefly, paying tribute to Ms
Gillard, who is stepping down from politics.</p>
            <p>The leadership change comes ahead of an election scheduled for
14 September, which polls suggest Labor will lose.</p>
            <p>Opposition leader Tony Abbott called on Mr Rudd to clarify
whether the election would be brought forward.</p>
            <p>"I congratulate the prime minister on his restoration to high
office," he said. "May he elevate that office... by telling the
Australian people when will they get the chance to decide who the
prime minister of this country should be and who should form the
government of this country?"</p>
            <p>Mr Rudd said he would "identify a date
for an election", suggesting that he would not stick with the date
set by Ms Gillard.</p>
            <p>"There's going to be an election, it will be held consistent
with the constitution and... there's not going to be a huge
variation one way or the other," he said.</p>
            <p>Mr Rudd returned to lead Australia's government three years and
three days after he was toppled in a similar Labor leadership
contest by Ms Gillard, then his deputy.</p>
            <p>He secured 57 votes to Ms Gillard's 45 in Wednesday's vote,
which followed months of speculation and bitter infighting over who
should lead Labor into the forthcoming election.</p>
            <p>Opinion polls have suggested Labor will suffer a crushing
defeat. But Mr Rudd is more popular with voters than Ms Gillard and
many believe the party will perform better under him.</p>
            <p>Speaking after his win on Wednesday, Mr Rudd said he resumed the
role of prime minister with "an important sense of energy and
purpose".</p>
            <p>"Why am I taking on this challenge? For me it's pretty basic,
it's pretty clear. I simply do not have it in my nature to stand
idly by and to allow an Abbott government to come to power in this
country by default," he said.</p>
            <p>Ms Gillard resigned as prime minister on Wednesday and said she
would leave politics, as she and Mr Rudd had agreed the loser would
before the vote.</p>
            <p>Despite their bitter rivalry, Mr Rudd praised his predecessor
when he addressed parliament shortly after being sworn in.</p>
            <p>"Through the difficult years of minority government the former
prime minister has achieved major reforms for our nation that will
shape our country's future," he said.</p>
            <p>"On top of all that, I acknowledge her great work as a standard
bearer for women in our country."</p>
            <p>Describing politics as a "very hard life", he also called on
fellow lawmakers "to be a little kinder and gentler with each
other".</p>
            <p>He added that further information on his ministerial line-up
would come later.</p>
            <p>Anthony Albanese has been sworn in as deputy prime minister and
Chris Bowen replaces Wayne Swan as treasurer.</p>
            <p>Six of Ms Gillard's ministers resigned after the party vote and
further shake-ups are expected.</p>
            <p>Ms Gillard's government depended on the support of independents
for its majority - reports suggest that enough of them have swung
behind Mr Rudd to give him control of parliament.</p>
            <p>The BBC's Nick Bryant, in Sydney, says it is an astonishing
return for a politician who has long been popular with the public
at large but despised by senior colleagues within his party.</p>
            <p>It is a measure of his unpopularity that a third of Julia
Gillard's ministry resigned rather than serve under him, our
correspondent adds.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370491948597"
                  href="/news/world-asia-22793352">Australia's election: 100 days to
go</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372351756257"
                  href="/news/world-asia-23086184">Gillard: Why was she ousted?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story" rel="published-1277337809892" href="/news/10398741">Profile: Julia Gillard</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Media reaction</h2>
            <p>By calling on a ballot and demanding the loser leave politics,
Gillard has ensured her role in the ousting of Rudd almost three
years ago and the ensuing national schism will in time pale
alongside her achievements... A competitive contest is good for
Australia. Thanks to Julia Gillard's decision, we now have one.
<a href="http://www.smh.com.au/opinion/editorial/resurgent-rudd-must-offer-nation-a-contest-over-policy-20130626-2oxm6.html">
(Editorial, Sydney Morning Herald)</a>
            </p>
            <p>[Mr Rudd's] task now is to resume office without the hubris that
consumed his first term as prime minister... Neither will Mr Rudd
get far by presenting himself simply as the candidate who is not Mr
Abbott. He must recognise that Mr Abbott is now an opposition
leader of experience and stature who, like Mr Rudd himself, has
been strengthened by the experience of the past three years.
<a href="http://www.theaustralian.com.au/opinion/editorials/rudd-must-drag-labor-back-to-the-centre/story-e6frg71x-1226670469127">
(Editorial, The Australian)</a>
            </p>
            <p>Julia Gillard has delivered the ultimate act of leadership and
paid the ultimate price, ending the most poisonous, inglorious
chapter in modern Labor Party history. But whether Kevin Rudd
transforms Labor's prospects at the election depends on whether he
can re-unite a fractured party that he helped divide, re-connect
with a hostile electorate and challenge a rampant opposition.
<a href="http://www.smh.com.au/opinion/politics/gillard-pays-ultimate-price-to-end-a-poisonous-chapter-20130626-2oxm9.html">
(Michael Gordon, political editor, The Age)</a>
            </p>
            <p>The more Labor squabbles, the more it turns on itself, the more
the Liberal and National parties are spared the necessity of
presenting a coherent platform for election. Why, in the
circumstances, should they bother?... Never mind its three-year
obsession with leadership, with that at last behind it the [Labor
Party] really ought to have a stab at leading, even if it is to
defeat. <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-06-27/green-labor-should-just-lead-even-if-it-is-to-defeat/4783176">
(Jonathan Green, ABC's The Drum blog)</a>
            </p>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-asia-23077299">Rudd: Saviour or 'recycled
failure'?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/blogs-magazine-monitor-23079177">Magazine
Monitor: Disemvowelled</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
