<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23133214"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="US President Barack Obama says he wants a &#34;new model&#34; for development in Africa during a visit to Tanzania on the last leg of his Africa tour."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T20:32:26"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68487000/jpg/_68487341_68486714.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Obama backs 'new model' for Africa"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Africa"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23133214"/>
         <title>BBC News - Obama backs 'new model' for Africa in Tanzania
speech</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">21:32</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Obama backs 'new model' for Africa in
Tanzania speech</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68489000/jpg/_68489762_68489282.jpg"
                 alt="President Obama"/>
               <p class="caption">President Obama said the model should be based
on trade and partnership</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">US President Barack
Obama has said he wants a "new model" for development during his
first visit to Tanzania.</p>
            <p>Mr Obama and his family were greeted by Tanzanian President
Jakaya Kikwete and troupes of dancers as they arrived in the main
city of Dar es Salaam.</p>
            <p>In a speech on the last leg of his Africa tour, the US president
said Tanzania had the potential to transform the region.</p>
            <p>Trade was expected to top the agenda in his talks with business
leaders.</p>
            <p>Asked whether the US had done enough to help the continent, he
said: "Ultimately the goal here is for Africa to build Africa for
Africans.</p>
            <p>"Our job is to be a partner in the process and Tanzania has been
one of our best partners."</p>
            <p>Mr Obama has been criticised for lacking a grand programme for
Africa, and many Africans have been disappointed at what they see
as his lack of engagement with the continent, despite his ancestry
there.</p>
            <p>The president said he wanted to move away from traditional forms
of international development and work more closely with businesses
in Africa.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68479000/jpg/_68479146_68479145.jpg"
                 alt="Clothing saying U.S.A"/>
               <p class="caption">As the BBC's Salim Kikeke reports, American
influence can be found in Tanzanian sport, music and fashion.</p>
            </div>
            <p>"We are looking at a new model that's based not just on aid and
assistance but on trade and partnership," he said.</p>
            <p>"Increasingly what we want to do is use
whatever monies that we're providing to build capacity."</p>
            <p>Examples he gave included investment in health systems, food
self-sufficiency and sustainable power sources.</p>
            <p>During his first visit to Tanzania, Mr Obama will also visit an
US-owned power plant following his announcement over the weekend of
a multi-billion-dollar electricity initiative.</p>
            <p>The $7bn (Ã‚Â£4.6bn) five-year initiative
is intended to double access to electricity in sub-Saharan Africa,
in partnership with African countries and the private sector.</p>
            <p>He made the announcement at South Africa's University of Cape
Town after the US first family had visited Robben Island, the
former jail where Nelson Mandela spent 18 years of his 27 years in
captivity during his fight against the apartheid regime.</p>
            <p>During his time in South Africa, the US leader did not visit Mr
Mandela, who remains critically ill in hospital suffering from a
lung infection, but he did met the Mandela family in private.</p>
            <p>Correspondents say roads have been closed and security stepped
up in Dar es Salaam for the US president's visit.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68489000/jpg/_68489464_68486714.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="US President Barack Obama (L) shakes hands during a welcoming ceremony at the State House in Dar es Salaam on 1 July 2013"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">President Obama received a warm welcome
at State House in Dar es Salaam</span>
            </div>
            <p>Hundreds of people lined the streets wearing T-shirts and
sarongs bearing images of Mr Obama, in the warmest welcome he has
received in his three-country visit to Africa, they say.</p>
            <p>The crowds forced Mr Obama's motorcade to slow at times as it
sped along a main road in the city that has been permanently
renamed "Barack Obama Drive", in honour of America's first
president of African descent, the Associated Press news agency
reports.</p>
            <p>"For development you need investments to utilise the huge
potential that there is so that this huge potential can translate
into incomes and jobs for our people and therefore development for
our country," President Kikwete told the BBC's Newsday programme
ahead of his arrival.</p>
            <p>While in the country, Mr Obama is due to launch a programme
helping Africa's eastern nations of Burundi, Kenya, Rwanda,
Tanzania and Uganda trade both with each other and with the US.</p>
            <p>He also signed an executive order aimed at preventing wildlife
trafficking, particularly the sale of rhinoceros horns and elephant
tusks.</p>
            <p>On Tuesday, Mr Obama will lay a wreath at a memorial outside the
US embassy in Dar es Salaam, in honour of 11 people killed in a
bombing by al-Qaeda in 1998.</p>
            <p>His wife Michelle Obama is expected to take part in African
First Ladies Summit organised by the George W Bush Institute and
hosted by her predecessor Laura Bush.</p>
            <p>Mr Obama's second tour to sub-Saharan Africa since becoming
president began in Senegal where he called on African governments
to give gay people equal rights by decriminalising homosexual
acts.</p>
            <p>The US president has excluded from his itinerary Kenya, where
his father was born, and Nigeria, Africa's biggest oil producer
which has been hit by an Islamist insurgency.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372701544227"
                  href="/news/world-africa-23138037">Letter from Africa: Dollar
dominion</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372539184379"
                  href="/news/world-africa-23115787">No easy ride for Obama</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372268790992"
                  href="/news/world-africa-23070006">Too little too late?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">For development you need investments to
utilise the huge potential that there is so that this huge
potential can translate into incomes and jobs for our people and
therefore development for our country”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Jakaya Kikwete</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Tanzania's president</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
