<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23234116"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Bolivia demands that the ambassadors of France, Spain, Portugal and Italy explain why their countries blocked President Evo Morales' jet last week."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-08T19:04:52"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68616000/jpg/_68616412_68616382.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Envoys summoned over Bolivia jet"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Latin America"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23234116"/>
         <title>BBC News - Edward Snowden case: Bolivia summons envoys over
jet</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">8 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">20:04</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Edward Snowden case: Bolivia summons
envoys over jet</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68616000/jpg/_68616388_68616382.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Evo Morales speaks during a meeting with Uru-Chipaya indigenous in Chipaya, Bolivia, Saturday, 6 July"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Evo Morales and his allies were furious
over the jet incident</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Bolivia has summoned
the ambassadors of France, Spain, Portugal and Italy to explain why
their countries blocked President Evo Morales' jet last week.</p>
            <p>Mr Morales was flying home from Moscow when his plane was forced
to reroute to Vienna, amid rumours that US fugitive Edward Snowden
was on board.</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden, a former CIA contractor, is wanted by the US on
charges of leaking secrets about US surveillance schemes.</p>
            <p>The European countries have variously denied closing their
airspace.</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden was not on the flight, and is still believed to be in
the transit area of Moscow's Sheremetyevo airport.</p>
            <p>But Spanish officials admitted that they had been told Mr
Snowden was on board the plane.</p>
            <p>Several Latin American countries have condemned the incident and
accused the US of influencing its European allies.</p>
            <p>"We are simply asking the government of Spain and the other
governments to clarify and explain where that version of Mr Snowden
being on the presidential plane came from," said Bolivian
Communications Minister Amanda Davila.</p>
            <p>"Who spread that fallacy, that lie?"</p>
            <p>Meanwhile, the diplomatic row spilled onto the streets of La
Paz, as thousands of Bolivians staged demonstrations against the US
and four European countries.</p>
            <p>Hundreds of protesters reportedly gathered outside the US
embassy, demanding that the US diplomatic mission be closed and
setting fire to US, Spanish, French and Portuguese flags.</p>
            <p>The US wants Mr Snowden extradited on charges of leaking secrets
he gathered while working as a contractor for the National Security
Agency (NSA), America's electronic spying agency.</p>
            <p>Ireland's High Court on Monday rejected a bid by the US to
obtain a provisional arrest warrant for Mr Snowden in the event he
landed on Irish soil.</p>
            <p>Judge Colm Mac Eochaidh said he was "compelled" to refuse the
request because it did not specify where the alleged offences were
committed. However, he said this should not prevent the US
authorities from making a fresh application.</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden, 30, has requested asylum in more than 20
countries.</p>
            <p>Several Latin American nations have indicated they would give
him protection if asked.</p>
            <p>Nicaragua confirmed on Monday that it had received a formal
asylum request, and indicated last week that it would give him
protection.</p>
            <p>Correspondents say the furore surrounding Mr Morales' plane has
made Latin America a likely destination for Mr Snowden.</p>
            <p>But he faces major difficulties in arranging passage from Moscow
if Western European nations will not allow him to fly over their
territory.</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden's leaks have led to revelations that the US is
systematically seizing vast amounts of phone and web data under an
NSA programme known as Prism.</p>
            <p>The Guardian and Washington Post interviewed him at length last
month in Hong Kong, where he fled after revealing details about
Prism.</p>
            <p>The Guardian published another video segment of that interview
on Monday, with Mr Snowden predicting that the US would accuse him
of "grave crimes".</p>
            <p>Mr Snowden left Hong Kong for Moscow on 23 June and has not been
seen since.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>US spy leaks</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372684702774"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23123964">Revelations of US spy
scandal</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372869435767"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23165992">Where will Snowden end
up?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372702760008"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23133216">Is it OK to spy on your
allies?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372348565338"
                     href="/news/world-latin-america-23077279">Wikileaks back in
spotlight</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Snowden leaks timeline</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <strong>5 June</strong>: First leak published in the Guardian
saying the National Security Agency (NSA) is <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-22793851">collecting the
telephone records</a> of millions of people in the US</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>6 June</strong>: Details of the <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-22811580">US Prism internet
surveillance programme</a> published by the Guardian and Washington
Post</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>9 June</strong>: Guardian <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-22836378">identifies
Edward Snowden</a> as the source of the leaks, at his own request,
and says he has been in Hong Kong since 20 May</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>14 June</strong>: US <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23012317">files criminal
charges</a> against Mr Snowden</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>23 June:</strong> Mr Snowden leaves Hong Kong for
Moscow, Ecuador confirms he has applied for political asylum</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>2 July:</strong> Bolivian leader Evo Morales' plane is
diverted to Vienna and apparently searched for Mr Snowden</li>
               <li>
                  <strong>6 July:</strong> Bolivia, Venezuela and Nicaragua say
they would offer Mr Snowden asylum</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-us-canada-22837100">Who is Edward
Snowden?</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-us-canada-23165992">Where will Snowden end
up?</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
