<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-23241269"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Bhaag Milkha Bhaag (Run, Milkha, Run), a biopic of the legendary Indian athlete Milkha Singh, is set for worldwide release on 12 July. The BBC's Geeta Pandey reports from Delhi."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-12T01:32:50"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68627000/jpg/_68627138_finalposter.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="'Flying Sikh': Indian sprinter Milkha Singh biopic set for release"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Asia/India"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-23241269"/>
         <title>BBC News - 'Flying Sikh': Indian sprinter Milkha Singh
biopic set for release</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">12 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">02:32</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">'Flying Sikh': Indian sprinter Milkha
Singh biopic set for release</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68627000/jpg/_68627627_downloads2.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="300"
                 alt="Farhan Akhtar (left) in Bhaag Milkha Bhaag and Milkha Singh (right)"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Actor Farhan Akhtar (left) plays the
legendary athlete Milkha Singh (right) in the biopic</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Bhaag Milkha Bhaag
(Run, Milkha, Run), a biopic of the legendary Indian athlete Milkha
Singh, is set for worldwide release on 12 July. The BBC's Geeta
Pandey met the film's director, Rakeysh Omprakash Mehra, and lead
actor, Farhan Akhtar, in Delhi.</p>
            <p>The film, depicting the life and achievements of the "Flying
Sikh", who overcame personal tragedy to represent India three times
at the Olympics, is perhaps the most-awaited Bollywood film of the
year.</p>
            <p>Director Rakeysh Omprakash Mehra says he decided to make a film
on Milkha Singh's life because it is a "fascinating" story.</p>
            <p>As a young boy who lived in a remote
village in Multan province, Milkha saw his parents and seven
siblings murdered during the Partition of India and the creation of
Pakistan in 1947.</p>
            <p>As his father fell, his last words were "Bhaag Milkha Bhaag",
exhorting his son to run for his life.</p>
            <p>The boy ran - first to save his life, and then to win
medals.</p>
            <p>Arriving in India as an orphan in 1947, he took to petty crime
and did odd jobs for survival until he found a place in the army.
It was there that he discovered his athletic abilities.</p>
            <p>Singh's exploits on the track and field are legendary in India -
he won five golds in international athletic championships, broke a
400m record at the 1960 Rome Olympics and was awarded the Helms
World Trophy in 1959 for winning 77 of his 80 international
races.</p>
            <p>Mehra, best known for his 2006 hit Rang De Basanti and Delhi-6
three years later, was chosen by Singh's golfer son, Jeev Milkha
Singh, to make the biopic. The athlete sold him the rights to his
story for one token rupee.</p>
            <p>The director, who grew up with the "folklore" of the
"larger-than-life" sprinter, says his film is not about Singh the
athlete, but rather "the spirit of Milkha, the colours of his
life".</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68630000/jpg/_68630192_bhaag_milkha_bhaag_poster.jpg"
                 alt="Bhaag Milkha Bhaag movie poster"/>
               <p class="caption">Farhan Akhtar and Sonam Kapoor talk about Bhaag
Milha Bhaag</p>
            </div>
            <p>"It's an amazing story - he was a local hero, the son of the
soil, who went out and conquered the world for us."</p>
            <p>Bhaag Milkha Bhaag, which took four years to make and cost $6.5m
(Ã‚Â£4.36m), begins in 1947 and ends in
1960.</p>
            <p>Actor Farhan Akhtar, who plays Singh on screen, says when Mehra
narrated the script to him, he "felt tremendously moved by the
story".</p>
            <p>"I was also surprised how ignorant I was about his life. We knew
about him as a sporting icon, we knew he was called the Flying
Sikh, but didn't know what made him the hero."</p>
            <p>Akhtar says he trained between four and five hours a day for the
role and had several meetings with Singh to learn about his running
style.</p>
            <p>"An athlete's body language is very different from an ordinary
person's. And Milkha had a unique running style. Most athletes run
with their arms bent at the elbows, but he ran with his arms
flailing about," says Akhtar.</p>
            <p>Singh told the BBC he used to run six hours every day.</p>
            <p>"I would not stop till I had filled up a bucket with my sweat. I
would push myself so much that in the end I would collapse and I
would have to be admitted to hospital, I would pray to God to save
me, promise that I would be more careful in future. And then I
would do it all over again."</p>
            <p>In the official trailer for the film, as actor Farhan Akhtar
races towards the finishing line in his white jersey, one is struck
by the striking resemblance he bears to Singh: the sunken cheeks,
the aquiline nose, the high cheekbones and identical body
language.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68627000/jpg/_68627631_img_1269(small).jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="300"
                 alt="Farhan Akhtar and Sonam Kapoor in Bhaag Milkha Bhaag"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Bollywood actress Sonam Kapoor plays
Milkha Singh's love interest in the film</span>
            </div>
            <p>And the athlete has given his screen version a big thumbs up.
"Akhtar is brilliant in the role. He has done a great job. He looks
like a duplicate Milkha Singh," he told the BBC.</p>
            <p>Singh won Gold at the 1958 Commonwealth Games in Cardiff and
went on to finish fourth in the 400 metres at the Rome Olympics,
missing out on a bronze medal by a whisker. Even though he never
won an Olympic medal, his only wish today is that "someone else
should win that medal for India".</p>
            <p>And he is hoping the film "will inspire the next
generation".</p>
            <p>"We had nothing in our times. The athletes and sportsmen in
those days didn't earn much money. We worked for the applause;
people's appreciation inspired and motivated us; we ran for the
country," he says.</p>
            <p>"People of my age and era are aware of me, but today's
generation doesn't know about me. I hope the film will inspire the
next generation, how hard work can take one far in the world."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1217435203000"
                  href="/1/hi/world/south_asia/7532626.stm">The 'Flying Sikh'
remembers</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-997971674000"
                  href="/1/hi/world/south_asia/1494770.stm">'Flying Sikh' snubs
award</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68627000/jpg/_68627629_img_5956.jpg"
              width="144"
              height="81"
              alt="Rakeysh Omprakash Mehra"/>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">It's an amazing story - he was a local hero,
the son of the soil, who went out and conquered the world for
us”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Rakeysh Omprakash Mehra</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Director, Bhaag Milkha Bhaag</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
