<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-22894459"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Are politically appointed diplomats a bad idea?"/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-27T23:11:37"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68166000/jpg/_68166927_141701874-2.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Should political fundraisers become ambassadors?"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/US and Canada"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-22894459"/>
         <title>BBC News - Should political fundraisers become
ambassadors?</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">00:11</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Should political fundraisers become
ambassadors?</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Tara
McKelvey</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News,
Washington</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68166000/jpg/_68166923_141695536-4.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="351"
                 alt="Howard Gutman"/>
               <span style="width:624px;">Howard Gutman, the current US ambassador to Belgium,
was a campaign donor</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Many of the US
ambassadors to swanky European capitals are campaign donors. Are
politically appointed diplomats a bad idea?</p>
            <p>Last week President Barack Obama recommended 10 new individuals
for ambassadorships. Two of them had raised money for his
presidential campaign - Denise Bauer for Belgium and James "Wally"
Brewster for the Dominican Republic.</p>
            <p>They are "bag men", people who give money to political campaigns
- a group that is increasingly female, despite its name.</p>
            <p>They are like dozens of other ambassadors who are chosen by the
White House for the postings - though they have no background in
foreign service.</p>
            <p>Rather than serving in the diplomatic
corps, political appointees have instead worked as business
executives, lawyers, consultants and in other professions.</p>
            <p>As non-career diplomats, they can be appointed "without
competition", according to the Office of Personnel Management.</p>
            <p>Giving money - and later becoming ambassador - is a
long-standing tradition in the US diplomatic world.</p>
            <p>In the early 1970s, President Richard Nixon was blunt about the
arrangements he had in place when talking with an aide about a
diplomatic posting to Belgium.</p>
            <p>"Anybody who wants to be an ambassador must at least give
$250,000," Nixon said. "I'm not going to do it for political
friends and all that crap."</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68167000/jpg/_68167144_52224395-2.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="An aerial view of the US embassy in Brussels, with park, pictured in 2005"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">The US embassy in Brussels, pictured in
2005</span>
            </div>
            <p>Political appointees are not necessarily wealthy. At times,
presidents nominate individuals who have personal ties.</p>
            <p>"There was an ambassador in the Bush administration who used to
bicycle with the president," says Robert Rizzi, a Washington lawyer
who helps clients through the official vetting process for
political appointees.</p>
            <p>Once the president has selected a candidate for an
ambassadorship, the individual appears before the Senate foreign
relations committee for a confirmation hearing.</p>
            <p>The proportion of political appointees among ambassadors has
remained the same - roughly one-third - since the 1950s.</p>
            <p>The political appointees are part of the "spoils system", says
Susan Johnson, president of the American Foreign Service
Association.</p>
            <p>"It undermines the whole concept of meritocratic professional
diplomatic service," she says. Many people have found fault with
the system over the years.</p>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68167000/jpg/_68167148_104497501-2.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Tony Bennett, Ted Sarandos (Netflix), Nicole Avant (centre), Harvey Weinstein and Georgina Chapman"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">Nicole Avant, centre at a New York
party, was ambassador to the Bahamas for less than two
years</span>
            </div>
            <p>Shortly after being elected president, Obama vowed to "reform
the political appointee process".</p>
            <p>A <a href="http://change.gov/agenda/ethics_agenda/">statement</a> on his
website reported that "in the Obama-Biden administration, every
official will have to rise to the standard of proven
excellence".</p>
            <p>Yet instead of declining under Obama, the percentage of
political appointees has remained the same.</p>
            <p>Today about 29% of ambassadorships are held by political
appointees, according to the <a href="http://www.afsa.org/ambassadorlist.aspx">American Foreign Service
Association</a>.</p>
            <p>The UK, Canada and other countries have political appointees -
but not as many. Jim LeBlanc, a consultant who used to work for a
Canadian ambassador, says: "It doesn't go as deep."</p>
            <p>Bruce Oreck is a lawyer who helped raise $575,000
(Ã‚Â£377,000) for Obama's presidential
campaign. He got a call from the White House after the
election.</p>
            <p>"They said, 'Would you be willing to serve and, if so, where
would you have an interest in serving?'" Oreck recalls.</p>
            <p>Oreck, whose father is the founder of
Oreck, a company that has sold millions of vacuum cleaners, is now
the ambassador in Helsinki. He had never seen the city before his
posting.</p>
            <p>"People who are successful are disciplined," Oreck says. "You
want people who've had that kind of success because they're going
to be good advocates for America."</p>
            <p>Some political appointees do well. Citigroup's Louis Susman
raised money for Obama and then went to London as ambassador.</p>
            <p>Shortly before he left in April, Susman had an audience with the
Queen, "a privilege rarely afforded to departing ambassadors",
reports the Telegraph.</p>
            <p>The ambassador in Paris, Charles Rivkin, helped raise $800,000
(Ã‚Â£524,000). "Neither the ambassador nor the
embassy in Paris have any comment on this topic," says embassy
spokesman Mitchell Moss.</p>
            <p>The ambassador in Lisbon, Allan Katz, raised $500,000
(Ã‚Â£328,000).</p>
            <p>Embassy spokeswoman Virginia Staab says: "In the US Foreign
Service, we aim to strike the perfect balance between career and
political appointees since each can provide strengths and
opportunities to further US foreign policy."</p>
            <p>Career diplomats such as Thomas Boyatt,
who served as ambassador to Colombia after working for years in the
foreign service, resent the way that wealthy individuals end up in
cushy posts.</p>
            <p>"The media used to call us 'the striped-pant boys'," says
Boyatt.</p>
            <p>"I used to say, 'The only stripes I ever had on my pants were
from my own blood.' That shut them up."</p>
            <p>Whether political appointees or career diplomats, they should
accept posts that are located in the developing world - rather than
accepting ambassadorships only to European or wealthy nations, says
Boyatt.</p>
            <p>The Obama administration has had an unusual number of high-level
disasters among its political appointees, many from postings in
Western nations.</p>
            <p>Cynthia Stroum, a political appointee who served as the
ambassador to Luxembourg, was "hostile and intimidating", according
to <a href="http://oig.state.gov/documents/organization/156129.pdf">a 2011
governmental report</a> about that embassy.</p>
            <p>"I'm baffled that I was forced to resign over such petty and
unsubstantiated allegations," Stroum says.</p>
            <p>Regarding the selection of ambassadors, Stroum says: "I have no
way of knowing how they made or continue to make their choices or
what criteria they use."</p>
            <p>Not all political appointees are fundraisers. Some are public
figures who are known on a national level or for their work in a
local community.</p>
            <p>One appointee, Douglas Kmiec, a former Catholic University of
America dean, resigned as head of the US mission in Malta in
2011.</p>
            <p>State department officials said he had been spending hours every
day writing about Catholicism - and not enough hours, apparently,
on his diplomatic work.</p>
            <p>Kmiec says he chose to resign "when individuals within the
department refused to follow the president's efforts to use
faith-based diplomacy".</p>
            <p>Another political appointee, Nicole Avant, the former ambassador
to the Bahamas, lasted less than two years. The state department's
office of inspections gave her <a href="http://oig.state.gov/documents/organization/184725.pdf">a negative
report</a>.</p>
            <p>She says she "had inherited a dysfunctional embassy. Under the
direction of the new executive team that I appointed, the embassy
began to recover."</p>
            <p>Critics say they wish career diplomats were serving in more
posts as ambassadors, since political appointees do not always fare
well.</p>
            <p>"There have been some that have turned out to be real busts,"
says the American Foreign Service Association's Susan Johnson.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine">In today's
Magazine</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373253012577"
                     href="/news/magazine-22971177">Revolution in the royal nursery</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373240476495"
                     href="/news/magazine-23179862">The sad life of a circus lion</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373066350296"
                     href="/news/magazine-23146086">10x10 things about 10 years of the
Magazine</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372980521482"
                     href="/news/magazine-23137492">Will there ever be another massive tank
battle?</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">Anybody who wants to be an ambassador must
at least give $250,000”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">President Richard Nixon</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>The price of an ambassadorship</h2>
            <ul>
               <li>Researchers JW Fedderke and D Jett examined US political
appointees in a 2012 paper, looking at campaign contributions and
postings based on criteria such as gross domestic product per
capita</li>
               <li>The greater the contributions to the campaign, they wrote, "the
more highly ranked the posting" - and they include "a price list"
for different postings</li>
               <li>A posting to Finland or France, for example, would likely be
granted to a fundraiser who had amassed $616,490 in campaign
contributions</li>
               <li>A posting to Portugal would likely go to a fundraiser who had
amassed $341,160</li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>An ambassador in trouble</h2>
            <p>A government report alleges a political appointee, later
identified as the ambassador in Brussels, Howard Gutman, "routinely
ditched" bodyguards to seek prostitutes in a park.</p>
            <p>From the embassy in Brussels, Gutman strenuously denied the
allegations and described them as "baseless". He says: "I live on a
beautiful park in Brussels that you walk through to get to many
locations and at no point have I ever engaged in any improper
activity."</p>
            <p>In 2010 Gutman said Belgium should send more troops to
Afghanistan, a suggestion that galled politicians in Brussels.</p>
            <p>Unlike career diplomats, Gutman has a background in politics. He
helped raised $500,000 (about Ã‚Â£320,000) for
Obama's presidential campaign and $275,000 for his
inauguration.</p>
            <p>
               <em>Sources: US state department, US embassy, Center for
Responsive Politics</em>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
