<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23275988"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Travyon Martin was shot dead &#34;through no fault of his own&#34; but because George Zimmerman deemed him a criminal, a prosecutor says in closing statements."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-12T00:35:29"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68680000/jpg/_68680207_68678210.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Martin's death 'no fault of his own'"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/US and Canada"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-23275988"/>
         <title>BBC News - Trayvon Martin death 'no fault of his own' -
prosecutor</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">12 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">01:35</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Trayvon Martin death 'no fault of his own'
- prosecutor</h1>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68680000/jpg/_68680214_68678210.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="George Zimmerman arrives at court in Sanford, Florida on 11 July 2013"/>
               <span style="width:464px;">George Zimmerman is worried about his
safety in the future, his lawyers say</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">An unarmed black
teenager was shot dead "through no fault of his own" but because a
neighbourhood watch volunteer deemed him a criminal, a prosecutor
has said near the end of a murder trial.</p>
            <p>Florida prosecutors said George Zimmerman, 29, lied about what
happened the night he killed Trayvon Martin, 17.</p>
            <p>The accused says he shot the teenager in self-defence during a
fight.</p>
            <p>He is charged with second-degree murder, but the judge has ruled
the jury can convict him of manslaughter.</p>
            <p>Defence lawyers for Mr Zimmerman are expected to make their
closing arguments on Friday, following 12 days of testimony.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68097000/jpg/_68097540_police5.jpg"
                 alt="Police Chief Cecil Smith"/>
               <p class="caption">Sanford's new police chief has been reaching out
to the community</p>
            </div>
            <p>Mr Zimmerman could face life in prison if convicted on the
murder charge. If found guilty of manslaughter, he could face up to
30 years in prison.</p>
            <p>On the night of 26 February 2012, Martin was walking from a
convenience shop to the home of his father's fiancee in Sanford,
Florida, when the fatal confrontation ensued.</p>
            <p>Mr Zimmerman, who was legally armed with a pistol, had been
sitting in his vehicle on a dark street when he saw Martin and
believed he was up to no good. Mr Zimmerman telephoned police, then
left his vehicle in apparent pursuit of the teenager.</p>
            <p>Moments later, Martin was dead of a gunshot wound to the
chest.</p>
            <p>Mr Zimmerman claimed he had shot Martin in self-defence when the
teenager tried to grab his gun. In the absence of witnesses
contradicting his account, police did not arrest him until six
weeks later, following mass protests across the United States.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68356000/jpg/_68356389_510d68e7-e6e2-4cf3-af3e-279ff28df18b.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Trayvon Martin"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Trayvon Martin was unarmed and walking home to his
father's house</span>
            </div>
            <p>After 12 days of testimony in Mr Zimmerman's murder trial,
prosecutor Bernie de la Rionda gave the state's closing remarks on
Thursday.</p>
            <p>He described Mr Zimmerman as a "wannabe cop" and said the
neighbourhood watch volunteer had followed the teenager with a gun
and provoked him into a fight.</p>
            <p>"[Trayvon] is dead through no fault of his own," he told the
jury of six women.</p>
            <p>"He is dead because another man made assumptions. Because his
assumptions were wrong, Trayvon Benjamin Martin will no longer walk
on this Earth."</p>
            <p>Without explicitly bringing up race, Mr de la Rionda said Mr
Zimmerman had "profiled" the young black hooded sweatshirt-clad
teenager as a criminal.</p>
            <p>"Who started this?" Mr de la Rionda asked the jury to consider.
"Who followed who? Who was minding his own business? And of the
two, who was armed?"</p>
            <p>During the trial, prosecutors argued that Mr Zimmerman had lied
in his account of the confrontation and that Mr Zimmerman, not
Martin, had been the aggressor.</p>
            <p>Martin's parents told the court the voice
heard screaming for help on an emergency call during the fight was
their son's.</p>
            <p>And a prosecution witness testified none of Mr Zimmerman's DNA
had been found on Martin's body - especially under his
fingernails.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile, Mr Zimmerman's defence team said that Martin had
attacked the defendant unprovoked, pummelled him and slammed his
head against the concrete pavement and made a grab for his gun,
while he struggled for his life and ultimately fired his gun in
self-defence.</p>
            <p>Mr Zimmerman chose not to testify. But his lawyers showed the
jury a video recording of Mr Zimmerman explaining to police his
version of events.</p>
            <p>The lawyers dwelt on Mr Zimmerman's injuries, which they said
showed the teenager was severely beating him before the fatal
shot.</p>
            <p>Both of Mr Zimmerman's parents, as well as friends and an uncle,
told the court the cries heard on the emergency call were those of
Mr Zimmerman.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68686000/jpg/_68686404_171504962.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="Assistant state attorneys John Guy (L) and Richard Mantei hold up Trayvon Martin's sweatshirt as evidence during George Zimmerman's trial 25 June 2013"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Jurors were shown the clothes Martin was
wearing the night he was killed</span>
            </div>
            <p>And forensic pathologist testified that Mr Zimmerman had fired
his gun from beneath Martin, evidence, the defence said, that the
teenager was beating him up.</p>
            <p>Florida community leaders have appealed for calm as the trial
heads towards its conclusion, fearing outrage if Mr Zimmerman is
acquitted.</p>
            <p>"It's all right to be vocal, but we don't want to be violent,"
said the Rev Walter Richardson, chairman of Miami-Dade County's
Community Relations Board, according to the Associated Press.</p>
            <p>"We've already lost one soul and we don't want to lose any
more."</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372092416167"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-23034619">Zimmerman 'wanted to kill'
teen</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1334181604719"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-17682245">Who are Martin and
Zimmerman?</a>
               </li>
               <li class="has-icon-boxedwatch">
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1370900950763"
                  href="/news/world-us-canada-22850257">Healing a community in Sanford
<span class="gvl3-icon gvl3-icon-boxedwatch">Watch</span>
                  </a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">We've already lost one soul and we don't
want to lose any more”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Rev Walter Richardson</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Miami-Dade Community Relations
Board</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
