<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23077279"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The whistle-blowing group Wikileaks is back in the public eye after playing a key role in the saga of US intelligence leaker Edward Snowden - but how do their interests coincide?"/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-28T09:08:50"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68410000/jpg/_68410898_68405744.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Snowden thrusts Wikileaks back into spotlight"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Latin America"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-23077279"/>
         <title>BBC News - Snowden affair puts Wikileaks back into
spotlight</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">28 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">10:08</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Snowden affair puts Wikileaks back into
spotlight</h1>
            <span class="byline">
               <span class="byline-name">By Becky
Branford</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC News</span>
            </span>
            <div class="caption body-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68405000/jpg/_68405743_2cb17872-816f-42b4-a82c-f5829e3087e4.jpg"
                 width="464"
                 height="261"
                 alt="Journalists pursue Edward Snowden at Moscow's Sheremetyevo airport on 23 June "/>
               <span style="width:464px;">As the world's media - and US
authorities - pursue Edward Snowden, Wikileaks is at his
side</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The whistleblowing
organisation Wikileaks has become closely embroiled in the story of
Edward Snowden - the US intelligence leaker accused of espionage in
the US who is currently believed to be seeking a safe haven from
the transit zone of Moscow airport.</p>
            <p>The affair has given fresh prominence to an organisation whose
profile had waned since its headline-grabbing release in 2010 of
hundreds of thousands of US state department diplomatic cables
along with secret documents relating to the wars in Iraq and
Afghanistan.</p>
            <p>Its reputation has been dented by allegations of sex crimes
levelled at its founder Julian Assange - who has now spent a year
inside the Ecuadorean embassy in London, avoiding attempts to
extradite him to Sweden.</p>
            <p>He claims the allegations are part of a witch-hunt against him
by the US, where there is an ongoing investigation into Wikileaks
and Mr Assange by the US justice department.</p>
            <p>The assistance Wikileaks has given Mr Snowden has thrust it back
onto the front pages and its representatives back into the TV
studios.</p>
            <p>According to Elias Groll of Foreign Policy magazine, the two
parties were not associated at the start of this saga - as
evidenced by the fact that Mr Snowden took his revelations to the
Guardian newspaper, bypassing Wikileaks "when this is Wikileaks'
natural territory".</p>
            <p>So how has Wikileaks assisted Mr Snowden, and how do their
interests coincide?</p>
            <p>Edward Snowden was first publicly identified by the UK's
Guardian newspaper as the source of leaks about US surveillance
programmes on 9 June, at which point he had been in Hong Kong for
three weeks since fleeing from his Hawaii home.</p>
            <p>Wikileaks' involvement in the affair
first began to be reported more than a week later, when it emerged
that it had made an ultimately unsuccessful bid to secure asylum
for him in Iceland.</p>
            <p>Wikileaks spokesman Kristinn Hrafnsson told the BBC on 24 June
that "we have been helping him on two fronts: on one side, our
legal team has been in contact and consultation and advising his
legal team - for obvious reasons our legal team has vast knowledge
in matters of extradition so it's quite natural that they could
assist in many ways.</p>
            <p>"Secondly we have been a go-between, carrying messages from Mr
Snowden and his team to officials and governments."</p>
            <p>Mr Assange claimed he had helped secure a refugee document of
passage from the Ecuadorean government after the US revoked his
passport, though Quito has since denied authorising any such
document.</p>
            <p>It is unclear whether Mr Snowden used an Ecuadorean document,
authorised or unauthorised, to enable his passage to Moscow -
where, Mr Assange confirms, Wikileaks has paid for Mr Snowden's
plane tickets, lodging and legal counsel.</p>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68405000/jpg/_68405741_bff6c45a-fe6c-442a-98ca-61e7f2a8fd14.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="File image of Wikileaks legal activist Sarah Harrison, from 21 June 2012"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Wikileaks activist Sarah Harrison -
shown here in a file image - is said to be accompanying
Snowden</span>
            </div>
            <p>
               <a href="http://wikileaks.org/Profile-Sarah-Harrison.html">Wikileaks
confirms</a> that Sarah Harrison - a member of the Wikileaks legal
team - "assisted Mr Snowden with his lawful departure from Hong
Kong" and is "escorting him at all times" while in Russia.</p>
            <p>Ms Harrison, who is still thought to be with Mr Snowden in
Moscow, is - <a href="http://www.standard.co.uk/lifestyle/london-life/whos-that-girl-confidante-to-julian-assange-and-now-on-a-mission-to-rescue-edward-snowden--meet-sarah-harrison-8674363.html">
London's Evening Standard claims</a> - Julian Assange's "powerful
lieutenant and his principal link to the outside world from his
room in the Ecuadorean embassy in Knightsbridge".</p>
            <p>Baltasar Garzon, the former campaigning Spanish judge and now
Wikileaks' legal director, is heading a team advising Mr Snowden on
strategies to keep out of the grasp of the US. In a recent tweet,
Wikileaks said it had hired a US attorney to represent him in the
longer term.</p>
            <p>Since Mr Snowden left Hong Kong and disappeared from public
view, key Wikileaks figures have taken to the airwaves to explain
why he should be hailed and not hounded for his disclosures.</p>
            <p>So Wikileaks' best and brightest have been at the heart of
efforts to protect Mr Snowden - why?</p>
            <p>Asked whether he felt "any feeling of satisfaction or vengeance"
at helping Mr Snowden thwart the US government, Mr Assange replied:
"I have personal sympathy with Mr Snowden, having lived through a
very similar experience, but the Wikileaks organisation more
broadly exists to defend the practical rights of whistleblowers to
bring their information to the public."</p>
            <p>There may be other benefits from Wikileaks' association with Mr
Snowden, in the face of a boycott from major financial companies
and dwindling public sympathy because of Mr Assange's personal
travails.</p>
            <p>It has issued multiple appeals for donations since Mr Snowden
flew to Moscow, though the BBC has been unable to obtain any
comment on how successful those have been.</p>
            <p>For Mr Groll, association with Mr Snowden can only be a boon for
Mr Assange. "Assange hasn't been much of a success lately - before
he was a valiant fighter for transparency, now he's holed up in an
embassy.... But now he's riding to the rescue."</p>
            <p>The association is a riskier one for Mr Snowden, he says.</p>
            <p>"The dangers for Snowden is that he ends up being discredited -
Assange is a hate figure in the US... so by associating with him,
he's risking his reputation.</p>
            <p>"Of course, he doesn't have much choice. We've seen an immense
smear campaign against Snowden and Assange - and this is another
way they can tarnish [Snowden's] credibility."</p>
            <p>Wikileaks has confirmed that "there are more revelations to be
expected" from Mr Snowden - but it remains to be seen whether, in
light of the assistance he has received from them, Mr Snowden will
change tack and release the new information through his new
allies.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>US spy leaks</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372684702774"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23123964">Revelations of US spy
scandal</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372869435767"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23165992">Where will Snowden end
up?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372702760008"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-23133216">Is it OK to spy on your
allies?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1370824107276"
                     href="/news/world-us-canada-22837100">Profile: Edward Snowden</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">I have personal sympathy with Mr Snowden,
having lived through a very similar experience”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Julian Assange</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Wikileaks founder</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
