<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23117608"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Former Anglo Irish Bank CEO apologises for the &#34;inappropriate&#34; language he used in recorded phone calls during the bank's collapse in 2008."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-06-30T14:54:29"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68466000/jpg/_68466859_angloirishbank.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline"
            content="Ex-bank boss 'sorry' for Anglo tapes"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Europe"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-23117608"/>
         <title>BBC News - Anglo tapes: Ex CEO David Drumm
apologises</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">30 June 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">15:54</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Anglo tapes: Ex CEO David Drumm
apologises</h1>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68464000/jpg/_68464445_angloirishbank.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="The former headquarters of Anglo Irish Bank"/>
               <span style="width:304px;">Executives at Anglo Irish Bank were recorded
laughing and swearing as their bank faced collapse</span>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">The former boss of
Anglo Irish Bank has apologised for the "inappropriate" language he
used in recorded phone calls during the bank's 2008 collapse.</p>
            <p>The recordings were leaked to the Irish Independent newspaper
and last week it published a series of articles giving details of
the bankers' conversations.</p>
            <p>Senior Anglo executives were heard joking over the bank's
massive losses.</p>
            <p>In an Irish Central interview, Mr Drumm said he was "shocked and
embarrassed" by the content of the tapes.</p>
            <p>He said there was "no excuse for the terrible language or the
frivolous tone and I sincerely regret the offence it has
caused".</p>
            <p>"I cannot change this now but I can apologise to those who had
to listen to it and who were understandably so offended by it."</p>
            <p>The phone conversations have caused
widespread anger among taxpayers and government ministers in the
Irish Republic.</p>
            <p>They were taped in September 2008, as the Irish government was
in negotiations to bail out a number of banks, amid an
unprecedented financial crisis.</p>
            <p>The government issued a blanket guarantee for deposits in Irish
banks, effectively making taxpayers liable for the debts run up by
the institutions.</p>
            <p>In the recordings, Mr Drumm can be heard laughing while one
Anglo executive sings the German national anthem, as deposits
flowed in from Germany as a result of the government guarantee.</p>
            <p>The former CEO was also recorded setting out Anglo strategy, in
its attempt to persuade the Irish Central Bank to give financial
support to their failing institution.</p>
            <p>Mr Drumm told his executives to go the the central bank with
their "arms swinging" and demand more money, by saying: 'We need
the moolah, you have it, so you're going to give it to us and when
would that be?'</p>
            <p>In more colourful language, another Anglo executive, John Bowe,
is heard saying that he plucked a figure of 7bn euros out of thin
air, when the authorities asked how much money would be needed to
rescue the bank.</p>
            <p>Mr Drumm, who ran Anglo between 2005 and 2008, later moved to
the United States, where he filed for bankruptcy.</p>
            <p>In an interview for the American website Irish Central, the
former bank boss said the first he heard of the Anglo tapes was
when he logged on to the Irish Independent last Monday in New
York.</p>
            <p>"I knew they were bad, bad, bad," Mr Drumm said.</p>
            <p>He was asked by US-based journalist Niall O'Dowd if he regretted
the language he had used in the calls.</p>
            <p>The former banker said: "I accept that the tone and language
used in the tapes is inappropriate and I fully understand why the
excerpts published have offended many people.</p>
            <p>"Listening to a recording made almost five years ago at a highly
stressful and volatile uncertain time is both embarrassing and a
shocking reminder of how much pressure my colleagues and I were
under at that time."</p>
            <p>Mr Drumm has denied claims that Anglo executives misled both the
government and banking regulators over the true scale of the bank's
losses.</p>
            <p>The government rescue package for Anglo eventually cost Irish
taxpayers around 30bn euros, which the Irish Prime Minister Enda
Kenny said was the "single biggest financial transaction ever made
in history of our state".</p>
            <p>The failed bank was nationalised in 2009, and the following year
the Irish government needed a bailout from the European Union and
the International Monetary Fund (IMF).</p>
            <p>Mr Kenny has said the Anglo tapes have damaged the Republic's
reputation and he wants to set up a parliamentary inquiry into the
collapse of the bank.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature related narrow">
            <h2>Related Stories</h2>
            <ul class="related-links-list">
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372407338442"
                  href="/news/uk-northern-ireland-23093988">Anglo bank tapes
'contemptible'</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372329916329"
                  href="/news/world-europe-23081752">'We need the moolah' said Anglo
boss</a>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <a class="story"
                  rel="published-1372240560633"
                  href="/news/world-europe-23061270">Anglo CEO 'joked over bank
losses'</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">"I knew they were bad, bad, bad”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">David Drumm</span>
            <span class="quote-credit-title">Ex-Anglo Irish Bank CEO</span>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
