<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23193282"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="Archbishop Desmond Tutu and the deputy president call for an end to a bitter row among members of Nelson Mandela's family, who remains critically ill."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-05T15:25:47"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68561000/jpg/_68561610_68561589.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Tutu: Don't besmirch Mandela name"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Africa"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-23193282"/>
         <title>BBC News - Desmond Tutu urges Nelson Mandela's family to end
feud</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">5 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">16:25</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Desmond Tutu urges Nelson Mandela's family
to end feud</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68560000/jpg/_68560888_68560887.jpg"
                 alt="Denis Goldberg"/>
               <p class="caption">Denis Goldberg said his friend Nelson Mandela
looked better than expected</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Two leading South
Africans have called for an end to a bitter row among members of
Nelson Mandela's family over the reburial of three of his
children.</p>
            <p>Deputy President Kgalema Motlanthe said he hoped the public
dispute could be resolved in a "dignified manner".</p>
            <p>Archbishop Desmond Tutu pleaded with the family not to
"besmirch" Mr Mandela's name with their squabble.</p>
            <p>President Jacob Zuma has meanwhile denied reports that Mr
Mandela, 94, was in a vegetative state.</p>
            <p>South Africa's first black president has
spent the past four weeks in a Pretoria hospital with a recurrent
lung condition.</p>
            <p>"Madiba remains in a critical, but stable condition. The doctors
deny that the former president is in a vegetative state," said a
statement from Mr Zuma, who visited Mr Mandela on Thursday.</p>
            <p>The statement came after court papers filed on behalf of Mr
Mandela's eldest daughter, Makaziwe, on 26 June said his health was
"perilous" and that he was "assisted in breathing by a life-support
machine".</p>
            <p>A lawyer has told the BBC this document was never read out in
court.</p>
            <p>Subsequent court papers seen by the BBC also on behalf of
Makaziwe Mandela, do not mention that her father was in a
"vegetative state".</p>
            <p>One of Mr Mandela's friends and fellow
former prisoners, Denis Goldberg, who visited the anti-apartheid
icon on Monday, also said he was responsive but was prevented from
speaking because he had tubes in his mouth.</p>
            <p>"I'm quite satisfied he was responsive to what I was saying," he
said.</p>
            <p>The BBC's Dr Smitha Mundasad says doctors would only diagnose a
vegetative state if a patient was unaware of their surroundings and
could not speak or respond to commands.</p>
            <p>Patients may, however, breath without assistance, she says.</p>
            <p>Crucially, the diagnosis is often only made after four weeks,
while a "permanent vegetative state", which has been mentioned in
the court documents, would only be made once the condition was
considered irreversible and after at least six months in the
UK.</p>
            <p>She does, however, note that different countries use different
criteria for diagnosis.</p>
            <p>Correspondents say there has been a long-running battle over Mr
Mandela's legacy, but that it has intensified as his health has
deteriorated.</p>
            <p>The feud over the reburial of Mr Mandela's children is linked to
the decision about where he will eventually be buried, as it is
thought he would like to interred alongside them.</p>
            <p>The legal documents were filed by Makaziwe and several other
relatives last week in order to persuade a judge to make a speedy
decision over whether to exhume the children.</p>
            <p>On Thursday, the three bodies were reburied, following a court
order, back in the village of Qunu, where Mr Mandela was brought up
and where he is said to want to be laid to rest.</p>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68553000/jpg/_68553873_68553872.jpg"
                 alt="Mandla Mandela"/>
               <p class="caption">Mandla Mandela: "It seems like anyone and
everyone can come and say 'I am a Mandela'"</p>
            </div>
            <p>Earlier, forensic tests confirmed the identity of the bodies
which had been exhumed by police from the homestead in the village
of Mvezo owned by Mr Mandela's grandson, Mandla.</p>
            <p>An affidavit filed by Mandela family members alleged that Mandla
had relocated the graves in 2011 to ensure that his grandfather
would be buried in Mvezo, against his wishes.</p>
            <p>At a news conference on Thursday, Mandla accused some of his
relatives of washing their dirty linen in public and battling for
control of his grandfather's assets.</p>
            <p>"In the past few days, I have been the target of attacks from
all sorts of individuals wanting a few minutes of fame and media
attention at my expense," he said.</p>
            <p>His family rivals were motivated by revenge as he had refused to
support their legal case to oust three of Mr Mandela's aides from
companies the ex-president had set up, Mandla added.</p>
            <p>Later, Deputy President Motlanthe criticised the behaviour of Mr
Mandela's family on a radio chat show in Johannesburg.</p>
            <p>"It's all very sad, but we've got to continue keeping the family
and Madiba in our prayers and hope, continue to hope, that Madiba
will recover and also that the family will manage its own affairs
in a dignified manner," he said.</p>
            <p>Archbishop Tutu, who, like Mr Mandela, won the Nobel Peace Prize
for his role in the struggle against white minority rule, appealed
to the family to overcome their differences.</p>
            <p>"Please, please, please may we think not only of ourselves? It's
almost like spitting in Madiba's face," he said in a statement.</p>
            <p>"Your anguish, now, is the nation's anguish - and the world's.
We want to embrace you, to support you, to shine our love for
Madiba through you. Please, may we not besmirch his name?"</p>
            <p>
               <a href="/news/world-africa-23083138">Mandela family
tree</a>
            </p>
            <p>
               <a href="/news/world-africa-23198560"
               title="Nelson Mandela: Beyond the rumours">Andrew Harding: Beyond the
Mandela rumours</a>
            </p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68525000/jpg/_68525988_sa_624_v4.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="474"
                 alt="Map"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>Mandela in hospital</h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372980874368"
                     href="/news/world-africa-23083138">Mandela family tree</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373022052486"
                     href="/news/world-africa-23198560">Beyond the rumours</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372691524885"
                     href="/news/world-africa-23070676">Family feud</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1372845254177"
                     href="/news/world-africa-23153579">Explore hospital messages</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature narrow">
            <h2 class="quote">“<span>Start Quote</span>
            </h2>
            <blockquote>
               <p class="first-child">It's almost like spitting in Madiba's
face”</p>
            </blockquote>
            <span class="endquote">End Quote</span>
            <span class="quote-credit">Archbishop Desmond Tutu</span>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Nelson Mandela's children</h2>
            <p>
               <strong>With Evelyn Mase:</strong>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>Thembekile born 1945, died 1969</li>
               <li>Makaziwe born 1947, died aged nine months</li>
               <li>Makgatho born 1950, died 2005</li>
               <li>Makaziwe, born 1954</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
               <strong>With Winnie Madikizela-Mandela:</strong>
            </p>
            <ul>
               <li>Zenani born 1959</li>
               <li>Zindziswa born 1960</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-africa-23083138">Explore Mandela family
tree</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
