<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:og="http://opengraphprotocol.org/schema/"
      xmlns:rnews="http://iptc.org/std/rNews/2011-10-07#"
      xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step"
      xmlns:es="http://www.marklogic.com/enhanced-search#"
      xml:lang="en-GB"
      xml:base="http://www.bbc.co.uk">
      <head profile="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcq-html/"
         resource="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23125387"
         typeof="rnews:NewsItem">
         <meta property="rnews:description"
            content="The Muslim Brotherhood's headquarters in Egypt's capital Cairo is ransacked, as the number of killed at protests against President Morsi rises to 16."/>
         <meta property="rnews:datePublished" content="2013-07-01T14:08:46"/>
         <meta property="rnews:thumbnailUrl"
            content="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68478000/jpg/_68478037_68477843.jpg"/>
         <meta property="rnews:headline" content="Brotherhood HQ in Cairo stormed"/>
         <meta name="CPS_SECTION_PATH" content="World/Middle East"/>
         <meta property="rnews:creator" content="http://www.bbc.co.uk#org"/>
         <link rel="copyright"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/terms/"
            title="Terms of Use"/>
         <link rel="http://purl.org/dc/terms/source"
            href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-23125387"/>
         <title>BBC News - Egypt protesters storm Muslim Brotherhood
headquarters</title>
      </head>
      <body>
         <div class="story-body">
            <span class="story-date">
               <span class="date">1 July 2013</span>
               <span class="time-text">Last updated
at</span>
               <span class="time">15:08</span>
            </span>
            <h1 class="story-header">Egypt protesters storm Muslim Brotherhood
headquarters</h1>
            <div>
               <img class="holding"
                 src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68484000/jpg/_68484935_68484934.jpg"
                 alt="Protesters set fire to the Muslim Brotherhood's headquarters in Cairo"/>
               <p class="caption">The BBC's Khaled Ezzelarab: "The president seems
to have lost control over the security forces"</p>
            </div>
            <p class="introduction">Anti-government
protesters in Egypt have stormed the national headquarters of
President Mohammed Morsi's Muslim Brotherhood in the capital,
Cairo.</p>
            <p>People ransacked the building in the Moqattam area and set parts
on fire.</p>
            <p>Officials say eight people have been killed in clashes outside
since Sunday, while eight others have died elsewhere.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile, four ministers are reported to have resigned, a day
after millions took to the streets across the country to demand the
president leave power.</p>
            <p>The al-Watan website said the ministers of tourism, environment,
communication and legal affairs had acted "in solidarity with the
people's demand to overthrow the regime".</p>
            <p>On Monday afternoon, Egyptian state television reported the
armed forces would issue a statement on the situation later in the
day, but did not provide further details.</p>
            <p>Earlier, the opposition movement behind the protests, Tamarod
(Revolt), gave Mr Morsi until Tuesday afternoon to step down and
call fresh presidential elections, or else face a campaign of civil
disobedience.</p>
            <p>Protesters across Egypt accuse the
president of failing to tackle economic and security problems since
being elected a year ago. His supporters insist he needs more
time.</p>
            <p>The crowds seen in Cairo's Tahrir Square on Sunday were the
biggest since the 2011 revolution that toppled Hosni Mubarak.</p>
            <p>Protests and sporadic outbreaks of violence were reported
nationwide.</p>
            <p>The health ministry said at least 16 people had been killed and
781 injured since Sunday.</p>
            <p>Three people died in the central province of Assiut, and another
four in Alexandria, Fayoum, Beni Suef and Kafr al-Sheikh. Another
protester suffocated to death at a protest outside the Ittihadiya
presidential palace in Cairo.</p>
            <p>Eight people were killed in clashes around the Muslim
Brotherhood's headquarters in Moqattam, the ministry added.</p>
            <p>Overnight, protesters threw petrol bombs and rocks at armed
guards inside the six-storey building, who retaliated by firing at
them.</p>
            <p>On Monday morning, the protesters stormed the headquarters and
began throwing objects out of broken windows. One protester was
seen removing parts of the signage, while another waved an Egyptian
flag from a window. Later, people began walking out carrying office
equipment.</p>
            <div id="slideshow_container" class="storybody-halfwide-include">
               <div id="ss_slides">
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68478000/jpg/_68478119_29ee6157-1601-4b5b-9d41-ceb274da9a62.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="People loot the Muslim Brotherhood's headquarters in Cairo (1 July 2013)"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">Protesters ransacked the Cairo
headquarters of President Mohammed Morsi's Muslim Brotherhood group
early on Monday.</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68478000/jpg/_68478115_eff0d645-f167-477e-98b2-165b6ba55374.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Protesters walk past graffiti depicting Mohammed Morsi near the presidential palace in Cairo (1 July 2013)"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">Earlier, the Tamarod protest group gave
Mr Morsi a day to leave step down, a year after he took
office.</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68478000/jpg/_68478811_f63c77be-7cf2-48ff-bfe6-98ca64883527.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Protesters in Tahrir Square demand resignation of Mohammed Morsi (1 July 2013)"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">The crowd in Tahrir Square on Sunday was
the biggest since the revolution in 2011. Hundreds returned to the
square on Monday.</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68478000/jpg/_68478809_4b1a96ac-7028-4f50-8fea-15f85177c9a1.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Protest camp outside the Ittihadiya presidential palace in Cairo (1 July 2013)"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">Many protesters spent the night on the
streets of Cairo, including outside the Ittihadiya presidential
palace.</span>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption body-width">
                     <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68478000/jpg/_68478117_f6842b60-bf76-4021-b71a-af82c5584449.jpg"
                       width="464"
                       height="261"
                       alt="Protesters in Tahrir Square demand resignation of Mohammed Morsi (1 July 2013)"/>
                     <span style="width:464px;">Protesters across Egypt have accused the
president of failing to tackle economic and security
problems.</span>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="ss_controls">
                  <a href="#prev" class="ss_prev ss_button ss_button_disabled">
                     <span>previous
slide</span>
                  </a>
                  <a href="#next" class="ss_next ss_button ss_button_disabled">
                     <span>next
slide</span>
                  </a>
               </div>
            </div>
            <p>"This is a historic moment. The
Brotherhood ruined the country, so stealing from them is
justified," one man, named Mohammed, told the AFP news agency.</p>
            <p>Many protesters accuse the president of putting the
Brotherhood's interests ahead of the country's as a whole.</p>
            <p>Brotherhood spokesman Gehad El-Haddad criticised the security
forces for failing to protect the building and warned that the
movement was considering action to defend itself.</p>
            <p>"It's very dangerous for one entity in society to take up
violence as a means of change because it may entice others to do
so," he told the Reuters news agency.</p>
            <p>Mr Haddad noted that self-defence committees had been set up
during the 2011 uprising, and said the Brotherhood's Guidance
Bureau would make an announcement later on Monday.</p>
            <p>"The people will not sit silent," he added.</p>
            <p>Some protesters had spent the night camped out in Tahrir Square
and also in front of the Ittihadiya presidential palace to the
north-east. They vowed to stay there until the president stepped
down.</p>
            <p>One man heading to the palace was confident it would not take
long.</p>
            <p>"Mubarak took only 18 days although he
had behind him the security, intelligence and a large sector of
Egyptians," Amr Tawfeeq told the Associated Press.</p>
            <p>Earlier, Tamarod issued a statement saying the protesters would
give Mr Morsi until 17:00 (15:00 GMT) on Tuesday to leave power and
allow state institutions to prepare for early presidential
elections.</p>
            <p>Otherwise, people would begin a campaign of "complete civil
disobedience", the group warned.</p>
            <p>It urged "state institutions including the army, the police and
the judiciary, to clearly side with the popular will as represented
by the crowds".</p>
            <p>The group also rejected offers of dialogue from the
president.</p>
            <p>"There is no way to accept any half measures," it said. "There
is no alternative other than the peaceful end of power of the
Muslim Brotherhood and its representative, Mohammed Morsi."</p>
            <p>On Saturday, Tamarod said it had collected more than 22 million
signatures - more than a quarter of Egypt's population - in
support.</p>
            <p>But Mr Morsi was defiant in an interview published on Sunday,
rejecting the opposition calls for early presidential
elections.</p>
            <p>"If we changed someone in office who [was elected] according to
constitutional legitimacy - well, there will be people opposing the
new president too, and a week or a month later they will ask him to
step down," he told the Guardian newspaper.</p>
            <p>"There is no room for any talk against this constitutional
legitimacy. There can be demonstrations and people expressing their
opinions. But what's critical in all this is the adoption and
application of the constitution."</p>
            <div class="caption full-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68464000/jpg/_68464017_cairo_protests_2013_624v2.jpg"
                 width="624"
                 height="400"
                 alt="Map"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="embedded-hyper">
            <div class="hyperpuff">
               <h2>
                  <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12315833">Egypt in
crisis</a>
               </h2>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373156235629"
                     href="/news/magazine-23199377">Shifting sands</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373146727395"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23214054">What now for
Brotherhood?</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373020716781"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23197801">Failed experiment</a>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <a class="story"
                     rel="published-1373067054933"
                     href="/news/world-middle-east-23205101">Two years in Tahrir
Square</a>
                  </li>
               </ul>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Analysis</h2>
            <div class="byline">
               <span class="byline-picture">
                  <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/48964000/jpg/_48964143_48964145.jpg"
                    alt="image of Jeremy Bowen"/>
               </span>
               <span class="byline-name">Jeremy Bowen</span>
               <span class="byline-title">BBC
Middle East editor, Cairo</span>
               <hr/>
            </div>
            <p>All sides in Egypt were surprised by the huge scale of the
demonstrations against the president.</p>
            <p>The opposition is a broad and informal coalition, which ranges
from supporters of the old Mubarak regime to people who risked
their lives to topple it. Their challenge is to find a way to
sustain the momentum of Sunday's protests.</p>
            <p>President Morsi's spokesman has called for dialogue. For that to
work, the president would have to offer major concessions, perhaps
on a rewritten constitution. He showed no signs of conciliation
during a major political speech last week, instead appealing to his
Muslim Brotherhood base.</p>
            <p>As for the demonstrators, they have called for his resignation
and early elections. Political chaos looks likely to continue.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="story-feature wide">
            <h2>Tamarod (Revolt)</h2>
            <div class="caption body-narrow-width">
               <img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/68477000/jpg/_68477293_68477292.jpg"
                 width="304"
                 height="171"
                 alt="A woman holds up a petition demanding President Mohammed Morsi's resignation (17 May 2013)"/>
            </div>
            <p>The Tamarod movement says more than 22 million people have
<a href="http://tamarod.com/index.php?page=english">signed a
petition</a> complaining that:</p>
            <ul>
               <li>Security has not been restored since the 2011 revolution that
toppled Hosni Mubarak</li>
               <li>The poor "have no place" in society</li>
               <li>The government has had to "beg" the International Monetary Fund
(IMF) for a $4.8bn loan to help shore up the public finances</li>
               <li>There has been "no justice" for people killed by security
forces during the uprising and at anti-government protests since
then</li>
               <li>"No dignity is left" for Egyptians or their country</li>
               <li>The economy has "collapsed", with growth poor and inflation
high</li>
               <li>Egypt is "following in the footsteps" of the US</li>
            </ul>
            <ul class="links-list">
               <li>
                  <a href="/news/world-middle-east-23077898">Egypt deeply
polarised as Morsi marks first year</a>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </div>
      </body>
   </html>
